第九章

他们上演了这部剧，演出非常成功。那之后，他们一年又一年地上演一部部戏剧。由于迈克尔像管理他们的家那样节俭地经营剧院，因此他们虽然有失手的时候，但并没有损失很多钱，戏剧演出成功的时候却挣了每一分能挣的钱。迈克尔很得意，他认为伦敦没有一个剧院经理像他这样能在剧作上花这么少的钱。迈克尔精于改装旧布景，使它们看起来像新的一样，他还给渐渐积攒起来的家具改头换面，省下了租赁的费用。他们赢得了有开创精神的名声，因为不想给那些有名的剧作家高额的费用，迈克尔总是愿意尝试不知名的剧作家的作品。他还寻找那些从未有过演出机会以及薪水很少的演员，也因而发掘了不少有利可图的新演员。

在经营了三年后，他们已经有充足的经济底子，足以让迈克尔从银行贷款买下一个刚刚建成的剧院的地契。在几番讨论后，他们最终决定将之命名为西登斯剧院。开业的第一部剧就很失败，接着上演的另一部也没有好转。朱莉娅害怕起来，有些泄气。她觉得这剧院走了霉运，公众开始厌烦她了。也就是在这段时间里，迈克尔展现了他最可贵的品质。他泰然处之。

“在这一行，你必须好坏都能一起接纳。你是英国最好的女演员。只有三个人，不论剧本好坏，都能叫座，你就是其中一个。我们已经发了两发哑炮。下部剧一定会有起色的，那时，我们不仅会收回之前我们损失的，还能大赚一笔。”

当迈克尔感到自己立稳了脚跟，他立刻试图买回多莉·德·弗里斯的股份，但多莉并不听从他的劝说，对他的冷漠也视而不见。这一次，他的狡猾找到了对手。多莉觉得没有理由卖出看起来还不错的投资，而且对剧院持股让她能与朱莉娅保持亲密联系。但现在，在新剧院经营状况不稳定的时候，迈克尔鼓足勇气试图摆脱她。但多莉义正词严地拒绝在他们遇到困难的时候抛下他们，于是他只能放弃了。他安慰自己，想着多莉可能会留给罗杰，她的教子，一大笔钱。除了在南非的几个侄子，她没有什么亲人，而且她看起来像是患有高血压。同时，他们可以随时去吉尔福德附近的别墅，这也带来不少便利，还节约了他们置办一栋郊区别墅的钱。第三部剧非常成功，迈克尔丝毫没有犹豫地指出他当时有多么正确。他说话的方式好像这部剧的成功全部归功于他。朱莉娅几乎希望这部剧和前两部一样失败，好杀杀他的气焰，因为他那自负的样子实在让人觉得可恶。当然，你必须承认，他有几分聪明，或者是精明，但他绝没有自己想象的那般聪明。他总是觉得在任何事情上都比别人知道得多。

随着时间流逝，迈克尔开始渐渐不再演戏。他发现自己对管理剧院更有兴趣。

“我想像管理市政府机关那样有条不紊地经营剧院。”他说道。

同时，迈克尔觉得在朱莉娅演戏的晚上去一些边远的剧院转转，并试图发掘好演员，可以更加高效地利用他的夜晚时间。他有一个小本子，里面记录了他对每一位看起来有前途的演员的笔记。然后他开始导演戏剧。每想到那些导演要求用那么多钱去排练一出戏剧，他总是抱怨连天。最近，有些导演甚至坚持要获得总收入的一部分作为报酬。最终，朱莉娅最中意的两个导演都没空，另外一个她信任的导演在演戏，因而无法全情投入导演的工作中。

“我非常想亲自试试。”迈克尔说道。

朱莉娅表示怀疑。他缺乏想象力，想法也极为普通。她不确定他是否能驾驭得了整个剧组。但唯一能请来的导演要求的报酬在两人看来高得离谱，除了让迈克尔一试之外也没有别的办法了。但迈克尔的表现超出了朱莉娅的预期。他细致缜密，工作很努力。让朱莉娅感到非常奇怪的是，迈克尔比以往任何导演都更能激发她的潜能。他知道她的能力极限，对她音调的每一处变化、美妙双眸的每一次注视以及她身体的每一个优雅的动作都非常熟悉，他给她的建议，让她成功地展现出她职业生涯迄今为止最好的表演。迈克尔与整个剧组的相处模式既宽容，又严格。当大家的脾气到达爆发边缘时，他那副好个性，再加上他真诚的友善，能让事情平息下来。在那之后，毫无疑问他应该继续导演他们自己的戏剧。剧作家们也都喜欢迈克尔，由于他缺乏想象，他只能按照剧本所写的来导戏，而且他时常不能确定剧本所描述的意思，只能去请教他们。

朱莉娅现在是个有钱女人了。她不得不承认，对于她的钱迈克尔如同对自己的钱那样爱护。他小心地关注着她的投资，当迈克尔把她户头的股票以高利润的价格卖出去时，高兴得如同自己挣了钱一般。他给她很大一笔薪水，并且非常骄傲地宣称她是伦敦最贵的女演员，但当他自己演出的时候，他给自己的薪水从来不会高出角色应得的报酬。当他导演戏剧的时候，他给自己二流导演的费用。他们共同承担房子的花销以及罗杰教育的开支。罗杰出生不到一周，他们便给他在伊顿公学报了名。不可否认，迈克尔在公平和诚实方面做得一丝不苟。当朱莉娅意识到她比迈克尔富有得多时，她想自己承担所有的费用。

“你没有任何理由这么做，”迈克尔说道，“只要我还付得起，我就会支付。你比我挣得多因为你值得那么多。我给你付高薪水因为那是你应得的。”

没人不敬佩他为了她而牺牲自我的克己精神。他放弃了自己的一切抱负，为了成就她的职业。甚至不喜欢迈克尔的多莉也承认他的无私奉献。每当朱莉娅想和多莉讨论迈克尔，总是被一种羞怯阻止，但精明的多莉很早就发现迈克尔让朱莉娅恼怒，于是多莉时不时地向她指出他对她的帮助有多大。所有人都赞美他。一个完美的丈夫。在她看来，除了她没人知道和他这样一个虚荣的怪物住在一起是什么感觉。当他在高尔夫球场上打败对手或者在生意场上占了某人的上风时显示出的扬扬自得的神情令人火冒三丈。他美化他的狡猾。他令人生厌，彻头彻尾地让人厌恶。他喜欢告诉朱莉娅他做的一切，以及他脑海中出现的一切诡计；起初仅仅是拥有他就让她开怀的时光多么美好，但这么多年来她渐渐无法忍受他的装腔作势。无论描述什么，他都要把大大小小的细节讲出来。他不仅仅对自己的商业头脑感到得意；随着年事增长，他竟无耻地为自己的英俊潇洒而感到自豪。年轻时，他对自己的美貌不以为然；现在却开始花更多心思在上面，并且不遗余力地保持他残留的风采。他对自己外表的关注几乎成了一种执念，对自己的体形也花了不少心思。他从不会吃让他长胖的食物，从不会忘记运动。他发现自己的头发稀疏起来，便向美发专家咨询。如果能让他的脸年轻起来，朱莉娅确信他会暗地里做手术。他已经养成某种坐姿，使他的脖子稍稍前突，这样他脖子上的皱纹就不会显现出来，并且他会弓起背，防止肚子下垂。如果他经过一面镜子，他必定会照一照。他渴望被恭维，能得到一句赞美便眉开眼笑。奉承话是他的食物和水。朱莉娅想起来是她让他养成了这个习惯，不禁苦笑起来。有许多年，她总是告诉迈克尔他有多美，现在他竟然离不开这些恭维了。这是他唯一的弱点。一个没工作的女演员只需当面告诉迈克尔他太帅了，他就会在脑子里想想是否有她能演的角色。这么多年来，朱莉娅知道，迈克尔并不在乎女人，不过等他到了四十五岁左右，竟然开始和女人打情骂俏。朱莉娅并不觉得这些调情会有什么实际结果。他只是希望得到她们的崇拜。据她所知，当那些女人追得过紧，他就会用她来做挡箭牌甩掉她们。要么是他不能冒险做任何伤害她的事情，要么是她嫉妒心强或者多疑，因此这段友谊最好到此为止。

“上帝知道她们看上了他什么。”朱莉娅对着空房子感叹道。

她随意拿了半打他最近的照片，一张一张仔细观察。她耸耸肩。

“好吧，我想我也不能责怪她们，我也曾爱上他。当然那时他更好看些。”

想起她曾经多么爱他，让朱莉娅有点伤感。因为她的爱消失了，她感到自己被生活欺骗了。朱莉娅叹了口气。

“我的背开始痛了。”她说道。

第十章

有人在敲门。

“请进。”朱莉娅说道。

是伊维进来了。

“您今天还不去休息吗，兰伯特小姐？”她看到朱莉娅坐在地板上，周围都是照片，“您在做什么？”

“做梦。”她捡起两张照片，“看这张照片，还有这张。”

一张是迈克尔最年轻帅气时饰演茂丘西奥时的照片，另一张是迈克尔演最后一个角色时的照片，他戴着白色的礼帽，穿着晨礼服，肩膀上挂着一副双筒望远镜。他看起来自鸣得意得不可救药。

伊维嗤之以鼻。

“哦，没必要冲着洒了的牛奶哭。”

“我一直在回忆过去，现在快忧郁死了。”

“一定的。当你开始回想过去，那就意味着你没有什么未来了，是吗？”

“快闭嘴吧，你这老母牛。”朱莉娅说道。如果她愿意，她可以非常粗俗。

“快点吧，否则会影响今晚的演出，我来把乱糟糟的屋子收拾一下。”

伊维是朱莉娅的服装师兼女仆。在米德尔普尔时，她就为朱莉娅服务，后来随她来了伦敦。她是伦敦本地人，看起来身子单薄，无精打采，瘦骨嶙峋。她有些上了年纪，一头红发总是不整齐，似乎需要大洗一番；她的两颗门牙没了，尽管朱莉娅多年来一直提出要为她补上，但她却不愿意。

“对于我的食量而言，我这几颗牙完全足够了。嘴巴里装那么多象牙才让我紧张呢。”

迈克尔很早就希望朱莉娅能至少再请一位外表更能适合这个职位的女仆，他曾试图说服伊维承认这些工作对她来说太多了，但伊维没有听。

“您怎么说都行，格斯林先生，但只要我还健康有力气，就不会再有其他人来伺候兰伯特小姐。”

“我们都老了，你知道吧，伊维。我们都不再年轻了。”

伊维用食指抹了一把鼻孔，吸了吸鼻涕。

“只要兰伯特小姐还可以饰演二十五岁的年轻女人，我就可以为她换衣服，做她的女仆。”伊维狠狠地看了他一眼，“而且既然这点活您出一倍的钱就能完成，为什么还要出两倍的价钱？”

迈克尔没脾气地笑了笑。

“我没有别的意思，亲爱的伊维。”

伊维催赶着朱莉娅上了楼。当朱莉娅没有午场演出的时候，她会在下午上床休息几个小时，然后做个轻轻的按摩。她脱了衣服，钻进了被窝。

“可恶，我的热水袋快冻成冰了。”

她看了看壁炉架上的钟表。难怪，热水袋被放在这里至少有一个小时了。她不知道自己在迈克尔的房间里待了那么久，翻阅那些照片，无所事事地回忆过去。

“四十六。四十六。四十六。当我六十岁的时候我就会退休。五十八岁的时候去南非和澳大利亚。迈克尔说我们会在那里大捞一笔。两万英镑。我可以出演所有以往的角色。当然，即便到了六十，我也能演四十五岁的女人。但有什么四十五岁的好角色呢？这些可恨的戏剧家。”

朱莉娅脑子里想着有没有一部一流戏剧的女主角是四十五岁，渐渐地睡着了。她睡得很沉，直到伊维叫醒了她，因为按摩师到了。伊维给她拿来了晚报，朱莉娅脱光衣服，按摩师按摩着她那细长的腿，她的肚子。朱莉娅戴上眼镜，又读了一遍她早上已经读过的戏剧消息、八卦专栏还有女性专题。此刻，迈克尔走了进来，坐在她床上。他经常会在这个时候来找她，和她聊上一阵子。

“他叫什么名字来着？”朱莉娅问道。

“谁的名字？”

“那个来吃午饭的男孩。”

“我不知道。我开车送他回了剧院。我没再想过他一下。”

这位按摩师，菲利普斯小姐，喜欢迈克尔。跟迈克尔在一起会很自在。他总是说一样的话，你知道如何应答。他也没什么架子，而且长得极其帅气。真的！

“菲利普斯小姐，她减肥效果不错吧？”

“哦，格斯林先生，兰伯特小姐没有一点赘肉。我觉得她身材保持得太好了！”

“真可惜我无法让你为我按摩，菲利普斯小姐。或许你能对我保持身材有所帮助。”

“您怎么说话呢，格斯林先生。您有二十岁男孩的身材。我不知道您是怎么做到的，我发誓我不知道。”

“简单生活，多动脑子，菲利普斯小姐。”

朱莉娅并没有在意他们在聊什么，但菲利普斯小姐的回答钻进了她耳朵。

“按摩当然非常管用，我一直这样认为，但您必须要注意自己的饮食，毫无疑问。”

“饮食！”她想，“当我六十岁的时候，我打算放任自己。我要吃所有我喜欢的黄油面包。早饭我要热面包卷，午饭和晚饭我都要吃土豆。还有啤酒，上帝，我多喜欢啤酒啊。豌豆汤和西红柿汤；糖浆布丁和樱桃馅饼。奶油，奶油，奶油。上帝啊，帮帮我，只要我还活着我就再也不想吃菠菜了。”

按摩后，伊维给她递来一杯茶，一片削掉肥肉的火腿，还有几片干吐司。朱莉娅起身，穿好衣服，和迈克尔一起去了剧院。她喜欢在幕布拉开前一个小时到达剧院。迈克尔会去他的俱乐部吃晚餐。伊维会坐出租车先行前往剧院，当朱莉娅到达她的更衣间时，一切都已经安排妥当。她再一次脱下衣服，穿上戏服。当她坐在她的梳妆台前开始化妆时，她注意到花瓶里插着一些鲜花。

“喂，谁送来的？是德·弗里斯夫人吗？”

多莉在她首场演出时送了她一个巨大的花篮，在她演出第一百晚和还有第二百晚（如果真的有这么一天），还有在此之间，只要她为自己的房子预订鲜花时，总会送一些给朱莉娅。

“不是，小姐。”

“查尔斯公爵？”

查尔斯·泰默利公爵是朱莉娅最早的也是最忠诚的爱慕者，当他路过花店时，他总会为朱莉娅订一些玫瑰。

“这是名片。”伊维说道。

朱莉娅看了一眼。托马斯·芬纳尔先生。塔维斯托克广场。

“住的什么鬼地方。你觉得这到底会是谁，伊维？”

“我觉得是某个被您的美貌迷倒的家伙。”

“这花肯定花了一英镑。塔维斯托克广场在我印象里并不是什么有钱人住的地方。你知道吧，买了这花，他可能一周都没钱吃饭了。”

“我想不至于吧。”

朱莉娅往脸上涂上油彩。

“该死，你太不浪漫了，伊维。就因为我不是个歌舞女郎，你就无法理解为什么会有人送我鲜花。上帝知道，我的双腿比她们都漂亮。”

“您和您的双腿都漂亮。”伊维说道。

“我不妨告诉你，我觉得在我这个年纪，有不知名的年轻男人送我鲜花没有什么不正常。我是说正好给你看看。”

“虽然我对男人也没什么了解，但如果他们看到您现在的样子，肯定不会送了。”

“去死吧。”朱莉娅说道。

当朱莉娅化好妆，伊维为她穿好长筒袜和鞋后，还有几分钟空闲，她坐在自己的桌子前，用她潦草粗放的字迹，写了一封热情洋溢的信给托马斯·芬纳尔先生，感谢他送来的鲜花。她天生就很有礼貌，而且回复所有仰慕者来信是她的一贯原则。这是她和公众保持联系的方式。写好信封后，她将卡片扔进废纸桶，准备穿上第一幕戏的戏服。催场员叩响了化妆间的门。

“开场演员请出场。”

这些话，虽然她已不知听了多少遍，却仍旧会让她内心颤动。它们像给她服了一剂补药。生活获得了意义。她即将从虚构世界步入真实世界。

第十一章

第二天，朱莉娅和查尔斯·泰默利共进午餐。他的父亲，丹诺伦特侯爵娶了一位女继承人，因此他父亲得到了一笔可观的财产。他喜欢在他位于希尔街的别墅中举办午餐派对，朱莉娅经常过去。其实在她内心深处，她对在那里遇见的那些达官显贵和阔太太都持有深深的蔑视，因为她是一个职业女性，一位艺术家，但她也知道这些关系会有用处。多亏这些关系，他们在西登斯剧院的首演才被报纸描述得非常精彩，她知道，在周末宴会上和一群显贵拍照会有很好的曝光效果。有一两位比她年轻的女主角不怎么喜欢她，因为她对至少两位公爵夫人直呼其名。但她并没有后悔这么做。朱莉娅不是一个非常健谈的人，但她眼睛明亮，举止优雅，一旦学会了上流社会的语言，她称得上一个令人愉悦的女人。她有模仿的天赋，但不怎么表现出来，怕影响到自己的表演，但在这些社交圈里，她极好地利用了自己这点长处，并因此获得了机智的名声。她很高兴她们都喜欢她，这些聪明悠闲的女人，但她一直暗地嘲笑她们竟然会为她的光彩倾倒。她在想，如果她们知道一个成功女演员的生活是多么不浪漫，以及她付出的所有辛苦，对自己仪表所倾注的爱护，还有不得不保持那些乏味而必需的习惯时，会有什么想法。但她友好地向她们提供化妆方面的建议，让她们仿制自己的衣服。她总是穿得很漂亮。即使迈克尔也乐意接受，只当她穿的衣服都不用自己花钱，并不知道她实际上花费了多少。

她的德行在这两个世界里都无懈可击。人人都知道她和迈克尔是模范夫妻。她是忠诚妻子的典范。同时，在这个特定的圈子里，人们都认为她是查尔斯·泰默利的情人。这段私情由于时间太久而得到了人们的认可和尊重，当二人同时被邀请去做客时，宽容的主妇们会把他们俩安排在相邻的房间里休息。这一猜测始于查尔斯夫人，她早已与查尔斯·泰默利分开，但事实上，这谣言毫无可信之处。唯一的证据是查尔斯爱慕朱莉娅二十年之久，同样也是因为朱莉娅，从未好好相处的泰默利夫妻，同意离婚。事实上，是查尔斯夫人介绍朱莉娅与查尔斯认识的。他们三人恰好在多莉家吃午餐，那时，朱莉娅作为一个年轻演员刚在伦敦取得第一次重大成功。那是个盛大的宴会，她很受尊重。查尔斯夫人，三十出头，是个公认的漂亮女人，虽然除了眼睛之外她的容貌并不值得称赞。但她凭着大胆、脸皮厚，成功摆出一副令人印象深刻的模样，她靠着桌子俯身向前，露出优雅的微笑。

“哦，兰伯特小姐，我想我在泽西的时候曾经认识你的父亲。他是位医生，对吧？他经常到我家里来。”

朱莉娅腹中涌起一阵恶心；她想起结婚前的查尔斯夫人是谁了，并意识到她设下的陷阱。朱莉娅发出一阵笑声。

“根本不是，”她回答道，“他是个兽医。他以前经常去您家里给那些母狗接生。那房子里全都是母狗。”

听到这样的回答，查尔斯夫人竟一时语塞。

“我母亲非常喜欢狗。”她回答道。

朱莉娅庆幸迈克尔不在那儿。可怜的家伙，如果他听到这话，定会觉得受到了莫大的屈辱。他总是称呼朱莉娅的父亲为兰伯特医生，念得好像这是个法国名字。他（朱莉娅的父亲）在大战结束不久后就去世了，于是她的母亲便搬去同她在圣马洛的遗孀妹妹一起居住，此后迈克尔开始称呼她为兰伯特夫人。在她的职业生涯之初，朱莉娅曾对此有些敏感，但当她成名后，她改变了想法。她倾向于——尤其是在显贵人物中间——强调她父亲是兽医这个事实。她无法解释个中原因，但她觉得这样做可以让大家都安分一些。

但查尔斯·泰默利明白，他的妻子是故意要侮辱这位年轻女人，他心中泛起怒火，于是故意向朱莉娅示好。他问起能否登门拜访，为她送上一些美丽的鲜花。

那时他年近四十，优雅的身躯上长了一个小小的脑袋，长相虽不好看但很高贵。他看起来很有教养，事实也如此，他的举止非常高雅。他是个艺术爱好者。他购买现代绘画，收藏古董家具。他热爱音乐，博览群书。起初，拜访这两个年轻演员在白金汉宫路上的小公寓让他觉得很有趣。他看得出他们很穷，与这对儿被他视为真正的波西米亚夫妻有联系让他很兴奋。他来过几次，他们请他在家里吃午饭，一个衣衫褴褛的名叫伊维的妇女服侍他们，这让他觉得与众不同。这才是生活。他并没有对迈克尔太在意，对他而言，迈克尔虽然长相出众，却只是一个资质平庸的年轻人，但他被朱莉娅迷住了。她性格温和，有魄力，活力四射，这都是他不曾见识过的。他去观看了几次她的表演，并把她的表演同他所认识的著名外国女演员们做了一番比较。在他看来，朱莉娅有非常独特的品质。她的魅力不容置疑。当他突然意识到她拥有天赋时，不禁有些激动。

“或许是另一个西登斯。一个更加伟大的爱伦·泰瑞(1)。”

那时候，朱莉娅并没有下午休息的习惯，她体壮如牛，从不觉得疲惫，因此他经常同她在公园散步。她感到他希望她有孩子般的天性。这非常适合她。表现得天真、坦诚、如同少女一样对一切事物感到高兴对她来说毫不费力。他带她去国家美术馆、泰特美术馆和大英博物馆，她如她说的那样享受。他喜欢给别人灌输，而她也很乐意接受。她记性很好，从他那儿学到了不少东西。后来她可以和最优秀的人士谈论普鲁斯特和塞尚，以至于会让人家对一个女演员能够有如此高的文化修养感到惊叹，这些都归功于他。她甚至在他自己意识到之前就明白他已经爱上了她。她觉得很可笑。在她看来，他是个中年男人，她把他看作一位友善的老家伙。那时她疯狂地爱着迈克尔。当查尔斯意识到自己爱上朱莉娅时，他的举止有了一些变化，他看起来非常腼腆，当他俩在一起时，他经常沉默不语。

“可怜的家伙，”她心里想，“他真是太绅士了，竟不知道对此要怎么办。”

但她已经准备好如何应对在她看来他迟早都会进行的表白。有一件事情她要让他明白。她决意不让他认为自己是爵爷，而她仅是个女演员，只要他随意召唤一声，她便会急不可耐地跳上他的床。如果他尝试那么做，她会对他扮演发怒的女主角，用珍妮·塔特布教给她的手势，猛然地伸出胳膊，食指顺势指向房门。另一方面，如果他心烦意乱，结结巴巴，她自己也得浑身发颤，带着哭腔诉说她从没思考过他对她的感情，哦，不，这一定会伤透了迈克尔的心。他们会抱在一起大哭一场，然后一切会恢复正常。以他那温文尔雅的性格，一旦他明白一切都不可能的时候，她相信他不会做出令人讨厌的事情。

但当事情发生时完全出乎她的意料。查尔斯·泰默利和朱莉娅一起在圣詹姆斯公园散步，他们看了鹈鹕，被景色启发，讨论了朱莉娅在某个周日夜晚出演米拉曼(2)的可能性。他们返回朱莉娅的公寓喝茶，吃了一块松脆饼。之后，查尔斯起身准备离去。他从口袋里掏出一幅微型画像，递给她。

“这是克莱朗(3)的画像。她是十八世纪的女演员，她有很多你的天赋。”

朱莉娅看着这张美丽聪明的脸庞，头发上涂着粉黛，心想相框上镶着的是钻石还是人造宝石。

“哦，查尔斯，你怎么会送我这样的礼物！你太可爱了。”

“我觉得你可能会喜欢它。就当是分别的礼物吧。”

“你要离开吗？”

她很惊讶，因为他未曾提起过此事。他看着她，面带浅浅的微笑。

“不。但我不打算再见你了。”

“为什么？”

“你心里和我一样明白。”

然后，朱莉娅做了一件有失体面的事情。她坐了下来，静静地看着这幅画像。她算计着时间，慢慢抬起双眼，直到与查尔斯的眼睛相遇。她几乎可以做到想哭就哭，这是她最厉害的成就之一，而现在，不发一点声响，没有一丝啜泣，眼泪顺着她的脸颊流了下来。她的嘴微微张开，眼神像受到伤害却不知由头的孩子，这样子简直可怜到让人无法忍受。他的脸上交织着痛苦。当他开口说话时，声音嘶哑，充满感情。

“你爱着迈克尔，对吧？”

她点了点头。她抿紧了嘴巴，似乎要努力控制自己，但眼泪还是不停地流下来。

“我一点机会都没有？”他在等她的答案，但她并没有回答，而是把手抬到嘴边，似乎在咬指甲，直到她用她那双迷蒙的泪眼盯着他。“难道你不知道继续见你会给我带来痛苦吗？你希望我继续见你吗？”

再一次，她微微点了点头。

“克拉拉总是因为你跟我过不去。她已经发现我爱上了你。正常来说，我们不应该再见面了。”

这次，朱莉娅稍稍摇了摇头。她抽泣了一下。她靠到椅子上，把头扭向了一边。她的整个身体都在表示她痛苦的绝望。血肉之躯都无法承受。查尔斯走向前，跪了下来，把那具伤心欲绝的身体拥入怀中。

“看在上帝的分上，请不要看起来这样难过。我无法忍受。哦，朱莉娅，朱莉娅，我如此爱你，我不能让你受这样的折磨。我会无条件接受一切，对你没有任何要求。”

她将她泪痕斑斑的脸转向他（“上帝，我现在该多么动人啊”），奉上双唇。他温柔地吻了她。那是他头一次吻她。

“我不想失去你。”她嘶哑地喃喃道。

“亲爱的，亲爱的！”

“一切就和以前一样？”

“就如同以前一样。”

她如释重负地叹了口气，在他怀中待了一两分钟。当他离开后，她站了起来，照了照镜子。

“你这个坏婊子。”她对自己说。

但她咯咯笑着，没有一点羞愧，然后她走进浴室清洗脸和眼睛。她感到非常兴奋。她听到迈克尔走了进来，便大声向他喊道。

“迈克尔，你看查尔斯刚刚给我的那幅画像，在壁炉架上。上面那些是钻石还是人造宝石？”

当查尔斯太太离开她丈夫的时候，朱莉娅有些紧张。查尔斯太太威胁说要起诉离婚，朱莉娅一点都不喜欢作为婚姻介入者出庭这件事。有那么一两周她都紧张兮兮的。她决定除非迫不得已，不会向迈克尔透露一句。她庆幸自己没有这么做，事实证明，查尔斯太太的这些威胁仅仅是为了从无辜的丈夫那里得到更多的赡养费。朱莉娅以精湛的演技应付查尔斯。双方都明白，她对迈克尔的爱使得他们无法有任何亲密的关系，但除此以外，他是她的一切，她的朋友，她的顾问，她的密友，她在一切紧急情况下有求必应的靠山，失意时可从他那儿寻求安慰。当细心敏感的查尔斯发现朱莉娅已经不再爱着迈克尔时，这成了一个棘手的问题。朱莉娅不得不使尽手段。并不是因为她忌惮成为他的情人；如果他是个演员，而且又爱了她这么久，她并不介意出于好意跳上他的床；但她就是对他提不起兴趣。她很喜欢他，但他那么优雅、有涵养、有文化，她无法将他看成自己的爱人。跟他上床就好像跟一件艺术品上床一样。而他对艺术的热爱让她心中对他有些嘲笑；毕竟她才是艺术的创造者，说到底他不过就是个观众。他希望她能与他一同私奔。他们可以在那不勒斯海湾的索伦托买一座有大花园的别墅，他们还会有一艘帆船，这样他们就能在那美丽的暗紫色的大海上优游岁月。爱情、美丽和艺术；世界消逝。

“这个可恶的笨蛋，”她想，“我怎么可能放弃我的事业，把我自己埋在意大利的某个洞里！”

她让他知道，她对迈克尔还有责任，他们还有个孩子；她无法让他从年纪轻轻开始就背上母亲是个坏女人的负担长大。不管有没有橘子树，一想到迈克尔的不幸福和她的孩子由陌生人照顾，她都无法在意大利那幢漂亮的别墅中有片刻安宁。一个人不能只顾自己，是不是？也要想想其他人。她是一个十分善良、很女人的人。有的时候，她会问查尔斯，为什么不离婚，然后再娶一个不错的女人。她无法忍受他将人生都浪费在她的身上。他告诉她，她是他唯一爱过的女人，他必须一直爱下去，直到最后。

“听着让人伤心。”朱莉娅说道。

尽管如此，朱莉娅还是把眼睛睁得大大的，如果她注意到任何女人对查尔斯有非分之想，她都会去刻意破坏。如果确有其事，她会毫不犹豫地显示她极度的嫉妒。朱莉娅和查尔斯很早就同意，凭借他良好涵养和她的好心，这安排极其周全，不是用具体的语言，而是在谨慎迂回的暗示明喻中达成，如果迈克尔有个三长两短，他们应该把查尔斯夫人解决掉，然后他俩就去结婚。但迈克尔非常健康。

这段时间，朱莉娅非常喜欢在希尔街吃午餐。聚会非常盛大。朱莉娅从不鼓励查尔斯去宴请他偶尔遇到的男演员或者剧作家，因此，她是那聚会上唯一一个需要挣钱养活自己的人。她旁边是一位能说会道的内阁大臣，又老又胖还谢了顶，极尽所能地取悦她；另一边是一位年轻的韦斯特雷斯公爵，看上去像个马倌，并且不停地吹嘘自己比一个法国人知道的法语俚语还要多。当他发现朱莉娅能说法语，他坚持要用法语和朱莉娅交流。午餐后，她被鼓动照着在法兰西喜剧院的方式朗诵《费德尔》中一篇陈词激烈的演讲，然后像一个英国学生在皇家戏剧艺术学院那样朗诵。她总是让客人们捧腹大笑，离开宴会时她沉浸在成功的狂喜中。那是天气明朗的一天，她决定从希尔街走到斯坦霍普广场。当她穿梭在牛津街熙攘的人群中时，很多人都认出了她，虽然她一直目视前方，但她感觉到了他们的注视。

“去哪里都得被人们盯着看真是太麻烦了。”

她放缓了脚步。天气真是好极了。

她用钥匙打开自己的家门，当她走进去时，听到电话铃响起。想都没想她便接起电话。

“谁？”

通常她接电话时会伪装起她的声音，但这次却忘记了。

“兰伯特小姐？”

“我不知道兰伯特小姐是否在家。请问这是谁？”她快速地用伦敦东区口音问道。

但刚刚那个单音节词已经背叛了她。电话中传来一阵笑声。

“我仅是想谢谢您写信给我。您明白的，根本无须如此麻烦。感谢您邀请我吃午餐，我想送您一些鲜花。”

他的声音和话语已经告诉了她这是谁。就是那个她不知道名字的容易脸红的年轻人。直到现在，虽然她已经看过他写的卡片，但她仍旧不记得他的名字。唯一让她留意的地方是他住在塔维斯托克广场。

“你太客气了。”她用自己的声音回答道。

“我想您应该不会某天跟我一起喝茶吧，是吗？”

绝对不会！她甚至不愿意跟公爵夫人一起喝茶；他把她当成了一个歌舞女郎。他有这样的想法简直让人觉得可笑。

“我不明白为什么不会。”

“您真的会？”他的口气听起来很迫切。他的声音很好听。“什么时候？”

那天下午她一点都不想去休息。

“今天。”

“好，我会从办公室溜出来。四点半？塔维斯托克广场138号。”

他这建议很周到。他本可轻易地提一个时髦的地方，在这种地方人们都会盯着她看。这证明他并不是仅仅为了得到媒体曝光才和她一起喝茶。

她打了一辆出租车到塔维斯托克广场。她扬扬自得。她在做一件好事。他能在多年之后跟他的妻子、孩子说，当他还是一个会计事务所里不起眼的小职员时曾和朱莉娅·兰伯特一起喝茶，这对他来说会多么精彩。而且，她是如此简单又如此自然。听过她闲聊的人，没有一个会猜出她是英格兰最伟大的女演员。如果他们不相信他的话，他会用她的照片证明，上面签着“你真诚的”。他会大笑，同时说道，如果他不是那么年轻无知，也不会厚着脸皮去邀请她。

当朱莉娅到达那房子，付过出租车费后，她突然想起，她还不知道他的名字，如果女仆来开门，她不知道该说找谁。在找门铃的时候，她注意到有八个门铃，分成四行，每行两个，每个门铃旁有一张卡片或是一张纸，上面用墨水写着名字。这是间老房子，被分割成了公寓。她非常绝望地开始看那些名字，想着有没有一个名字会让她记起点什么，当门被打开后，他站在她面前。

“我看到您的车到了，于是我跑了下来。很抱歉我住在三楼。希望您别介意。”

“当然不会。”

她爬上没有铺地毯的楼梯。当她到达第三层时，有点喘不上气来。他一跃而上，急切得像只年轻的山羊，朱莉娅心里想着，但她不愿暗示她情愿更悠闲一些。他带她进入的房间相当大，但几乎没有装饰。桌上放着一盘蛋糕和两个杯子，一个糖罐和牛奶罐。陶器是最便宜的那种。

“请坐，”他说道，“水正烧着呢。我很快就好。我的煤气灶在浴室里。”他离开后，她向四周看去。

“可怜的家伙，他一定跟一只教堂的老鼠一样穷。”

这房间让她想起她初登舞台时住过的那些地方。她注意到，他可怜地想要掩饰这间屋子既是卧室也是客厅的事实。墙边摆着的长沙发肯定就是他夜里睡的床。过去的时光在她的想象中隐退，非常奇怪，她觉得自己又变得年轻了。在像这样的房间中他们曾有多少欢乐，曾享受过难以置信的食物，有放在纸袋子里的熟食，还有在煤气灶上煎熟的鸡蛋和培根。他手里端着棕色茶壶泡的茶走了进来。她吃了一块有粉色糖霜的方形松糕。这种东西她有好几年都没吃过了。锡兰红茶，很浓，加了牛奶和糖，让她回到那些她以为已经忘记的时光。她看见自己还是一个年轻的、默默无闻的、努力奋斗的女演员。松糕味道很好。这时需要有个手势来配合，但她只想到一个：她摘下了自己的帽子，把头一甩。

他们聊天。他看起来很害羞，比起电话里的他害羞得多；这也没什么奇怪的，现在她就在他面前，他肯定非常不知所措，她努力让他放轻松。他告诉她，他的父母住在海格特，他的父亲是位律师，他也曾在那里住，但他想要成为自己的主人，终于在他的雇用契约的最后一年他得以逃离家庭，租了这间小公寓。他正在为他的结业考试做准备。他们还聊了剧院。自他十二岁起，她出演的每部戏他都看过。他告诉她，有一次，他十四岁时，在午场演出结束后，他站在剧场后门口，当她出来时他请她在签名簿上签名。他长着一双蓝眼睛和一头浅棕色的头发，非常可爱。可惜他把头发梳得平平的。他皮肤白皙，脸红得厉害；她在想他是不是患有肺病。虽然他的衣服很便宜，但非常得体，她喜欢他这样，他看上去非常干净。

她问他为什么选择在塔维斯托克广场居住。塔维斯托克广场在中心位置，他解释道，而且，他喜欢这些树。从窗户望出去的景色很美。她站起来看，这是采取行动的好方法，然后她就可以戴上帽子，跟他道别。

“是，很不错，不是吗？很伦敦；让人有一种愉快的感觉。”

在她说这些话时，她转向站在身边的他。他用一只胳膊搂住了她的腰，扎实地吻了她。她一生中还未有哪个女角色比现在的她更加惊愕。她愕然不知所措，竟不知要做什么。他的嘴唇很柔软，他身上有种年轻的香味，让人欢欣。但他的所作所为简直荒唐可笑。他用舌尖强行撬开她的嘴唇，现在，他用两只胳膊抱住了她。她并没有感到生气，她也不想笑，她不知道自己是什么感受。而现在，她知道，他正温柔地牵着她走，他的嘴唇仍旧紧贴着她的，她清清楚楚地感受到他身体的灼热，就好像他体内有个小火炉，简直不同凡响；既而，她发现她躺在了那张沙发床上，而他就躺在她身边，亲吻她的嘴唇、她的脖子、她的脸颊和她的眼睛。朱莉娅内心感到一阵莫名的剧痛。她用双手捧着他的脸，吻了他的唇。

几分钟后，她站在壁炉架旁的梳妆镜前，修饰一下自己。

“瞧我的头发。”

他递给她一把梳子，她梳了一下。然后她戴上了帽子。他就站在她身后，她看到自己肩后那张有着热切的蓝色眼睛的脸，带着一丝淡淡的微笑。

“我还以为你是个特别害羞的人。”她对着他在镜子里的影子说道。

他咯咯地笑了。

“我什么时候再见你？”

“你还想再见我？”

“非常。”

她快速地想了想。这太荒谬了，她当然没有再见他的任何意愿，允许他刚才的行为简直愚蠢至极，但应付一下也好，如果她告诉他这事儿没有下一次了他可能会纠缠不休。

“我会给你打电话的。”

“你发誓。”

“以我的名誉做担保。”

“别让我等太久。”

他坚持同她一起下楼，等她上了一辆出租车。她原本想自己下楼，这样就能看一眼门楣上的门铃旁贴着的名片。

“可恶，我至少应该知道他的名字。”

但他没有给她任何机会。当出租车驶离后，朱莉娅蜷缩在车的角落里，咯咯地笑起来。

“被强奸了，天。事实就是被强奸了。在我这个年纪。而且都没有一句恳请原谅的话。把我当成了轻佻女人。十八世纪的喜剧，简直就是这个样。我应该是个女仆，穿着裙撑，还有那些可笑的蓬松的东西——它们叫什么来着？——就是用来放大臀部的那玩意儿，再加上围裙以及脖子里的围巾。”之后，她模糊地想起了法科(4)和哥德史密斯(5)，便杜撰了这样一段台词。“阁下，占一个可怜的乡村女孩的便宜可不光彩。若是夫人阁下的侍女阿比盖尔太太知道夫人的弟弟夺走了我作为这样地位的年轻女孩最宝贵的珍品（我的贞洁），她对此会说什么呢？真丢人，哦，丢人啊，阁下。”

当朱莉娅到家时，按摩师已经在等她了。菲利普斯小姐和伊维正在聊天。

“您去哪里了，兰伯特小姐？”伊维说道，“我想知道您休息得如何。”

“该死的休息。”

朱莉娅脱下衣服，夸张地将它们扔了一地。然后，她全裸着身体，跳到床上，在上面站了片刻，像从海浪中升起的维纳斯，接着将自己抛到床上，四肢伸展开来。

“这是什么意思？”伊维问道。

“我感觉很好。”

“如果我这么做，人们指定说我喝醉了。”

菲利普斯小姐开始按摩她的脚，揉捏得很温柔，让她休息而不是让她疲惫。

“您刚才进屋的时候，就像一阵旋风，”她说道，“我觉得您看起来像年轻了二十岁。您的眼睛光芒四射。”

“哦，把这话留给格斯林先生吧，菲利普斯小姐。”接着她又补充道，“我觉得我像两岁的娃娃。”

后来在剧院也是如此。阿尔奇·德克斯特，她的男主角，走进她的更衣室同她说一些事情。她刚刚化完妆。他被惊住了。

“喂，朱莉娅，今晚你怎么了？天，你看起来棒极了。为什么？你看起来不超过二十五岁。”

“我有一个十六岁的儿子，假装我有多么年轻一点作用都没有。我四十啦，而且我也不介意别人知道。”

“你对你的眼睛做了什么？我从来没有见过它们如此耀眼。”

她感到状态极佳。这部名叫《粉扑》的戏他们已经演了好几周了，但今晚朱莉娅像是第一次表演这部戏一样。她的演出非常精彩，收获了从未有过的笑声。她一直都极具吸引力，但今晚她的吸引力似乎更加光芒四射地弥漫在整个剧场里。迈克尔恰巧在包厢的一个角落里观看了最后两场戏，演出结束后他走进她的更衣室。

“你知道提词员说今晚我们的演出延长了九分钟吗？观众笑得太多了。”

“七次谢幕。我差点儿以为观众会闹个通宵。”

“那样的话，你只能怪你自己了，亲爱的。这世界上没有别的演员能有你今晚这般的表现。”

“跟你说实话，我也很享受。上帝啊，我饿了。晚餐我们吃什么？”

“洋葱牛肚。”

“哦，太好了！”她伸出胳膊抱住了他的脖子，亲吻了他，“我喜欢洋葱牛肚。哦，迈克尔，迈克尔，如果你爱我，如果你那副铁石心肠里还有一点柔情，让我喝杯啤酒吧。”

“朱莉娅。”

“就这一次。我并没有经常让你为我做一些事情。”

“好吧，在你今晚这么精彩的演出后，我想我没办法拒绝你，但明天我一定会让菲利普斯小姐整治你一番。”

————————————————————

(1) 爱伦·泰瑞（Ellen Terry，1847—1928），英国舞台剧女演员，她扮演莎士比亚剧中的角色最为人所知。

(2) 米拉曼为英国喜剧作家威廉·康格里夫（William Congreve，1670—1729）的代表作《如此世道》中的女主人公。

(3) 克莱朗（Clairon，1723—1803）为法国女演员，以演拉辛名剧《费德尔》中的女主人公费德尔著称。

(4) 法科（George Farquhar，1677—1707），英国剧作家。

(5) 哥德史密斯（Oliver Goldsmith，1728—1774），英国小说家。

第十二章

朱莉娅上了床，两脚放到了热水袋上，欢喜地看了看自己玫瑰粉和淡青色的房间，摆着金色天使的梳妆桌，心满意足地叹了口气。她觉得这一切多么有蓬巴杜夫人(1)的格调啊。她熄了灯，但毫无睡意。她很想去奎格饭店跳舞，但不是和迈克尔一起，而是和路易十五国王(2)或者巴伐利亚的路德维希(3)或是阿尔弗雷德·德·缪塞(4)跳舞。号角和法国歌剧舞会。她想起查尔斯送她的那幅画像。此刻她的心情同那时一般。她已经很久没有过这样刺激的经历了。她本应该为那段小插曲而感到羞愧；天哪，事后她感到非常害怕，但事实上每当她回忆起此事都会咯咯笑起来。

那也是一次偶然事件。那时她一直都有演出，从未休息，而她急需一次休假。她出演的戏剧不再卖座，而他们即将开始排练新剧，就在这时，迈克尔将剧院租给了一家法国公司六周时间。朱莉娅正好有时间休假。多莉在戛纳租了一幢房子准备在那里度过这个季节，朱莉娅可以去和她待一阵子。她离开时正好在复活节前夕，开往南方去的火车上十分拥挤，朱莉娅没能买到卧铺，但是库克公司的人说没有问题，而且到了巴黎车站就可以为她找到卧铺。令她惊慌的是，在他们到达巴黎后，她发现根本没有人知道她卧铺的事，列车长告诉她所有的卧铺都有人了，唯一的可能性仰仗于有人最后没来坐火车。她非常不喜欢在一等座的角落里坐一整夜这个想法，于是神情忧郁地去吃了晚饭。她坐在一张两人位的餐桌旁，不久一个男人走了过来，坐在她的对面。她并没有注意他。此刻，列车长对她说十分抱歉，却也帮不上什么忙。她闹了一番，但无济于事。列车长走后，坐在她对面的男人开始同她讲话。虽然他说的法语非常流利地道，但她注意到他并非法国人。面对他的询问，她礼貌地同他讲了她的遭遇，并说了她对库克公司、火车公司以及人类办事低效的意见。他表示很同情，并说吃完晚饭后他会去车厢里看看，说不定哪个列车员能够帮忙安排一下。说不定有哪位列车员收了小费后能把事情办妥。

“我简直要累死了，”她说道，“我愿意出五百法郎买一个卧铺。”

对话就这样开始了，他说他是巴黎西班牙使馆的一个专员，准备去戛纳过复活节。虽然她同他聊了近一刻钟，但她并没费心观察他的长相。现在她注意到他长着胡子，黑色拳曲的络腮胡和黑色拳曲的八字胡，但胡子在他脸上长得很奇怪，两个嘴角下面有两块斑，让人感觉很古怪。再加上他黑色的头发，下垂的眼皮和长长的鼻子，他让她想起见过的某个人。突然间她记起来了，脱口而出：

“你知道吗，我刚才怎么也想不起来你让我想起了谁。你特别像提香(5)为弗朗西斯一世画的肖像，挂在罗浮宫的那幅。”

“有一双细小的猪眼睛那幅？”

“不，你的眼睛很大，我觉得是胡子很像。”

她瞥了一眼他眼睛下方的皮肤；肤色有些紫罗兰色，没有皱纹。虽然长着让人看起来显老的胡子，但他还是一个年轻人；他不超过三十岁。她在想他是不是一位西班牙大公。他穿得并不考究，但外国人经常穿得一般；他的衣服可能花了不少钱，虽然剪裁拙劣；而他的领带，虽然花里胡哨，但她认出那是夏尔凡(6)牌子的。在他们餐后喝咖啡时，他提议能否请她喝一杯酒。

“您真是太好了。这或许会让我睡得好一些。”

他递了一支烟给她。他的烟盒是银色的，她不喜欢，但当他合上烟盒时，她注意到烟盒的角落处镶着一枚金色的小皇冠。他准是一位伯爵什么的。银色烟盒上镶金色的皇冠真是别致，真可惜他得穿着那些现代衣服！如果他穿得像弗朗西斯一世，他会看起来很出挑。她竭力做出优雅的样子。

“我觉得我应该告诉你，”他说道，“我认识您。允许我加一句，我对您非常敬慕。”

她用她那漂亮的眼睛盯了他一会儿。

“您看过我演出？”

“是的，上个月我在伦敦。”

“那是个有趣的小戏剧，是吧？”

“是您让它变得有趣的。”

当侍者过来收费，她坚持自己付她自己的账单。这个西班牙人陪她去了车厢，说他会去看一看能否帮她找到一个卧铺。一刻钟后他走了回来，带来一位列车员，告诉她他为她找到一间小包房，如果她把行李交给列车员，他会带她过去。她非常高兴。他把自己的帽子扔在她腾出来的空位上，朱莉娅沿走廊跟着他。到达包房后，他吩咐列车员把行李架上的手提箱和公文包拿到这位女士原来的那节车厢去。

“您把您的包房让给了我？”朱莉娅叫道。

“这是火车上唯一的一间。”

“但我不能要。”

“拿走吧。”西班牙人对列车员说道。

“不，不。”

列车员看到陌生人的点头示意，拿走了行李。

“我不介意。我可以在任何地方睡觉，但一想到如此伟大的艺术家要在一个拥挤的车厢里同其他三人过夜，我一刻钟也无法合眼。”

朱莉娅继续抗议，但没有过分强调。他太有心了。她不知道如何感谢他。他甚至不让她付卧铺的钱。他眼中几乎含着泪地恳求她，允许他享有这非凡的特权为她献上这微不足道的礼物。她随身只带着一个化妆包，里面放着她的面霜、睡衣和她上厕所用的东西。他把这包放到桌子上。他只请求能够和她坐一会，抽一两支烟，到她想睡觉。朱莉娅无法拒绝。床已经铺好，他们坐在上面。几分钟后，列车员带来一瓶香槟和两个杯子。这是一次特别的小经历，朱莉娅享受其中。他非常有礼貌，很是殷勤，这些外国人明白应该如何对待一位有名的女演员。当然，伯恩哈特每天都碰得到这种事情。还有西登斯，当她走进客厅，所有人都会起立，好像她是皇族一样。他恭维她那一口流利的法语。生于泽西，在法国受教育？哦，难怪。但为什么她没选择用法语演戏而是英语？如果她用法语演戏，准会和杜丝一样有名气。她让他想起杜丝，同样动人的眼睛，白皙的皮肤，而她的表演中也同样富有情感以及出奇的自然。

他们喝了半瓶香槟，朱莉娅意识到已经很晚了。

“我觉得我应该睡了。”

“那我应该走了。”

他起身，亲吻了她的手。当他走后，朱莉娅插上插销，脱了衣服。她关掉了包房内所有的灯，只留了头顶上的一盏，开始阅读。不久，有人敲门。

“谁？”

“非常抱歉打扰您。我把我的牙刷忘在洗手间了。我能拿一下吗？”

“我上床了。”

“我不刷牙睡不着。”

“好吧，他倒是很爱干净。”

朱莉娅耸了耸肩，伸手拔出插销。这种情况下装正经就太愚蠢了。他走了进来，走进洗手间，不一会儿就出来了，挥舞着一把牙刷。当她刷牙时她就注意到那牙刷了，以为是隔壁包房的。那时两间包房共享一个洗手间。此刻西班牙人似乎注意到那了瓶酒。

“我很渴，您介意我喝一杯香槟吗？”

朱莉娅沉默了一秒。那是他的香槟，他的包房。嗯，好吧，一不做，二不休。

“当然不介意。”

他给自己倒了一杯，点了一支烟，坐在她的床的边缘。她挪了挪，给他腾出一些空间。对此他认为理所当然。

“您根本无法在那车厢睡觉，”他说道，“那儿有个人呼吸声很重。我倒更愿意他直接打鼾，这样就可以把他叫醒了。”

“真抱歉。”

“哦，没关系。最不济我就在您门外的走廊上蜷一晚。”

“他不会期望我邀请他跟我一起睡在这里吧，”朱莉娅对自己说道，“我开始觉得这一切都是设计好的圈套。休想，小伙子。”然后她大声说道：“很浪漫，当然，但不舒服。”

“您真是太迷人了。”

她庆幸自己的睡衣很漂亮，并且还没有涂面霜。事实上，她还没卸妆。她的嘴唇鲜红，在身后的阅读灯的映衬下，她非常清楚自己看上去并不糟糕。但她讥讽地回答道：

“如果你觉得因为你把包房让给了我，我就允许你跟我睡觉，那么你想错了。”

“正如您所说的，当然。但是为什么不呢？”

“我不是那种十分迷人的女人。”

“那您是什么样的女人？”

“一个忠贞的妻子和一位慈爱的母亲。”

他叹了口气。

“好吧，那我跟您道晚安了。”

他把烟头掐灭在烟灰缸中，握了她的手，并亲吻了它。他的嘴唇顺着她的胳膊慢慢地往上移。这动作让朱莉娅感到一阵兴奋。男人的胡子让她的皮肤发痒。然后他俯下身，亲吻了她的嘴唇。他的胡子有种霉味，她觉得很特别；她不确定这味道让她反感还是让她兴奋。说起来也奇怪，她想起她从未被长胡子的男人亲吻过。似乎这样很不得体。他关掉了灯。

直到亮光透过窗帘的缝隙提醒他们天已破晓，他才离开她。朱莉娅心灵和肉体都垮了。

“我们到达戛纳时，我肯定没个人样了。”

太冒险了！他很有可能会谋杀她或者偷她的珍珠项链。回想起她给自己招来的危险，她的身子一阵冷一阵热。他也去戛纳。假设在那儿他声称自己是她的熟人，她如何将他介绍给她的朋友？她很确定，多莉不会喜欢他。他可能会勒索她。要是他想再来一次这种事，她该怎么应付？毫无疑问，他很热情，他已经问过她会待在哪里，虽然朱莉娅没有告诉他，但如果他想查他一定能查到；在戛纳这种地方，避免和他相遇几乎不可能。他可能会对她纠缠不休。如果他像他说的那样爱慕她，他不可能就此罢休，而且外国人都不可靠，他可能会大闹一场。唯一的慰藉是他只在戛纳待到复活节后，她可以装作很累，告诉多莉她更愿意在别墅里安静地待着。

“我怎么能这么愚蠢？”她生气地喊道。

多莉会在车站接她，如果他愚笨到上前来跟她说再见，她会跟多莉说他把自己的包房让给了她。这样就不会有什么问题。要尽可能地说实话。不料，戛纳站下了很多乘客，朱莉娅出了车站后直接上了多莉的车，并没有看到他。

“我今天什么都没有安排，”多莉说道，“我想你会很累，而且我想这二十四小时里单独和你待着。”

朱莉娅深情地抓了一下她的胳膊。

“太好了。我们就在别墅待着，敷敷脸，好好地聊天。”

但第二天，多莉已经对她们去哪里吃午饭做了安排，而且她们将会在克鲁瓦塞特河上的一个酒吧里会见他们的房东，一起喝鸡尾酒。天气真不错，风和日丽。她们下了车后，多莉停下来和司机交代什么时候接她们，朱莉娅在一旁等着。突然间，她的心脏猛地一跳，那个西班牙人正在朝她走来，而他身边有个女人挽着他的胳膊，另一边是个小女孩牵着他的手。她没有时间转过身去。就在那时，多莉和司机说完了话，准备同朱莉娅一起穿过马路。西班牙人走了过来，看了她一眼，似乎完全没有认出她来，他正在和身边的女人热切地交谈，就这样走了过去。就在这时，朱莉娅明白他同她一样不愿再和彼此相遇。那个女人和孩子很明显是他的妻子和女儿，他来戛纳同她们一起过复活节。真是让人松了口气！现在，她可以毫无担忧地尽情享受假期了。但当她陪多莉来到酒吧，朱莉娅心想男人们真是恶心。你简直无法相信他们的任何一句话。一个男人，有这样迷人的妻子和可爱的女儿，还在火车里跟别的女人乱搞，简直不要脸。你还以为他们会讲些体面。

不过，渐渐地，朱莉娅的愤怒消退了，后来常常满是喜悦地回想起这桩奇遇。毕竟这件事挺有趣。有时，她会任自己胡思乱想，在幻想中重复那一夜的事情。他是最适合不过的情人了。当她成为一个老女人，还有韵事可以追忆。他的胡子让她无法忘记，那种贴在她脸上的奇异的感觉，还有那淡淡的霉味，让她讨厌又令她感到刺激。这么多年来，她一直在寻找长胡子的男人，她觉得，如果这样一个男人向她求爱，她简直无法抗拒。但现在几乎没有男人留胡子，这对她来说是一件幸事，因为她一看见留胡子的男人膝盖就会有些发软，而留胡子的男人却又不来向她献殷勤。她很想知道那个西班牙人是谁。一两天后她在赌场看到他玩九点，于是询问了两三个人是否认识他。但没人知道，他就这样没有名字地停留在她的记忆中，她的身体里。巧合的是，她也不知道那日下午那个行为出人意料的年轻人叫什么。这让她觉得好笑。

“要是我事先知道他们要对我放肆就好了，我至少会跟他们要名片。”

想着这些，她开心地入睡了。

————————————————————

(1) 蓬巴杜夫人（Madame de Pompadour，1721—1764），法国国王路易十五的情妇、著名交际花。

(2) 路易十五（Louis XV，1710—1774），法国国王，在1715年至1774年执政。他执政的早期受到法国人民的拥戴。但是，他无力改革法国君主制和他在欧洲的绥靖政策，使他大失民心，导致他最后成了法国最不得人心的国王之一。

(3) 路德维希（Ludwig Otto Friedrich Wilhelm，1845—1886），维特尔斯巴赫王朝的巴伐利亚国王（1864—1886年在位）。路德维希二世在巴伐利亚的历史中一直被认为是最狂热的城堡修建者，由于他对新天鹅堡的修建，在民间被称为“童话国王”。

(4) 阿尔弗雷德·德·缪塞（Alfred de Musset，1810—1857），法国贵族、剧作家、诗人、小说家。

(5) 提香（Tiziano Vecelli或Tiziano Vecellio，约1489—1576），意大利文艺复兴后期威尼斯画派的代表画家。

(6) 1838年创立于巴黎，因制作精良的男士衬衫和领带而闻名。

第十三章

几天后的一个早晨，朱莉娅正躺在床上阅读一个剧本，仆人从地下室打电话询问她是否要跟一位芬内尔先生通电话。她对这个名字没有任何印象，就在她要拒绝的时候，她突然想到可能是跟她艳遇的年轻人。她的好奇心促使她让他们接了电话。她认出了他的声音。

“你承诺要给我打电话的，”他说道，“我厌倦等待了，所以我给你打电话。”

“这几天我都非常忙。”

“我什么时候能去见你？”

“等我一有空的时候。”

“今天下午如何？”

“我今天有日场演出。”

“日场演出后来喝杯茶吧。”

她笑了。（“年轻的小家伙，不，你不能再那样对待我了。”）

“我做不到，”她回答道，“我会在更衣室休息，直到夜场演出。”

“你休息的时候难道我不能去见你吗？”

她犹豫了一下。或许最好让他过来；伊维进进出出，菲利普斯小姐也会在七点的时候过来，这样就不会有什么胡来的可能，而且这也是个不错的机会，能友善但是坚定地告诉他，那日下午的事情不会再发生了，哦，他真是个可爱的小东西。她要准备好说辞，向他解释清楚这事儿有多么荒谬，他必须答应她把整件事情从他的记忆中抹掉。

“好吧。五点半的时候过来，我请你喝杯茶。”

从下午到晚上演出之间她在化妆间里度过的那三个小时，是她繁忙的生活中最惬意的时刻。剧组的其他成员都走了；伊维会在那儿伺候她，门卫会保证她的隐私。她的化妆间就像一艘船的船舱。整个世界都远去，她享受这一刻的与世隔绝。她感到令人神往的自由。她会打个盹儿，读会儿书，或者在沙发上舒服地躺一会，任思绪随意飘荡。她会想她正在出演的角色，还有她曾经演过的最喜欢的角色。她想到她儿子罗杰。愉快的遐想在她的脑海里漫步，就像情人在树林里闲逛。她喜欢法国诗，有时会给自己背诵上一段魏尔伦(1)的诗句。

伊维在五点半的时候递给她一张名片。“托马斯·芬内尔先生。”她看着名片读道。

“带他进来，再上些茶。”

她已经决定要如何对待他。她会很亲切，但会保持距离。她会对他的工作表示出友善的兴趣，并询问他的考试进展如何。然后她会跟他聊一聊罗杰。罗杰已经十七岁了，还有一年就会去剑桥读书。她会暗示他，以她的年纪都可以做他的母亲了。她会假装他们之间从未发生过任何事情，然后他会主动离开。此后，除非透过舞台前的脚灯观看她的演出，他再也不会见到她，甚至会觉得整件事情都是他脑子里虚构的。但当她见到他时，看着他那瘦小的身板、潮红的面颊，还有他那双蓝色的眼睛，如此迷人又带着孩子气，心里突然一阵剧痛。伊维离开房间并关上了门。朱莉娅躺在沙发上，她伸出胳膊，将手递给他，嘴唇上浮现雷卡米埃夫人(2)般优雅的微笑，但他却一下子跪倒在地，狂吻起她来。她亦情不自禁，两只胳膊搂住他的脖子，热情地回吻他。

（“哦，我的决心。上帝，我不会爱上他了吧。”）

“看在上帝的分上，坐下吧。伊维一会儿就送上茶来。”

“告诉她别打扰我们。”

“你什么意思？”但他的意思非常明确。她的心脏开始加速跳动，“那太荒谬了，我不能。迈克尔可能会过来。”

“我想要你。”

“你觉得伊维会怎么想？冒这种险简直愚蠢到家了。不，不，不。”

门外有敲门声，伊维端着茶走了进来。朱莉娅让她把桌子摆在她沙发旁，在沙发另一边摆一把椅子，让年轻人坐。她和伊维说着没必要的对话。她感觉到他在看她。他的眼睛移动得很快，跟随着她的手势和她脸上的表情；她回避那双眼睛，但她能感觉到那眼神中的焦虑以及他迫不及待的欲望。她心慌意乱，觉得自己的声音听起来不那么自然。

（“我到底是怎么了？上帝，我几乎无法呼吸。”）

当伊维准备离开时，男孩做了个手势，这手势完全出于本能，与其说朱莉娅看到了他的手势倒不如说她感受到了。她无法直视他。他的脸变得无比苍白。

“哦，伊维，”她说道，“这位绅士想跟我谈论一个剧本。别让别人打扰我。我需要你时会按铃。”

“好的，小姐。”

伊维离开房间并关上了房门。

（“我是个笨蛋。我是个该死的笨蛋。”）

他挪开了桌子，双膝跪地，将她抱在怀中。

菲利普斯小姐快来的时候，她才打发他走了，并按铃叫了伊维。

“剧本不错吗？”伊维问道。

“什么剧本？”

“他跟您讨论的剧本啊。”

“他很聪明。当然他还年轻。”

伊维低头看了一眼梳妆台。朱莉娅喜欢一切都放在原有的位置，如果有瓶油膏或者睫毛膏没有被一丝不差地放回到原来的位置，她会发脾气。

“你的梳子呢？”

他刚刚用梳子梳过头，粗心地将它放在了茶桌上。当伊维看到梳子时，她若有所思地盯着梳子好一会儿。

“这梳子怎么跑到那儿去了？”朱莉娅轻声喊道。

“我还在想呢。”

这让朱莉娅措手不及。在化妆间做那种事情当然荒唐至极。天，锁眼里都没有插把钥匙。伊维保管钥匙。尽管如此，这种危险也增添了一丝刺激。想想她竟能这样疯狂就觉得有趣。他们现在已经订好了约会的日子。汤姆，她问他在家里他父母如何称呼他，他回答托马斯，而她无法称呼他这个。汤姆想带她去能跳舞的地方吃晚饭，他想和她跳舞，正好迈克尔要去剑桥待一晚上，排练大学生写的一系列独幕剧。他们能在一起待上好几个小时。

“你可以天亮了再回。”他说道。

“那我第二天的演出怎么办？”

“我们顾不上为此担心。”

她没有让他来剧院接她，当她到达他们选好的饭店时，他正在大厅里等她。在见到她的那一刻，他的脸上浮现喜悦之情。

“这么晚了，我担心你不会来了。”

“对不起，有些无聊的人在演出结束后过来找我，我无法摆脱他们。”

然而，事实并非如此。整个晚上，朱莉娅兴奋得好像第一次参加舞会的小女孩。她不由得想自己有多可笑。当她卸掉舞台妆容，为了赴宴重新打扮后，她又觉得不满意。她涂了蓝色的眼影，又擦掉，涂了腮红，又抹干净，换了另外一种颜色。

“您这是要做什么？”伊维问道。

“我想看起来像二十岁，你这个笨蛋。”

“如果再化下去，您看起来就像您现在的年纪了。”

她从未见过他穿晚礼服。他光芒四射如同一枚崭新的大头针。虽然他也就是普通个子，但瘦削的体形让他看上去很高。尽管他装出一副阅历丰富的样子，领班侍者为他们点菜时，他仍旧露出羞涩的模样，这让她有些感动。他们跳了舞，他跳得不好，不过，朱莉娅觉得他略微笨拙的样子很迷人。人们认出了她，她也意识到大家的注视让他觉得脸上有光。一对跳舞的年轻人走到他们的桌子前，向她问好。当他们离开后，他问道：

“那不是丹诺伦特侯爵和侯爵夫人吗？”

“是的。乔治还在伊顿公学读书时我就认识他了。”

汤姆目送他们离去。

“她本是塞西莉·劳斯顿小姐，对吗？”

“我忘记了，是吗？”

似乎朱莉娅对她一点兴趣都没有。不一会儿，又有一对儿从他们身边经过。

“看，那是莱巴德夫人。”

“她是谁？”

“你不记得了吗？几周前他们在位于柴郡的家中举办了一场盛大的聚会，威尔士亲王也去了。《旁观者》上登着呢。”

哦，他的消息都是从那儿得来的。可怜的小东西。他在报纸上读到那些名人的事情，时不时地会在饭店或者剧院看到他们本人。这对他来讲当然非常兴奋。浪漫。要是他知道他们有多无聊就好了！那种对于照片被登在画报上的人们的无邪的热情让他显得非常幼稚，她看着他，眼神中充满温柔。

“你以前有带过别的女演员来吃晚餐吗？”

他的脸变得通红。

“从来没有。”

她不愿让他付账单，她大概能猜到，这顿饭差不多花了他一周的薪水，但她明白，如果她提出付钱，会伤到他的自尊心。她随意地问了问时间，他本能地看了看手腕。

“我忘记戴手表了。”

她疑惑地看着他。

“你是把它当了吗？”

他又一次红了脸。

“不。我今晚穿衣服太着急了。”

只需看一眼他的领带，她就知道事实并非他所说的那样。他在骗她。她知道，为了请她吃晚餐，他当了自己的手表。她有些哽咽，恨不得立刻就将他拥入怀中并亲吻他蓝色的眼睛。她爱慕他。

“我们走吧。”她说道。

他们开车回到了他在塔维斯托克广场卧室兼客厅的家。

————————————————————

(1) 魏尔伦（Paul Verlaine，1844—1896），法国象征派诗人。

(2) 雅克·路易·大卫1800年为法国一位银行家的太太画的肖像画《雷卡米埃夫人像》的主人公，画中雷卡米埃夫人身着白色罗马式长袍，靠卧在罗马式卧榻上，长袍垂搭在靠榻前，色彩与形体相谐，呈现一种高雅古朴的休憩状态。

第十四章

第二天，朱莉娅去了卡地亚商店，买了一块手表送给汤姆·芬内尔，以补偿他当掉的那只。两三周后，正好是他的生日，她又送了他一个金烟盒。

“你知道吗，这是我这辈子最想要的东西。”

她在想他眼睛里是否有泪水。他激动地亲吻她。

在此之后，借着各种理由，她送了他珍珠饰纽、袖口链扣、马甲纽扣。给他准备礼物让她觉得兴奋无比。

“我什么都给不了你，这让我太难受了。”他说道。

“给我那只你为了请我吃饭而当掉的手表。”

那是一只小小的金表，价钱不会超过十英镑，但她喜欢时不时戴一下。

直到他们第一次共进晚餐之后，朱莉娅才肯承认，她爱上了汤姆。这件事情让她觉得震惊，但同时她也感到振奋。

“我以为我再也不会恋爱了。当然这段感情不会持续。但为什么我不能及时行乐呢？”

她决定一定要让他再来斯坦霍普广场。没过多久，机会就出现了。

“你还记得你的那个年轻会计吧，”她向迈克尔说道，“他叫汤姆·芬内尔。前几天晚上我出去吃晚餐时遇上了他，于是我邀请他下周日参加宴会。我们需要一个临时凑数的男宾客。”

“哦，你觉得他行吗？”

这是一个很盛大的宴会。就是因为这个缘故她邀请了他。她觉得能当面见到只在照片里见过的人，对他来说一定很开心。她已经意识到，他有些势利眼。这样更好；她可以介绍他认识他想认识的那些聪明人。朱莉娅很精明，她很清楚汤姆并不爱她。跟她发生感情纠葛纯粹为了满足他的虚荣心。他是一个性欲强烈的年轻男人，喜欢性生活。从一些暗示以及她逼他说出的故事来看，他从十七岁开始就跟很多女人上过床。他爱性本身而不是那个人。他把性爱看作天下最大的乐趣。而且她能理解为什么他在女人中间这么成功。他那副清瘦的身体有一些吸引人的东西，他瘦得皮包骨头，正因如此，他的衣服才显得那么合身，他的清秀干净让人着迷。他的羞涩加上他的胆大妄为让他令人无法抗拒。当一个妇人被当作年轻女子，会让她倍感荣幸，以至于就会干脆翻滚到床上去。

“当然，他所拥有的是性感。”

她知道，他的美貌来自他的年轻。当他变老时，他会变得干瘪、枯瘦、憔悴；他脸蛋儿上那迷人的潮红会变成紫光，而他精致的皮肤会布满皱纹，面露憔悴；可是，一想到她所爱上的关于他的一切只能持续短暂的时间，这种感觉让她内心更加充满柔情。她对他心生异样的怜悯之情。他富有青春活力，而她像小猫舔奶一样贪婪地享受着他的气息。但他并不是一个有趣的人。虽然他也会被朱莉娅的笑话逗乐，但他自己从没讲过笑话。她并不介意。他的沉闷让她感到宁静。跟他在一起时，她感到前所未有的轻松愉快，而她一个人的活跃足以抵得上两个人的。

人们不停地告诉朱莉娅她看起来年轻了十岁，并且她的表演空前优秀。她知道这是真的而且她知道这其中的原因。但她必须谨慎行事。她必须保持头脑清醒。查尔斯·泰默利总是说，一个女演员所需要的并不是聪慧，而是敏感，对于这一点他或许是对的；也许她并不聪明，但她的直觉敏锐，她相信自己的直觉。而她的直觉告诉她，绝对不能告诉汤姆她爱上了他。

她小心翼翼地告诉他，她并不想占有他，他可以自由地做他喜欢做的事情。她展示出一副认为此事荒唐可笑的态度，双方都不必看得过重。然而事实上她竭尽全力束缚住他，使他为她所有。他喜欢聚会，于是她带他去各种聚会。她让多莉和查尔斯·泰默利邀请他共进午宴。他喜欢跳舞，她就为他拿到舞会邀请。为了他，她会亲自去这些舞会，待上一个小时，她看得出，当周围的人围着她转的时候，他有多得意。她知道他被那些大人物吸引，于是她介绍他认识这些社会名流。幸运的是，迈克尔也喜欢他。迈克尔喜欢说教，而汤姆是个不错的倾听者。他在自己业务方面很精明。一天，迈克尔对她说：

“汤姆真是个聪明的家伙。他对所得税很懂行。他告诉我一种方法，能为我下次报税节省那么两三百英镑。”

正在寻找新演员的迈克尔，经常在晚上带他去看戏剧，要么在伦敦，或者是郊区，演出结束后他们会接上朱莉娅，三人共进晚餐。有时，迈克尔会邀请汤姆星期天一起打高尔夫，如果当天没有聚会，他会带汤姆回家一起吃晚餐。

“有个像他那样的年轻人在身边真不错，”他说道，“他让人不会老得生锈。”

汤姆非常喜欢这栋房子。他会和迈克尔玩西洋双陆棋，或者和朱莉娅玩单人纸牌戏，如果他们打开留声机，他便会负责更换唱片。

“对罗杰来说他会是个不错的朋友，”迈克尔说道，“汤姆头脑清醒，又比罗杰大许多。他应该会对罗杰产生很好的影响。不如邀请他和我们一起度假？”

（“幸亏我是个好演员。”）但她仍旧努力克制了一下自己，才避免那让她心脏怦怦直跳的狂喜从她的声音和脸上流露出来。“这主意倒不错，”她回答道，“如果你愿意，我会问问他。”

他们的戏剧会一直演到八月底，迈克尔在塔普洛租了一栋别墅，他们会在那儿度过盛夏。朱莉娅得去市里演出，迈克尔有业务需要时也得赶到市里去，但她白天和星期天都会待在乡下。汤姆有两星期假期，他欣然接受了邀请。

但有一天，朱莉娅注意到汤姆异常沉默。他脸色苍白，那生龙活虎的劲头也离他而去。她知道肯定有什么不对劲，但他不肯告诉她是什么；他只是说自己担心死了。最后，她强迫他坦白，原来他向一些商人借了钱，现在他被催着还债。她带他进入的生活圈子让他入不敷出，而跟她去参加盛大的宴会时，他羞于穿自己那廉价的衣服，于是他去了一家昂贵的裁缝铺，给自己定制了几套西服。为了还上这笔钱，他去赌马，结果他下赌注的马输掉了比赛。对于朱莉娅来说，他欠的钱不算什么，区区一百二十五英镑，在她看来，为了这样一件小事烦恼实在荒谬。她立刻说，她会给他这笔钱。

“哦，我不能。我不能拿一个女人的钱。”

他脸红了；仅仅是这种想法就让他感到耻辱。朱莉娅尽其甜言蜜语之所能。她跟他讲道理，她假装被冒犯，她甚至流了几滴眼泪，最终，算是他给她帮忙，才同意从她这里借走这笔钱。第二天，她给他送了封信，里面是两百英镑的银行支票。他给她打电话，告诉她那钱远远超出了他想要的。

“哦，我知道人们总是隐瞒他们欠债的真实数字，”她笑着说道，“我肯定你欠的钱比你告诉我的还要多。”

“我向你保证我没有说谎。我不会对你说谎。”

“那剩下的就以备不时之需吧。我讨厌我们出去吃晚餐时看你结账。还有出租车费和其他费用。”

“不，真的。这太丢人了。”

“真是胡说八道！你知道我的钱多得都不知如何处置。你连让我帮你摆脱困境从而获得的快乐都要吝惜吗？”

“你真的太好了。你不知道这对于我来说是多么大的解脱。我不知如何感谢你。”

但他的声音听起来很不安。可怜的年轻人，他太传统了。但她刚刚所说的是真的，给他钱让她体会到之前从未有过的激动；它在她的内心搅动起意外的激情。她在脑子里盘算好了另一个计谋，当汤姆和他们在塔普洛一起度假时，她可以轻松地实施。汤姆在塔维斯托克广场的那个卧室兼客厅的房子虽然乍看起来别有情趣，那些简陋的家具曾感动过她。但时间已经剥夺掉这些感动。有一两次，她在楼梯间遇到一些人，感觉他们都在用奇怪的眼神盯着她。有一个不检点的女管家打扫汤姆的房间，为他做早饭，朱莉娅觉得那女人知道他们之间的事情，并且在暗中监视自己。有一次朱莉娅在屋子里的时候有人试图打开锁着的门，当她离开时，那女管家正在打扫楼梯的扶栏。她厌恶地看了一眼朱莉娅。朱莉娅讨厌楼梯间弥漫着的发霉食物的味道，她那犀利的眼神不久就发现汤姆的房间也没那么干净。肮脏的窗帘，破烂的地毯，劣质的家具；这些都让她感到厌烦。正巧在不久前，一直在寻找合适投资的迈克尔在斯坦霍普广场附近买进了一排汽车间。他发现，如果把自己不用的租出去，自用的就可以不花一分钱。汽车间上面有好几个房间。他把它们分成两套小公寓，一套给他们的司机用，另一套他建议租出去。这套公寓目前还空着，朱莉娅向汤姆建议他应该租下来。那样的话就太棒了。他下班后她可以溜过去，和他待上一个小时；有时演出结束后她也可以顺道过去，没人会晓得。他们可以在那里逍遥自在。她同他讲起他们一起装饰屋子的乐趣；她敢肯定他们的房子里有很多他们不想要的东西，储存在他那里，也算帮了他们的忙。其余的他们可以一起购买。对于拥有自己的公寓这想法他有些心动，但根本不可能；那租金即使很少，也已超出了他的承受范围。朱莉娅知道这一点。她也知道如果她建议由她来出这笔钱他会很有骨气地拒绝。然而她想，在河畔悠闲而舒适的两个星期假期，她准能消除他的顾虑。她看出这个主意对他的诱惑有多大，她完全有把握想出办法使他相信他同意她的建议其实是帮她的忙。

“人们做他们想要做的事情不需要真正的理由，”她想道，“他们所要的其实是借口。”

朱莉娅满是兴奋地期待着汤姆来塔普洛做客。那样，她就可以同他早晨在河里泛舟，下午在花园里闲逛，多浪漫。由于罗杰就在身边，她决定他们之间不能胡来；攸关体面。但能够和他整天相处，就如同在天堂一样。当她有日场演出的时候，他可以和罗杰一起玩。

但事情跟她想象的完全不一样。她怎么也没想到，罗杰和汤姆会彼此喜欢，一拍即合。他们之间相差五岁，她想——或者说她曾考虑过这个问题的话——汤姆会把罗杰看成一个青少年，当然是个不错的小伙子，但也只是个小孩子，能帮你拿拿东西，当你不想被他打扰就可以打发他去自己玩。罗杰十七岁了。他长相不错，长着红色的头发和蓝色的眼睛，但是你所能夸他的也就是这些了。他既没有他母亲的活力和丰富的表情，也没有继承他父亲的俊朗。朱莉娅对他有些失望。当他还是个孩子时，朱莉娅经常和他照相，那时候他可爱极了。现在他有些迟钝，总是一副一本正经的样子。坦白讲，如果你仔细观察他，他唯一值得一提的就是他的牙齿和他的头发。朱莉娅很喜欢他，但觉得他有些愚钝呆板。当她单独和他在一起时，时间总是过得有些沉重缓慢。她跟他谈曲棍球这些她认为他一定会感兴趣的事情，但他对这些似乎也没什么可说的。她担心他不够聪明。

“当然他还很小，”她满是希望地说道，“可能等他长大一些就会变好。”

自打他上预备学校开始她就几乎不怎么见他。假期期间，她夜间总是演戏，他会跟他父亲或者别的男生朋友一同出去，星期天的时候他和他父亲会一起打高尔夫。如果碰上她中午出去吃饭，很有可能她两三天都不会见到他，除了早晨他去她房间的那短短几分钟。真可惜他无法一直都是那个可爱漂亮的小男孩，可以在她房间里玩耍但不会打扰到她，能笑嘻嘻地冲着照相机，一手搂着她的脖子，跟她一起拍照。有时她会去伊顿公学看望他，和他一起喝茶。当她看到他房间摆着几张她的照片时着实让她受宠若惊。她知道，当她去伊顿的时候，会在校园里多少引起一些轰动，而他的寄宿家庭的主人——布拉肯布里奇先生对她殷勤备至。半学年结束后，迈克尔和朱莉娅已经搬到了塔普洛，罗杰也直接回到了那里。朱莉娅热情地亲吻他。他并没有她期待的那样兴奋。他漫不经心，似乎突然间变得老成世故。

他随即告诉朱莉娅他想在圣诞节的时候离开伊顿，他认为他已经学到那里可以教给他的一切东西，他想去维也纳待几个月，在去剑桥之前学习德文。迈克尔本希望他去参军，但他坚决不同意。他还不知道自己将来想做什么。朱莉娅和迈克尔从一开始就非常担心他会选择登台做演员，但他似乎对此毫无兴趣。

“反正他什么事也成不了。”朱莉娅说道。

他过自己的日子。他去河边或者在花园里躺着看书。他十七岁生日时，朱莉娅送了他一辆时髦的敞篷车，于是他就开着它以极其危险的速度在乡间乱窜。

“有一点倒是很欣慰，”朱莉娅说道，“他倒不是个麻烦鬼。他自娱自乐的能力倒是不错。”

星期天，很多客人来他们家里做客，有男演员和女演员，一位应时作家，还有零星几个他们的名人朋友。朱莉娅发现这些聚会非常有趣，她知道人们喜欢来他们家里做客。在罗杰回家后的第一个星期天，来了一大批客人。罗杰对客人们很礼貌。他像个深谙世故的老手，作为主人之一，尽责地招待客人。但在朱莉娅看来，他显得说不出的冷漠，好像他在扮演一个他并没有投入其中的角色，而且她有种不安的感觉：他对这些人完全不接受，而且在冷眼评判他们。她的印象是，他一点都不把这些人当回事儿。

汤姆计划下个周六到达，她会在演出结束后开车带他去乡下。那是个月光如水的夜晚，那个时间路上已经空无一人。开车让人着迷。朱莉娅想要这么一直开下去。她依偎在他身上，而他不时地在黑暗中亲吻她。

“你开心吗？”她问道。

“当然。”

迈克尔和罗杰已经休息，餐厅里还放着晚餐。这幢寂静无声的房子使他们感到自己仿佛不请自来。他们可能是一对流浪者，夜里漫步到一幢陌生的房子，发现了一桌丰盛的饭菜摆在他们眼前。真是浪漫，甚至有些《天方夜谭》里故事的味道。朱莉娅带汤姆看了他的房间，就在罗杰房间的隔壁，之后就去休息了。她一直睡到第二天早上很晚才醒。那是个晴朗的日子。为了能和汤姆独处，她并没有邀请其他人来做客。当她穿好衣服，他们会一起去河里泛舟。她吃了早饭，沐了浴。她穿了一件和阳光明媚的河岸景色很协调的白色连衣裙，戴了一顶红色宽檐草帽，这帽子的颜色给她脸上抹了一层温暖的光泽。她几乎没有化妆。她照了照镜子，满意地笑了笑。她看上去非常年轻漂亮。她漫步到花园，那儿有一片草地延伸到河边，她看到迈克尔被一堆星期天的报纸包围着。他独自一人。

“我以为你去打高尔夫了。”

“没有，那俩男孩去了。我想如果我让他们单独去，他们能玩得尽兴。”他友好地笑了笑，“对我来说他们有些太活跃了。他们今早八点就在洗澡，吞下早餐后立刻就开着罗杰的车走了。”

“我很高兴他们能成为朋友。”

朱莉娅是认真的。不能和汤姆一起去河边让她有点失望，不过她很希望罗杰喜欢汤姆，她有种直觉：罗杰不会随意喜欢某个人；反正她能和汤姆一起待两个星期。

“我不介意告诉你，他们让我觉得自己是个该死的中年人。”迈克尔说道。

“胡说。你比他们都漂亮，你知道的，我的宝贝。”

迈克尔微微扬起下巴，缩了缩肚子。

男孩们直到午饭快准备好的时候才回来。

“对不起，我们回来得太晚了，”罗杰说道，“那儿乌泱乌泱的都是人，几乎每个发球区我们都得排队等着，我俩打了个平手。”

他们又饿又渴，又兴奋又满足。

“今天这里没请别人真是太好了，”罗杰说道，“我还担心你会请一堆人来做客，我们不得不表现得像小绅士一样。”

“我想休息一下会很不错。”朱莉娅说道。

罗杰看了她一眼。

“休息一下会对你有好处，妈妈。你看起来非常疲惫。”

（“他那双该死的眼睛。我绝对不能表现出我会介意。感谢上帝，我能表演。”）

她开心地笑了笑。

“我昨晚一夜未眠，在想我们到底要怎么处理你的那些粉刺。”

“我知道，简直太让人讨厌了，不是吗？汤姆说他曾经也长过。”

朱莉娅看了汤姆一眼。他穿着网球衫，领口敞开，头发蓬松，阳光照射着他的脸，他看起来难以置信的年轻。他看上去一点都不比罗杰大。

“不论怎样，他的鼻子都会蜕皮，”罗杰笑着说道，“那时他就成了一道风景了。”

朱莉娅感到微微的不适。在她看来，似乎汤姆摆脱了那年长的几岁，以至于他不仅仅在年龄上变成了罗杰的同龄人。他们讨论一堆无聊的事情。他们食量巨大，还大杯大杯地喝啤酒。迈克尔，饮食依旧极为节制，充满乐趣地看着他们。他欣赏他们的年轻和旺盛的精力。他让朱莉娅想起一只躺着晒太阳的老狗，轻轻地在地上拍打着自己的尾巴，看着一对小狗在它身边玩闹。他们在草坪上喝了咖啡。朱莉娅觉得在那儿的阴凉里坐着，看着小河，非常舒适。汤姆穿着白色长裤，显得修长又优雅。她以前从未见过他抽烟斗。她觉得他这样子莫名动人。但是罗杰在取笑他。

“你抽烟斗是因为它让你感到更男人还是因为你喜欢？”

“闭嘴。”汤姆说道。

“咖啡喝完了？”

“是的。”

“走吧，我们到河上去。”

汤姆向她抛去一个疑惑的眼神，被罗杰看到了。

“哦，没事的，你无须为我尊敬的双亲操心，他们有星期天的报纸陪伴。妈妈刚刚送了我一艘赛艇。”

（“我不能发脾气。我不能发脾气。我怎么这么蠢，为什么要送他一艘赛艇？”）

“好吧，”她说道，脸上带着宽容的微笑，“去河上玩吧，但小心别掉下去。”

“即使掉下去了也不会伤到我们。我们会回来喝茶的。球场标好了吗，爸爸？喝完茶我们想去打网球。”

“我敢说你父亲能再喊来一个人，这样你就能打双打了。”

“哦，没关系。单打更有趣，而且运动量也更大。”然后罗杰对汤姆说，“我们赛跑，看谁先到船屋。”

汤姆飞奔而去，罗杰紧随其后。迈克尔拿起一份报纸，找着他的眼镜。

“他们处得不错，不是吗？”

“看来是这样。”

“我担心罗杰在这儿跟我们单独待着会很无聊。有个人能陪他玩挺不错的。”

“你不觉得罗杰有点不体贴吗？”

“你是说打网球吗？哦，我亲爱的，我玩不玩无所谓。这俩男孩想自己玩再正常不过了。在他们看来，我是个老东西了，他们会觉得我会毁了他们的比赛。归根到底，最要紧的是他们玩得开心。”

朱莉娅深感内疚。迈克尔是很单调的，只知道鼓弄他的钱，还很自满，但他很善良，一点都不自私！他没有嫉妒之情。只要不花他的钱，使别人快乐会让他感到真正的满足。她对迈克尔的想法一清二楚。确实，他的思想一向平庸陈腐；但另一方面，他绝无半点让人羞耻的念头。他值得拥有她的爱慕之情，可她却不可抑制地对他生厌，这真让人懊恼。

“我觉得你作为一个男人比我作为一个女人要好得多，我的甜心。”她说道。

他冲她友善地笑了笑，轻轻地摇了摇头。

“不，亲爱的，我外表很棒，但你有天赋。”

朱莉娅咯咯笑了。你能从一个永远不知道你在说什么的男人身上得到不少乐趣。但当他们评论一个女演员有天赋的时候，他们到底指的是什么？朱莉娅也经常问自己，到底是什么让她置身于同辈人之上。她也曾被众人诋毁。有一段时间，朱莉娅总是被拿来和这个或者那个当时走红的女演员进行对她不利的比较，但现在没有人对她的卓越演技提出异议了。她确实不像电影明星那样在世界上享有盛名；她曾试过演电影，但并没有成功；她那张在舞台上灵活并富有表现力的脸在却不知为什么在电影银幕上不奏效。一次试镜后，在迈克尔的同意下，她拒绝再接受时不时向她投来的邀请。她那庄重的态度为她赢来不少有用的曝光。但朱莉娅并不嫉妒电影明星；他们来来去去；她一直都在。有机会时，她会去观看伦敦剧院里那些扮演主角的女演员的表演。她慷慨地赞美她们，而且她的赞美很真诚。有时，她甚至觉得她们演得那么好，以至于她无法理解为什么人们对她要大惊小怪。以她的聪明才智，她不可能不知道大众对她的评价，但她并没有恃才傲物，自视甚高。她的表演完全出于自然，根本没法想象可能有另外的表演方法，但是人们似痴若狂地叫好不止，这一直使她惊奇。评论家赞美她表演的多样性。他们尤其赞美她塑造角色的能力。她并没有意识到她在刻意地观察人们，但当她开始研习一个新角色时，种种模糊的回忆就不知从哪里涌现出来，于是她发现她知道她要演的这个角色的方方面面，而此前她对此毫不知情。想起她认识或者她在大街上、聚会上遇到的人都会对她有所帮助；然后她将这些回忆同她的个性相结合，这样就构建了一个基于事实但又被她的经验、表演技巧和惊人的吸引力丰富的人物形象。人们以为她只在台上的这两三个小时里进行表演；他们不知道当她表面上看起来全神贯注地跟别人讲话或者专注于什么事情的时候，她所扮演的角色都一直待在她的脑子里。她经常觉得，她是两个人：一个是女演员，受大众欢迎的、伦敦最会穿衣服的女人，这是个影子；而她晚上要扮演的那个女人，那是实质。

“我要是知道天赋是什么才见鬼呢，”她对自己说道，“但这一点我很肯定，如果我能变回十八岁，我会愿意付出一切。”

但她知道这不是真的。如果她有机会回到过去，她真的会吗？不。不会。她看重的，并不是知名度，或者你所谓的成名，也不是她对观众的掌控，观众对她怀有的真诚的爱，更不是这些所能带给她的金钱；她看重的，是她感到来自体内的力量，她对角色这种媒介的掌控，这让她欣喜若狂。她能进入一个角色，也许是一个不太好的角色，台词可笑，但凭借她的个性，她的灵巧机敏，她能够为这个角色注入生命。没有人能像她这样处理一个角色。有时，她感觉自己像上帝。

“而且，”她笑道，“汤姆那会儿也还没有出生呢。”

他愿意和罗杰一起玩是很自然的事情。他们属于一代人。今天是他假期的第一天，她必须让他好好享受；未来还有两周呢。他不久就会对跟一个十七岁的男孩整天待在一起感到厌倦。罗杰是很可爱，但他很无趣；她不打算因母爱而看不见这一点。她必须十分注意，不要显现出半点困扰的样子。从一开始她就下决心，她不会对汤姆有任何束缚；如果他感到他欠她什么，那会非常要命。

“迈克尔，为什么你不把那套公寓租给汤姆？现在他通过了考试，已经是一个注册会计了，不能继续在一间卧室兼客厅的房子里了。”

“这主意不错。我会向他建议的。”

“这样一来，也省去了中介的费用。我们能帮他装修房子。我们有一堆存起来不用的东西。与其放在阁楼里发霉，不如让他使用。”

汤姆和罗杰回来后吃了饱饱的一顿茶点，然后接着去打网球，直到天色暗了下来。晚饭后，他们玩多米诺骨牌。朱莉娅继续扮演一个年轻的母亲，欢喜地看着她的儿子和他的男伴朋友。她早早地上了床。不多一会儿，他们俩也上了楼。他们的房间就在她的正上方。她听到罗杰进入了汤姆的房间。他们开始聊天，她和他们房间的窗户都开着，她听到他们热烈交谈的声音。她恼怒着他们哪来那么多话聊。她一向觉得他们俩都不太健谈。不多一会儿后，迈克尔的声音打断了他们。

“现在，孩子们，你们都去睡觉。明天你们可以接着聊。”

她听到他们在笑。

“好的，爸爸。”罗杰喊道。

“一对话匣子，说你们俩呢。”

她又听到罗杰的声音。

“好的，晚安，老男孩。”

然后是汤姆衷心的回答：“再会，朋友。”

“白痴！”她生气地对自己说。

第二天早晨，当她正在吃早饭时，迈克尔走进她的房间。

“那俩男孩已经去亨特科姆打高尔夫了。他们想玩几轮，问是否需要回来吃午餐。我跟他们说不需要。”

“我不太喜欢汤姆把这里当成了旅店。”

“哦，我的宝贝，他们就是一对孩子。我说，让他们尽情开心吧。”

一整天她都见不到汤姆，为了及时赶到剧场，她必须五六点的时候就要起程前往伦敦。迈克尔当然可以一团和气地任凭他们怎么做。但她受伤了。她有点想哭。他准是没有把她放在心上，现在她心里想的全是汤姆；她本来下定决心，今天定要和昨日有所不同。她一醒来就抱定要宽容大度，要逆来顺受，但她没有准备好这当头一击。

“报纸送到了吗？”她闷闷不乐地问道。

她内心满是怒火地开车到了城里。

接下来的一天并没有好多少。男孩们没有去打高尔夫，但他们玩起了网球。他们无休止的活动深深地激怒了朱莉娅。汤姆穿着短裤，光着腿，上身穿板球衫，看起来不超过十六岁。他们一天洗三四次澡，他无法让自己的头发贴在头皮上，一旦头发干了，乱蓬蓬的鬈发就会铺满头顶。这样他看起来愈发年轻，但是，也更加迷人。朱莉娅心里难过。她感到他的行为莫名其妙地变了；有罗杰的陪伴，他已经不是那个伦敦城里对自己衣着小心翼翼、讲究着装合宜的年轻人了，他变成了一个懒散的小男生。他没有一点暗示，甚至没有一个眼神暴露过，他是她的情人；他对待她的态度就好像她只是罗杰的母亲。他说的每一句评论，无论淘气还是礼貌地讲，都在暗示她属于上一代人。他的行为没有丝毫向一个迷人女性献殷勤的意味，而是对一个没出嫁的姑姑所展示的宽容和亲切。

朱莉娅恼恨汤姆竟俯首帖耳地围着一个比他小得多的孩子转。这说明他缺乏个性。但是她不怪他；她怪罗杰。罗杰的自私令她厌恶。这也可以用他年纪还轻来搪塞。除了对他自己，他对别人的快乐的无动于衷显示出他可鄙的性情。他既不聪明也不体贴。他的所作所为就好像这房子、仆人，还有他的父母都是为了他的方便而存在的。她多次想要严厉训斥他，却总不敢在汤姆面前扮演一个训子的母亲的角色。并且，当你斥责罗杰的时候，他会表现出深深受伤的样子，像一头受惊的雌鹿，让人十分恼火，他会让你觉得你很不友善且不公正。她也可以展示出那个样子，那是他从她这里遗传的一种眼神；在舞台上她一次又一次地使用这种眼神以达到感人的效果，她知道这眼神说明不了什么，不过当她在他的眼睛里看到这种神情时，却让她心烦意乱。只要一想到他的这种眼神，就会让她对他变得温柔。那种情感上的突然变化让她看到了真相：她嫉妒罗杰，疯狂地嫉妒。这一认识多少让她有点震惊；她不知道该大笑还是该感到羞耻。她思索了一会儿。

“好吧，我要毁了他的计划。”

她不会让接下来的星期天像之前那样度过了。感谢上帝，汤姆是个势利的人。“一个女人通过她的魅力吸引男人，通过他们的恶习掌控他们。”她喃喃道，想着这是她自己发明的格言，还是她演的某个剧里的台词。

她吩咐仆人打了几个电话。她邀请丹诺伦特夫妇来共度周末。查尔斯·泰默利正在亨利镇，也接受了星期天的邀请，并会带着他的主人——财政大臣梅休·布赖恩斯顿爵士——一同前来。为了让他和丹诺伦特夫妇开心——因为她知道上层阶级的人们不喜欢在他们认为是波希米亚式的圈子里彼此相遇，却喜欢遇到各种各样的艺术家——她特地邀请了跟她搭档做男主角的阿尔奇·德克斯特和他美丽的妻子，阿尔奇的妻子用婚前的姓名格雷斯·哈德威尔做艺名。她非常确定，会有一对侯爵夫妇在周围徘徊，还有一位内阁大臣让人印象深刻，汤姆不会跟罗杰去打高尔夫或者在赛艇里待一下午。在这样的宴会上，罗杰会默默地守着一个学校男生的本分，没有人会注意到他，而汤姆会看到她是多么的光芒四射。心里期盼胜利到来的日子里，她咬紧牙关竭力忍受。她很少看到罗杰和汤姆。在有日场演出的日子，她根本见不到他们的面。他们如果不玩什么体育游戏，就开着罗杰的汽车在乡野间乱兜。

戏剧结束后朱莉娅载着丹诺伦特夫妇来到乡下。罗杰已经上床休息了，但迈克尔和汤姆还在等着和他们一起吃晚餐。那是一顿不错的晚餐。仆人们也已经休息了，他们自己动起手来。朱莉娅注意到汤姆害羞又热切地确保丹诺伦特夫妇的所有要求得到满足，还注意到当他能有所效劳时急忙跃起的殷勤劲儿。他殷勤得有点用力过猛。丹诺伦特夫妇是一对没什么架子的年轻人，他们从未想过他们的头衔会让人觉得有什么了不起，当汤姆拿走他用过的盘子并递给他一个新盘子，让他好继续吃下一道菜时，乔治·丹诺伦特显得有些尴尬。

“罗杰明天不会打高尔夫了，我觉得。”朱莉娅对自己说。

他们一直说说笑笑到凌晨三点，当汤姆对她说晚安时，他眼里闪烁着光芒；但是因为爱还是香槟，那她就不清楚了。他紧紧握了一下她的手。

“真是个令人愉快的聚会。”他说道。

朱莉娅下楼走进花园时，时间已经不早了，她穿着一件蝉翼纱的衣裳，特别漂亮，她看见罗杰坐在长椅上，手里拿着一本书。

“在读书？”她说道，扬起她那着实漂亮的眉毛，“为什么不去打高尔夫了？”

罗杰看起来有点闷闷不乐。

“汤姆说太热了。”

“哦？”她迷人地笑了，“我还担心你在想你应该留下来照顾我的客人们。这儿会来很多人，没有你我们也能轻松地招呼他们。其他人呢？”

“不知道。汤姆正和塞西莉·丹诺伦特在那儿装模作样呢。”

“她很漂亮，你知道。”

“在我看来，今天将会无聊透顶。”

“我希望汤姆不会这么觉得。”她说道，好像她真的很担心。

罗杰没有说话。

这一天过得真如她所希望的那样。她确实也没怎么见到汤姆，但是罗杰见得更少。汤姆在丹诺伦特夫妇那里大受欢迎；他向他们解释如何避免支付那么多的所得税。他恭敬地听财政大臣讲舞台艺术，听阿尔奇·德克斯特分析政治形势。朱莉娅状态极佳。阿尔奇·德克斯特脑子很灵活，不仅肚子里有一堆剧院的故事，而且还能把它们讲得出神入化。他们俩让一桌宾客午餐期间开怀大笑。下午茶后，大家打网球打累了，一定要让朱莉娅（也并非违背她的意愿）模仿格拉迪斯·库珀、康斯坦斯·科利尔和格蒂·劳伦斯的表演。但朱莉娅并没有忘记查尔斯·泰默利是她最忠诚的、没有获得报答的情人，因此她特意和他在黄昏中散了一会儿步。跟他在一起，她既不需要嘻嘻哈哈也不需要才华横溢，她很温柔沉静。虽然白天的时候她的表现让人觉得才华横溢，但此刻她的心在痛；她叹着气，神情哀伤，断断续续的话语真诚地使他明白，虽然她的职业生涯屡屡成功，但她的生活却空洞乏味，她不禁觉得自己错过了什么。有时她会想到那不勒斯湾索伦多的别墅。一个美丽的梦。也许如果她开口，她就会拥有幸福；她一直都是个傻子；舞台上的成功说到底不就是一种幻影？丑角们。人们从未意识到那部戏剧有多真实；总是“把戏演下去”(1)那一套之类的。她极度寂寞。当然，她无须告诉查尔斯她心痛并非因为失去的机会，而是因为一个年轻人喜欢和她儿子打高尔夫胜过和她做爱。

但是后来，朱莉娅和阿尔奇·德克斯特待在一起。晚餐后，他们全都坐在客厅里，他们两人没有事先跟大家打招呼，就开始随便交谈着，突然吵起架来，就好像他们是一对情侣在争风吃醋。一时间，大家都没有意识到这是个笑话，直到他们相互的指责变得越来越过分，大家才知道上当受骗了，众人大笑起来。之后，他们即兴表演一个喝醉了酒的绅士在杰明街上勾搭一名法国妓女的场面。在这之后，正当那一小撮观众哄堂大笑之际，他们又严肃认真地演出了《群鬼》中阿尔文太太企图勾引曼德斯牧师的那场戏。最后，为了彰显戏剧效果，他们表演了过去在戏剧界聚会上经常演出的节目。这虽是一部英文版的契诃夫的戏剧，但情绪激动之处，听起来倒像是俄语版的。朱莉娅动用了她所有演悲剧的天赋，但又强调它的闹剧性质，因此妙趣横生。她把心里真正的苦痛倾注在戏里，而又以生动的诙谐感予以嘲弄。观众们在座位上前仰后合，捧腹大笑，以至于笑得痛苦地呻吟起来。或许朱莉娅从来没有演得这样精彩过。她是在演给汤姆看，演给他一个人看。

“我看见了伯恩哈特和雷耶纳。”财政大臣说道，“我见到了杜丝、爱伦·泰瑞和肯德尔夫人。死而无憾。(2)”

朱莉娅，光芒四射，身子后仰陷入椅子里，大口喝干了一杯香槟。

“如果我没有坏了罗杰的计策，我就把名字倒着写。”她心里想道。

即便这样，当朱莉娅第二天一早下楼时，发现那两个小伙子已经去打高尔夫了。迈克尔开车送丹诺伦特夫妇回伦敦。朱莉娅很疲惫。当汤姆和罗杰回来吃午餐时，她费劲地表现出很开心健谈的样子。下午，他们三人到河里划船，但朱莉娅觉得，他们带着她并不是因为想要如此，而是他们不得不这么做。想起她是如何期盼汤姆的假期时，她忍住没让自己叹气。现在她正计算着假期还剩多久。当她坐进去伦敦的车里时，她深吸一口气。她并没有生汤姆的气，而是被深深地伤害了；她气她自己，因为她对自己的情感完全失去了控制。但当她回到剧场，她感觉自己如同从噩梦中醒来一般摆脱了对他的痴迷；在她的更衣室里，她重新掌控了自己，日常生活的琐事变得不值一提。当自由触手可及时，一切都不重要了。

这周就这样过去了。迈克尔、罗杰和汤姆都过得不错。他们游泳，打网球，打高尔夫，在河里漂流。假期还有四天就结束了。假期还有仅仅三天就结束了。

（“我现在能坚持了。等回到伦敦一切就会不同。我不能显示出我有多难过。我必须假装一切正常。”）

“我们真是捡到便宜了，竟有这么好的天气。”迈克尔说道，“汤姆真是来对了，不是吗？可惜他不能再待一周。”

“是啊，真的太可惜了。”

“我觉得他对罗杰来说是个不错的朋友。一个完全正常的、心地纯洁的英国男孩。”

“哦，完全是这样。”（“大笨蛋，大笨蛋。”）

“他们吃饭的样子让人十分愉快。”

“是的，他们看起来很享受自己的食物。”（“上帝，我希望他们能被噎死。”）

汤姆星期一早晨会乘早班火车回伦敦。德克斯特夫妇在伯恩头镇有座房子，并邀请他们星期天一起吃午餐。他们将一起乘汽艇去。既然汤姆的假期快要结束了，朱莉娅很高兴她连眉头都没有皱一下，从而流露她心中的愤怒。她很确定，汤姆不知道他深深地伤害了她。到头来她必须要宽容大度，他还只是个孩子，而且如果你真要仔细算起来，她都可以做他的妈妈了。她对他的感情本来就是荒唐的，但现在既然已经产生了，她情不自禁；她从一开始就告诉自己，她不能让他感觉到她对他有什么要求。星期天晚上没有别人来吃晚餐。她想在最后一晚上能单独和他在一起；虽然这是不可能的，但他们可以单独在花园里散会儿步。

“我在想他是否注意到，自他来到这里就没有吻过我？”

他们可以去划船。要是能在他怀里待几分钟就太美了，那样能弥补所有这一切。

德克斯特夫妇的聚会很戏剧化。阿尔奇·德克斯特的妻子格雷斯·哈德威尔在演音乐喜剧，还有一群在她当时参加演出的戏里跳舞的漂亮姑娘，朱莉娅非常自然地出演了一个没有架子的头牌女演员的角色。她对这些在歌舞班中白金色头发被烫成波浪形、只拿三英镑周薪的年轻姑娘显得很亲切。很多客人带来了柯达相机，她友好地和他们拍照。当格雷斯·哈德威尔在作曲家的伴奏下唱着自己那著名的歌曲时，她报以热烈的掌声。当那个逗趣的女人模仿她最出名的角色，她跟其他人一样开怀大笑。一切都欢快喧闹，轻松快活。朱莉娅自己也很享受，但到七点的时候，她不想再待下去了。当她正在感谢两位宴会主人的热情款待时，罗杰来到她身边。

“我说，妈妈，有一群人要去梅登海德吃饭跳舞，他们想让我和汤姆同去。你不介意的，对吧？”

此刻，热血冲向了面颊，她的脸红扑扑的。她禁不住厉声问道：

“那你们打算怎么回来？”

“哦，没关系，我们会让人载我们回去。”

她无助地看着他，不知道该说什么。

“一定会开心极了。汤姆非常想去。”

她的心沉了下来。她费了极大的劲儿才没有发脾气。她控制住了自己。

“好吧，亲爱的。不要玩得太晚。记住汤姆明早还要早起。”

汤姆已经走了过来，听到了最后这句话。

“你确定你不介意？”他问道。

“当然不。我希望你玩得开心。”

她笑靥如花地望着他，但眼睛中却是深深的恨意。

“我也很高兴这俩孩子走了，”当他们返回汽艇时迈克尔说道，“我们很久都没有过一个属于我们俩的夜晚了。”

她紧紧攥着拳头，阻止自己告诉他闭上他的蠢嘴。她恼羞成怒。这是压垮她的最后一根稻草。汤姆已经忽视了她两周，他对她甚至没有起码的礼节，而她却一直如天使一般。世界上没有任何女人会像她一样展示出如此耐心。换任何别的女人，早就会跟他讲，如果他不懂基本的社交礼仪，最好赶紧离开。自私，愚蠢，平庸，他就是这样的人。她甚至希望他不是明天就离开，这样她便可以享受将他的行李扔出门外的乐子。一个微不足道的小人物竟敢如此对待她；诗人、内阁大臣和世袭贵族都会为了和她共餐的机会而放弃最重要的约会，而他为了和一群头发漂白成金色不懂演戏的蠢货跳舞把她扔在一边。这足以说明他有多愚蠢。你还以为他会心存感激。不应该吗？他穿的这身西服就是她付的钱。还有他那引以为傲的烟盒，难道不是她给他的吗？还有他戴的那戒指。我的天，她得跟他扯平了。没错，而且她知道她该怎么做。她知道他最敏感的地方，知道如何做才能最残忍地伤到他。那样会戳到他的痛处。当她在脑子里反复想着这计谋时，她感到一点安慰。她迫不及待地要执行此计，一到家便径直回了房间。她从包里拿出四个一英镑和十便士，然后写了一封简短的信。

亲爱的汤姆：

因明天早晨就见不到你了，特送些钱供你打赏使用。给管家三镑，给为你洗衣服的女仆一镑，给司机十便士。

朱莉娅

她喊来伊维，告诉她这封信应该由喊汤姆起床的女仆递给他。当她下楼吃晚餐时，她感到舒服多了。吃饭期间，她和迈克尔聊得有声有色，之后，他们玩了会儿伯齐克纸牌。即使她绞尽脑汁想一礼拜，也想不出比这更能羞辱汤姆的事情了。

但当她躺到床上后却无法入睡。她在等罗杰和汤姆回来。有个念头让她坐立不安。或许汤姆会意识到他的行为很糟糕，如果他仔细想一想，他肯定能看出他让她多不开心；他可能会感到抱歉，当他回来后，跟罗杰说晚安后，会悄悄来到她屋里。如果他这么做，她会原谅他的一切。那封信可能还在管家的储藏室里；她能轻易地溜下去把它取回来。终于来了一辆车。她打开灯看了看时间，三点了。她听到两个年轻人上楼，各自回了房间。她等着。她一直开着床头灯，这样他开门时能看清楚。她会假装她睡着了，当他惦着脚尖走过来，她会慢慢睁开眼，冲他笑笑。她等待着。在安静的夜晚，她听到他上了床，熄了灯。她目视前方一会，耸了一下肩，打开她床头的抽屉，从一个小瓶中取出两三片安眠药。

“如果我再不睡觉，我就要疯了。”

————————————————————

(1) 原文为意大利语，Vesti la giubba。

(2) 原文为拉丁语，Nunc Dimittis。

第十五章

朱莉娅直到十一点才醒来。在她的信中夹着一封没有邮票的信。她认出汤姆干净得像商务文书一样的字迹，把信拆了开来。信封里有四英镑和十便士。她感到有点不适。她并不知道自己希望他怎么回复那封傲慢得让人感到屈辱的信。她没想过他会回复。她感到困扰，她本想就是伤一伤他的感情，但现在她担心自己做得有点过了。

“不管怎样，我希望他付了仆人们小费。”她咕哝着让自己安心。之后，她耸耸肩膀，“他会回心转意的。让他知道我并不是一直都那么甜美对他没坏处。”

但是，她一整天都是若有所思的样子。当她到达剧院时，一个包裹正等着她。她一看包裹上的地址，就知道里面是什么。伊维问她是否要打开。

“不用。”

但当她独自一人时，她立刻打开了包裹。里面有袖扣、马甲纽扣、珍珠饰纽、腕表和汤姆引以为荣的烟盒。没有一句解释。她的心沉了下来，她意识到自己在发抖。

“我真是个该死的傻瓜！为什么我不收敛我的脾气？”

她的心脏痛苦地跳动着。她无法怀着如此痛苦的心情上台演出，她会演得非常糟糕；无论如何她都必须跟他谈一谈。他住的那栋房子里有部电话，在他的房间里设有分机。她给他打了电话。幸运的是他在家。

“汤姆。”

“是？”

回答前他沉默了一会儿，他的声音里充满了不耐烦。

“这是什么意思？为什么你把这些东西都送回来了？”

“你今早收到那些钱了吗？”

“是的。我完全搞不懂是怎么回事。我冒犯到你了吗？”

“哦，没有，”他回答道，“我喜欢被当成一个男宠对待。我喜欢钱被人丢在脸上的感觉，连我的小费都要别人给我。我觉得你没有给我回伦敦的三等座火车票的票钱很奇怪。”

虽然朱莉娅目前正处在令人可怜的焦虑中，她连话都说不出口，但听到他笨拙的讽刺，几乎笑了出来。他真是个小傻子。

“但你不会觉得我想要故意伤害你吧。以你对我的了解，你肯定知道，那是我绝对不会做的事情。”

“那就更糟糕了。”（“该死。”朱莉娅心里想。）“我从来不该让你送我那些礼物。我压根不该让你借我那些钱。”

“我不知道你在说什么。肯定有什么可怕的误会。今晚演出结束后来接我吧，我们讲清楚。我肯定能解释明白。”

“我今晚跟我家人去吃晚饭，会睡在家里。”

“那明天吧。”

“明天我也有事。”

“我必须见你，汤姆。凭我们的交情，不能就这样分手。你不能不听我解释就指责我。为我根本没有犯过的错而惩罚我，这太不公平了。”

“我觉得我们不见面会更好。”

朱莉娅感到越来越绝望。

“但我爱你，汤姆。我爱你。让我再见你一次，如果你还生我的气，那我们也只好就此结束。”

电话那端是一阵长久的沉默。

“好吧。周三日场演出结束后我会过来。”

“不要把我想成没心肝的人，汤姆。”

她挂了电话。不管怎么样，他还是要来的。她收起他还给她的这些东西，并把它们藏到确保伊维看不到的地方。她脱了衣服，穿上她粉色的旧晨衣，开始化妆。她心情不好：这是她第一次告诉他她爱他。她不得不受到这样的侮辱，求他来看她，这让她恼怒不已。在这以前，总是他主动要求她来做伴的。想到现在他们之间的位置已公然颠倒过来了，她心中怏怏不乐。

周三朱莉娅的日场演出很糟糕。热浪影响营业，场内气氛冷淡。朱莉娅对此漠不关心。惶恐不安的情绪折磨着她的心，她顾不上考虑戏演得怎么样了。（“他们究竟干吗要在这样的日子来剧院看戏呢？”）等戏演完了，她感到高兴。

“我在等芬内尔先生，”她告诉伊维，“我跟他见面时不想被人打扰。”

伊维没有回答。朱莉娅看了她一眼，只见她看起来神情冷酷。

（“让她见鬼去吧。我才不管她在想什么！”）

他现在应该已经到了。已经过了五点。他一定会来；毕竟，他承诺了，不是吗？她穿上一件晨衣，不是她化妆时穿的那件，而是一件杏色的男式丝绸晨衣。伊维没完没了地在那儿整理东西。

“看在上帝的分上，别小题大做了，伊维。让我独自待会。”

伊维没有说话。她一丝不苟地按照朱莉娅的要求继续按部就班地整理梳妆台上的物品。

“该死，我对你说话呢，你干吗不回答？”

伊维转过身，看着她。她若有所思地挠了挠鼻孔。

“您可能是位伟大的女演员……”

“从这里滚出去。”

卸了舞台妆后，朱莉娅没有再涂脂抹粉，除了遮挡了一下她轻微的黑眼圈。她皮肤光滑白皙，但没有脸蛋儿上的胭脂和嘴唇上的口红，她面容憔悴。她身上的男式晨衣让她显得无助、脆弱又潇洒。她的心脏跳得让她难受，她非常焦虑，可是照着镜子她却喃喃自语地说：《艺术家的生涯》中最后一幕里的咪咪。几乎是下意识的，她像得了肺病一样咳嗽了一两声。她关掉了梳妆台上雪亮的台灯，在沙发上躺了一会儿。此刻响起了敲门声，伊维通报芬纳尔先生来了。朱莉娅伸出了一只白皙纤细的手。

“我躺一会儿。恐怕我身体不太舒服。你自己找把椅子坐。你能来真是太好了。”

“很抱歉。你怎么了？”

“哦，没什么。”她努力用苍白的嘴唇笑了笑，“过去这两三个晚上我睡得不太好。”

她把一双美丽的眼睛转向他，沉默地盯着他看了一会儿。他的脸阴沉沉的，但她看出他很害怕。

“我在等你告诉我你对我有什么不满意。”最终她声音低沉地说。

她注意到那声音有点颤抖，但很自然。（“上帝，我相信我也很害怕。”）

“回头重谈那个没什么意义了。我唯一要告诉你的就是：我恐怕无法立刻还给你我欠的那两百英镑，我没有那么多钱，但我会一点一点还给你。我讨厌让你容我些时间，但我也没办法。”

她从沙发上坐了起来，双手贴到她那碎了的心上。

“我不明白。我两个晚上都没有睡觉，翻来覆去想这件事情。我以为我要疯了。我一直都在试图理解，但我无法明白，做不到。”

（“这是我在哪个剧里说的台词？”）

“哦，是的，你可以，你非常明白。你在生我的气，你想要报复我。而且你也这么做了。你报复得太准了。你再明白不过地表达了对我的蔑视。”

“但我为什么要报复你？为什么要生你的气？”

“因为我和罗杰去了梅登海德的那个聚会，而你希望我回家。”

“但我告诉你去吧。我说了我希望你过得愉快。”

“我知道你说了，但你的眼睛闪烁着怒火。我不想去，但罗杰非常想去。我告诉他我觉得我们应该回去，与你和迈克尔吃晚餐，但他说你会很乐意我们离开，我不想就此小题大做。等我看到你怒气冲天的时候，回头已经来不及了。”

“我没有生气。我不知道你脑子里为什么有这样的想法。你当然应该去那个聚会。你不会认为我会坏到不肯让你在你两周的假期里寻点乐子吧。我可怜的小乖乖，我唯一担心的就是你会感到无聊。我太想让你过得开心了。”

“那你为什么给我送来那些钱，写那封信？太侮辱人了。”

朱莉娅的声音在发抖。她的下巴开始颤抖，她的肌肉不听使唤的样子令人莫名地感动。汤姆不自在地移开了视线。

“一想到你把你辛苦挣的钱浪费在小费上，我就无法忍受。我知道你并不富有，而且高尔夫球场的场地费肯定花了你不少钱。我讨厌那些和年轻男人们约会并让他们支付一切的女人。这样做太不顾及别人了。我对待你就如同对待罗杰一样。我从未想过那么做会伤了你的自尊。”

“你愿意发誓吗？”

“当然愿意。我的上帝，这么几个月的相处后，难道你还如此不了解我吗？如果你所认为的是真的，那我应该是一个多么残酷卑鄙的女人，一个多么无情下流低俗的禽兽！我在你心里就是这样的吗？”

一个无法回答的问题。

“不管怎样都不重要了。我不应该接受你那些昂贵的礼物，还让你借钱给我。这让我陷入糟糕的处境。我之所以认为你轻视我，是因为我觉得你有权利轻视我。事实是我没有钱去跟那些比我富有那么多的人交往。我真蠢，还以为能这样做。这段时间很有趣，我过了一段精彩的时光，可到现在结束了，我不打算继续见你了。”

她深深地叹了口气。

“你一点都不在乎我。这才是你的意思。”

“你这么说可不公平。”

“你是我的一切。你知道这点。我很孤独，与你的友情对我来说意义重大。我周围都是一群蹭吃蹭喝的寄生虫，而我知道你并不图我什么。我觉得我可以依靠你。我特别喜欢和你待在一起。你是这世界上唯一一个与我相处时，我可以完全做自己的人。你不知道能帮得上你一点忙会让我多开心吗？我送那些小礼物并不是为了你，而是为了我自己；看到你使用我给你的那些东西让我非常开心。如果你对我有一点爱怜之心的话，这些礼物就不会使你感到羞辱，你会因为欠我的情而受到感动。”

她再一次把眼睛转向他。她总是能很轻易地哭出来，而现在她又这么难过，哭对她而言根本无须费劲。他从来没有见过她哭。她能泣而不啜，张着她那双美丽的黑色眼睛，脸有些僵硬。硕大而沉重的泪滴流了下来。而她的沉默、她那一动不动的悲痛的身体，极为感人。自从演完《创伤的心》之后，她就再没有哭得那样厉害。上帝，那部剧简直让她心力交瘁。她并没有看着汤姆，她眼睛直瞪瞪地注视前方；她确实悲伤得有些神情恍惚，但又怎么样呢？她体内另外一个自我知道她在做什么，这个自我感知她的不幸，同时又观察它的表现。她感到他面色变得苍白。她感到突然有一阵痛苦绞着他的心弦，她感到他的血肉之躯无法承受她那极度的痛苦。

“朱莉娅。”

他的声音沙哑。她慢慢地将湿漉漉的眼睛转向了他。他看到的并不是一个哭泣的女人，而是整个人类的不幸，是人类命运无法测量的、极度悲伤的痛苦欲绝。他跪在她面前，将她抱在怀里。他感到心烦意乱。

“我最亲爱的，最亲爱的。”

有一会儿，她一动不动。就好像她不知道他在那儿。他亲吻她流着眼泪的眼睛，他的嘴向她的嘴上凑过去。她把嘴给了他，好像她毫无力气，好像她对发生在自己身上的一切几乎都毫无意识，似乎她已经没有了意志。她用一个几乎察觉不到的动作将自己的身体靠向他，渐渐地用双手搂住了他的脖子。她躺在他的怀里，并非呆滞，而是好像她失去了所有的力量和活力。他尝到了她眼泪的咸味。最终，她疲惫不堪，两只柔软的手臂紧紧抓着他，躺回到沙发上。他的嘴唇紧贴着她的。

如果你在一刻钟后看到她如此欢快愉悦，脸上泛着红晕，你一定想不到，不久前她刚刚经历了一场暴风雨般的哭泣。他们各喝了一杯威士忌苏打，抽了一根烟，看着彼此，眼中充满喜爱。

“他是个可爱的小东西。”她想。

她突然想到应该好好款待一下他。

“里卡比公爵和公爵夫人今晚会来剧院，我们会一起去萨沃伊饭店吃晚餐。我想你不会来的，是吧？我特别希望有个男伴，凑成四个人。”

“如果你希望我去，我当然会去。”

他脸上凸显的红晕告诉她见到这样显贵的人对他来说是多么兴奋的一件事。她并没有告诉他里卡比夫妇只要有免费的饭吃，哪里都愿意去。虽然很是害羞，但汤姆还是收回了他退还给朱莉娅的那些礼物。当他离开后，朱莉娅坐在化妆镜前，好好地审视了一番自己。

“我真是太幸运了，不用担心哭泣会肿眼睛。”她说道。她按摩了一阵眼皮，“男人都是一群大傻瓜。”

她很开心。一切都没问题了。她又重新得到了他。不过，在她脑海后面或者内心深处萌生了对汤姆的一些鄙夷，因为他是一个这么无知的蠢货。

第十六章

他们的这次争吵，以某种奇妙的方式消除了他们之间的隔阂，让两人关系更加密切。当她再次提出公寓的问题时，汤姆并没有像她预想中的那样抵触。在他和朱莉娅重新复合，拿回她的礼物并同意忘记那借款后，汤姆看起来似乎已经将自己道德上的顾虑都置于一边了。他们一起开心地装修公寓。司机的老婆替他打扫屋子并为他做早餐。朱莉娅有一把公寓钥匙，有时会自己进去，独自坐在那小小的客厅里，等他从办公室回来。他们一周在外共进两到三次晚餐并且跳舞，然后坐出租车回到公寓。朱莉娅过了一个愉快的秋天。他们上演的戏剧很成功。她感到灵动而年轻。罗杰圣诞节的时候回到家中，但只待了两周，然后就去了维也纳。朱莉娅预计他会霸占汤姆，她决定不去计较。年轻人自然会和年轻人相互吸引，她告诉自己，如果有那么几天他们两个形影不离，以至于汤姆忽略了她的存在，这也没什么值得她焦虑的。她现在拥有他。能成为她的情人，他感到很骄傲，这给了他不少自信，而且他很高兴和一大群知名人士有不错的交情，虽然他都是通过朱莉娅认识的这些人。他现在非常渴望加入一个上层俱乐部，朱莉娅目前正在帮他找门路。查尔斯从未拒绝过朱莉娅，她很肯定，用点伎俩她一定能够哄骗他提议让汤姆加入他所属的那个俱乐部。对于汤姆来说，有钱花是一件新奇又愉快的体验；她鼓励他奢侈一点；她明白，他会习惯这种生活方式，然后意识到他无法离开她了。

“当然这一切不会长久，”她告诉她自己，“但到头来，对他来讲这是一次很棒的经历。这会让他成为真正的男子汉。”

然而，虽然她自己认为这关系不会长久，但她并不真正明白其中的理由。随着时间消逝，他渐渐变老，他们之间不会有特别的不同。再过十年或十五年，他不再如此年轻，而她还会像现在这般年纪。他们在一起相处得很舒服。男人是习惯性的动物；这让女人能牢牢地控制他们。她从未感到比他年纪大，同时她也确信他从未想过他们年龄之间的差异。对此有那么一阵子她的确感到不安。她正躺在他的床上。他站在梳妆台旁，穿着衬衫，梳他的头发。她全身赤裸，以提香笔下的维纳斯那样的姿势躺在那里，她记得到一所乡间别墅做客时看到过这幅画。她觉得自己摆出了一副可爱的画面，完全意识到自己所展现的美丽动人的形象，便保持着这个姿势。她开心而满足。

“这就是浪漫。”她想，嘴角挂着一抹浅浅的微笑。

他在镜子里看到了她，转过身，没说一句话，抽起被单遮住了她的身体。虽然她充满爱意地朝他微笑，但还是让她心里一惊。他是害怕她着凉吗？还是他那英国人的腼腆个性被她的裸体吓到？又或者，在他男孩子的欲望得到满足后，看到她衰老的身体让他有点恶心？当朱莉娅回家后，她再次脱掉所有的衣服，在穿衣镜前审视了自己。朱莉娅决定对自己不留情面。她观察她的脖子，那里没有一点岁月的痕迹，尤其是当她把脸抬起来的时候；她的乳房小而坚实，说是女孩子的乳房都不为过。她的小腹扁平，臀部小巧，那儿有一些肥肉，像一根长香肠，但所有人都有，不过菲利普斯小姐可以在那儿用用力气了。没人会说她的双腿不漂亮，她的腿纤长而美丽；她用双手抚摸着自己的全身，她的皮肤如同天鹅绒一般柔软，白皙且没有一颗黑痣。当然，她眼睛下面有一些细纹，但你得仔细盯着看才能发现；据说有种手术可以让人摆脱这些细纹，或许可以去打听一下；幸运的是，她的头发没有褪色，因为不管染得怎样好，都会让脸看起来僵硬；她的头发依旧是鲜明的深棕色。她的牙齿保养得也非常好。

“假正经，就是这样。”

一瞬间她回忆起火车上那个蓄胡子的西班牙人，顽皮地对着镜子里的自己笑笑。

“他可一点都不害臊。”

不过尽管如此，从那天起，她开始小心自己的行为举止，以按照汤姆的体面标准行事。

朱莉娅的名声非常好，她觉得自己没有必要犹豫是否应该和汤姆一起出现在公众场合。对她来说去夜总会是一种新体验，她很喜欢，虽然她比任何人都清楚不论她去哪里都会被注视，但她却从未想过她这些习惯上的变化会引起公众的议论。在对婚姻忠贞二十年后，当然她没有把西班牙人的事情算作数，任何意外都可能发生在一个女人身上。朱莉娅很自信，认为没有人会怀疑她跟一个小到可以当她儿子的年轻人有私情。她从未想过，汤姆可能并没有她想象中的那么小心谨慎，也从未想过他们一起跳舞时她的眼神会背叛她。她自视享有特权，所以从没想到人们最终开始沸沸扬扬地说起闲话。

当流言传到多莉·德·弗里斯的耳朵中时，她笑了。应朱莉娅的要求，她邀请汤姆参加各种聚会，还有一两次邀请他来乡下的别墅度周末，但她从未把汤姆放在心上。他看起来是个不错的小家伙，当迈克尔忙碌时还可以做朱莉娅的陪同，但微不足道。他是那种不论在哪里经过都引不起注意的人，甚至在跟他见过面后依然想不起他长什么样子。他就是为了让参加聚会的人数变成双数才会去邀请的那种人。朱莉娅会开心地称他为“我的男孩朋友”或者“我的年轻男人”；如果他们之间真有什么私情，她不可能对此表现得如此镇静坦诚。而且，多莉非常清楚，朱莉娅的生活中只有两个男人，迈克尔和查尔斯·泰默利。但同时又觉得朱莉娅可笑，在这么多年的洁身自好后，突然开始一周去三四次夜总会。最近多莉没怎么见到她，她的无视有点伤到多莉的自尊。多莉在戏剧界有很多朋友，于是开始打探。对于她听到的一切，她一点也开心不起来。她不知道对此该做何感想。有件事情是很确定的，朱莉娅并不知道人们在她背后都议论什么，必须得有人告诉她。不能是她，她没有这个勇气。即使是在这么多年的交情后，她还是有点害怕朱莉娅。朱莉娅是个脾气很好的女人，虽然她的语言经常显得唐突，但她很难被惹怒。可她有种气质不允许你跟她胡来，你会觉得如果跟她闹得太大你会为此感到后悔。但必须得做些什么。多莉在脑子里翻来覆去地将此事思虑了两个礼拜，忧心忡忡；她试图将自己受伤的情感暂且先搁置在一边，完全从朱莉娅的演艺事业出发，最后她得出结论，得让迈克尔跟她讲。她从来没喜欢过迈克尔，但他毕竟是朱莉娅的丈夫，她有义务告诉迈克尔，让他给正在发生的这一切画上句号。

于是，多莉打电话给迈克尔，并约他在剧院见面。迈克尔对多莉就像她对他一样，也没有任何好感，虽然是由于另外的原因，当他听到她想见他的时候，迈克尔不由得诅咒了一声。他很懊恼无法让多莉出售她的那部分股份，还憎恨她给出的一切建议，他认为那是横加干涉。但当多莉出现在他的办公室时，他还是友好地问候了她，亲吻了她的脸颊。

“请坐，别客气。来这儿是不是为了看看这个老剧院是否还在给你挣红利？”

多莉·德·弗里斯已经六十岁了。她很胖，大鼻子和厚厚的红嘴唇使她的脸看起来硕大无比。她的黑绸连衣裙有一丝男性风格，但她脖子上戴了一串双圈珍珠项链，腰部和帽子上分别戴了一个钻石胸针。她的短发染成鲜明的铜黄色，嘴唇和指甲涂得火红。她的声音洪亮低沉，但当她激动时，说出的字眼会叠加听不清，并暴露出一丝伦敦底层人的口音。

“迈克尔，我为朱莉娅的事情感到心烦意乱。”

迈克尔，这个完美的绅士，稍稍挑起眉毛，紧闭着他那薄薄的嘴唇。他可不打算跟多莉谈论自己的妻子。

“我觉得她最近做得实在有点过分。我不知道什么冲昏了她的脑子。她现在去的那些聚会、那些夜总会还有其他的事情。毕竟，她不再是个年轻女人了；她会把自己耗尽的。”

“哦，一派胡言。她强壮得跟头牛一样，她非常健康。她比前几年显得还要年轻。别看她做完一天的工作去找点乐子就嫉妒她。现在她演的角色并不费力，我很开心她能出去玩一玩。这仅仅说明她多么有活力。”

“她从来没有对那种事情感兴趣过。突然间，她就开始去那种氛围糟糕的地方跳舞到深夜两点，这太奇怪了。”

“那是她唯一的运动。她可不会穿上短裤跟我去公园里跑步。”

“我觉得你应该知道人们都在说些什么。这些言论对她的名声可不太好。”

“你到底是在说什么？”

“她这种年纪，跟一个那么年轻的男孩，如此引人瞩目地在公共场合出现，这简直太荒谬了。”

迈克尔看着多莉，并没有理解她在说什么，当他明白过来时，他大笑不已。

“汤姆？别犯傻了，多莉。”

“我不是犯傻。我知道我在说什么。像朱莉娅那么出名的人，总是跟一个男人在一起，人们自然会说闲话。”

“但汤姆是我们俩的朋友。你很明白，我没办法带她出去跳舞。我得第二天早上八点起床，在开始工作前去运动。活见鬼，在三十年舞台生涯后，我还是知道一点人性的。汤姆是一个纯朴诚实的英国男孩，他是个绅士。我敢说他爱慕朱莉娅，那个年纪的男孩经常会觉得他们爱上了比自己年纪大的女人，但这不会对他产生什么伤害，只会给他带来好处；但认为朱莉娅会对他有什么想法——我可怜的多莉，你真让我觉得好笑。”

“他无趣、迟钝、普通且还很势利。”

“好吧，如果他是你所说的那种人，而朱莉娅跟他形影不离，这难道不让你觉得奇怪吗？”

“只有女人会知道女人能做什么。”

“这句话不错，多莉。我们可能会请你写下一部戏剧。现在让我们把这个问题解决掉。你能直视我的脸，告诉我，你真的认为朱莉娅和汤姆有私情？”

她直勾勾地看着他的脸，眼睛里充满了痛苦。虽然刚开始当她听到关于朱莉娅的流言时她付之一笑，但她无法抑制住后来侵占了她脑子的疑虑；她记起了很多小事，当时觉得没什么，但现在看来非常可疑。她遭遇了在她看来无法忍受的痛苦。证据？她没有证据；她的直觉告诉她不能不信。她想回答是，这种冲动几乎无法控制；但她还是控制住了。她不能背叛朱莉娅。这个笨蛋可能会告诉朱莉娅，然后朱莉娅就再也不会跟自己说话了。他可能会暗中监视朱莉娅，并抓她的现行。没人能预测如果她说了实话会发生什么。

“不，我不确信。”

她的双眼满是泪水，泪珠顺着她巨大的脸颊流下来。迈克尔看到了她的痛苦。他觉得她很可笑，但他意识到她非常难过，心地善良的他想要给她安慰。

“我确信你并不这么认为。你知道朱莉娅有多喜欢你，如果她有了新朋友，你不能嫉妒，你知道的。”

“上帝知道我并不嫉妒她什么，”她抽泣地说道，“最近她对我变得非常不同。她变得很冷漠。我对她如此忠诚，迈克尔。”

“是的，亲爱的，我知道。”

“如果我把为国王效劳的热诚，用一半来侍奉我的上帝……”

“哦，得了，还没有那么糟糕。你知道，我不是那种会跟别人谈论自己老婆的人。我总是觉得这事儿不成体统。但你知道，老实说，你一点也不了解朱莉娅。性对于她来说什么都不是。我们刚结婚那会儿，一切都不同，我不介意告诉你毕竟那几年她让我的日子也不怎么好过。我并不是说她是一个女色情狂或是类似的什么，但有时她会让人很疲惫。床上生活很好，但生活中还有其他事情。可自打罗杰出生，她完全变了。生孩子让她安定下来。她将所有这些本能都带入要演的戏中。多莉，你读过弗洛伊德；他把这个叫作什么来着？”

“哦，迈克尔，我才不关心什么弗洛伊德。”

“升华。就是这个。我经常会想是什么让她成为如此成功的女演员。演戏是一件需要花费全部时间的工作，如果你想演得好，你必须把自己全部都投入进去。对于那些认为演员们过着放荡不羁的生活的公众我很没有耐心。我们才没有时间做那种荒唐的事情。”

迈克尔说的这些话让多莉非常生气，她恢复了自制。

“不过迈克尔，你和我可能认为朱莉娅跟那个蹩脚小子混在一起没什么。但这对她的名声可不好。毕竟，你们的一大资产就是模范的婚姻生活。所有人都羡慕你们这一点。公众很喜欢把你们当作彼此深爱、亲密和谐的一对儿。”

“我们确实是这样，见鬼。”

多莉渐渐失去耐心。

“但我告诉你，人们在说闲话。你没有那么愚蠢，不会预想不到他们一定会这么说。我的意思是，如果朱莉娅一直就有接二连三的花边新闻，没人会注意，但在她过了这么多年规规矩矩的生活后，突然发生现在这样的事情——所有人自然都会开始说闲话。这对生意影响很坏。”

迈克尔快速地瞥了她一眼，微微地笑了。

“我明白你的意思了，多莉。我知道你说的有一定道理，而且在这种情况下，我觉得你完全有理由说这样的话。当我们刚刚开始经营剧院的时候你对我们非常好，我非常不愿意让你失望。我的解决方法是，我会把你的股份买过来。”

“买我的股份？”

多莉挺直了身子，刚才还愁容不展的脸立刻板了起来。她怒不可遏。迈克尔继续温柔地说道：

“我明白你的意思。如果朱莉娅整夜在外寻欢作乐，一定会反映在她的表演上。很明显。她有一批妙不可言的观众——一批老太太，她们来看我们的日场演出，就因为她们认为她是个那样可爱的好女人。我不介意承认，如果她的行为引起大家关于她不好的闲言碎语，这的确会影响收入。我很了解朱莉娅，她不会让任何人干涉她的行动自由。我是她的丈夫，我必须忍受这一点。可你的位置不一样。如果你乘着这个有利时机退出去的话，我不会责怪你。”

多莉现在警惕起来。她可不愚蠢，在商业方面她跟迈克尔棋逢对手。她生气极了，但愤怒让她自制。

“凭着这么多年的交情，我以为，迈克尔，你会更懂我一些。我觉得，出于义务，我必须让你警惕，但同时我也会跟你们共浮沉。我不是那种弃沉船而逃的女人。我敢说，比起你，我更输得起我的那部分钱。”

看到迈克尔脸上清晰显现出的失望让她心满意足。她晓得他对金钱看得很重，希望她刚才说的话使他心痛。迈克尔很快就镇定下来。

“好吧，多莉，那么你再想想。”

多莉拎起包，两人说着友善的客套话分了手。

“愚蠢的老婊子。”当门在多莉身后关上的那一刻，迈克尔说道。

“自负的老蠢驴。”多莉乘坐电梯下楼，嘘声说道。

但当多莉进入她那非常昂贵的豪华汽车，开回蒙塔古广场时，她再也无法抑制住满眶的沉重痛苦的眼泪。她感到自己老了，孤独寂寞，郁郁寡欢，妒火中烧。

第十七章

迈克尔自己觉得富有幽默感。在他和多莉谈话后的那个星期天晚上，他漫步到朱莉娅的房间，朱莉娅正在梳妆打扮。他们准备提早吃晚餐，之后去看电影。

“除了查尔斯，今晚谁还来？”他问她。

“我找不到另外一个女伴了，我喊了汤姆。”

“好！我想见见他。”

想到肚子里藏着的笑话，他忍不住笑了出来。朱莉娅很期待这个夜晚。在电影院的时候，朱莉娅会安排汤姆坐在她身边，这样当她低声和查尔斯说话的时候汤姆会握着她的手。亲爱的查尔斯，承蒙他的爱慕如此长久深情；她会对他格外亲切一些。查尔斯和汤姆同时抵达。汤姆第一次穿着他的新晚礼服，他和朱莉娅暗暗互换了一个小小的眼神，他表示满意，她表示问候。

“嘿，年轻人，”迈克尔欢快地说道，搓着双手，“你知道我听到关于你的什么消息吗？我听说你在败坏我妻子的名声。”

汤姆吃惊地望了他一眼，脸涨得通红。脸红的习惯让他难堪，但他却改不掉。

“哦，亲爱的，”朱莉娅开心地喊道，“太好了！我这一生都在努力找人来败坏我的名声。谁告诉你的，迈克尔？”

“一只小鸟。”他调皮地说道。

“那么，汤姆，如果迈克尔跟我离婚，你可得娶我，你知道吧。”

查尔斯微微笑着，眼中满是忧伤的柔情。

“你都做了什么，汤姆？”他问道。

这年轻人明显的窘态使查尔斯感到心情沉重，迈克尔则兴高采烈。朱莉娅看起来同他们一样觉得有趣，实际上她保持着警觉，小心谨慎。

“很明显，这小子在朱莉娅应该上床睡觉的时候带着她去逛夜总会了。”

朱莉娅开心地叫起来。

“汤姆，我们应该否认呢，还是应该厚着脸皮挺下去？”

“那让我告诉你们我是怎么跟那只小鸟说的吧，”迈克尔插话进来，“我告诉她，只要朱莉娅不拉着我陪她去夜总会就行了……”

朱莉娅不再听他说什么了。“多莉。”她想，奇妙的是，她用来形容多莉的词和前几天迈克尔用的一模一样。晚饭准备好了，他们愉快的谈话转移到了别的话题。虽然朱莉娅开心地参与其中，虽然看起来她把全部精力都放在了她的客人身上，甚至还津津有味地听了已经听过二十遍的迈克尔有关戏剧界的故事之一，但在她内心，她跟多莉正进行一场生动的对话。多莉蜷缩在她面前，她直言不讳地告诉多莉她对她的看法。

“你这头老母牛，”她对多莉说，“你怎么敢掺和我的私事？不，不许说话。不要试图找借口。我知道你跟迈克尔说了什么。无法原谅。我以为你是我的朋友。我以为我能依靠你。好吧，你的行为结束了我们的关系。我不会再跟你说一句话。再也不会。再也不会。你以为我会看上你那些陈腐不堪的钱吗？哦，说这不是你本意一点用都没有。要不是靠我，你能有什么名堂，我倒想知道。你得到的那些名气，你在这个世界上如果有一点重要性，那都是因为你恰巧认识我的缘故。是谁让你的聚会这些年来一直高朋满座？你以为人们去你的聚会是为了见你吗？他们是来看我的。再也不会这样了。永远不会。”

事实上，这更像是一场独白，而不是对话。

后来，在电影院，如她设想的，她坐在汤姆旁边，握着他的手，但她却感到汤姆异常冷漠，像一片鱼翅。她怀疑汤姆还在忐忑不安地思考迈克尔的话。她希望有个机会能跟他说几句话，让他不要担心。毕竟，没人能像她那样巧妙地应对此事。泰然自若，就是这个词。她在想，多莉到底跟迈克尔说了什么。她最好查清楚。问迈克尔是不行的，那样的话会显得她对此事很重视；她必须直接去问多莉。最好不要跟多莉闹翻了。当她想到她和多莉对话的场景，不由得微笑起来。她会甜言蜜语，能够哄骗多莉说出所有实情，绝对不会让多莉察觉她有一丝生气。很奇怪，当她想到人们在议论她时，她的后背打了一阵冷战。说到底，如果她都不能够随心所欲的话，还有谁能够呢？她的私人生活跟其他任何人无关。同时，不得不承认，如果人们在她背后嘲笑她，也不是什么让人感到愉快的事情。她在想，如果迈克尔知道实情后会怎么做。他不可能同她离婚后继续替她经营剧院。如果他有点脑子，应该选择不闻不问。但迈克尔有些方面很可笑；时不时他会气势汹汹，开始他那套上校的做派。他能突然说出，去他妈的，他必须要表现得像个绅士这种话。男人都是这样的蠢货，为了泄愤竟会伤害到自己，专门跟自己过不去。当然，对她来说这倒没什么大不了的。她可以去美国演一年，直到丑闻平息，然后可以和别人一起继续经营剧院。但那样的话可真够令人讨厌的。此外，还有罗杰要考虑；他会感觉到的，可怜的家伙；他自然会觉得屈辱；逃避事实没什么好处，在她的年龄，为了一个二十三岁的男孩离婚，她会被认为是个彻头彻尾的蠢蛋。当然，她不会蠢到要嫁给汤姆。查尔斯会娶她吗？她转头看着暗光中他那高雅的轮廓。他疯狂地痴迷了她好多年；他正是女人用一个小手指就能任意摆布的那些有骑士精神的白痴中的一个。他可能会不介意代替汤姆作为离婚诉讼的共同被告，那倒是不错的结局。查尔斯·泰默利夫人。听起来不错。也许她有一些草率。她去汤姆的公寓时总是很小心，但可能被马车房里的一两个司机看到她出入了，于是胡思乱想。那个阶层的人的想法很肮脏。至于夜总会，她更乐意和汤姆去那些安静的，没人会看到他们的地方去，但他不喜欢。他喜欢人群，他想要见到时髦的人物，他也想引人注目。他喜欢显摆她。

“可恶，”她对自己说道，“可恶，可恶。”

这一晚，朱莉娅并没有她预想中的那样享受电影。

第十八章

第二天，朱莉娅用私人电话打给了多莉。

“亲爱的，似乎有好久没见到你了。这段时间你自己忙什么呢？”

“并没有什么。”

多莉的声音听起来很冷漠。

“听着，罗杰明天就到家了。你知道，他要离开伊顿了。我会派车早一点去接他回来，我想让你过来吃午餐。不是聚会，就只有你、我、迈克尔和罗杰。”

“明天我有约要出去吃午餐。”

有二十年了，只要朱莉娅邀请多莉一同做什么事情，她永远都会奉陪。电话那端的声音听起来充满敌意。

“多莉，你怎么能这么无情？罗杰会非常失望的。他第一天到家；另外，我也想见你。我好久都没见到你了，非常想念你。难道不能失约一次？就这一次，亲爱的，午饭后我们好好聊一聊，就你和我？”

当朱莉娅愿意的时候，没有人能比她更具有说服力，谁的声音都不如她的柔情似水，谁的恳求都不如她的无法抵挡。电话那端有一阵停顿，朱莉娅知道多莉在和她自己那受伤的感情做斗争。

“好吧，亲爱的，我会想想办法的。”

“亲爱的。”朱莉娅挂掉电话后咬牙切齿地说道，“这头老母牛。”

多莉来了。她对罗杰说他长大了，以及一些她认为适合这个年纪的男孩的话，罗杰在一旁彬彬有礼，并适时地用他那沉重的微笑予以回应。他让朱莉娅感到困惑。他话很少，只顾听着其他人的对话，似乎全神贯注，但朱莉娅有种奇怪的感觉，觉得他在想自己的事情。他似乎以一种抽离的好奇心在观察他们，就好像他在观察动物园里的动物。这让人有点不安。当机会来了，朱莉娅便说出为多莉所准备的那一小段对话。

“哦，亲爱的罗杰，你知道你可怜的父亲今晚很忙。我有两张帕拉狄昂剧院第二场的戏票，汤姆想跟你在皇家咖啡馆吃饭。”

“哦！”罗杰停顿了一下，“好的。”

她转向多莉。

“有汤姆这样的人能陪罗杰一起真是太好了。他们是很好的朋友，你知道吧。”

迈克尔瞟了多莉一眼，眼睛里放着光。他说道：

“汤姆是个非常体面的男孩。他不会让罗杰惹上什么麻烦的。”

“我以为罗杰会更愿意跟他伊顿的朋友们一起出去。”多莉说道。

“老母牛，”朱莉娅心里想着，“老母牛。”

当午饭结束后，她邀请多莉去她的房间。

“我要上床睡一会儿，我休息的时候你可以跟我聊天。属于两个老女孩之间的谈话，这正是我想要的。”

她用胳膊亲切地缠住多莉粗壮的腰身，领着她上了楼。一开始，她们聊一些无关紧要的事情，衣服、仆人、化妆还有丑闻；然后朱莉娅倚着她的胳膊肘，用信任的眼光看着多莉。

“多莉，有些事情我想告诉你。我需要建议，而这世上唯有你的建议我会听。我知道我能相信你。”

“当然，亲爱的。”

“似乎有人在传一些有关我的很不好听的话。有人去跟迈克尔讲了，告诉他社会上有好多关于我和可怜的汤姆·芬内尔的流言。”

尽管她的眼睛依旧闪烁着迷人而富有感染力的光芒，她知道多莉无法抵御这眼神，但她密切注视着对方，看多莉脸上会不会显露出震惊或表情有所变化。然而她什么也没看到。

“谁告诉迈克尔的？”

“我不知道。他不肯说。你知道当他绅士起来的时候是什么样。”

她不知是否只是她的想象，似乎多莉听到了这话后稍稍放松了些。

“我想知道真相，多莉。”

“我很开心你来问我，亲爱的。你知道我有多讨厌干涉别人的事情，如果你自己不提起它，谁也不会诱使我提到它。”

“我的宝贝，如果连我都不知道你有多么忠诚，还有谁知道？”

多莉脱掉鞋子，扎实地坐在她的椅子里。朱莉娅的目光始终都没有离开她。

“你知道人心可以多坏。你一直都过着平静规矩的生活。你几乎不会外出，要么就只跟迈克尔或者查尔斯·泰默利出去。他不一样；所有人都知道他爱慕了你这么多年。因此，突然间你跟着一个做你剧院账务的公司职员满世界跑，这看起来很可笑。”

“他并不只是个职员。他父亲为他买了那个公司的一部分股份，他是一个初级合伙人。”

“是的，他一年挣四百英镑。”

“你怎么知道的？”朱莉娅立刻问道。

这次，她很肯定多莉有一点不安。

“你劝我去他的公司咨询收入税的事情。其中一个主要的合伙人告诉我的。就凭他那点薪水，竟能住得起一套公寓，穿得阔气，还带人去夜总会。”

“据我所知，他父亲还给他额外的津贴。”

“他父亲是伦敦北部的一个律师。你应该很清楚，如果他父亲给他购买了合伙股份，是没有能力再给他什么津贴了。”

“你肯定不会猜想是我在养着他吧。”朱莉娅说道，发出清脆的笑声。

“我什么也没乱猜，亲爱的。而其他人在这么做。”

朱莉娅既不喜欢多莉所说的话，也不喜欢她说话的方式。但她没有表露出任何不舒服的信号。

“太荒唐了。比起跟我的友谊，他更是罗杰的朋友。当然，最近我跟他一起跑东跑西，但那是因为我觉得我的生活太死板了。我厌恶了每天去剧院、自己照顾自己。没有生活可言。毕竟，如果我现在不享受一下，我再也不会有机会了。我越来越老了，多莉，你知道，这也用不着否定。而且，你知道迈克尔的样子，当然他很可爱，但他令人厌烦。”

“不会有人比过去的他更令人厌烦吧。”多莉尖酸地说。

“我本以为，人们不会觉得我会跟一个比自己小二十岁的男孩发生什么私情。”

“二十五岁，”多莉纠正道，“我也以为这样。不幸的是，他并没有很小心谨慎。”

“你这是什么意思？”

“他告诉艾维丝·克赖顿他会在你的下一部戏剧中帮她争取到一个角色。”

“艾维丝·克赖顿是谁？”

“哦，她是个我认识的年轻演员。她美得如同一幅画。”

“他只是一个傻孩子。我设想他或许觉得可以让迈克尔同意吧。你知道，迈克尔是如何对待他的那些小角色的。”

“他说他能让你做任何他想做的事情。他说你完全听他的。”

幸亏朱莉娅是个好演员。有一秒，她的心脏停止了跳动。他怎么能那么说？蠢东西。该死的蠢货。但她立刻让自己镇定下来，轻轻地笑了笑。

“一派胡言！我一点都不信。”

“他是个极其普通，甚至有点恶俗的年轻男人。如果你对他的小题大做让他昏了头，这一点也不惊奇。”

朱莉娅好性子地微笑着，坦诚地看着多莉。

“但是，亲爱的，你不会觉得他是我的情人吧？”

“如果我不这么觉得，我就是唯一那个不这么认为的人了。”

“那么你这么认为吗？”

有一阵多莉没有回答。她们紧紧盯着彼此，心中满怀恨意；但朱莉娅还是微笑着。

“如果你用人格担保，对我发誓，我当然会相信你。”

朱莉娅让声音变得低沉严肃。这确实有了一种真诚的效果。

“我从来没有对你撒过谎，多莉，我年纪这么大了也不可能再对你撒谎。我向你发誓，汤姆对我而言仅仅是一个朋友。”

“你把我心头一块重重的石头搬走了。”

朱莉娅知道多莉并没有相信她，多莉也知道朱莉娅很明白这一点。她继续说道：

“但为了以防万一，为了你好，朱莉娅宝贝儿，明智一些。不要再跟那个年轻人四处跑了。甩掉他。”

“哦，我不能那么做。那样的话不就承认了人们所想的是对的吗？反正我问心无愧。我没什么可羞耻的。如果我让可恶的流言影响了我的行为，我会瞧不起我自己。”

多莉穿上了鞋，从她的手提包中拿出口红涂嘴唇。

“好吧，亲爱的，你这年纪也知道自己想要什么了。”

她们冷淡地分了手。

但多莉的一两句话让朱莉娅有点震惊，让她难以释怀。流言如此接近事实让她惶惶不安。但这真的有什么了不起吗？很多女人都有情人，谁又会管呢？一个女演员。没人会期望一个女演员是守规矩的典型。

“是我那该死的美德。这才是问题的症结所在。”

她有一个贞洁无比的女人的名声，丑闻的毒舌从来触摸不到她，而现在看起来，她的名声更像是她为自己建起来的一座监狱。但还有更糟糕的。汤姆说的她完全任他摆布是什么意思？这深深地冒犯了她。愚蠢的小傻子。他怎么敢这么说？她不知道对此该怎么办。她本想对他痛骂一番。但那又有什么用？他会否认这一切。唯一的方法就是什么都不说；现在一切都为时已晚，她必须接受一切。逃避真相一点用都没有，他不爱她，他做她的情人就是因为这关系满足了他的自尊，给了他在乎的一切，在他眼里这关系至少给他带来一种地位。

“如果我有脑子的话，我应该甩掉他。”她生气地大笑了一声，“说起来容易。但我爱他。”

奇怪的是，当她审视内心时，发现并不是朱莉娅·兰伯特这个女人在憎恨这种冒犯，她不关心自己，实际上，对朱莉娅·兰伯特这个女演员的冒犯让她内心刺痛。她曾经经常觉得，她的才能，评论家口中的天才，但这词太宏大，那就叫她的天赋吧，其实并不属于她自己，甚至不是她的一部分，而更像是外在的什么东西通过她——朱莉娅·兰伯特这个女人——来表达自己。它似乎是降临在她身上的一种奇怪而无形的人格，通过她做出一些她并不知道自己可以做的一些事情。她是一个普通的还算美丽的、正在衰老的女人。她的天赋既没有年龄又没有形体。它是一种在她身体上起着作用的精神，就像小提琴家弹奏他的小提琴一样。正是对这精神的轻蔑让她难过。

她试着入睡。她习惯于在下午睡一会儿，只要一静下心来就能入睡，但是这次她翻来覆去，总是睡不着。最后她看了眼时钟。汤姆一般在五点稍过一点儿从事务所回来。她渴望着他；在他的怀抱里会有安宁，和他在一起时，一切都抛到九霄云外了。她拨了他的电话号码。

“哈喽？是的。你是谁？”

她把话筒按在耳朵上，目瞪口呆。这是罗杰的声音。她把电话挂了。

第十九章

那一夜朱莉娅没有睡好。听到罗杰回来，她醒了，打开灯，看到是夜里四点。她皱了皱眉头。第二天早晨，她正想起身，他从石楼梯上咔嗒咔嗒走下来了。

“我能进来吗，妈妈？”

“进来。”

他还穿着他的睡袍和晨衣。她冲他微笑，因为他看起来如此充满朝气，又如此年轻。

“昨晚你回来得太晚了。”

“不，没有很晚。我一点回来的。”

“撒谎。我看表了，是四点。”

“好吧，是四点。”他乐呵呵地同意了。

“你们到底做什么去了？”

“表演结束后我们去了别的地方，吃了晚饭。我们还跳舞了。”

“和谁？”

“我们挑的几个女孩。汤姆之前认识她们。”

“她们叫什么？”

“一个叫吉尔，一个叫琼。我不知道她们的全名。琼是个演员。她问我是否能在您的下部剧中让她当预备演员。”

反正她们俩都不是艾维丝·克赖顿。自从多莉提到后，这个名字一直出现在她的脑海里。

“但那些地方不会开到四点。”

“不，我们先回到汤姆的公寓。汤姆让我保证不告诉您。他说你会非常生气。”

“哦，我的宝贝，我不会因为这么点小事就生气的。我向你保证不会对此提一个字。”

“如果要怪也得怪我。昨天下午我去看汤姆，我们安排了这一切。所有我们在戏里看到和在小说里读到的关于爱情的那套玩意儿。我快十八岁了。我想我应该亲自看看这都是怎么回事。”

朱莉娅从床上坐起来，睁大眼睛，满是疑问。

“罗杰，你什么意思？”

他镇定而严肃。

“汤姆说他认识一对还不错的女孩。之前他拥有她们俩。她们住在一起，所以我们可以给她们打电话，并约她们在表演结束后见。他告诉她们我还是一个处男，她们最好投硬币决定谁跟我。当我们回到公寓后，他带着吉尔进了卧室，把我和琼留在客厅。”

有一阵儿她并没有在想汤姆，而是对罗杰所说的话感到十分不安。

“我觉得没什么了不起的。看不出有什么大惊小怪的。”

她说不出话来，眼眶里满是泪水，泪珠迅速地顺着脸颊流了下来。

“妈妈，怎么了？你为什么在哭？”

“可你还是个小男孩。”

他朝她走过来，坐在她的床边，张开双臂拥抱了她。

“亲爱的，别哭。如果我知道这会让你不安，我不会告诉你的。反正这事儿迟早会发生。”

“但是太早了。太早了。让我觉得我自己好老。”

“你一点都不老，亲爱的。‘年龄不能使她衰老，习惯也腐蚀不了她的变化无穷的伎俩。(1)’”

她破涕而笑。

“你个小傻子，罗杰，你以为克利奥帕特拉会喜欢那老蠢驴对她的赞颂吗？你应该再等待一段时间嘛。”

“不再等了也不错。现在我都明白了。说实话，对此我觉得很恶心。”

她深深地叹了口气。被他温柔地抱着对她是一种慰藉。但她为自己感到遗憾。

“你没有生我的气吧，亲爱的？”他问道。

“生气？不。不过如果这事情一定要发生的话，我希望它不是这么平淡。你谈论它的口气就好像是在讲一次有趣的实验。”

“我觉得某种意义上是这么回事。”

她冲他微微一笑。

“你真的认为那就是爱？”

“它是大部分人所指的，不是吗？”

“不，不是。他们说的是痛苦和气愤、羞愧、狂喜、天堂和地狱；他们说的是强烈的生活之感，还有彻头彻尾的厌恶；是自由和奴役；是平和与不安。”

罗杰倾听这番话时的沉静使得她透过睫毛看了他一眼。他的双眼中有一种奇怪的神情。她不知道那意味着什么，就好像他在沉重地听着从很远的地方传来的声音。

“听起来一点劲儿也没有。”他喃喃道。

她双手捧着他那光滑的脸，亲吻了他的嘴唇。

“我是个笨蛋，不是吗？你看，我还把你当作我怀里的那个小婴儿。”

罗杰眼中闪过一道光。

“你笑什么，你这猴子？”

“我们这姿势会拍出很美的照片，不是吗？”

她忍不住大笑起来。

“你这头猪。你这头讨厌的猪。”

“我说，关于那个预备演员的事情，有什么机会给琼吗？”

“告诉她，让她某天来见我。”

但当罗杰离开时，她叹了口气。她很沮丧，感到非常孤独。她的生活如此丰富精彩，从没有时间操心过罗杰。当然，在他患百日咳或者出麻疹的时候，她会紧张起来，但大体上罗杰都非常健康，于是她心安理得地将他抛于脑后。然而，她总是觉得，在她想要照顾他的时候，他就在那儿等着她的照顾，而且，她经常想，等他长到可以分享她的兴趣爱好时会很美好。现在，她震惊地意识到，她还没有来得及拥有他，就已经失去了他。当她想到从她身边夺走罗杰的那个女孩时，她下意识地抿起了嘴唇。

“预备演员？见鬼去吧。”

她沉浸在自己的痛苦中，反倒没有为汤姆的不忠而感到悲痛。她骨子里一直明白，他对她不忠诚。在他这个年纪，以他这样放纵的脾性，再加上她忙于剧院的表演以及她的身份强加于她的各种约会，很明显，他有足够的机会随心所欲。她闭上了双眼。她希望自己不知道这一切。这是第一次，有关他不忠的事实摆在了她的面前。

“我必须忍受这些。”她叹气道。各种想法在她的脑子里飘荡。“这就像你明明在说谎，却不知道自己在说谎，这才是最致命的；我想，知道自己是个傻瓜比不知道要好一些。”

————————————————————

(1) 引自莎士比亚剧本《安东尼和克利奥帕特拉》。

第二十章

汤姆和他的家人去了伊斯特本(1)过圣诞节。朱莉娅在节礼日(2)有两场演出，因此，格斯林一家待在城里过节；他们去了多莉·德·弗里斯为了迎接新年而举办的盛大聚会；几天之后，罗杰就去了维也纳。汤姆在城里的时候，朱莉娅也几乎见不到他。她并没有问罗杰他们一起满城转悠都做了些什么，她不想知道，她强迫自己不去想，并尽可能多地参加各种聚会，以此分散她的注意力。再说，还有她的演出；一旦她进入剧院，她的愤怒、屈辱，还有她的嫉妒都得到了缓解。她仿佛在她的油彩罐内找到了人类的悲哀侵袭不到的另一个人格，这给了她战胜一切的力量。凭借这个便利的庇护所，她能够支撑一切。

罗杰离开的那天，汤姆从他的办公室打电话给她。

“今晚你做什么？要不要去狂欢一下？”

“不，我很忙。”

事实并非如此，这些脱口而出的话非她所愿。

“哦，是吗？那么，明天呢？”

如果他表现出一点失望，如果他让她取消他以为存在的约请，她可能会有勇气立刻跟他决断。但他的漫不经心将她打败了。

“明天可以。”

“好的。演出结束后我去剧院接你。再见。”

当他出现在她的更衣间时，朱莉娅已经准备好了，正在等着他的到来。她出奇地紧张。当他看到她时，他的脸上泛起光芒，当伊维离开房间后，他拥抱着她，热情地吻了她的嘴。

“这下我好过多了。”他笑道。

看着他，如此年轻，有朝气，天真烂漫，活力四射，你不会想到他给朱莉娅带来多少痛苦。你不会想到他如此虚伪。很明显，他一点都没有意识到，已经半个多月了他几乎没有见她。

（“哦，上帝，要是我能告诉他见鬼去吧该有多好。”）

但她看着他，漂亮的双眼中都是欢乐的笑意。

“我们去哪儿？”

“我在奎格饭店订了个位子。他们那儿有个新节目，是个美国魔术师，表演可精彩啦。”

晚餐的时候，朱莉娅兴奋地讲个不停。她告诉他这些日子去的各种聚会，还有她摆脱不掉的那些戏剧界的集会，看起来似乎仅仅是因为由于她的邀约，他们才没能见得上面。看到他对这事儿理所当然的态度，让她不安。他很开心见到她，这很明显，他对她所做的事和所见的人都很感兴趣，但显而易见他并没有想念她。朱莉娅告诉汤姆她接到了去纽约演出的邀请，以及对方提出的条件，她想知道汤姆对此作何反应。

“太棒了，”他说道，双眼闪着光芒，“多好的机会！你不会失败，你准能挣到一大笔钱。”

“唯一的问题是我不太愿意离开伦敦。”

“为什么不？我以为你会非常愿意。目前的剧目上演太久了，你也知道，演到复活节肯定就会结束了。而且，如果你想在美国一显身手，没有比这个更好的剧本了。”

“我不明白为什么不演到夏天结束。另外，我不喜欢陌生人。我喜欢我的朋友们。”

“我觉得这想法太愚蠢了。你的朋友们没有你也会过得很好。同时，你会在纽约有段美妙的时光。”

她那欢快的笑声令人信服。

“还以为你千方百计地想摆脱我呢。”

“当然我会非常想念你。但就只有几个月。如果我有这样的机会，我一定会抓住它。”

晚餐结束后，饭店的门卫为他们叫了一辆出租车，他告诉司机公寓的地址，好像他们应该理所当然地回到那儿去。在出租车里，他搂着她的腰，吻了她。后来，当她躺在他的怀抱里，在那张小小的单人床上，她感到过去两周所忍受的所有痛苦对于她现在感受到的内心的平静都算不上什么。

朱莉娅继续和汤姆出入那些时髦的饭店和夜总会。如果人们认为汤姆是她的情人，随他们去吧；她已经不再在乎了。但不止一次，当她想让汤姆陪她一起去什么地方，他都已经有约了。汤姆在搞定收入税这方面很有一套，这名声在朱莉娅那些有名的朋友中间已经传开了。丹诺伦特一家邀请他去乡下共度周末，在那儿他遇见了一些很愿意借助他专业知识的人。汤姆开始接收到朱莉娅不认识的人的邀请。熟人们也会向朱莉娅提及汤姆。

“你认识汤姆·芬内尔，对吧？他很聪明，不是吗？我听说他帮助吉列安一家在收入税上省了几百英镑。”

朱莉娅听到这些一点也开心不起来。他是通过她才能去这些他想去的聚会。现在看起来，似乎他已经不再需要她了。他和蔼可亲，一点也不装腔作势，穿着得体，外表清秀、整洁，让人喜欢；他能帮助人们省钱；朱莉娅对他迫不及待地想要进入的那个世界非常了解，知道很快他就能在里面站稳脚跟了。她对那个世界里的女人们的道德原则没什么赞誉，她能够数出不止一个有意愿把他抢到手的女贵族。朱莉娅欣慰的是她们都是些同猫食一样低贱的货色。多莉曾说他一年只有四百镑；靠这点钱他肯定无法在那个圈子里生存。

在她跟汤姆提到去美国演出这事儿之前，她就已经决定要拒绝邀请了；他们目前的剧目一直很叫座。但是就在这时候，偶尔影响剧院的没由头的萧条期席卷伦敦，因而营业收入骤然下降。看起来他们无法将这部戏演到复活节之后了。他们有一部新剧被寄予厚望。这部剧叫《当今时代》，原本计划在秋季推出。这里有一个很不错的角色给朱莉娅，还有一个角色很适合迈克尔出演。这是一部能轻松上演一年的戏剧。迈克尔不想五月就推出，随后暑季马上来临，但目前来看也没有别的办法，于是他开始寻找演员。

一天下午，在日常演出的间歇，伊维给朱莉娅带来一张纸条。她惊讶地看到了罗杰的笔迹。

亲爱的妈妈：

我来向您介绍我曾提起的琼·丹佛小姐。她非常想加入西登斯剧院，不论角色多么小，如果她能作为一个预备演员就知足了。

你亲爱的儿子

罗杰

看到他写得一本正经，朱莉娅微笑起来；她被逗乐了，因为他已经长大到开始试图给自己的女朋友找工作了。然后，她突然想起琼·丹佛是谁。琼和吉尔。她是那个引诱可怜的罗杰的女孩。她的脸严肃起来。但她也很好奇，想见见她。

“乔治在吗？”乔治是看门人。伊维点点头，打开了门。

“乔治。”

他走进来。

“带来这封信的那个女孩现在还在吗？”

“还在，小姐。”

“告诉她，演出结束后我会见她。”

她在戏里最后一幕穿着一袭有拖裙的晚礼服，那是一袭很华丽的服装，完美地显出了她美丽的体形。她深色的头发上别着钻石发饰，手臂上戴着钻石手镯。她看起来如同角色需求的那般，有女王风范。她在最后一次谢幕后立刻接见了琼·丹佛。朱莉娅能够转眼之间就从她的角色跳入她的个人生活，但现在，她毫不费力地依旧继续扮演那个傲慢、冷淡、端庄而极有教养的女人。

“我让你等了这么久，我想，我不能让你再等到我卸妆换完衣服了。”

她亲切的微笑是女王的微笑；她的礼貌使你保持着一种尊重的距离。她一眼就看清了走进化妆间的那个年轻姑娘。她年轻，长着一张美丽的小脸蛋和一个狮子鼻，但浓妆艳抹，化得媚俗。

“她的腿太短了，”朱莉娅想，“非常二流。”

很明显她已经穿上了她最好的衣服，刚才那一眼已经告诉朱莉娅一切。

（“沙夫茨伯里大街的货色。赊账买的。”）

这个可怜的东西现在紧张得很。朱莉娅让她坐下来，递给她一支香烟。

“你旁边有火柴。”

朱莉娅看到她试图点烟的时候手在发抖。第一根火柴灭了，她划了火柴盒三次才点着第二根。

（“要是罗杰能看到现在的她就好了！廉价的腮红，廉价的口红，惊慌失措。他以为她是个欢快可爱的小东西。”）

“你演戏时间很久了吗？对不起，我忘记你的名字了。”

“琼·丹佛。”她的嗓子很干，几乎无法说话。她的烟灭了，只能无助地拿着。她回答了朱莉娅的问题。“两年。”

“你多大？”

“十九岁。”

（“撒谎。你至少有二十二岁了。”）“你认识我儿子？”

“是的。”

“他刚离开伊顿，去维也纳学习德文。当然他很年轻，但他父亲和我认为在去剑桥前最好能在国外待上几个月。你演过什么角色？你的烟灭了。不再来一根吗？”

“哦，没关系，谢谢。我一直都在外地巡演。但我渴望在伦敦演戏。”绝望给了她勇气，她说出了明显是准备好的话。“我对您非常景仰，兰伯特小姐。我总是说，您是戏剧界最伟大的女演员。我从您身上学到的要远比我在皇家戏剧艺术学院那一年学到的多。我最大的愿望就是进入您的剧院，兰伯特小姐，你要是能设法让我演一点什么，我知道那将是一个女孩子所能得到的再好不过的机会。”

“你能摘下帽子吗？”

琼·丹佛摘下了她那顶廉价的帽子，快速地甩了甩她修得短短的鬈发。

“你头发真漂亮。”朱莉娅说道。

仍然是以那种稍带傲慢但又无限亲切的微笑，那种女王在皇家游行中给予她的臣民的微笑，朱莉娅注视着她，没有说话。她想起珍妮·塔特布的名言：除非必要，不要停顿，如果要停顿，就要尽可能长久地停顿。她几乎能听到那女孩的心跳，她感到她在那套成衣里、在她的皮囊里蜷缩着。

“是什么让你想到让我儿子向我推荐你？”

琼的脸在化妆品的遮盖下渐渐变红，她咽了口唾沫才开始回答。

“我在朋友的房子里遇见他，我告诉他我有多仰慕您，他说或许您下部剧可能会有什么角色给我。”

“我正在考虑这些角色。”

“我并没有在想真的演个角色。如果我能做个预备演员，我是说，那样我就可以参加排练，学习您的技巧。这本身就是一种培养，所有人都这么认为。”

（“愚蠢的小傻子，想拍我的马屁。就好像我不知道这一套似的。而且我为什么要培养她？”）“多谢你这么说。我只是一个非常普通的人。公众都太和善了，非常和善。你是个漂亮的小东西，而且很年轻。年轻真是太美好了。我们的宗旨就是要多给年轻的人机会。毕竟我们不可能永远待在舞台上，我们觉得，培养男女演员并在合适的时候替代我们，是我们对公众的义务。”

朱莉娅用她那修饰得悦耳的声音，把这些话说得淳朴至极，让琼·丹佛的心立刻温暖起来。她已经说服了这位老大姐，预备演员是稳稳到手了。汤姆·芬内尔早跟她说了，她只要把罗杰摆布得好，是很容易有所收获的。

“哦，那是很久之后的事了，兰伯特小姐。”她说道。她的双眼，她那双漂亮的黑色眼睛散发着光芒。

（“你说得太对了，我的女孩，太对了。我敢打赌我七十岁的时候也能把你从舞台上演下去。”）

“我必须再想一想。我还不知道我们下部剧需要什么样的预备演员。”

“我听见有人说艾维丝·克赖顿要演那少女的角色。我想或许我可以做她的替补。”

艾维丝·克赖顿。朱莉娅的双眼没有显露出这个名字对她有任何意义。

“我丈夫提起过她，但一切还没有定。我根本不认识她。她聪明吗？”

“我认为是的。我曾跟她一起在皇家戏剧艺术学院上学。”

“他们跟我说，她美得如同一幅画。”朱莉娅站起身来，表示接见到此为止。于是，她放下了她的女王架子，换了一个调子，一下子变成了一个助人为乐、兴高采烈而且和蔼可亲的女演员。“好吧，亲爱的，你把姓名和地址留下，有消息我通知你。”

“您不会忘记我吧，兰伯特小姐？”

“不，亲爱的，我向你保证不会的。很高兴见到你。你的性格真讨人喜欢。你自己能找到出去的路，对吗？再见。”

“她休想踏进这个剧院。”琼走后，朱莉娅在心里说，“这条肮脏的小母狗诱惑了我的儿子。可怜的小家伙。可耻，真可耻，就这么回事；这样的女人必须被阻止。”

她一边脱下美丽的礼服，一边望着镜子里自己的影子。她目光冷酷，嘴边带着嘲讽的笑。她对着镜子里的影子说：

“我可以告诉你这句话，老朋友：有一个人休想演《当今时代》，那个人就是艾维丝·克赖顿小姐。”

————————————————————

(1) 英格兰东南部海港城市。

(2) 圣诞节次日。

第二十一章

但大约一周后，迈克尔就提到了她。

“我说，你听说过一个叫艾维丝·克赖顿的女孩吗？”

“从来没有。”

“我听人说她很不错，是个淑女等等。她父亲在部队。我在想，是否要她来演奥娜。”

“你怎么听说她的？”

“汤姆说的。他认识她，他说她很聪明。她在星期天夜间秀上表演。事实上就是下个星期天。他说或许值得去看一眼。”

“那么，你怎么不去？”

“我准备去桑威奇(1)打高尔夫。你会很讨厌去看看吗？我估计那戏很烂，但你能知道是否值得让她读一读那角色的台词。汤姆会跟你一起去。”

朱莉娅的心跳骤然加快。

“没问题，我会去的。”

她打电话给汤姆，让他过来，在去剧院前他们先一起吃点东西。汤姆到的时候，她还没有准备好。

“是我迟到了，还是你早到了？”当她走进会客厅时说道。

她看到汤姆已经等得不耐烦了。他既紧张又着急。

“他们八点整开始，”他说道，“我讨厌在一部剧开场后到。”

他的焦虑已经告诉了她想知道的一切。她则慢慢享用她的鸡尾酒。

“我们今晚要去看的那位女演员叫什么名字？”她问道。

“艾维丝·克赖顿。我急于知道你对她的看法。我觉得她是个新兴之秀。她知道你今晚会去。她非常紧张，但我告诉她没有必要。你知道那些星期天晚上的剧目都是什么样的；排练潦草等等；我说你会理解这些的，会很宽容。”

整个晚餐他都在不停地看表。朱莉娅扮演一个世故的女人。她一会儿聊这个，一会儿聊那个，并注意到他心不在焉。一旦有机会，他便把对话扯回到艾维丝·克赖顿身上。

“当然我还没有对她说什么，但是我觉得她很适合奥娜这个角色。”正如朱莉娅所有出演的剧本，他都会在戏上演前读一遍一样，他已经读过《当今时代》的剧本。“她很像这个角色，我敢保证这点。她很努力，当然这对她来说也是非常好的机会。她对你仰慕至极，非常想和你一起演戏。”

“这是可以理解的。这意味着可以连演一年，还会有一大堆剧院经理会看到她。”

“她头发颜色正合适，肤色很白；她跟你很相衬。”

“现在以染发和漂白的技术，舞台上可并不缺少金发女郎啊。”

“但她的是天生的。”

“是吗？今早我收到罗杰的一封信。他似乎在维也纳过得不错。”

汤姆的兴致淡了下去。他看了看手表。当咖啡上来的时候，朱莉娅说没法喝。她说必须得重做。

“哦，朱莉娅，这一点也不值当。我们会迟到太久的。”

“我觉得如果迟到了几分钟没什么要紧的。”

他的声音充满苦恼：“我保证了我们不会迟到。她在剧目一开始有一场很不错的戏。”

“对不起，但是不喝咖啡我没法出门。”

在他们等咖啡的时候，她继续谈笑风生。他几乎不作回答。他焦虑地看着门。当咖啡来了，她却开始刻意地品尝，让人着急得发疯。当他们上了车，他已经是横眉冷对的状态，沉默地目视前方，脸上郁郁不乐，嘴巴生气地噘着。朱莉娅不无得意。他们在幕布升起的两分钟前进入剧院，当朱莉娅出现在那儿时，观众爆发了掌声。朱莉娅一边向打扰了的人们致歉，一边挤到她那位于剧院中央的座位。当她恰到好处地入场时，观众响起欢迎的掌声，她以微笑答谢，同时，她低垂的目光谦逊地表明并不承认这掌声跟她有任何关系。

幕布升起，一段短短的场景过后，两个女孩出现在舞台上，一个既漂亮又年轻，另外一个则年长很多，长相很普通。不久朱莉娅转向汤姆，悄声说道：

“哪一个是艾维丝·克赖顿，年轻的还是年长的？”

“年轻的那个。”

“哦，当然了，你说过她很漂亮，不是吗？”

她看了一眼汤姆的脸。他已经没有刚才生气的表情了；转而，一个欢快的微笑荡漾在他的嘴角。朱莉娅将注意力转移到舞台上。艾维丝·克赖顿确实很漂亮，没人能够否认这点，她有一头可爱的金发，一双精致的蓝眼睛，还长着一个小巧笔挺的鼻子；但朱莉娅并不喜欢她这种类型。

“无趣，”她对自己说，“歌舞女郎而已。”

她看了一阵艾维丝的表演，她看得很认真；然后她靠回座椅上，叹了口气。

“她根本不会演戏。”她下结论道。

当幕布拉上后，汤姆急切地转向她。他已经完全没有了刚才的坏脾气。

“你觉得她怎么样？”

“她确实跟画一样漂亮。”

“我知道这点。但是她的演技呢？你觉得她演得好吗？”

“是的，很聪明。”

“我希望你能过去亲自告诉她。这会给她莫大的鼓励。”

“我？”

他不知道他在要求她做什么。她，朱莉娅·兰伯特，会到后台祝贺一个小角色的女演员，这简直前所未闻。

“我答应了在第二幕结束后我会带你过去。赏个脸吧，朱莉娅。这会让她非常开心的。”

（“浑蛋。该死的浑蛋。好吧，我忍了。”）“当然，如果你觉得这会对她有什么意义，我乐意过去。”

第二幕结束后，他们穿过铁门，汤姆带着她来到艾维丝·克赖顿的化妆间。她和一同入场的那个普通女孩共享这间化妆间。汤姆替她作了介绍。她有些做作地伸出一只软弱无力的手。

“见到您我太高兴了，兰伯特小姐。这化妆间太不像样了，请您别介意好吗？但就为了一个晚上而把它整理得好一些也没什么意义。”

她一点也不紧张。事实上，她镇定自若。

（“态度真强硬。指望这个大好机会，给我来上校女儿那一套。”）

“您能过来真是太好了。我担心这算不上什么戏剧，但像我这样的起点，只能有什么角色演什么角色了。他们给我送来剧本的时候我也很迟疑，但我很喜欢那个角色。”

“你演得很好。”朱莉娅说道。

“您这么说真是太客气了。我希望我们能多排练几回。我尤其想让您看看我的演技。”

“你知道，我在这行这么多年。我一直认为，是金子总会发光的。你不这么觉得吗？”

“我知道您的意思。当然，我想要积累更多的经验，我知道这些，但我更需要的是一个机会。我知道我能表演。如果我能得到一个可以让我投入进去的角色就好了。”

她等了一会儿，想让朱莉娅说自己的新剧目里正好有适合她的角色，但朱莉娅继续微笑地看着她。朱莉娅极其可笑地发现自己竟被当作助理牧师的妻子，而大地主的太太正对她示以仁慈。

“你演戏时间很久了吗？”她最终问道，“很奇怪我从来没有听说过你。”

“我演了一段时间的歌舞剧，但我觉得那是在浪费我的时间。上一个演出季我一直在外巡演。如果可以，我再也不想离开伦敦了。”

“戏剧界竞争很激烈。”朱莉娅说道。

“哦，我知道。除非你有影响力或其他什么，想出人头地简直看起来毫无希望。我听说您很快要上一出新剧。”

“是的。”

朱莉娅继续微笑着，态度和蔼得不像话。

“如果里面有个角色能给我，我会非常愿意和您一起演戏。很遗憾格斯林先生今晚无法过来。”

“我会把你的情况告诉他的。”

“您觉得真的有机会给我吗？”在她的自信中，在她为了给朱莉娅留下深刻印象而装出的乡间别墅人士的气派中，都贯穿着一种急于求成的焦躁，“如果您能替我说句话，那对我帮助太大了。”

朱莉娅若有所思地看了她一眼。

“比起我丈夫采纳我的建议，更多的是我听他的建议。”她微笑道。

为了让艾维丝·克赖顿换衣服准备第三幕剧，他们离开了化妆间，朱莉娅看到艾维斯在跟汤姆说再见时给了他一个询问的眼神。朱莉娅意识到汤姆轻轻地摇了摇头，虽然她没有看到他的动作。她的感觉在那一刻非常敏锐，她把这段无声的对话转化成了语言。

“演出结束后一起吃晚餐吗？”

“不，可恶，我去不了，我得送她回家。”

朱莉娅表情严肃地听完了第三幕，由于那是一出严肃的剧目，倒也符合。演出全部结束后，一个苍白的、疲惫不堪的作者结结巴巴地讲了一番话，汤姆则问她晚上想去哪里吃晚饭。

“我们回家吧，聊一聊。”她说道，“如果你饿了，我确信厨房里有你能吃的东西。”

“你是说斯坦霍普广场吗？”

“是的。”

“好吧。”

她感觉到，他为她不想回公寓而松了一口气。在车里的时候，他沉默不语，她知道他同她一起回去不高兴。她猜，可能有什么人举行晚宴，艾维斯·克赖顿会去参加，汤姆也想过去。当他们回到家时，房子又暗又空。仆人们都上床休息了。朱莉娅建议他们应该去地下室找点吃的。

“除非你想吃，我并不想吃什么。”他说道，“我喝一杯威士忌苏打就好，然后就去休息了。明天办公室工作很繁重。”

“好的。拿到会客厅来吧，我去开灯。”

当他上来的时候，她正对着镜子化妆，直到他倒好威士忌，坐了下来，她才停下来，转过身。他看起来非常年轻，魅力四射，穿着他那身漂亮的衣服，坐在那个大大的扶手椅里，于是，那晚她感到的所有痛苦，过去几天吞噬了她的嫉妒心，顿时消散在她的激情中。她坐在他椅子的扶手上，充满爱意地抚摸他的头发。他生气地把身子往后缩。

“别这么做，”他说道，“我讨厌头发被弄乱。”

这好像一把刀刺进她的心脏。他从未用这种语气跟她说过话。但她轻轻地笑了笑，站起身来，端着他为她倒的威士忌，坐到了他对面的椅子里。他做出的动作，说的话，都是出于本能的，他有些窘迫。他躲闪她的目光，脸上再次显现郁郁不乐的神情。这一刻是决定性的。有一阵子，他俩都保持了沉默。朱莉娅的心脏痛苦地跳着，但最后，她强迫自己说话。

“告诉我，”她微笑着说道，“你跟艾维斯·克赖顿上床了吗？”

“当然没有。”他大喊道。

“为什么没有？她很漂亮。”

“她不是那种女孩。我尊敬她。”

朱莉娅没有让自己的任何感情表露在脸上。她的举止非常随意；她可能是在谈论古今帝国的衰亡或帝王的逝世。

“你知道我本该说什么吗？我该说你疯狂地爱着她。”他仍旧不肯直视她的眼睛。“有可能你们已经订婚了吗？”

“不。”

他现在看着她，但那双眼睛充满敌意。

“你向她求过婚吗？”

“我能吗？像我这样一个该死的浑蛋。”

他说得如此愤慨，让朱莉娅感到惊讶。

“你什么意思？”

“兜圈子有什么意思？我怎么能让一个正派的女孩嫁给我？我就是个被包养的男孩，上帝知道，你当然明白。”

“别犯蠢了。我不过送了你几件礼物，有什么可大惊小怪的。”

“我不应该接受。我一直知道这是错误的。这一切不知不觉，直到我陷入其中了才意识到发生了什么。我负担不起你让我过上的生活；经济上捉襟见肘。我不得不从你那儿拿钱。”

“为什么不？毕竟，我是个很有钱的女人。”

“你那该死的钱。”

他双手捧着一个玻璃杯，一时冲动之下将它摔在了壁炉里。那杯子四分五裂。

“你没必要破坏这个快乐的家。”朱莉娅嘲讽地说道。

“对不起。这不是我的本意。”他坐回到他的椅子里，把头扭向一边，“我对自己感到羞愧。失去自尊不是什么好事。”

朱莉娅犹豫了一下。她不知道该说什么。

“你遇到困难的时候，帮助你一下看起来非常顺理成章。对我来说是件乐事。”

“我知道，你这方面做得很老练。你几乎让我相信让你为我还债是我在给你帮忙。你让我轻易地变成个无赖。”

“很遗憾你会这么认为。”

她语气酸溜溜的。她开始觉得有点生气了。

“没什么值得你遗憾的。你想要我，你收买了我。如果我那么下贱，允许自己被收买，这跟你没什么关系。”

“你有这种感觉多久了？”

“从一开始。”

“这不是真的。”

她知道，让他良心觉醒的是他对那位他自以为纯洁的姑娘产生了爱情。可怜的蠢货！难道他不知道，如果艾维丝·克赖顿认为一个助理舞台监督可以给她弄到一个角色，她就会跟他睡觉吗？

“如果你爱上艾维斯·克赖顿，你为什么不告诉我？”他痛苦地看着她，但没有回答。“你害怕这会夺走她在新剧中表演的机会？你现在应该足够了解我了，我不会让感情上的事情妨碍剧院业务的。”

他几乎不相信他的耳朵。

“你这是什么意思？”

“我觉得她的确是个新秀。我会告诉迈克尔，我觉得她会演得很好。”

“哦，朱莉娅，你真够朋友。我从不知道你是这么非同寻常的女人。”

“你早该直接问我，我会告诉你的。”

他舒了口气。

“我亲爱的，我太喜欢你了。”

“我知道，我也非常喜欢你。跟你一起四处瞎逛很有趣，你又总是打扮得很漂亮，对任何女人来讲你都是她们的荣耀。我喜欢和你上床，我觉得你也喜欢和我上床。但是让我们面对现实吧，我可从来没有爱过你，正像你从来没有爱过我一样。我知道这事长久不了。你迟早一定会恋爱，那时我们的事就完了。现在你堕入情网了吧，是不是？”

“是的。”

她决定让他说出口，但当他真的说出来的时候，这话给她的痛是致命的。然而，她依旧好性子地微笑着，“我们一起过了不少快乐的时光，但你不觉得现在我们应该结束了吗？”

她说得如此自然，几乎像是在开玩笑，没人能猜到她内心的痛苦已经到了无法忍受的地步。她胆战心惊地等着他的回答。

“我非常抱歉，朱莉娅；我必须重获我的自尊。”他不安地看着她，“你没有生我的气吧？”

“因为你将你那易变的感情从我身上转移到艾维斯·克赖顿身上吗？”她的眼睛里跳跃着淘气的笑影，“我亲爱的，当然没有。毕竟，你所爱的人还是这个圈子里的。”

“我非常感激你为我做的一切。我不希望你认为我忘恩负义。”

“哦，我的小宠物，别说胡话了。我没有为你做什么。”她站起身，“现在，你必须得离开了。明天你工作繁忙，而我现在累坏了。”

汤姆心里卸下了一块重石。但他对此也并没有很开心，他对她如此友好但同时又有些嘲讽的语气感到困惑；他感到有点沮丧。他走上前与她吻别。她犹豫了一刹那，然后带着友好的微笑，凑上一边面颊给他亲吻，接着又凑上另一边。

“你自己可以出去，对吧？”她把手搭在嘴边以掩饰精心设计的哈欠，“哦，我太困了。”

汤姆离开后，朱莉娅立刻关掉灯，走向窗边。她谨慎地从窗帘缝隙中向外观望。她听到他关上了房子的大门，看到他走了出去。他左右看看。她立刻猜到他在找出租车。眼前一辆车都没有，他开始向公园的方向走去。她知道，他要去参加晚宴聚会和艾维斯·克赖顿会合，并告诉她这个好消息。朱莉娅一屁股坐到一把椅子里。她演了一场戏，演得好极了，现在她筋疲力尽。眼泪，没人能看到的眼泪顺着脸颊流下来。她非常不开心。只有一件事情能让她忍受她的不幸，那就是她对这个为了一个甚至都不知如何演戏的小角色女演员而放弃她的愚蠢男孩所产生的冷冷的鄙夷。真是荒唐。这个小角色不仅不会利用她的双手，连如何穿行过舞台都不明白。

“如果我有一点幽默感，我非得笑掉我的大牙，”她大声说道，“这是我听过的最有趣的笑话。”

她想着汤姆以后要怎么办。那套公寓的租金到季度结算日就到期了。里面有许多东西都属于她。他不会想再回到塔维斯托克广场的客厅兼卧室的公寓了。她想到他通过她结交的那些朋友。他善于利用他们。他们发现他有用处，他就可以跟他们保持关系。但要带着艾维斯对他来说就不那么容易了。艾维斯是一个铁石心肠、唯利是图的小东西，朱莉娅对此非常确定，当他的钱花得不那么痛快的时候，她就不会那么在乎他了。这个笨蛋竟然会被她的假贞洁吸引！朱莉娅知道这种类型的女人。很明显，她仅仅是在利用汤姆得到西登斯剧院的角色，当她拿到角色的时候，她就会把他抛到九霄云外。想到这点，朱莉娅跳起来。她答应了汤姆，艾维斯会拿到《当今时代》里的一个角色，因为这角色出现在朱莉娅演的那场里，但她并没有对自己的承诺太当真。还得迈克尔才能做最后的决定。

“上帝，她会得到那个角色。”她大声说道，不怀好意地笑起来，“天知道，我是个好性子的女人，但凡事都有个度。”

她想到将要扭转汤姆和艾维斯·克赖顿的局面，不禁感到得意。她狞笑着坐在黑暗里，策划如何实施此事。但时不时她会再次开始哭泣，因为她的潜意识里不断涌现着那些极为痛苦的回忆。汤姆苗条青春的肉体贴着她，他温暖赤裸的身子，还有他嘴唇特有的感觉，他的微笑，既羞怯又调皮，还有他鬈发的味道。

“我要不是笨蛋，我就什么都不说。如今我应该了解他了。他只是一时迷恋。他会醒悟过来，然后如饥似渴地重新回到我身边来。”

现在，她疲惫不堪，于是站起身来，上床去睡了。她服了些安眠药。

————————————————————

(1) 英格兰东南部肯特郡的一个海港。

第二十二章

第二天六点，朱莉娅一醒来就开始想念汤姆。她回忆她对汤姆说的一切，以及他对她说的一切。她感到厌烦又不快。唯一的安慰便是她淡漠轻松地处理了他们的关系破裂这件事，他不会猜到他让她多么痛苦。

整整一天她都非常难过，无法思考其他事情，她因为自己无法停止想念汤姆而生自己的闷气。如果她能将自己的痛苦和一个朋友倾诉一下，也不至于像现在这样难以忍受。她想要有人来安慰她，有人来告诉她，汤姆根本不值得她挂念，并且让她确信汤姆对她非常不好。以往她会向查尔斯或多莉倾诉。查尔斯当然会给予她所有想要的同情，但这对他打击太大，毕竟，他已经深爱了她二十年，如果告诉他，她将他乐意牺牲十年生命而换来的东西给了一个资质平平的年轻人，这太残酷了。她是他的理想女人，粉碎了这个形象她就太无情了。此刻，能得到如此高贵、有教养、优雅、爱她爱得至死不渝的查尔斯·泰默利的安慰一定会让她好过许多。当然，如果她向多莉吐露心声，多莉会觉得受宠若惊。近来她们没怎么见面，但朱莉娅知道，只要她给多莉打电话，多莉就会过来。即使多莉已经猜到了事实，但当朱莉娅和盘托出后，多莉也会被震惊并感到嫉妒，同时感谢一切都已经结束了，多莉会原谅她。将汤姆碎尸万段对她俩来说都是种安慰。当然，承认汤姆玩弄了她不是什么光彩的事，多莉很精明，她不可能被朱莉娅对汤姆说的那些谎话糊弄。她想对着什么人大哭一场，但如果是她主动选择结束，也就没有哭的理由。这将使多莉赢得一分，而且无论多莉怎样同情，你总不能对人性抱有奢望，以为她真会因朱莉娅的威风受挫而感到遗憾。多莉一向崇拜她。朱莉娅不愿让她窥见自己的弱点。

“看起来唯一能选择的人就只有迈克尔了，”她咯咯地笑着说，“但我想这也不行。”

她知道他会怎么说。

“我亲爱的姑娘，我真的不应该是你这种故事的倾诉对象。该死，你把我放在一个非常尴尬的位置。我自觉我是一个胸襟开阔的人，我或许是个演员，但说到底我是个绅士，我的意思，我的意思是，这事儿太不堪了。”

直到下午迈克尔才回到家，当他进入朱莉娅的房间时，她正在休息。他告诉她有关他周末的事情，以及他的比赛结果。他打得很好，有几局挽回得很出色，他把挽回的情形讲得非常详细。

“顺便问一句，昨晚你去看的那个女孩怎么样？她演得好吗？”

“我确实这么认为，你知道。她很漂亮。你肯定会喜欢上她。”

“哦，我亲爱的，在我这个年纪，不会喜欢上什么人了。她有演技吗？”

“当然，她缺乏经验，但我觉得她有天赋。”

“哦，好吧，我最好让她来一下，亲自看一看。我怎么能联系到她？”

“汤姆有她的地址。”

“那我现在就打给他。”

他拿起电话，拨通了汤姆的号码。汤姆接了电话，迈克尔把地址写在一张纸上。

对话仍在继续。

“哦，我的老伙计，很遗憾听到这消息。运气太差了！”

“怎么了？”朱莉娅问道。

他让她别说话。

“好吧，我不想对你太严格。别担心。我确定我们能想出个让你满意的安排。”他用手捂住话筒，转向朱莉娅，“我要邀请他下周日来吃晚餐吗？”

“如果你想的话。”

“朱莉娅说，周日你能来一起吃晚餐吗？哦，真遗憾。好吧，再见，老朋友。”

他挂掉了电话。

“他有约会。这个小流氓跟那女孩有一腿？”

“他跟我保证没有。他尊重她。她是个上校的女儿。”

“哦，她是个淑女。”

“我竟然不知道他俩有牵连，”朱莉娅尖酸地说道，“你刚才跟他在说什么？”

“他说他们给他减了工资。市场不景气。他不想租那套公寓了。”朱莉娅的心脏突然一阵狂跳。“我让他别担心。我会让他免费住着直到行情好转。”

“我不知道你为什么要这么做。毕竟，这纯粹是生意上的安排。”

“对像他那样的年轻家伙来讲，运气实在不好。而且你知道他对我们有用；如果我们宴会差一个人的话，总是可以招呼他过来，而且当我想让人陪着打高尔夫的时候，他就在附近，这很方便。一个季度就二十五英镑而已。”

“我真想不到你这个人竟会这样盲目地慷慨起来。”

“哦，别担心，我会失之东隅，收之桑榆的。”

此时，女按摩师到了，他们的对话就此结束。朱莉娅庆幸不久就会去剧院，可以暂时结束漫漫一日的痛苦；当她从剧院返回家里时，会再喝一点安眠药水，从而获得几个小时的短暂遗忘。她觉得几天后最痛苦的时期就会过去了；最重要的是咬紧牙关挺过这段时间。她必须分散一下自己的注意力。当她出门前往剧院时，她让男仆打电话给查尔斯·泰默利，看他明天是否有空陪她在丽兹饭店共进午餐。

午餐的时候查尔斯异常殷勤。他的仪表、举止都彰显着他属于不同于汤姆的世界，顿时，她对去年因为汤姆而进入的圈子感到一阵厌恶。他谈论政治、艺术和书籍；于是，她的灵魂平静下来。她对汤姆只是一时迷恋，她现在明白那是害人的；她打算从那段感情中逃离出来。她打起精神。她不想一个人待着，她知道即使午餐后她回到家中也无法入睡，于是她问查尔斯能否带她去国家美术馆。这让查尔斯感到莫大的愉悦；他喜欢谈论画，并且讲得头头是道。这让他们回到她在伦敦初露头角的旧时光，那时他们一起共度了许多下午时光，在公园里漫步，或是在博物馆里闲逛。第二天，她有日场表演，之后一天她参加了午餐聚会，而当他们分开时又约定周五一起午餐，然后去泰特美术馆。

几天后，迈克尔告诉她，他已经聘用了艾维斯·克赖顿。

“她的长相满足角色需求，这一点毫无疑问，她会和你形成鲜明的对比。我是听了你的推荐才录用她的。”

第二天早晨，仆人从地下室打电话上来说有芬内尔先生的电话。她的心脏似乎停止了跳动。

“把电话接上来。”

“朱莉娅，我要告诉你，迈克尔聘用了艾维斯。”

“是的，我知道。”

“他对艾维斯说是听了你的推荐才聘用她的。你太够义气了。”

这会儿朱莉娅的心跳剧烈地加快了，她竭力控制住自己的声音。

“哦，别说傻话啦，”她欢欣地回答，“我早对你说没问题的。”

“我很高兴这一切都定下来了。她基于我告诉她的情况，已经接受了那个角色。一般情况下她不读剧本是不会接受任何角色的。”

朱莉娅听到汤姆这样说的时候，幸亏汤姆没有看到此刻她的脸。她本想尖刻地回答，聘用这种小角色演员时从来不会让他们读剧本，但她温柔地说道：

“好吧，我觉得她会喜欢的，难道你不这么认为？那是很不错的角色。”

“而且你知道，她会尽全力演好这个角色的。我相信她会引起轰动的。”

朱莉娅深吸一口气。

“太棒了，不是吗？我是说，这个角色可能让她成名。”

“是的，我已经跟她说了这些。我说，我什么时候再去见你？”

“我会打电话给你，好吗？太可恶了，接下来几天我的日程全部都是约会。”

“你不会丢下我就因为……”

她发出一阵低沉而沙哑的笑声，那种让观众很开心的笑声。

“别犯傻。哦，上帝，我的浴缸正在放水。我必须去看看。再见，我亲爱的。”

她放下电话。他的声音！她内心的痛苦简直无法忍受。她坐在床上，在痛苦中来回晃着身子。

“我该怎么做？我该怎么做？”

她以为她已经过了这道坎，但刚才那通简短愚蠢的对话表明，她对他的爱没有丝毫减弱。她想要他。她一天到晚无时无刻不在思念他。她不能没有他。

“我可能永远忘不掉他了。”她哀号道。

剧院再一次成为她唯一的庇护所。让人觉得讽刺的是，她正在演的戏里最精彩的那一场，也是让这部戏获得成功的那一场，正是两个情人的分手戏。他们出于责任感而分手；而朱莉娅，在剧中，为了正义而牺牲了她的爱，她获得幸福的希望以及她所热爱的一切。这是一场从一开始就非常吸引她的戏。她演得感人至深。她把她精神中所有的痛苦之情都置于这场戏的表演中；她所演的不再是一个伤心的角色，而是她自己的。在现实生活中，她竭力遏制这种非常可笑的激情，这爱情配不上她这样的女人，她强迫自己尽量不去想这个给她带来严重创伤的穷小子；但当她演这段戏的时候就放任自己。她丝毫没有控制自己的痛苦。她对自己失去的感到绝望，她对演她情人的男人所倾注的爱是她对汤姆仍旧怀有的狂热而炽烈的爱。剧中的女主角面临的空虚生活的前景正是她自己的空虚生活的前景。但至少让人安慰的是，她感到自己从未演得如此美妙动人。

“我的天，能展现这样的表演，所受的痛苦也值了。”

她从未这样多地将自我融入一个角色。

一两周后的一晚，她在演出结束后回到化妆间，因她刚刚所表达的情感而筋疲力尽，同时又因无数次的返场谢幕而感到扬扬得意，她发现迈克尔在那儿坐着。

“哈喽？你刚才不会也在观看吧？”

“是的。”

“但你两三天前刚看过。”

“是的，我已经连看了四个晚上了。”

她开始脱衣服。迈克尔从椅子上起身，在房间里来回走动。朱莉娅看了他一眼，发现他微微皱着眉头。

“怎么了？”

“那正是我想知道的。”

她心里一惊，脑子里闪过迈克尔可能听到了更多关于汤姆和她的流言的念头。

“伊维为什么不在这里？”她问道。

“我让她出去了。我有些事情要跟你说，朱莉娅。你大发脾气有什么用？你得听我说。”

一阵冷战刺痛她的脊梁。

“好吧，你想说什么？”

“我听到了一些事情，我想我最好自己来看看。起初我以为只是个意外。因此在我确定之前什么都没说。你怎么了，朱莉娅？”

“我怎么了？”

“是的。为什么你表演得这么糟糕？”

“我？”朱莉娅完全没有想到迈克尔会跟她说这个。她满眼怒火地看着迈克尔，“你可真笨，我从未演得像现在这样好过。”

“胡扯。你演得糟糕透了。”

当然，听到他说的是她的演技后，朱莉娅松了口气，但迈克尔所说的太可笑了，即使她感到非常愤怒，也不由得大笑。

“你这该死的白痴，你根本不知道你在说什么。哼，关于表演，我不知道的都是不值得我去知道的东西；你知道的都是拜我所赐。如果你还算个说得过去的演员的话，那也得归功于我。毕竟，‘布丁好不好，吃了才知道’。你晓得我今天谢幕多少次？这部戏演到现在，还从没这样精彩过。”

“这些我全知道。观众都是些蠢货。如果你大喊大叫，手舞足蹈，总会有一堆可恶的傻瓜朝你愚蠢地喊来喊去。过去四个晚上，你所进行的就是假模假式的游说表演。从头到尾都太假了。”

“太假了？但我对剧中的台词每个字都深有体会。”

“我不管你的感受是什么，你并没有在表现它们。你的表演一团乱。你在夸张；你演过了；你的表演一刻都不能让人信服。这简直是我一生中看到的最糟糕最过火的表演。”

“你太让人讨厌了，你怎么敢这么说我？你才是假模假式的演员。”

她张开手，重重地给了迈克尔一巴掌。他笑了。

“你可以打我，你可以骂我，你可以喊破喉咙，但事实是你的表演烂到地狱了。我不打算以你现在的表演开始彩排《当今时代》。”

“那你去找一个能演得比我更好的人来彩排吧。”

“别犯傻，朱莉娅。我自己可能不是个好演员，我也从来没有这么认为过，但我分得清好的表演和坏的表演。而且，我对你再了解不过了。我打算星期六张贴布告，然后我想让你出国。我们会在秋季的时候推出《当今时代》。”

迈克尔沉静坚定的语气让朱莉娅平静下来。确实，当说到演戏，迈克尔知道有关朱莉娅的一切。

“我演得真的那么糟吗？”

“非常糟。”

她思索了一下。她知道哪里出了问题。她让自己的感情随她一起放逐；她是在感受而不是在演戏。又是一阵寒战贯穿她的脊梁。这是个严重问题。心碎无所谓，但是不能让破碎的心来影响演戏……不，不，不。这是两码事。她的表演比世界上任何一桩恋爱都更重要。

“我会试着控制我自己。”

“强迫自己也没什么用。你太累了。是我的错，我早就应该带你去度假。你需要的就是好好休息。”

“剧院怎么办？”

“如果不能把它租出去，我会重新上演一部我能出演的剧，比如《红桃是王牌》。你总是讨厌那部剧里你的角色。”

“所有人都说这个演出季会非常棒。没有我的演员阵容，你休想一部旧剧能有多大成功；你一分钱都挣不到。”

“我一点都不在乎。唯一要紧的就是你的健康。”

“哦，上帝，请不要再这么宽容了，”她喊道，“我承受不起。”

突然间，朱莉娅哭了起来。

“亲爱的。”

迈克尔抱着朱莉娅，让她和自己并排坐在沙发上。她绝望地紧紧抱着迈克尔。

“你对我太好了，迈克尔，我恨自己。我太坏了，我是个荡妇，我是个可恶的婊子。我从里到外都糟糕透了。”

“就算你说的都是对的，”迈克尔微笑道，“但这掩盖不了你是个好演员的事实。”

“我不知道你是怎么做到对我如此耐心。我待你太卑鄙无耻了。你待我太好了，而我却无情地牺牲了你。”

“现在，宝贝，别再说你以后会后悔的话了。下次我就会提起它们与你作对。”

他的温柔融化了她，她为自己这么多年来觉得他无聊至极而狠狠责骂自己。

“感谢上帝，我拥有你。没了你我该怎么办？”

“你不会没有我的。”

他紧紧地抱着她，虽然她还在哭泣，但已开始感到慰藉。

“很抱歉刚才对你那么恶劣。”

“哦，亲爱的。”

“你真的觉得我是个假模假式的女演员？”

“哦，亲爱的，杜丝都没法跟你相提并论。”

“你真的那么认为？给我你的小手帕。你从来没见过萨拉·伯恩哈特的戏，是不是？”

“是的，没有。”

“她欢嚷吵闹得可厉害呢。”

他们默默地坐了一会儿，朱莉娅渐渐地平静下来。她的心里充满了对迈克尔深沉的爱。

“你依然是全英国最好看的男人，”最后她喃喃说道，“谁也不能让我改变这个想法。”

她感到迈克尔缩回了肚皮，挺起了他的下巴，这在她看来非常可爱、动人。

“你说得很对。我很累。我情绪不好，苦不堪言。我只觉得心里一片空虚。唯一的办法是走开一阵。”

第二十三章

朱莉娅打定主意后，轻松起来。想到可以立即逃离折磨着她的痛苦，这让她觉得一切变得容易忍受。布告张贴出来了；迈克尔召集重演《红桃是王牌》的演员班底开始排练。朱莉娅闲坐在剧院座位上，充满趣味地看着参加重演的女演员表演她几年前曾经演过的角色。在她刚刚开始舞台生涯时，坐在熄了灯的、套着防尘套的剧场里，观看一个个剧中人物由演员演出来，那种激动迄今没有消失。仅仅是在剧院中就让她平静；没有什么地方能更让她感到快乐。观看排练让她放松下来，因此晚上上台表演的时候她感觉自己焕然一新。她意识到迈克尔说的都是真的。她控制住了自己，将自己的私人感情埋藏在意识背后，才能获得对角色的把控，于是她再次展现了自己精湛的演技。她的表演不再是用来发泄她个人的情感，而是又重现她创作的天赋。对表演重获驾驭之力让她感到暗暗欢喜，这给予她一种力量和自由的感觉。

但是这种成功的努力使她精疲力竭，当她不在剧院的时候，只觉得百无聊赖，灰心丧气。她丢失了那旺盛的生命力。一种新的羞耻感打败了她。她觉得自己过气了。她叹息着对自己说没有人再需要她了。迈克尔建议她应该去维也纳和罗杰待一阵子，虽然她喜欢这样的安排，但还是摇摇头。

“我只会影响他的生活方式。”

她担心罗杰会讨厌她。他正在享受自己的生活，而她只会挡了他的路。她无法忍受罗杰会觉得带她四处去逛或者时不时与她共进午餐或晚餐是一件令人厌烦又不得不做的事情。他应该和他的同龄朋友一起开心地玩。她决定去和她母亲住几日。兰伯特太太——迈克尔总是坚持称呼她为德·兰伯特夫人——已经和她的妹妹法卢夫人在圣马洛住了许多年了。每年兰伯特太太会去伦敦和朱莉娅住上几天，但今年因为身体原因没有成行。她已经是个七十多岁的老太太了，朱莉娅知道她会非常乐意自己的女儿陪她住上一段时日。在维也纳，有谁会在乎一个英国女演员？在那儿，她就是个普通人。但在圣马洛，她将是一个引人注目的人物，那两位老太太可以拿她在她们的朋友们面前得意地献宝，倒也有趣。

“我的女儿，英国最伟大的女演员”，以及诸如此类的话。

可怜的老姑娘，她们活不了太久了，过着单调无趣的生活。当然，对朱莉娅来说会非常无聊，但对她们来说会是个盛会。朱莉娅有种感觉，也许在她辉煌而成功的事业中多少忽视了她的母亲。此次她可以做些弥补。她要让自己做到和蔼可亲。她对迈克尔亲切有爱，并始终非常内疚地感到对不起迈克尔。她觉得自己自私傲慢，并想要补偿这一切。她急于做出牺牲，于是写信告知母亲，自己即将前往她那里。

直到离开伦敦的最后一天，她极自然地避开与汤姆相见。上演的戏剧于前一晚闭幕，傍晚她就要起身前往圣马洛了。汤姆六点左右过来和她说再见。迈克尔、多莉、查尔斯·泰默利还有其他一两个人也在，因此汤姆和她也没有机会独处。朱莉娅已经不难跟他自然地进行对话。与他相见并没有让朱莉娅产生令她害怕的那种痛苦，只不过是一阵迟钝的心痛。他们没有对外界公开她离开的时间和地点，剧院的媒体代表也仅仅给几家报纸打了电话，所以朱莉娅和迈克尔到达车站时，车站上只有五六个新闻记者和三个摄影师。朱莉娅和迈克尔分别跟他们说了几句客套话，然后媒体代表把记者带到一旁，并给他们简单介绍了朱莉娅的计划。同时，朱莉娅和迈克尔摆好姿势，让摄影记者在闪光灯的照射下拍摄他们手挽着手、相互吻别的样子。最后，朱莉娅从车厢窗户探出半个身子，将手递给站在站台上的迈克尔。

“这群人太讨厌了，”她说道，“简直没办法逃开他们。”

“我不明白他们是怎么知道你要离开的。”

看到这景象而聚集过来的一小群人跟他们礼貌地保持着一定的距离。媒体代表走过来跟迈克尔说，他觉得记者得到的信息够写一篇专栏了。火车驶出了车站。

朱莉娅拒绝带着伊维一起去。她觉得，若想重获平静，她必须与旧日的生活彻底分割开。伊维在那个法国家庭中会格格不入。对于法卢夫人，也就是朱莉娅的嘉莉姨妈，在她是小姑娘的时候就嫁了一个法国人，现在已是个很老很老的老太太，法语说得比英语还顺口。她丈夫去世多年，她唯一的儿子战死疆场。她住在山上一幢高耸狭窄的石头房子里，当你穿过鹅卵石的街道跨入这门槛，就进入了宁静的过去时代。半个世纪以来这里一切都没有变化。画室摆了一套路易十五风格的家具，套着罩子，这些罩子一个月只拿掉一次，为了小心翼翼地刷一刷下面的丝绸。水晶灯用棉布包着，防止苍蝇叮。壁炉架前是用孔雀毛精巧地编成的火炉栏，用玻璃挡着。虽然这屋子从来不用，但嘉莉姨妈每日都亲自打扫。餐厅镶有护壁板，这里的椅子也罩着防尘罩。餐具柜上搁着一个银饰架、一个银咖啡壶、一个银茶壶和一只银盘子。嘉莉姨妈和朱莉娅的母亲——兰伯特太太——同住在一间晨室，这是间细长狭窄的屋子，布置着法兰西帝国时代的家具。墙上挂着椭圆形的画，是嘉莉姨妈和她已故丈夫的油画像，还有他父母亲的油画像，还有一幅她已故的儿子小时候的彩色画像。她们在这儿做针线活儿，看报纸，读天主教的《十字架报》《两个世界评论报》和当地的日报，晚上在这里玩多米诺骨牌。除了周四晚上，神父和拉加尔德舰长——一位退伍的海军军官——来共进晚餐外，她们还在这里吃饭；但是朱莉娅来了以后，她们决定在餐室里吃饭比较方便。

嘉莉姨妈还在为她的丈夫和儿子服丧。她穿着亲自编织的那件黑色小毛衣，很少有热得穿不住的时候。兰伯特太太也穿着黑色丧服，可是当神父先生和舰长来吃晚饭时，她会在肩上披上一条朱莉娅送给她的网眼白围巾。晚饭过后，他们会玩普拉丰牌戏，输赢以一百分两苏计算。兰伯特太太因为在泽西岛住过多年，现在依旧去伦敦，知道外面世界的情况，她说有种叫约定桥牌的游戏很流行，但是舰长说这游戏很适合美国人，他玩普拉丰就足够了，神父说他觉得惠斯特没人玩了很可惜。然而，男人们从来不满足于自己拥有的；他们总是想要变化，变化，变化。

每个圣诞节朱莉娅都会给她母亲和姨妈贵重的礼物，但她们从未使用过。她们把这些来自伦敦的可贵礼物骄傲地展现给她们的朋友，然后用棉纸包好，存放在橱柜之中。朱莉娅本想给她母亲买辆车，但被拒绝了。她们极少出门，出门也可步行；若有司机，她们还需担心司机会偷她们的汽油。如果让司机在外面吃饭，她们担心会让她们破产；如果让司机在家里吃饭，这会让安妮塔心神不安。安妮塔是她们的厨子、管家兼女仆。她已经在嘉莉姨妈身边陪伴了三十五年。她的侄女安琪儿会帮着干些粗活儿，但安琪儿很年轻，她还不到四十岁，因此，屋里总有一个男人在场不大妥当。

她们让朱莉娅就住在她上学时在嘉莉姨妈家住的那间屋子里。这屋子让她产生一种奇特的令人心碎的感觉，颇让她感动。然而她很快就适应了这里的生活。嘉莉姨妈出嫁后就变成了一个天主教徒，兰伯特夫人在其丈夫去世后在圣马洛安定下来，接受了神父的指导，没过太久也成了信徒。这两位老夫人很虔诚。她们每天早晨同去望弥撒，星期日参加大弥撒。此外，她们极少出门。若出门也是礼节性地去拜访某位家中有亲人去世或者有孙子孙女订婚的老太太。她们读报纸、杂志，为了慈善做很多针线活儿，玩多米诺骨牌，听听朱莉娅送给她们的收音机。虽然神父和舰长每周四与她们共进晚餐的习惯持续了许多年，但每到这一天她们仍旧十分惶恐。这位舰长有水手的心直口快，她们对此不以为奇，若有什么东西烹调得不合他口味，他会毫不犹豫地说出来，甚至连那神父，尽管他是个圣人，也有喜欢吃的和不喜欢吃的。例如，他很喜欢诺曼底板鱼，但他坚持要用最好的黄油来烹饪，而这种黄油在战后价格十分昂贵。每个周四早晨，嘉莉姨妈会从她暗藏钥匙的地方拿出地窖钥匙，亲自从地窖里拿出一瓶红葡萄酒。她们姐妹会在一周内把剩余的酒喝完。

她们对朱莉娅关心备至。她们为她准备了草药茶，竭力不让她坐在可能有穿堂风的地方。事实上，她们一生的一大部分时间都致力于避免穿堂风了。她们让她躺在沙发上，并焦虑地让她遮住自己的脚。她们同她理论她穿的衣服。那些丝袜太薄，一眼就能看穿；那她贴身穿着什么？如果嘉莉姨妈发现她光穿着一件无袖的宽松内衣，也会毫不惊奇。

“她连那个都没穿。”兰伯特夫人说道。

“那她穿了什么？”

“内裤。”朱莉娅说。

“总还戴着胸罩吧，我想。”

“当然没有。”朱莉娅尖刻地回答道。

“那侄女，你裙子下面什么都没穿？”

“算是吧。”

“太荒唐了。”嘉莉姨妈说。

“这太不像话了，我的女儿。”兰伯特夫人说道。

“我并不是故作正经，”嘉莉姨妈又说道，“我必须说这可一点都不得体。”

朱莉娅给她们展示了她的衣服，在她到达后的第一个周四，她们一起讨论了她应该穿什么出席晚餐。嘉莉姨妈和兰伯特夫人彼此争论起来。兰伯特夫人认为，既然她女儿带来了晚礼服，她应该穿着，但嘉莉姨妈觉得很没有必要。

“以前我去泽西看你的时候，我的宝贝，那些绅士来赴晚宴，我记得你会穿一件茶会礼服。”

“当然，茶会礼服会很适合。”

她们充满希望地看着朱莉娅。她摇了摇头。

“用不了太久我就得穿寿衣了。”

嘉莉姨妈穿着一件厚重的高领黑丝裙，戴着一串黑玉珠子，兰伯特夫人也穿了一件类似的，不过她披了一件蕾丝长方披肩，戴了一串人造宝石项链。舰长敦实矮小，满脸皱纹，白发剪得像刷子一般，嘴巴上威风的胡子染成了深黑色。他对朱莉娅很是殷勤，虽然七十多岁了，吃晚饭时还在餐桌底下暗暗碰了她的脚。出去的时候，他抓住机会捏了她的屁股。

“性感。”跟着两个老太太走进客厅时，朱莉娅神气十足地对自己喃喃道。

她们对她大惊小怪，这倒不是因为她是个有名的女演员，而是因为她身体欠佳，需要休息。不久，朱莉娅惊讶地发现，她的名气对她们来说不是什么炫耀的资本，倒成了尴尬之事。她们出去拜访时，都没有主动邀请她，更不用说想要拿她出风头。嘉莉姨妈还一直保持着在泽西养成的下午茶的习惯，从未间断过。一天，在朱莉娅到达不久后，她们邀请了几位太太来喝下午茶，兰伯特夫人午饭时对她女儿说道：

“我的宝贝，我们在圣马洛有一些很不错的朋友，但即使这么多年过去了，她们依旧将我们当成外国人，因此我们不想做什么看起来古怪的事情。很自然，我们也不想让你撒谎，但除非你不得以必须提及此事，你嘉莉姨妈觉得，最好不要向别人说你是个女演员。”

朱莉娅被吓了一跳，但依着她那幽默的秉性，她竟感到想笑。

“如果今天下午我们邀请的朋友之中有哪个碰巧问起你丈夫是做什么的，就说是经商的，这么说也不算不真实，对吧？”

“完全不会。”朱莉娅说道，让自己笑了笑。

“当然我们知道英国女演员和法国的不一样，”嘉莉姨妈善意地说道，“法国女演员有情人已经是心照不宣的事情。”

“哦，我的天。”朱莉娅感叹道。

她在伦敦的日子，还有那里的精彩、得意和痛苦，似乎越来越遥远。不久，她就发现能用平常心态去思考汤姆和她对汤姆的感情了。她认识到，比起她的心，受到更多伤害的是她的虚荣。日子单调地过着。很快，唯一能让她想起伦敦的事情就是周一送来的周日报纸。她拿了一大摞，整日沉浸在阅读中。她感到有点不安。她漫步在城墙上，看着海湾里星罗棋布的小岛。灰色的天空让她思念英国的天空。但到周二早晨，她就又重新沉浸到这种乡下生活的宁静中。她大量地阅读从当地书店买来的小说，英语的、法语的，还有她最爱的魏尔伦。他的诗歌中含有淡淡的忧伤，很适合灰色的布列塔尼镇，很适合那些忧郁的老石头房子，还有那些陡峭弯曲的幽静街道。两位老太太娴静的习惯、平静无事的日常生活还有她们悄声的闲谈，激起她的同情。很多年来她们的生活平淡无奇，直到她们死去也不会再有什么新鲜事发生了，她们的生活是多么没有意义。奇怪的是她们很知足。她们既不知怨恨也不知嫉妒。她们已经达到了朱莉娅站在舞台脚光灯前，向热烈鼓掌的观众鞠躬时所感到的那种超然离群的境界。有时她觉得那种超然是她最珍贵的财富。这种超然于她是来自傲气，于她们则来自屈辱。这两种情况都带来一种弥足珍贵的事情，精神上的自由；只是在这两位老太太身上更为牢固。

迈克尔每周给她写一封简短务实的信，信里他会告诉她西登斯剧院的收入，还有为了下一部剧他所做的准备；但查尔斯·泰默利每天都给她写信。他告诉她伦敦城里的闲话，他以他那迷人、有教养的方式谈论他看过的那些画和他读的那些书。他亲切地引经据典，调皮地显现他的渊博。他进行哲学讨论又不故意卖弄。他告诉她，他爱慕她。那是朱莉娅收到过的最动人的情书，为了传之后世，她决定好好保留。有一天也许会有人将它们出版，人们会去国家肖像美术馆看她那幅由麦克沃伊画的肖像，想到她是这个凄婉动人的爱情故事的女主角而喟叹。

在她离开的头两周里，查尔斯对她尤为亲近，她不知道没了他自己要怎么办。他对她总是有求必应。他同她的对话，带着她进入了一个不同的世界，舒缓了她的神经。她陷入泥潭的灵魂，在他崇高的精神中得到了净化。跟他逛美术馆，看看画，让她安定。她对他极为感激。她回想他爱着她的这么多年，到现在他已经等了她二十多年之久。她待他并不好。若得到她，这会给他带来极大的幸福，而对她而言也没什么伤害。她在想为什么拒绝了他那么久。或许因为他太忠诚，因为他的忠诚太卑微了，或许仅仅因为她想在他心里维持自己的理想形象。这实在是愚蠢的，她太自私了。她突然欣喜地意识到，她终于能对他多年来的温柔耐心和无私忘我予以报答。她并没有忘掉迈克尔十足的关怀在她心中所激起的不相配感，她依旧因为长期对他感到不耐烦而深深懊悔。她离开英国时内心急于自我牺牲的感觉依旧在她胸中急切地燃着烈火。她觉得查尔斯正是值得她奉献自我的对象。一想到当他明白她的意图时的惊讶，她亲切又慈悲地笑了笑；一时间他会几乎不敢相信，之后便是何等的陶醉和狂喜！这么多年来他对她蓄积着的爱将如一股巨大的激流冲破闸门，将她淹没。想到他无限的感激，令她的心膨胀起来。但是他依旧无法相信自己的好运气；当一切结束后，她会躺在他的怀抱里，偎依在他身边，温柔地低语：

“这一切可值得这么多年的等待？”

“像海伦一般，你对我的一吻让我此生永恒(1)。”

能给一个人这么多幸福，真是不可思议。

“离开圣马洛前我会写信给他。”她如此决定了。

春季已过，进入夏季，时间到了七月底，朱莉娅将起程前往巴黎查看她定制的衣服。迈克尔想在九月份上演新剧，排练也会在八月开始。她带着剧本到了圣马洛，想要研习她的角色，但她所居住的环境让她无法如愿。她有空余时间，不过，在那个灰蒙蒙的简朴又舒适的小镇里，在两位兴趣只限于郊区教堂和她们家庭琐事的老人的陪伴下，即便这是一部好剧，她也提不起兴趣。

“是我该回去的时候了，”她说道，“如果我真的认为剧院不值得他们如此大惊小怪，那才真是该死。”

她向母亲和嘉莉姨妈道别。她们对她非常亲切，但她略微感觉到，她们并没有为她的离开而感到遗憾，她离开后她们便可回到被她打断之前的生活。而且，让她们感到欣慰的是再也不会出现不得体的危险了，例如你总是冒着和一个女演员在一起的风险，这可能会引起圣马洛的太太们的非议。

她下午到达巴黎，被领入利兹饭店的套房后，她满意地叹了口气。重回奢华的生活真是一件让人享受的事情。三四个人向她送来了鲜花。她沐浴更衣。一直为她做衣服的查理·德夫里尔已经是她的老朋友了，打电话来说要带她去布洛涅森林吃晚餐。

“我度过了一段很愉快的时光，”她告诉他，“当然对那两位老姑娘来说，有我在身边也非常愉快，但我觉得如果我再多待一天我便成了她们讨厌的人了。”

在这样一个美妙的夜晚，乘车在香榭丽舍大街上行驶，让她内心充满欢悦。她很高兴再次闻到汽油的味道。汽车、出租车、喇叭声、栗树、街灯，路上拥挤的人群，还有咖啡馆外坐着的人们，让人着迷。当他们到达充满欢声笑语、文明而奢华的马德里城堡，再次看到穿着入时、化妆得体的女人和肤色深棕、身穿晚礼服的男人时，她感觉棒极了。

“我觉得自己像流放回来的皇后。”

朱莉娅用了几天的工夫愉快地选购她的衣服，并首次试穿戏服。她每时每刻都享受其中。但她是个个性十足的女人，一旦下了决心必然会坚持到底；在前往伦敦前，她给查尔斯写了封信。他已去过了古德伍德(2)和考斯(3)，在他去往萨尔茨堡(4)前，会在伦敦待上二十四小时。

亲爱的查尔斯：

很快就能见到你真的是太好了。周三我当然有空。我们能一起共进晚餐吗？你还爱我吗？

你的朱莉娅

粘信封时她喃喃道：雪中送炭(5)。这是一句迈克尔被邀请向慈善机构捐款时常常引用的一句拉丁语，通常他会将人们希望他捐款数额的一半邮寄回去。

————————————————————

(1) 典出英国剧作家、诗人马洛（Christopher Marlowe，1564—1593）的剧本《浮士德博士的悲剧》：“可爱的海伦，用一吻使我永生吧。”

(2) 位于英国西萨塞克斯郡的一个特色小镇，有著名的赛马场。

(3) 英格兰的一个港口城镇和民政教区，位于怀特岛。

(4) 奥地利城市。

(5) 原文为拉丁语，Bis dat qui cito dat。

第二十四章

周三早上，朱莉娅做了美容，烫了头发。对于出席晚餐的服装，她在两条裙子的选择上犹豫不决，一条是极为美丽、让人想起波提切利的《春》的印花蝉翼纱裙，另一条是剪裁优雅、彰显她处女般苗条年轻身形的白色绸缎裙；但当她沐浴时，她决定要穿那件白色绸缎裙：它非常微妙地暗示她想要做出的牺牲是她对迈克尔长期忘恩负义的赎罪。她什么珠宝也没有戴，只戴了一串珍珠项链和一个钻石手镯；除了她的结婚戒指之外，也只有一个镶方形钻石的戒指。她本想把皮肤敷成浅棕色，让自己看起来像个户外女孩，这很适合她，但想到之后她要做的事情，便放弃了这个打算。她无法像将全身涂抹成黑色来饰演奥赛罗的男演员一样，将自己全身都敷成浅棕色。朱莉娅素来是一个准时的女人，当前门打开迎进查尔斯的时候，她正从楼上走下来。她和查尔斯打招呼，眼神中满是温柔，既迷人淘气又亲切无比。查尔斯如今一头稀疏的白发留得很长，随着年事渐高，他那智者的、非同凡响的五官也有些下垂；他有点驼背，衣服看上去似乎需要熨烫。

“真是个奇怪的世界，”朱莉娅想，“男演员极力想看起来像绅士，而绅士则极力打扮得像演员。”

毫无疑问，她对他产生了应有的影响。他给了她完美的开场白。

“为何今夜的你看上去如此可爱？”他问道。

“因为我很期待与你共进晚餐。”

她那一双美丽传情的眼睛注视着他的眼睛。她张开嘴唇，像她在罗姆尼所画的汉密尔顿夫人的肖像画上看到的那样吸引人。

他们在萨瓦(1)进餐。饭店领班带他们坐在临着过道的一张餐桌旁，这样他们就能被人们极好地注意到。虽然此时是外出的季节，然而饭店餐厅依旧坐满了人。朱莉娅向几个她看到的朋友点头微笑。查尔斯有许多话要告诉她；她讨好般兴致勃勃地听着。

“你是世上最好的陪伴，查尔斯。”她告诉他。

他们来得迟了，晚餐吃得很不错，当查尔斯喝完他的白兰地，人们已经开始来吃夜宵了。

“天哪，剧院演出已经结束了？”他说道，看了一眼手表，“每当我和你在一起时，时间总是过得飞快。你觉得他们是不是想赶我们走了？”

“我还一点都不想去睡觉。”

“我想迈克尔此刻要到家了吧？”

“我觉得是。”

“你为什么不来我家，我们聊一聊？”

这就是她所谓的领会暗示。

“我很愿意。”她回答道，语气中添加了一丝她觉得会与她脸蛋儿极其相称的羞涩。

他们上了他的车，向希尔街开去。他领她来到他的书房。书房在底层，向外望出去是一座小花园。法式窗户大开着，他们坐在沙发上。

“关掉一些灯，让夜色进入房间。”朱莉娅说道。她引用了《威尼斯商人》里的台词，“‘正是这么个夜晚，阵阵香风轻轻地摩弄着树叶……’”

查尔斯关掉了所有灯，只留了一盏罩着灯罩的台灯。当他再次坐下来，朱莉娅依偎着他。他用胳膊搂着她的腰，她将头倚在他肩上。

“这就是天堂。”她喃喃道。

“这几个月我太想念你了。”

“你调皮淘气了吗？”

“嗯，我买了安格尔(2)的一幅画，花了不少钱。你走之前我必须得向你展示一下。”

“一定记着。你把它放在哪里了？”

自打进入房间那一刻起，她便在想引诱是发生在书房还是楼上。

“在我卧室。”他回答道。

“那真是舒服多了。”她想。

想到可怜而年迈的查尔斯要玩那样的小伎俩将她带到他的卧室，她便暗暗窃笑。男人都是一些笨蛋！害羞胆怯，这就是他们的毛病。她想到了汤姆，突然一阵剧痛直刺她的心胸。可恶的汤姆。查尔斯果真非常可爱，她下决心要回报他长久的爱慕。

“你一直是我极好的朋友，查尔斯。”她用低沉、略带沙哑的声音说道。她稍稍转过身，这样一来脸贴得他非常近，她的嘴唇，又像汉密尔顿夫人一样，微微张开，“可是我却并没有对你太好。”

她看起来是那么娇柔顺从，像一个等待采撷的成熟桃子，看起来他要不可避免地亲她。然后，她会用她那柔软雪白的胳膊绕住他的脖子。但他仅仅微笑着。

“你千万别这么说。你一直都极好。”

（“他害怕了，可怜的家伙。”）“我觉得没有人像你这样爱过我。”

他轻轻捏了她一把。

“我依旧爱你。你知道。我的生活里没有别的女人。”

鉴于他没有亲吻她献上去的嘴唇，朱莉娅稍稍转了身。她若有所思地看着电火炉。可惜它没有开着。这场合若有火炉就好了。

“如果那时我们一起逃跑，一切会多么不同。嗨哟。”

她从来也没太弄明白“嗨哟”是什么意思，但在舞台上用得很多，并会配上一声叹息，听起来很悲伤。

“英国会失去它最伟大的女演员。我现在知道那时提出此事的我有多自私。”

“成功并非一切。我有时想，是不是在满足我愚蠢的小抱负的时候，耽误了世界上最伟大的事情。毕竟，爱情才是唯一重要的事。”而现在，她又用温柔迷人、空前美丽的眼睛再次看着他，“你知道吗，我想假如我现在能回到过去的年月，我就会说带我走。”

她的手慢慢滑下，握住了他的手。他文雅地捏了捏。

“哦，我的宝贝。”

“我经常想到我们梦想中的别墅。橄榄树、夹竹桃还有蓝色的大海。宁静。有时我惊骇于自己生活的沉闷和粗俗。你那时所提供的是美。现在太迟了，我知道；那时我不知道自己有多在乎你，我从未想过，随着时光逝去，你对我来说越来越重要。”

“听到你说这些真让人开心，我的宝贝。弥补了不知多少。”

“为了你，我愿意做世上的任何事，查尔斯。一直以来我都太自私了。我毁了你的生活，我不知道自己在做什么。”

她的声音低沉，有些发抖，她仰起头，使得她的脖子看起来像白色的柱子。她的露肩装显现出一部分小巧坚实的乳房，她用手把它们略微向前抬起。

“你千万别那么说，你千万不能那么想。”他温柔地回答，“你一直都是完美的。其他样子我也不会喜欢。哦，我的宝贝，人生如此短暂，爱情更是转瞬即逝。而人生的悲剧就在于我们有时能得到我们想要的。而今回顾一下我们在一起的漫长岁月，我知道你比我聪明。‘在你的形体上，岂非萦绕着古老的传说，以绿叶为其边缘？’你记得下一句是什么吗？‘你永远，永远吻不上，虽然够接近了——但也不必心酸；她不会老，虽然你不能如愿以偿。你将永远爱下去，她将永远壮丽！’(3)”

（“白痴。”）“如此美好的诗句，”她叹气道，“可能你是对的。嗨哟。”

他继续背诵，这一伎俩在朱莉娅看来稍显烦人。

啊，幸福的树木！
你的枝叶不会剥落，从不曾离开春天。
幸福的吹笛人也不会停歇，
他的歌曲永远是那么新鲜……

这给了朱莉娅思考的机会。她盯着没开着的火炉，目光专注，好像她被这些绝美的诗词迷住。很明显他并没有理解她的意图。这也不足为奇。二十年了，她对他热情的祈求充耳不闻，因此他已死了这条心也是很自然的。就好像珠穆朗玛峰，如果那些坚忍的登山运动员辛苦地试了那么久，希望到达山顶却徒然，最后却发现有更便捷的道路，他们只会不相信自己的眼睛：他们会以为这里面有圈套。朱莉娅觉得自己需要表达得更明白些；她必须，可以说，伸手拉一把这位疲惫的朝圣者。

“太晚了，”她温柔地说道，“给我看看你的新画，然后我必须得回家了。”

他站起来，她把双手递给他，让他帮她从沙发上站起来。他们上了楼梯。他的睡衣和晨衣整整齐齐地放在椅子上。

“你们单身汉给自己安排得真好。好一间舒适的卧室。”

他把镶框的画从墙上拿了下来，递给她到灯下观赏。这是一幅戴着贝雷帽、穿着灯笼袖低领裙的敦实女人的铅笔肖像。朱莉娅觉得画中的女人普通无奇，那裙子更是可笑。

“真是引人入胜。”她喊道。

“我知道你会喜欢。是一幅好画，不是吗？”

“非常好。”

他将那幅小画放回原处。当他再次转过身来，她站得离床很近，双手放在背后，样子有点像被太监首领带领去给大维齐尔(4)过目的切尔卡西亚奴隶；她的举止有一丝谦逊的回避，一丝令人愉快的羞怯，同时还有处女对即将进入她的王国的期待。朱莉娅叹了一口气，声音性感撩人。

“我的宝贝，这真是一个美妙的夜晚。我从未感到和你如此亲近。”

她慢慢从背后抬起手，精妙自然地抓住时机，将手移到身前，伸出胳膊，双手手心朝上，仿佛无形地捧着一只尊贵豪华的盘子，而在这盘子之上是她奉献上的一颗真心。她美丽的眼睛更显温柔顺从，嘴上带着羞涩屈服的微笑。

她看到查尔斯的微笑冻结在他的脸上。此刻他全都明白了。

（“上帝，他不想要我。这一切都是虚张声势。”）这一启示一时让她不知所措。（“上帝，我怎么摆脱这一切？我现在看起来是多么蠢。”）

她几乎失去了镇定。各种思绪在她脑海中如闪电般闪过。他站在那儿，尴尬地看着她，极力掩饰自己的窘迫。朱莉娅惊慌失措。她不知道该如何处理捧着那只尊贵盘子的双手；上帝知道，那手虽小，但此刻却像是两条羊腿挂在那儿。她更不知道该说什么。每一秒都让她的姿势和处境更加难以忍受。

（“卑鄙小人，肮脏的卑鄙小人。这些年一直在愚弄我。”）

朱莉娅做了唯一能做的，她保持着那个姿势，心里默数着数，以免她走得太快。她把两手渐渐靠拢，直到双手握住，然后将头仰起，再把双手慢慢地抬起，放到了她脖子的一侧。她这个姿势和其他的动作一样可爱，正是这个姿势提醒了她该说什么。她低沉有磁性的声音颤抖而充满感情。

“我很高兴，回顾过去，我们之间没有什么值得懊恼自己的事情。人生之苦并非死亡，而是爱情死去。（她是从某部剧中听到的这句。）如果我们是情人，你早就厌恶我了，那现在我们回望过去就只有对我们自己人性弱点的遗憾了。刚才你说的雪莱关于人变老的诗句是什么？”

“是济慈，”查尔斯纠正道，“‘她不会老，虽然你不能如愿以偿。’”

“对，继续。”

“‘你将永远爱下去，她将永远美丽！’”

她大大地张开双臂，将鬈发向上一甩。她有话说了。

“是真的，不是吗？‘你将永远爱下去，我将永远美丽。’如果为了片刻的疯狂就抛弃掉我们友谊所带来的幸福，我们就是一对傻子。我们没什么可羞愧的。我们很纯洁。我们能够昂首挺胸，直面世人。”

她本能地觉得这是一句退场的台词，于是动作也跟了上来，她高昂着头，退到门口，猛地把门打开。她的力量让她将这种舞台感一路带到楼下。然后，她让这种感觉消散，极其自然地转向跟着她的查尔斯。

“我的斗篷。”

“车在那儿，”为她披斗篷的时候查尔斯说道，“我开车送你回去吧。”

“不，让我自己走吧。我想将这一时刻铭记于心。我走之前亲我一下。”

她将嘴唇向他送去。他亲吻了她的双唇。但她挣出身来，扼制了抽泣，猛地推开大门，向着等在那里的汽车奔去。

当她到家后，站在自己的卧室里，大大地舒了口气。

“可恶的蠢货。想想我竟被如此愚弄。感谢上帝，我脱身得还算可以。他真是个浑蛋，我觉得他没有看出来我的意图。”不过，那个僵硬的微笑让她不安，“他可能有所怀疑，但不会很肯定，之后他一定会觉得自己犯了错。我的天，我讲了什么混账话。不过我得说，这些话被完全接受了。幸亏我及时明白过来。再过一分钟我就会把衣服脱光。那就不能一笑了之了。”

朱莉娅开始窃笑。刚才的情景当然很令人悔恨，他让她看上去像个傻子，但如果你有一丁点儿幽默感，你就会看到其中可笑的一面。没人能分享这事儿让她觉得遗憾；虽然这故事对她不利，但不能否认这是个精彩故事。令她无法释怀的是她竟然将这些年来他上演的一部痴情不悔的喜剧当真了；因为这当然只是一种姿态；他喜欢将自己视为那个忠贞的爱慕者，很明显，他最不想要的就是他的忠贞得到回报。

“欺骗我，他做到了，完全让我上了他的当。”

但一个想法闪现在朱莉娅脑子里，让她停止了微笑。当一个女人热情的献身被一个男人拒绝，她会得出一两个结论：要么他是同性恋，要么他性无能。朱莉娅若有所思地点了一支烟。她问自己，查尔斯是否利用他对自己的深情引开世人对他真正性取向的关注。但她摇了摇头。如果他是同性恋，她一定会有所察觉；毕竟，自打战争结束后，这种事情就成了热门话题。他极有可能是性无能。她想了想他的年纪。可怜的查尔斯，她再次微笑了。如果情况真是这样，处于尴尬甚至可笑位置的就是他，而非她。他一定被吓傻了，可怜的家伙。当然没有哪个男人愿意将此事告诉一个女人，尤其是他疯狂爱着的女人；她越想越觉得这种解释合理。她开始为他感到难过，甚至有些对他充满母亲般的怜悯。

“我知道我要做什么，”她说道，开始脱衣服，“明天我会送一大束白百合给他。”

————————————————————

(1) 法国东部地区。

(2) 安格尔（Jean-Auguste-Dominique Ingres，1780—1867），法国新古典主义画家。

(3) 引文来自济慈所作《希腊古瓮颂》。

(4) 伊斯兰国家的首相的称号。

第二十五章

第二天早晨，朱莉娅醒来后在床上躺了一会儿才拉铃。她思考着，当她想起前一夜的经历，她不由得为自己的沉着应对感到沾沾自喜。当然不能说她是转败为胜，但从战略撤退的角度来看，她的行为称得上技艺精湛。虽然她感到很不自在，但查尔斯独特的行为或许有别的解释。说不定是因为她缺乏魅力。这个念头在昨晚的时候划过她的脑海，虽然当时她认为这是极不可能的，但是不可否认，早晨的时候这个念头又在困扰她。她拉了铃。一般来讲，由于朱莉娅吃早餐的时候迈克尔总会进来，当伊维给她拉起帘子时，会递给她一面镜子和一把梳子，还有她的脂粉和口红。以往，朱莉娅会迅速地梳几下头发，然后用粉扑潦草地在脸上扑点粉，但今天早晨，朱莉娅却费了点心思。她用心地涂了嘴唇，抹了腮红，仔细梳理了头发。

“公允地讲，”她说道，依旧看着镜中的自己，伊维将早餐托盘放到她的床上，“你觉得我是个长相好看的女人吗，伊维？”

“回答这问题前，我得知道这是不是个陷阱。”

“你这个老贱人。”朱莉娅说道。

“你不是什么漂亮女人，你知道。”

“没有哪个伟大的女演员是漂亮的。”

“像你昨晚打扮得那样花枝招展，再加上身体背着光，看起来更糟了，你知道。”

（“这对我一点好处都没有。”）“我想说的是，如果我打定主意想勾搭一个男人，你觉得我能成功吗？”

“就我对男人的了解，这事儿一点也不难。你现在想勾搭谁？”

“没人。我就是泛泛而谈。”

伊维吸了吸鼻涕，食指抠了抠鼻孔。

“别那样吸鼻涕。如果你想擦鼻涕，就擦。”

朱莉娅慢慢地吃着她的煮鸡蛋，沉浸在自己的想法中。她看着伊维，一个长相可笑的老东西，但人不可貌相。

“告诉我，伊维，有男人试图在大街上勾搭过你吗？”

“我？我倒想看他们试试。”

“我跟你说实话吧。有很多女人总是告诉我，男人们是怎样在大街上尾随她们的，如果她们停下站在商店的橱窗前，他们就会上前来，得到她们的注意。有时她们不得不费好大劲才能摆脱他们。”

“真恶心。”

“我不知道。我觉得这很让人受用。你知道，说来也怪，从来没有人在大街上跟随过我。我不记得曾有人试图搭讪我。”

“哦，那你夜里去埃奇韦尔路走一走。一定会被搭讪的。”

“如果真发生了，我不知道应该怎么应对了。”

“叫警察。”伊维面无表情地说。

“我认识一个女孩，她正在朝邦德街的一家帽子商店的橱窗前张望，一个男人走上前来，问她是否想要一顶帽子。她回答说想要，然后他们进了商店，她选了一顶，说了姓名和地址，男人当即付了钱，然后她说‘非常感谢你’，便走出了商店，而那男人还在等着找零钱。”

“这只是她告诉你的故事。”伊维吸了吸鼻涕，很是怀疑。她困惑地看了一眼朱莉娅，“这是什么意思？”

“哦，没什么。我就是没想明白为什么从来没有男人上前来跟我搭讪。我并非没有性吸引力。”

但是，她有吗？她下了决心要对此测试一番。

那个下午，朱莉娅睡完午觉，起来化了比日常浓重的妆，没有叫伊维，自己穿上一件既不普通又不容易看出价格昂贵的连衣裙，戴了一顶红色的宽檐草帽。

“我不想看起来像个妓女，”她看着镜子里的自己说道，“但我也不希望自己看起来太正派。”

她悄悄地走下楼梯，不让人听到她的响动，轻轻地关上门。她有一点紧张，更多的是兴奋；她觉得自己正在做一件让人惊悚的事情。她穿过康诺特广场，进入埃奇韦尔路。时间大约是五点左右。路上车水马龙，到处都是公共汽车、出租车和卡车；骑车的人在车流间穿梭前行，十分危险。人行道上挤满了人。她慢慢地向北边走去。起初，她目视前方，绝不左右张望，但很快她就意识到这样做毫无益处。如果她想引起周围人的注意，就必须朝他们看去。有两三次她看到六个人盯着商店橱窗看，她也停了下来，看着橱窗，但没有人注意到她。她继续向前走去。人们从她身边走过，他们看起来行色匆匆。没人注意到她。当她看到有个男人朝她走来时，她大胆地朝他看了一眼，但那人却面无表情地走了过去。她突然想到自己的表情太严肃了，然后她让嘴角微微挂着一丝笑意。有两三个男人以为她在冲他们微笑，他们很快将目光转移。其中一个男人从她身边经过后，她回头看了一眼，发现那人也正在回头看她，但注意到她的目光后，便匆匆赶路了。她感到有些被冷落了，决定不再四处张望。她继续往前走。以前她总是听说伦敦的人们是世界上最得体的，但这一刻这种得体实在有点不近人情。

“这种情形在巴黎、罗马或者柏林的街道上根本不会发生。”她思索着。

她决定走到马里波恩大街，然后再返回来。如果一次都没有被搭讪就回了家，这也太丢人了。她走得非常慢，以至于路人有时会撞到她。这让她有些恼怒。

“我本该试试牛津街，”她说道，“那个笨蛋伊维。很明显埃奇韦尔路已经很干净了。”

她的心脏突然狂喜地跳了一下。她捕捉到一个年轻男人的眼睛，她确定里面有光芒闪现。他从她身边走过，她竭尽全力才让自己没有转回头去。她惊了一下，因为不一会儿他再次从她身边经过，他竟折返了回来，而这次他正盯着她看。她瞥了他一眼，然后羞涩地朝下看去。他退了回去，她知道他在跟着她。一切都很好。她在一间商店的橱窗前停了下来，朝里看去，他也停了下来。现在她知道该如何表现了。她假装对那些陈列的商品入了迷，但就在她准备离开前又微带笑意地看了他一眼。他个头很矮，看起来像个职员或者商场巡视员，穿一件灰色西装，戴一顶棕色软边呢帽。他不是朱莉娅心中想要勾搭的对象，但事实在这儿摆着，他显然试图要搭讪她。朱莉娅已全然忘记了自己刚刚还觉得疲惫。她不知道接下来会发生什么。当然她不会让事情进展得过于离谱，但她很好奇他下一步要做什么。她在想他会跟她说什么。她既兴奋又开心；心里的负担终于卸了下来。她慢慢地踱步，她知道他紧随其后。她又在一家商店橱窗前停了下来，这次他就站在她身后。她又停在另一家商店的橱窗前，这次他站在了她的身边。她的心开始狂跳不止。这确实开始像一场冒险了。

“他会不会邀请我同他一起去旅店。我觉得他负担不起。电影院。对。会很好玩。”

她面朝他站着，微微带着笑意。他摘下帽子。

“兰伯特小姐，是您吗？”

她差点吓得灵魂出窍。她震惊到无法沉着镇定地予以否认。

“我觉得我看到您那眼就认出您来了，所以我又折返回来确认了一下，我对自己说，看，如果那不是朱莉娅·兰伯特，那我就是拉姆齐·麦克唐纳(1)。然后，您不再向商店橱窗望去，这给了我看清您的机会。我觉得诧异的是在埃奇韦尔路上看到您。这太离奇了，如果您懂我的意思。”

事实可比他想的要离奇得多。不论怎样，如果他知道她是谁，这一切就都不重要了。她本应猜到，在伦敦她走不了多远就会被认出来。他说话带着伦敦东区口音，面色苍白，但朱莉娅报以开心友好的微笑。一定不能让他觉得她在摆架子。

“请原谅我未被介绍就跟您说话，但我不想错过这个机会。您能给我签名吗？”

朱莉娅倒吸了口气。不会就因为这个他跟了她十分钟吧。他肯定是以此为跟她说话的借口。好吧，她可以配合一下。

“我很高兴。但我在大马路上可给你签不好。人们会盯着看。”

“没错。您看，我打算去喝下午茶，下个拐角有一家里昂餐室(2)。为什么不一起喝一杯？”

她继续演戏。当他们喝完茶后，他估计就会建议去看电影了。

“好吧。”她说道。

他们一直走到那家饭店，在一张小桌子前坐了下来。

“两杯茶，小姐，”他说道，“还要什么吃的吗？”朱莉说什么也不要，他又说道：“一客烤饼和黄油，小姐。”

朱莉娅现在终于能好好看看这个男人了。虽然敦实矮小，但他长相不错。他的黑头发涂了发蜡紧贴着头皮，眼睛秀美，但他的牙齿不好，而且他那苍白的皮肤让他看起来很不健康。他的举止中有一丝冒失，让朱莉娅不是很喜欢，但她理智地想了想，你不大可能指望一个在埃奇韦尔路上勾搭你的青年会有紫罗兰那样的腼腆。

“别的慢慢来，先让我们签好名，可以吗？说做就做，这是我的座右铭。”

他从口袋掏出一支钢笔，又从一本鼓鼓的小笔记本里拿出一张大卡片。

“这是我们公司的商业名片，”他说道，“在这上面签就行。”

朱莉娅看他把花招耍到现在，觉得可笑，但她好心情地在卡片后面签了自己的名字。

“你收集签名吗？”她问道，淡淡一笑。

“我？不。我觉得都是胡闹。我女朋友收集。她有查理·卓别林的和道格拉斯·费尔班克斯的，还有其他我根本不认识的。如果你愿意我可以给你看她的照片。”

从他的笔记本里他抽出一张快照，上面是个相当时髦的年轻女郎，像电影明星一样笑着，露出一口牙齿。

“漂亮。”朱莉娅说道。

“当然啦。今晚我们打算去电影院。等我给她看您的签名，她肯定会非常惊喜。当我知道那是您的时候，我对自己说的第一件事就是，我死也要为我的格温拿到朱莉娅·兰伯特的签名。趁着今年八月放假的时候，我们就要结婚了，您知道；我们要去怀特岛度蜜月。有了这个我会跟她好好寻开心。等我告诉她我和您一起喝了茶，她一定不会相信的，她会觉得我在开玩笑，然后我会给她看您的签名，明白吗？”

朱莉娅礼貌地听着，但微笑已经从她脸上消失了。

“恐怕我一会儿得走了，”她说道，“我已经迟到了。”

“我也没有太多时间。您看，要去见我的女朋友，我恨不得立刻离开这里。”

女服务员端来茶的时候就把账单放在了桌子上，当他们起身时，朱莉娅从她包里掏出一个先令。

“您这是做什么？您不会认为我会让您付钱吧。我邀请的您。”

“您太客气了。”

“可是我来告诉您，您能做什么，某天您可以让我带着我女朋友去您剧院的休息室里见您。就跟她握握手，明白吗？这对她来说意义很大。可不是么，她会一辈子念叨这事儿的。”

有那么几分钟，朱莉娅的态度变得很严厉，而现在，虽然依旧优雅，但几乎已经盛气凌人了。

“对不起，但我从来不在后台见陌生人。”

“哦，抱歉。但你不介意我这么问吧？我是说，我并不是为了我自己。”

“不介意。我很理解。”

她冲着一辆沿着马路牙子缓缓驶来的出租车招了招手，然后将手递给这个年轻人。

“再见，兰伯特小姐。再见，祝你好运，祝你一切顺利，还要谢谢你的签名。”

朱莉娅坐在出租车的角落里，恼羞成怒。

“可恶的畜生。他还有他的女朋友。竟敢问是否能带她来见我。”

朱莉娅回到家后，径直上楼去了她的卧室。她一把抓掉头上的帽子，生气地将它扔在床上。她跨步走到穿衣镜前，看着自己。

“老了，老了，老了，”她喃喃道，“毫无办法；我完全没有性吸引力了。你不会相信，是吗？你会说这一切太可笑了。但还有其他的解释吗？我从埃奇韦尔路的这头走到那头，上帝知道我把那角色演得多完美，但没有一个男人对我有一点兴趣，除了一个可恶的商店店员，而他竟然是为了他的女朋友要我的签名。太荒谬了。一群性冷淡的杂种。我真不知道英国的未来在哪里。大英帝国！”

最后几个字她说得充满嘲讽，准能让前座整排的内阁大臣们惊慌失措。她开始做起手势来。

“如果认为我没有性吸引力，还能到达我今天的位置，那简直太可笑了。人们为什么要来看一个女演员？因为他们想跟她上床。难道你要告诉我，即使我没有性吸引力，我也能将一部糟糕的戏剧演上三个月，还场场满座吗？性吸引力到底是什么东西？”

她暂停了一下，若有所思地看着自己。

“当然我能演得性感。我能演任何东西。”

她开始想那些以性感而臭名昭著的女演员，尤其是其中的一位，莉迪亚·梅恩，她总是演荡妇的角色。她算不上一个真正的女演员，但在某些角色上她演得很到位。朱莉娅模仿力极强，现在她开始模仿莉迪亚·梅恩。像莉迪亚那样，她让眼睑淫荡地半掩着眼睛，她的身体在裙子里扭来扭去。她让眼睛流露出莉迪亚那种挑逗的眼神，用蛇一般蠕动的姿势发出诱惑的邀请，这是莉迪亚的专长。她开始用莉迪亚的声音说话，懒洋洋地拖长调子，让每句话听起来都淫荡不堪。

“哦，我亲爱的男人，那种话我听得太多了。我不想在你和你的老婆之间惹什么麻烦。男人们为什么不能让我一个人待会儿呢？”

这是朱莉娅无情讽刺的模仿。真是残忍。她感到非常有趣，大笑了起来。

“好吧，有一件事情，我可能没有性吸引力，但看了我的模仿后，也不会有人觉得莉迪亚有什么性感可言了。”

这让她大感宽慰。

————————————————————

(1) 拉姆齐·麦克唐纳（Ramsay MacDonald，1866—1937），英国工党领袖。

(2) 里昂餐室是由里昂（J. Lyon）在伦敦开设的联号快餐店。

第二十六章

排练开始了，这缓解了朱莉娅深受困扰的情绪。迈克尔在她出国期间重新上演的旧戏目既不成功，也不太糟糕，但比起关掉剧院，他情愿一直上演这出戏，直到《当今时代》可以上演了。因为他一周要演两个日场，天气又热，因此他决定排练不必太过紧张。一个月前他们就开始了排练。

虽然朱莉娅在舞台上演了那么多年，但她从未失去排练时那种兴奋感，《当今时代》的第一次排练依旧让她激动得不能自已。这是一场新冒险的开始。她并没有感觉自己像一个女主角，而是像个出演自己首个小角色的小丫头那样开心和渴望。但同时，她又美妙地体验到她自己的权利。她再一次有了使用它们的机会。

十一点，她登上舞台。剧组人员无所事事地站着。她亲吻了那些她认识的艺术家，并与他们握手，迈克尔文雅地向她介绍那些她不认识的人。她友好地和艾维斯·克赖顿打招呼。朱莉娅夸她长得非常漂亮，并表达了对她帽子的喜爱；也跟她描述了自己在巴黎为她挑选的那些漂亮裙子。

“你最近见到汤姆了吗？”朱莉娅问道。

“没有。他去度假了。”

“哦，好的。他真是个不错的小家伙，不是吗？”

“很可爱。”

这两个女人注视着对方的眼睛，彼此微笑着。艾维斯朗读台词时，朱莉娅看着她的表情，听着她的语调。朱莉娅冷笑了一下。这正是她所预料的。艾维斯属于那类第一次彩排后就对自己把握十足的女演员。她并不知道自己将遭遇什么。汤姆对朱莉娅来说已经无足轻重了，但她和艾维斯还有一笔账没算清，她可不打算就这么算了。这个荡妇！

这部剧是《谭格瑞的续弦夫人》的现代版，但随着这一代人行为举止的变化，这部剧已改为喜剧。一些原有的老角色被保留下来，奥布里·谭格瑞，现在是个年迈的老人，出现在第二幕中。在波拉死后，他第三次结了婚。科特莱昂太太原想对他和他的第二任妻子所遭遇的不幸进行补偿，可是现在的剧本里她已成为一个乖戾、傲慢的老太太。他的女儿埃琳和休·阿戴尔同意不计前嫌，因为波拉的死似乎将他陷入婚外恋情的记忆抹掉了；他们都已经再婚了。他现在是个退伍的准将，打打高尔夫，或者哀叹哀叹大英帝国——“上帝，老兄，要是我有办法，就让那些可恶的社会学者一个个挨着墙根站好，然后枪毙掉。”而这个时候的埃琳已经是个中年女子，经过了拘谨的青春岁月，变成了一个热情、现代、心直口快的女人了。迈克尔扮演的角色叫罗伯特·汉弗莱斯，同平内罗剧本中的奥布里一样，是个有个独生女的鳏夫；他在中国担任过多年领事，攒了一些钱，退休后定居在一个堂兄留给他的房子里，就在谭格瑞家附近。他的女儿奥娜（这就是艾维斯·克赖顿要演的角色）正在学医，打算去印度行医。在国外待了这么多年，罗伯特没有朋友，一人独居在伦敦，勾搭上一个叫马顿太太的妓女。马顿太太和波拉是一类人，但她不如波拉那样专情；夏天和冬天，她在戛纳接活儿，中间的时间住在阿尔伯马尔街上一套公寓房间里，接待一批英国皇家部队的军官。她打得一手好桥牌，高尔夫球打得更好。这个角色很适合朱莉娅扮演。

作家紧扣原剧台词。奥娜向她父亲宣布，她要放弃自己的医学研究，并在她出嫁前会一直跟他住在一起，她刚刚和埃琳的儿子——一个年轻的卫兵——订婚。心存不安的罗伯特·汉弗莱斯向她透露了想要娶马顿太太的想法。奥娜听完后表现得很冷静。

“你肯定知道她是个妓女，对吧？”她冷漠地说道。

罗伯特倍感尴尬，讲起了马顿太太不幸的一生，他想为她所遭受的一切苦难进行弥补。

“哦，别说这些没用的，”她回答道，“你要是真的能做到，倒是一件大好事。”

埃琳的儿子曾是马顿太太无数情人中的一个，正如埃琳的丈夫曾是波拉·谭格瑞的情人一样。当罗伯特·汉弗莱斯将妻子带回乡下的家中时，这事儿已经被人们发现，他们觉得必须通知奥娜。让他们惊讶的是，奥娜一点都不动声色，她早就知道了。

“我知道这事儿时感到非常开心，”她告诉她的继母，“您瞧，亲爱的，您可以和我聊他在床上的表现。”

这是艾维斯·克赖顿最好的一场戏，整整有十分钟之久，迈克尔从一开始就意识到这场戏的效果和重要性。迈克尔认为，艾维斯那冷漠的、一本正经的漂亮正是这场戏中最生动的存在。但在差不多六次排练后，他开始认为那就是艾维斯的全部演技。他和朱莉娅讨论了此事。

“你觉得艾维斯塑造能力如何？”

“说这个还有些早。”

“我对她不太满意。你说她能演戏。我看不出来。”

“这是个板上钉钉的角色，她肯定演不出错来。”

“你跟我一样明白，根本没有什么板上钉钉的角色。不管一个角色多么好，都得尽力演好才行。我不确定现在将她踢走，换个人来演，是不是更好。”

“这不容易，我觉得你得给她个机会。”

“她太笨拙了，她的手势有时毫无意义。”

朱莉娅思索了一会儿。她自有让艾维斯留在剧组的理由。她很清楚，如果她现在被换掉，她一定会向汤姆抱怨是因为朱莉娅对她的嫉妒。他爱她，会相信她说的一切。他可能甚至会觉得，朱莉娅为了报复他，将这口气撒在了她的身上。不，不，她必须得留下。她必须得出演那个角色，并且以失败告终；汤姆必须亲自看到她是个什么样的演员。他们俩都以为这部剧会让她出名。蠢货。这部剧会扼杀她。

“你知道你有多聪明，迈克尔。我敢肯定你可以训练出她来，如果你愿意费点心。”

“但问题就是这个，她似乎无法领会指导。我明确地告诉她该怎么读一句台词，她总是用自己的方式说了出来。你不会相信，但有时我不禁觉得她有一种错觉，以为自己比我还要厉害。”

“你让她太紧张了。当你让她做什么的时候，她紧张得不知道自己该做什么。”

“天，没有比我更容易相处的人了。我从来没有对她疾言厉色过。”

朱莉娅对他报以柔情蜜意的微笑。

“你打算假装你真的不知道她怎么了吗？”

“不知道，怎么了？”

他看着她，一脸茫然。

“别装了，亲爱的。难道你没有注意到她疯狂地爱着你吗？”

“我？可我以为她实际上已经跟汤姆订了婚。胡扯。你总是会幻想这些事情。”

“但这很明显。毕竟她并不是第一个拜倒在你那致命美貌之下的人，而且我也不认为她会是最后一个。”

“上帝知道，我不想拆可怜的汤姆的台。”

“这不是你的错，对吧？”

“你想让我怎么做？”

“好吧，我觉得你应该对她友善一些。她很年轻，你知道，可怜的小东西。她所想要的就是有人助她一臂之力。如果你给她开几次小灶，跟她一起研习角色，我相信你会创造奇迹。为什么不选一天带她出去吃午饭，跟她聊聊呢？”

她看到迈克尔考虑这提议时眼中闪烁的光芒，以及嘴上隐约挂起的微笑。

“当然，最重要的事情就是尽我们所能演好这部戏。”

“我知道这事儿让你感到厌烦，但坦诚地讲，为了这部剧，我觉得这么做是值得的。”

“你知道我从来不会做让你心烦的事情，朱莉娅。我是说，我更愿意立刻开了这个女孩，找别人来演她的角色。”

“我觉得那么做会是个错误。我相信如果你对她花足了心思，她会有很好的表现。”

他在屋子里来回走了一两次。他似乎在从各个角度考虑这个事情。

“好吧，我想从剧团每个演员身上挖掘出最好的表现就是我的工作。针对不同演员，都必须找到最好的方法。”

他伸出下巴，吸回肚子，挺直后背。朱莉娅明白艾维斯·克赖顿将会保住这个角色，第二天排练时，迈克尔将她带到一边，和她进行了一次长谈。朱莉娅非常清楚他在说些什么，她用眼角的余光注视着他们，不多一会儿就看见艾维斯在点头微笑。他约她跟他一起吃午饭。朱莉娅怀着得意的心情继续琢磨自己的角色。

第二十七章

当罗杰从奥地利回来时，他们已经排练了两周。他在卡林西亚湖待了几周，又在伦敦待了一两天后，和朋友一起去了苏格兰。由于迈克尔早早吃完晚饭去了剧院，朱莉娅自己去见了他。她穿衣服时，伊维像往常一样抽动鼻子，说她花这么多精力打扮就好像要去见一个年轻男人。她希望罗杰以她为荣，她穿着夏天的连衣裙从站台上缓缓走着，毫无疑问她会看起来非常年轻漂亮。你会错误地以为，她对自己所引起的关注毫不知情。享受了一个月的阳光浴的罗杰，皮肤成了深棕色，但脸上依旧有不少粉刺，比起他新年离开伦敦时看起来瘦了一些。她满怀深情地拥抱了他。罗杰微微笑了笑。

他们俩一起吃了晚餐。饭后，朱莉娅问他想不想去看戏或者去看电影，但他说他更愿意待在家里。

“那更好了，”她回答道，“我们就聊聊天吧。”

事实上，迈克尔嘱咐朱莉娅在合适的时候同罗杰谈一谈。既然他很快就要去剑桥读书了，他应该清楚自己将来想做什么。迈克尔有点担心他会在那里虚度时间，最后去了一个经纪人公司或者上舞台表演。他觉得朱莉娅比他机智，且对罗杰更有影响力，他便敦促她把外交部工作的好处以及律师的光辉前途都讲给罗杰听。朱莉娅觉得，如果在两三个小时的谈话中她无法把谈话引到这个重要的话题上，那才奇怪。晚饭的时候，她试图让罗杰讲讲维也纳。但他沉默寡言。

“哦，我就做了那些平常的事情，你知道的。我观光旅游，很努力地学习德语。我去一些喝啤酒的地方看了看，还看了不少歌剧。”

她在想他有没有发生什么风流韵事。

“不管怎样，你回来时没有带着一位维也纳的未婚妻。”她说道，想要把他的话引出来。

他若有所思又觉得有些好笑地看了她一眼。你甚至可能觉得他知道她的意图所在。很奇怪；虽然他是她的儿子，她跟他在一起时并不感到自在。

“不，”他回答道，“我太忙了，顾不上那种事情。”

“我估计你去了所有的剧院。”

“我去了两三次。”

“你看到有什么对我有帮助的吗？”

“你知道，我从来不会想那些。”

他的答案可能听起来有些没礼貌，但他回答时都报以微笑，他的微笑总是很甜。朱莉娅又在想，他怎么会既没有遗传迈克尔的美貌，也没有遗传她的魅力。他那头红发倒是还可以，但那苍白的睫毛让他的脸看起来有些空洞。只有老天知道，有这样的母亲父亲，他是从哪儿获得这么一副粗笨样子的。他现在已经十八岁了；是时候该瘦下一点来了。他看起来有点冷漠；一点都没有她那勃勃的生机；她能想象如果是她在维也纳待了六个月，她会如何生动地描述自己的经历。可不是吗，她已经将自己和嘉莉姨妈还有她母亲在圣马洛的日子编成了故事，让人们哄堂大笑。他们都说她讲的如同戏剧一样，而她自己觉得她讲的比大多数的喜剧都要精彩。她把这故事讲给罗杰听。他脸上挂着迟钝的微笑静静地听着；但她不安地认为，他并不像她那样认为这故事好笑。她在心里叹了口气。可怜的家伙，他不可能有幽默感。然后他的评论让她有机会提起了《当今时代》。她跟他讲了这部戏的故事概要，解释了她的角色；她跟他讲了剧组演员，描述了背景道具。晚餐结束时，她突然意识到她一直在讲她自己还有她所感兴趣的。她不知道自己为什么会这么做，闪念间她觉得是罗杰将对话从他和他的事情上引开，转到了这个方向。但她把这问题先搁在一边。他还没聪明到这份儿上。后来，当他们坐在客厅听广播抽烟的时候，朱莉娅觉得时机到了，便以表面上看起来最随意的方式问出了她准备好的问题。

“你想清楚自己将来要做什么了吗？”

“还没有。着急吗？”

“你知道我在这方面什么都不清楚。但你父亲说如果你想做律师你应该在剑桥学习法律。另一方面，如果你想去外交部工作，你应该学习现代语言。”

他盯着她看了许久，带着他那奇怪的、充满意味的表情，让朱莉娅很难保持她轻松幽默又从容慈爱的表情。

“如果我相信上帝，我应该成为一个牧师。”他最后说道。

“一个牧师？”

朱莉娅不敢相信自己的耳朵。她感到浑身不自在。但他的答案已经在她的脑子里沉淀，一瞬间，她看到他成为一个被一群谄媚的神职人员簇拥着的红衣主教，居住在罗马一座漂亮豪华的布满了美妙画作的宫殿里；然后，他成为一个圣徒，戴着主教冠，穿着缀满金丝的法衣，做着仁慈的手势，布施面包给穷人。她看到自己穿着一件锦缎连衣裙，戴着一串珍珠项链。俨然博尔吉亚家族(1)的母亲。

“十六世纪时，这职业还可以，”她说道，“现在为时太晚了。”

“确实很晚了。”

“我无法明白是什么让你有了这个念头。”他没有回答，以至于她不得不再问一次，“难道你过得不开心吗？”

“很不开心。”他微笑道。

“你想要什么？”

他再次向她投以那种令人不安的注视。很难知道他是否是认真严肃的，因为他的眼睛微微闪烁着喜悦的光芒。

“真相。”

“你说什么呢？”

“你看，我一生都活在弄虚作假的氛围中。我想打开天窗说亮话。你和父亲可以呼吸这种空气，这是你们所知道的唯一的空气，你们觉得这是天堂的空气，但它让我窒息。”

朱莉娅聚精会神地听着，试图明白他的意思。

“我们是演员，成功的演员。这就是为什么我们能够自你出生开始就用奢华包围着你。你能用一只手就数清楚有几个演员将自己的儿子送到了伊顿公学。”

“我很感激你们为我做的一切。”

“那你责备我们什么？”

“我没有责备你们。你们已经做了能为我所做的一切。不幸的是，对我来说，你们也夺走了我对一切事物的信仰。”

“我们从来没有干涉过你的信仰。我知道我们不是宗教人士，我们是演员，在一周八场演出后，我们希望星期天属于我们自己。我很自然地以为学校会负责管理这些事情。”

他再次开口前稍稍犹豫了一下。你会以为他需要做些调整才能继续。

“当我还是个孩子，十四岁的时候，有天晚上我站在舞台的侧翼看你演戏。那肯定是场很精彩的戏，你说话说得那么真诚，那么感人，我禁不住哭起来。我被彻底感动了。我不知道该如何描述，我的情感升华了；我为你感到伤心，我觉得自己是个小英雄；我觉得自己再也不会做卑鄙无耻或见不得人的事情。然后，你来到后台，离我站的地方很近，你脸上全是泪水；你背对着观众，用你平常的声音对舞台经理说：‘那个该死的电工是怎么打灯光的？我告诉他不要打蓝色灯光。’紧接着，你气都没换一下，就转身面向观众，痛苦地哀号，又继续演戏。”

“但，亲爱的，那就是表演。如果一个女演员感受到她所表现的一切情绪，她会把自己撕成碎片。我很清楚地记得这场戏。它曾经博得满堂彩。我人生中还从未听过那么多掌声。”

“我觉得我是个傻瓜，竟然会相信它。我相信了你在台上说的一切。当我发现这些都是假的，我内心有些东西被击毁了。自那之后，我再也不相信你说的了。我曾经上当被愚弄，但我下定决心再也不会这样了。”

她给了他一个令人愉快和放松的微笑。

“亲爱的，我看你是在胡说八道。”

“当然你会这么认为。你并不知道真实和假装之间有什么不同。你从不停止表演。这是你的第二天性。你在这里的宴会上表演。你冲着仆人表演，冲着父亲表演，你面对我时也在表演。对我，你扮演一个喜欢我、宠溺我的著名母亲。你并不存在，你只是你所扮演的数不清的角色之一。我经常会想，你是否真的存在，或者你仅仅是你扮演的那些人的一个媒介。当我看到你独自进入一个空房间时，有时我会想突然打开房门，但我又害怕这样做，因为里面万一一个人都没有呢。”

她快速地瞥了他一眼。她发起抖来，因为他说的话给了她一种可怕的感觉。她全神贯注地听着，有些焦虑，因为他看起来很严肃，并且她感到他正在讲述多年来压在他心上的重担。她从未听他讲过这么多话。

“你觉得我是假的吗？”

“并不是。因为假是你的一切。假是你的真实。就好像对于不知道黄油是什么的人来说，人造黄油就是真黄油。”

她有一种模糊的罪恶感。像《哈姆雷特》中的王后说的那样：“让我来绞你的心肝；我要那么做，假使那不是穿刺不透的石心肝。”她的思绪蔓延开来。

（“不知我扮演哈姆雷特是不是太老了。西登斯和萨拉·伯恩哈特都演过他。我的腿比我见过演这个角色的所有男演员的腿都优美。我要问问查尔斯的想法。当然还有那该死的无韵诗。他不用散文写真是愚蠢。当然啦，我可以在法兰西喜剧院用法语演出。上帝呀，那该多棒啊。”）

她看到自己穿着黑色的紧身上衣和长长的丝绸长筒袜。“哎哟，可怜的约里克(2)。”她继续思考着。

“你总不能说你父亲不存在。这过去二十年，他一直都在扮演他自己。”（“迈克尔可以出演国王，当然他不能说法语，可万一如果我们决定在伦敦一试呢。”）

“可怜的父亲，我想他很擅长他的工作，但他不够聪明，是吧？他一直忙着成为英格兰最英俊的男人。”

“我认为你这么评价你父亲很不好。”

“难道我说了什么你原来不知道的事情吗？”他冷漠地问道。

朱莉娅想微笑，可又不允许打破脸上那稍带痛苦的威严相。

“促使我们彼此相爱的是我们的弱点，而不是我们的强项。”她回答道。

“您是在哪部戏里说的这句台词？”

她强忍住内心的恼怒。那些话很自然地就到了嘴边，但当她诉说这些话时，才意识到是出自一部戏剧。小杂种！但这些话来得很适时。

“你真冷血。”她悲伤地说道。她开始越来越觉得自己像哈姆雷特的母亲。“难道你不爱我吗？”

“如果我能找到真实的你，我可能会。但你在哪儿？如果有人剥夺了你的表现欲，如果有人把你的演技拿走，如果有人像剥洋葱一样一层一层剥掉你的装腔作势和虚伪，还有你演过的角色所给你的标签和虚假情感的碎片，他会最终发现一个灵魂吗？”他神情严肃而悲伤地看着她，微微一笑，“我确实喜欢你。”

“你认为我爱你吗？”

“以你的方式。”

朱莉娅突然感到心慌意乱。

“要是你知道你生病时我有多痛苦就好了！我不知道如果你死了我该怎么办！”

“你会在你唯一孩子的棺材前完美地扮演一个失去孩子的母亲角色。”

“算不上什么好表演，就好像我有机会彩排几次似的。”朱莉娅尖刻地回答道，“你看，你并没有明白，表演并非本性；它是艺术，艺术是你创造出来的。真实的悲痛是很丑陋的；演员的工作就是不仅表现其真实，并且要有美感。如果我真的像我在六七部戏剧中那样快死了，你觉得我还会在乎我的动作是否优雅，我断断续续的话语是否足够清晰地传达给最后一排观众吗？如果这一切都是虚假的，那贝多芬的奏鸣曲一样虚假，我也不会比弹奏它的钢琴家更假。说我不喜欢你太刻毒了。我一心爱你。你一直是我生命中的唯一。”

“不。你喜欢孩子时的我，能跟你一起拍照。那是很不错的照片，有很好的宣传效果。但自从那以后，你就不怎么在乎我了。我只会让你感到厌烦。你总是很高兴见到我，但你很庆幸我能管束自己，并不会占用你的时间。我不责怪你；你生命里没有给任何人留时间，除了你自己。”

朱莉娅开始有点不耐烦了。他所说的太接近事实，让她不安。

“你忘了年轻人总是让人觉得很厌烦。”

“我认为你说得太对了，”他微笑道，“但为什么你无法忍受我不在你的视线中？那也仅仅是表演。”

“你让我很不开心。你让我觉得我好像没有为你尽到义务。”

“但你尽了。你一直都是一个非常棒的母亲。你为我做了一些我会一直都很感激的事情，你没有管我。”

“我不明白你想要什么。”

“我告诉你了。真实。”

“但你去哪儿能找到？”

“我不知道。可能它不存在。我还很年轻；我还无知。我觉得或许在剑桥，见识新的人，阅读新的书，我可能会知道去哪里寻找它。如果他们说，真实只存在于上帝那里，那我就完蛋了。”

朱莉娅的内心被搅乱了。她没有真正理解他说的话，他说的一字一句，重要的并不是它们的意思，而是它们是否被接受，但她敏感地察觉到他内心的感受。当然他只有十八岁，对他过分认真就太愚蠢了，她总是觉得他的这些想法都是从别人那儿得来的，里面一定有好多装腔作势的成分。有人有过自己的想法吗？难道不是都会有点装模作样？当然，或许在那一刻他感受到了他所说的一切，如果她对此表示不屑可不太好。

“当然，我知道你的意思，”她说道，“我在这世界上最大的心愿就是你能够开心。你父亲我来负责，你可以做任何你想做的事情。你必须要寻求你自己的救赎。我明白。但我希望你应该先确定你所有的这些想法并不是病态的。可能你在维也纳太孤独了，我敢说你读书读得太多了。当然，你父亲和我属于不同的一代，我想我们可能无法帮到你。为什么你不跟你的同龄人谈谈你的想法？比如汤姆？”

“汤姆？一个可怜的小势利鬼。他一生仅有的抱负就是成为一个绅士，可是他看不明白，他越努力，就越无望。”

“我以为你非常喜欢他。去年在塔普洛你跟他形影不离。”

“我并没有不喜欢他。我利用了他。他能告诉我许多我想知道的事情。但我觉得他是个无足轻重的小笨蛋。”

朱莉娅想起她曾对他们之间的友谊嫉妒得发狂。想起她浪费在他身上的那些嫉妒之情让她很愤怒。

“你把他甩了，不是吗？”他突然问道。

她大吃一惊。

“我觉得你这么做很明智。他可不够你的等级。”

他用镇静的目光看着他，突然间，令人作呕的恐惧感袭击了她，她害怕他知道汤姆曾做过她的情人。不可能，她告诉自己，那只不过是那有愧的良心在作祟；在塔普洛什么都没发生；也不可能有任何可怕的留言传到他耳朵里；然而，从他的表情中可以看出他对此知情。她感到羞愧。

“我邀请他来塔普洛仅仅是因为我觉得能让你有个同龄的男孩一起玩很不错。”

“确实如此。”

他眼中闪烁着一丝戏谑。她感到绝望。她想问问他在笑什么，但是没有勇气；因为她知道答案；他并没有生她的气，她可以忍受这一点，他只是觉得好笑。她受到深深的伤害。她想大哭，但这只能让他大笑。而且她能对他说什么？他不相信她所说的一切。表演！头一回，她感到不知所措。她在面对她不知道的事物，神秘又令人恐惧的事物。可能是真实的吗？就在那一刻，他们听到一辆汽车开来的声音。

“你父亲回来了。”她喊道。

真让人松了口气！这场面简直无法忍受，她很庆幸，迈克尔的到来必定结束这一切。不一会儿，热情洋溢的迈克尔冲进屋子，伸着下巴，收紧肚子，尽管五十岁了，还是令人难以置信的英俊，他以他那充满男子气概的方式伸出双手迎接他六个月未见的唯一的儿子。

————————————————————

(1) 博尔吉亚家族是意大利著名家族，在十五、十六世纪出过两位教皇。

(2) 指《哈姆雷特》中的国王。

第二十八章

三天后，罗杰去了苏格兰。朱莉娅巧妙地让他俩没有机会再独处。当他们不凑巧需要在一起待几分钟时，两人也会谈一些无关紧要的事情。见到他离开，朱莉娅并没有感到遗憾。她无法从她脑袋里清除她和他的那段奇怪的对话。其中，有一点尤为让她莫名其妙地忧虑；那就是他所暗示的如果她进入一个空房间，然后某个人突然打开了门，发现那房间里根本没有任何人。这让她觉得非常不舒服。

“我从来不是一个绝代佳人，但我身上有一样东西人们从来没有否定过，那就是个性。就因为我可以用一百种不同的方式来扮演一百个不同的角色，便认定我没有自己的个性，这太荒谬了。我能做到这一切是因为我是个相当不错的女演员。”

她试图思考当她独自进入一个空房间时会发生什么。

“但我从来都没有独自一人，即便是在一个空房间里。总会有迈克尔，或者伊维，或者查尔斯，或者观众；当然，这并不是实实在在的，而是精神上的。我必须跟查尔斯说说罗杰。”

不幸的是，查尔斯并不在市里。但他会在彩排的时候回来，首演夜也会来；二十年来他从未错过这些时刻，并且在彩排后他们总是会一起吃晚餐。迈克尔会留在戏院里，忙着处理灯光和其他道具，这样他们就能独处。他们能好好聊一聊。

朱莉娅研究着她的角色。她并不用观察的方式来刻意创造将要表演的角色；她有个本领，能进入她所扮演的角色的世界，用角色的思维进行思考，用角色的感官来体会。她的本能让她捕捉到上百种细微的感触，随后这些细小的感触会让观众因其逼真而感到惊讶不已；但当人们问起她这些感触的来源，她又回答不上来。现在，她要展现这个勇敢但又故作潇洒的马顿太太，这个能打高尔夫又能像正派小伙那样对一个男人讲话，但本质上又是一个令人尊敬、渴望婚姻进入安稳状态的中产阶级妇女。

迈克尔从来不喜欢彩排的时候有一堆人围观，这次，为了将戏剧的神秘性保留到首演，除了查尔斯，他只让摄影记者、裁缝等必须在场的人观看了彩排。朱莉娅的表演也有所保留。她无意在首演前展现自己所能给予这角色的全部。她只需适当表演就够了。在迈克尔井井有条的指导下，一切进展得都非常顺利，到十点的时候，朱莉娅和查尔斯已经坐在萨伏伊饭店的烧烤屋里了。她问他的第一句话便是他认为艾维斯·克赖顿怎么样。

“很不错，非常漂亮。她穿第二场的戏服非常可爱。”

“我不打算穿我第二场的戏服。查理·德夫里尔为我做了另外一件。”

他并没有看到朱莉娅向他投来的略带幽默的眼光，即便他看到了，也猜不出那是什么意思。迈克尔听了朱莉娅的建议后，在艾维斯·克赖顿身上花了不少心思。他在楼上自己的私人房间里对她单独进行指导，告诉她每一个发音和手势的运用。朱莉娅有理由相信，迈克尔不仅与她一同吃了几次午餐，还带她外出共赴晚宴。这一切的结果就是她将这个角色演得不同寻常的精彩。迈克尔搓了搓手。

“我对她很满意。我觉得她会引起轰动。我有点想把她签下来。”

“我不会这么做，”朱莉娅说道，“至少不会在首演夜之前。在呈现给观众之前，你无法确定演出是否会顺利进行。”

“她是个很好的女孩，一个十足的淑女。”

“是个很好的女孩，我想是因为她疯狂地爱着你，又是十足的淑女，因为她一直在抗拒你的勾引，直到她拿到合同。”

“哦，我亲爱的，别犯傻了。我老得都可以做她父亲了。”

但他得意扬扬地微笑着。她非常清楚，迈克尔的示爱不过是牵牵手，在出租车里吻上一两下，但她知道，她对他不忠的怀疑让他很受用。

但现在，朱莉娅在适当照顾自己身材的前提下满足了自己的胃口，开始跟查尔斯说起她心里的事情。

“亲爱的查尔斯，我想跟你谈谈罗杰。”

“哦，好，他前几天回来了，对吧？他怎么样？”

“亲爱的，发生了很糟糕的事情。他变成了一个令人担忧的学究，我不知道该拿他怎么办。”

她向查尔斯复述了他们之间的对话，漏掉了一两件她认为不太方便提及的事情，但她整体上说得比较准确。

“悲剧的是他一点幽默感都没有。”她最后说道。

“毕竟，他只有十八岁。”

“他说那些话的时候，我十分震惊。我觉得自己就像听到他的驴开始跟他讲话的巴兰。”

她开心地看了他一眼，但他甚至都没有笑。他并不觉得她的评论有她认为的那么好笑。

“我无法想象他是从哪里来的这些想法。如果要说这些胡扯都是他自己想出来的，那就太荒唐了。”

“你确定那个年纪的男孩不会比我们大人想象的要思考得多吗？这是一种精神上的青春期，结果往往很奇特。”

“这些年来，罗杰一直怀揣这些想法却守口如瓶，简直虚伪。他可能在指责我。”她大声笑了笑，“跟你讲实话，当罗杰对我说这些的时候，我觉得我像哈姆雷特的母亲。”然后，她紧接着说道：“我在想如果我扮演哈姆雷特，会不会太老了？”

“格特鲁德不是个很好的角色吗？”

朱莉娅感到有趣，放声大笑起来。

“别犯傻，查尔斯。我不会演王后。我会演哈姆雷特。”

“你觉得这角色适合女人来演？”

“西登斯夫人演过，萨拉·伯恩哈特也演过。它将是我职业生涯上的一个里程碑，你懂我的意思吧。当然，有无韵诗的难题。”

“我听有些男演员讲过，跟散文没多大区别。”他回答道。

“是，但并不一样，不是吗？”

“你对罗杰好吗？”

她对查尔斯突然讲回刚才的话题感到惊讶，但她只是笑了笑。

“哦，非常好。”

“要对年轻人的荒诞行为做到有耐心其实很困难；他们跟我们讲二加二等于四，就好像我们从来不知道一样，并且，当他们刚刚发现母鸡能下蛋，而我们又无法分享他们的惊讶时，他们又会大失所望。他们的夸夸其谈和大声咆哮中很多都是胡言乱语，但不完全是。我们应该同情他们；应该尽最大努力去理解他们。我们应该记得，当我们最初面对生活的时候，有多少需要忘记，有多少需要学习。放弃一个人的理想不是一件容易的事情，每日残酷的事实就是要吞下去的苦药。年轻人精神上的矛盾冲突可能会非常严重，而对解决它们又无能为力。”

“但你不会真的觉得罗杰的那番话有什么道理吧？我觉得都是他在维也纳学到的一套胡言乱语。真希望我们没有把他送到那儿去。”

“你可能是对的。可能再过一两年，他就看不到光荣的云彩，并接受生活的锁链。他可能会发现自己寻找的东西，如果不是在上帝身上，就是在艺术里。”

“我可不希望他成为一名演员，如果你是这个意思的话。”

“不，我觉得他并不想成为演员。”

“当然，他也不可能成为剧作家，他一点幽默感都没有。”

“我敢说，他应该很乐意进入外交部。在那儿没有幽默感正好可以成为他的一大长处。”

“你觉得我应该怎么办？”

“什么也别做。随他去吧。这或许是你能给予他的最大的慈爱。”

“但我总是担心他。”

“没有必要。要抱有希望。你以为你生了一只丑小鸭；或许他会变成一只白天鹅。”

查尔斯的回答并不是朱莉娅想要的。她原以为查尔斯会更同情她。

“我想他可能是变老了，可怜的宝贝儿。”她想，“他正在失去对事情的控制。他肯定阳痿好些年了；为什么以前我从来没想过这一点。”

她问了问时间。

“我想我该走了。我必须要好好休息一晚。”

朱莉娅睡得很好，她一醒来就感到浑身兴奋。今晚就是首演。回想到昨晚彩排结束她离开剧院时，人们已经在正厅后座和顶层后座的门外聚集，她感到一阵激动，现在是早上十点，估计那儿已经有一条长长的队伍了。

“幸好今天天气不错，可怜的粗人。”

以往在首演夜前她总是紧张得不得了。她会一整天感到不适，随着时间流逝，甚至有了想要离开舞台的心情。但现在，经过这么多次的磨炼后，她已经能镇定自若地面对了。整个上午，她仅仅感到开心，并有一点兴奋；直到下午，她才开始觉得不适。她变得沉默，想要独处，还有一点易怒；迈克尔早已从多年经验中摸透了她的脾气，此时也刻意不去招惹她。她的手脚开始冰凉，等她到达剧院时，手脚冷得像冰块一样。但是，她的恐惧并没有那么让人不悦。

那天早上，朱莉娅除了中午前到西登斯剧院对台词之外，并没什么可忙的，因此她在床上待到很晚。迈克尔要对布景做最后的调整，没有回来吃午餐，于是她自己吃了饭。然后，她上床美美地睡了一个小时。她想整个下午都休息；菲利普斯小姐六点的时候会给她稍稍按摩一会儿，她想在七点的时候到达剧院。但当她醒来后，她感到自己焕然一新，实在无法继续躺在床上，于是她决定起来出去走一走。那天风和日丽，阳光普照。她喜欢城市胜过乡村，喜欢街道胜过树林，因此她并没有去公园，而是在附近的广场漫步。这个时节的广场人迹罕至，她闲散地看着周围的房子，心想比起这些房子，她多么喜欢自己的那幢。她感到很自在，心情轻松。不久，她觉得是时候回去了。她刚刚走到斯坦霍普广场，就听到一个她一下就能辨认出的声音在喊她的名字。

“朱莉娅。”

她转过身来，汤姆满脸堆笑地迎上来。自她从法国回来还没有见过他。他穿着一身整洁的灰色西服，戴着一顶棕色帽子。他被太阳晒黑了。

“我以为你不在城里。”

“我周一回来的。没有打电话是因为我知道你忙着最后的排练。我今晚会来；迈克尔给了我一张正厅前排的票。”

“哦，我很开心你能来。”

很明显他见到她很开心。他的脸上洋溢着热切之情，眼里泛着光。她很高兴地发现，看到他已经不会在她心里惹起任何涟漪。他们聊天时，朱莉娅在想，他身上到底有什么竟让她以前如此神魂颠倒。

“你究竟为何像这样在这里闲逛？”

“我来散散步。我正打算去喝茶。”

“来跟我一起喝一杯吧。”

他的公寓就在拐角处。事实上，他正是在沿着小巷回家的时候看到她的。

“你怎么回来得这么早？”

“近来办公室没什么忙的。你知道，我们有一个合作伙伴几个月前去世了，这样一来我会拿到更大的份额。这就是说我可以接着住在那套公寓里。迈克尔在这事儿上很慷慨，他说我可以不交房租先住着，直到情况好转一些。我实在不愿被迫搬到别的地方去。请一定要来，我很愿意请你喝茶。”

他兴冲冲地喋喋不休，让朱莉娅觉得好笑。听他说的这些话，你很难想象他们之间曾发生过什么。他看起来一点都不尴尬。

“好吧。但我只能待一小会儿。”

“好的。”

他们走进小巷，她在他前面走上那狭窄的楼梯。

“你进客厅待着，我去烧水。”

她走进去，坐了下来。她向四周看了看，对她来说，这里发生过多少悲欢往事啊。一切都没有改变。她的照片还摆在老地方，但在壁炉架上还摆着艾维斯·克赖顿的一张大照片。照片上写着“致汤姆，艾维斯赠”。朱莉娅把一切都看在眼里。这房间好像她曾经演过戏的一个场景；她感到有些熟悉，但这一切对她而言都不再有意义。彼时让她心力交瘁的爱，她强迫自己压抑的嫉妒，以及委身于对方时的狂喜，这一切并没有比她曾演过的角色多几分真实。她为自己的漠然沾沾自喜。汤姆拿着她送的茶点台布走进来，利索地布置好茶具，那茶具也是她送给他的。她不知道，为何看到他仍旧随意地使用她送他的那些小礼物使她想要大笑。然后，他端着茶走进来，他们并排坐在沙发上喝茶。他对她讲了更多有关他经济条件改善的情况，并以亲切友好的方式承认，多亏通过她，他才能给事务所带来那些业务，让他得以保住更大份额的利润。他跟她讲了他刚刚结束的假期。朱莉娅很清楚，他对他带给她的痛苦一无所知。这也让她想要大笑。

“我听说今晚你会大获成功。”

“能成功就很棒，对不对？”

“艾维斯说你和迈克尔都对她非常好。当心别让她轻而易举地因此剧而成功。”

他说话的语气虽然是在开玩笑，但朱莉娅怀疑是否艾维斯告诉他这是她所期望的。

“你跟她订婚了吗？”

“没有。她想要自由。她说订婚会阻碍她的艺术生涯。”

“阻碍她的什么？”朱莉娅脱口而出，来不及收回，但她立刻恢复镇定，“是的，我当然明白她的意思。”

“我自然不想挡她的路。我是说，假如今晚后她获得了去美国发展的大好机会，我非常理解她应该有充分的自由去接受它。”

她的艺术生涯！朱莉娅暗自笑了。

“你知道，我觉得你真的是个大好人，看到你对她这样好。”

“为什么要这么说？”

“哦，好吧，你知道女人是什么样子！”

他说这些时，伸出胳膊搂住了她的腰，并亲吻了她。她径直笑了出来。

“你真是个混账小东西。”

“亲热一会儿怎么样？”

“别犯傻了。”

“有什么可犯傻的？你不觉得我们分开太久了吗？”

“我主张跟你彻底分开，不再复合。艾维斯怎么办？”

“哦，她是不同的。来吧。”

“你难道忘了我今晚是首演吗？”

“时间足够。”

他用两只手臂搂着她，轻轻地吻她。她双眼充满嘲笑地看着他。突然间她下了决心。

“好吧。”

他们站起来，走进卧室。她摘下帽子，脱下裙子。他像以前那样抱着她。他亲吻她闭着的双眼，还有她引以为傲的小乳房。她让自己的身体配合他，但她的心灵保持冷漠。她出于友好而回敬他的吻，但她发现自己在思考晚上要表演的角色。她似乎变成了两个人，一个是她情人怀中的情妇，另一个是已经在脑海中看到模糊的黑黝黝的一片观众并听到登台时热烈掌声的女演员。过了一会儿，当他们并肩躺在床上，他的手臂搂着她的脖子，她已经彻底忘记了他的存在，因此当他打破长久的沉默时，她被惊了一下。

“难道你已经不在乎我了吗？”

她微微抱了他一下。

“当然在乎，亲爱的。我很宠爱你。”

“今天你很奇怪。”

她意识到他的失望。可怜的小东西，她并不想伤害他的感情。他真的很可爱。

“马上就是首演夜了，我现在不在状态。你一定别介意。”

当她非常明确地得出结论，她已经不再把他放在心上了，不禁对他感到深深的怜悯。她轻轻地抚摸着他的脸颊。

“小甜心。（不知迈克尔有没有给排队的人送茶。这花不了多少钱，但他们却会感激不尽。）你知道，我必须得起来了。菲利普斯小姐六点会过去。伊维要急死了，她不知道我去哪儿了。”

她一边穿衣服，一边开心地聊着天。虽然她没有看他，但她知道汤姆有些不自在。她戴上帽子，然后双手捧起他的脸，给了他一个友好的吻。

“再见，我的宝贝儿。今晚过得愉快。”

“祝你好运。”

他尴尬地笑了笑。她察觉到，他不知道该拿她怎么办。朱莉娅溜出公寓，如果她不是英格兰一等一的女演员，不是一个五十岁的女人，她会从斯坦霍普广场一路蹦跶着回到家里。她扬扬得意，神气十足。她用钥匙开了大门，进去后把门关上了。

“我看罗杰的话确实有些道理。爱情并不值得人们为此大惊小怪。”

第二十九章

四小时后一切都结束了。演出从头到尾都很顺利；尽管现在是一个寻欢作乐的季节，但观众们度假回来很乐意去剧院消遣，并已经准备好了被逗乐的心情。这是这个演出季的好兆头。每一幕结束后都有热烈的掌声，结尾谢幕多达十二次；朱莉娅单独谢幕了两次，连她都被观众的热情反应所震惊。她吞吞吐吐地说了几句为这种场合预先准备好的话。最后是全剧团集体谢幕，交响乐团奏响了国歌。朱莉娅满怀兴奋和喜悦走向自己的化妆间。她从未感到如此自信。她从未像今天这样表演得如此出色、多彩和老练。演出以朱莉娅一段慷慨激昂的长篇演讲结束，身为一个从良的妓女，她批判了婚姻使她陷入的那个轻浮无用、伤风败俗的圈子。那篇演讲足足有两页纸那么长，英格兰没有别的女演员能够像她讲得那样引人入胜。凭借她对时机的巧妙把握，加上她美妙的声音，以及她控制自如的感情，她奇迹般地让这段演讲成为这场表演中令人振奋甚至惊心动魄的高潮。没有任何激烈的动作能更加让人激动，没有任何意想不到的结局能更让人出乎意料。整个剧团的演出都非常棒，除了艾维斯·克赖顿。朱莉娅低声哼着小曲，走向她的化妆间。

迈克尔紧跟着她进入房间。

“演出看起来大获成功。”他用双臂抱住朱莉娅，亲吻了她，“上帝，你的表演太出色了。”

“你自己也不赖，宝贝儿。”

“那是我唯一拿手的角色，”他满不在乎地回答道，依旧对自己的演技保持谦虚，“你讲那段长篇演讲的时候听到观众出声了吗？这会让评论家们大为震惊。”

“哦，你知道他们什么样子。他们会把全部的注意力都放在该死的剧本上，然后在最后三行提一下我。”

“你是世界上最伟大的女演员，亲爱的，但上帝啊，你是个婊子。”

朱莉娅大睁着双眼，表现出极为天真的惊讶。

“迈克尔，你什么意思？”

“别假装无辜。你完全知道我的意思。你认为你能骗得了像我这样的老手吗？”

他双眼闪烁地看着她，朱莉娅艰难地控制住自己才没有大笑出来。

“我像个刚出生的婴儿一样无辜。”

“别装了。如果有人处心积虑地扼杀了一场演出，那你就是扼杀了艾维斯的。我都没法跟你生气，因为你干得太漂亮了。”

现在，连朱莉娅都遮掩不了她上扬嘴角处的微笑了。赞赏总是让艺术家们感激。艾维斯的主要戏份在第二幕，是和朱莉娅的对手戏，迈克尔完全将这场戏排练成艾维斯的戏。这确实是剧本需要，朱莉娅排练时一如既往地完全听从迈克尔的指挥。为了凸显她的金发碧眼，他们让艾维斯穿上浅蓝色戏服。为了形成对照，朱莉娅选择了一件相宜的黄色裙子，这也是她排练时一直穿的裙子。但同时她还订购了另外一件戏服，是光彩夺目的银色，当她穿着这件裙子在第二幕登场时，迈克尔吓了一跳，艾维斯更是惊慌失措。这套衣服耀眼华丽，在灯光下吸引了观众的注意。相较之下，艾维斯的蓝色裙子显得沉闷无比。等两人一起演到关键时刻，朱莉娅就像魔术师从帽子里变出一只兔子一样掏出了一条红色雪纺大手帕，拿在手里玩弄。她挥舞着它，将它铺展开就好像要端详它，她将它拧成一团，用它擦额头，还用它轻轻地擦鼻涕。着迷的观众无法将眼睛从那块红布上挪开。她走到舞台前，让艾维斯对她说话时不得不背朝观众；当她们一起坐在沙发上时，她拉着艾维斯的手，那动作在观众看来充满感情又极为自然，然后深深地坐到沙发里，迫使艾维斯只能侧脸面对观众。朱莉娅在排练的时候就注意到，艾维斯侧脸看起来像只绵羊。作者给艾维斯的台词在起初排练时让剧组觉得十分好笑。在观众还没有意识到这些台词有多有趣前，朱莉娅就立刻切入了自己的回答，由于观众急于听到她说了什么，便抑制住了笑声。这场原本设计为极其有趣的一幕带了一丝冷嘲的色彩，艾维斯扮演的角色让人有些厌恶。由于缺乏经验，艾维斯在没有获得预料中的掌声后惊慌失措；她的声音变得刺耳，手势变得笨拙。

朱莉娅从艾维斯手中接过这场戏，演得极为生动有趣。但她的最后一击却是临时想法。艾维斯要讲一大段独白，朱莉娅紧张地将她的红手帕拧成一个球；这动作本身就表明了一种感情；她双眼困惑地凝视着艾维斯，两行沉甸甸的泪珠顺着脸颊流下。你感到这个女孩对自己的轻佻感到羞愧，你看到她因自己对正义的小小理想、对善良的渴望受到无情的嘲弄而陷入痛苦，但就在那一分钟里，朱莉娅通过那几滴眼泪和痛苦的眼神，揭露了女人悲惨痛苦的一生。艾维斯的演艺生涯就此结束了。

“我真太蠢了，竟然想给她一份合同。”迈克尔说道。

“为什么不呢？”

“在你给了她一刀之后？绝对不行。你真是个淘气的小家伙，嫉妒心竟然这么重。你不会真的以为她对我意味着什么吧？你应该知道，你是我至今唯一的女人。”

迈克尔以为朱莉娅玩这么一出是由于他和艾维斯极为刺眼的调情所致，虽然对艾维斯来讲运气不佳，但迈克尔忍不住觉得有些得意。

“你这头老驴。”朱莉娅微笑着，心里非常清楚他在想什么，对他的错误乐不可支，“毕竟，你是全伦敦最帅的男人。”

“可能确实如此。但我不知道编剧会怎么说。他是个自命不凡的家伙，你可没按照他写的来演那出戏。”

“哦，让我来对付他，我会搞定他。”

此刻有人敲门，进来的正是编剧。朱莉娅高兴地呼喊着走向他，双臂搂住他的脖子，亲吻了他的双颊。

“你开心吗？”

“看起来很成功。”他冷冷地回答道。

“我亲爱的，这戏会演上一年。”她双手搭在他肩膀上，正面瞧着他，“但你是个顽皮的，顽皮的男人。”

“我？”

“你几乎毁掉了我的表演。当我演到第二幕时，突然间我明白那一幕是怎么回事儿了，那时我差点崩溃。你知道那一幕，你是编剧；为什么你不教我们好好排练？就好像那一幕除了表面意思外再没有深层含义了？我们只是演员，你怎么能期待我们——理解你的微妙之处？这是你剧作里最棒的一幕，我差一点搞砸了。这世界上除了你没人能写出这一幕。你的剧本很棒，但那一幕简直棒极了，可谓天才之作。”

编剧红了脸。朱莉娅生气地看着他。他感到既害羞又满足又骄傲。

（“不出二十四小时，这个傻瓜就会真的认为这一幕这样演就是他的本意。”）

迈克尔满脸笑容。

“来我的化妆间坐坐，喝杯威士忌苏打吧。我肯定投入这么多情感后你需要来一杯。”

他们出门时，汤姆正好走进来。他兴奋得满脸通红。

“我的宝贝儿，太了不起了。你简直棒极了。天啊，演出太精彩了。”

“你喜欢？艾维斯很不错，不是吗？”

“不，她糟透了。”

“我亲爱的，你什么意思？我觉得她非常迷人。”

“你彻底把她打败了。即使在第二幕，她都不漂亮。”

艾维斯的艺术生涯！

“我说，你之后去做什么？”

“多莉要为我们举办宴会。”

“你能推辞掉跟我一起去吃晚餐吗？我疯狂地爱着你。”

“哦，胡说八道。我怎么能让多莉失望？”

“哦，跟我走吧。”

他的眼神极其热切。她能看出他从未像现在这样对她有如此热烈的欲望，她为自己的最终胜利而欢欣鼓舞。但她坚定地摇了摇头。走廊里传来一群人说话的声音，他们俩都知道有一队朋友正从狭窄的走廊里走来，你推我搡地要来向她表示祝贺。

“让这些人都见鬼吧。上帝，我太想吻你了。我早上会给你打电话。”

门被猛地打开，肥胖的多莉冒着汗，热情洋溢地头一个冲了进来，大伙把化妆间挤得透不过气来。朱莉娅任凭自己被各色人亲吻着。在这群人中有三四个有名的女演员，她们毫不吝啬对朱莉娅的赞美之词。朱莉娅出色地表演了毫不做作的谦逊。走廊里挤满了人，大家都想一睹她的芳容。多莉费劲地走了出去。

“别太晚，”她对朱莉娅说道，“今晚将有个绝妙的宴会。”

“我会尽早到的。”

最后，朱莉娅摆脱了人群，脱了戏服，开始卸妆。迈克尔走进来，穿着一件晨衣。

“听着，朱莉娅，你得自己去多莉的宴会了。我得去戏票代售处看看，我去不了，我得去盯紧他们。”

“哦，好吧。”

“他们现在正等着我呢。明天一早见。”

迈克尔离开了，留下她和伊维两人。她为多莉的宴会准备的礼服被摆在一把椅子上。朱莉娅涂上了卸妆膏。

“伊维，芬内尔先生明天会打电话过来，你说我出去了，好吗？”

伊维望向镜子，与朱莉娅眼神相对。

“如果他再打过来呢？”

“我不想伤害他，可怜的家伙，但我觉得从现在起我会非常忙碌。”

伊维大声地吸着鼻涕，以她那令人恶心的习惯，用食指抠了抠鼻孔。

“我明白。”她冷冰冰地说道。

“我一向觉得你并不是看起来那么傻。”朱莉娅继续弄着她的脸蛋，“那椅子上的裙子是怎么回事？”

“那件？那是你说参加宴会要穿的裙子。”

“收起来。我不能没有格斯林先生的陪伴独自去赴宴。”

“这是自从什么时候开始的事？”

“闭嘴，你这个丑老太婆。有人打电话来就说我头很疼，得回家休息，但格斯林先生会尽力去赴宴。”

“那是特意为你举办的宴会。你怎么能让你的老朋友这样失望？”

朱莉娅跺了跺脚。

“我不想去赴宴。我就不会去赴宴。”

“家里没有为你准备的食物。”

“我不想回家。我会去饭店吃晚餐。”

“和谁一起？”

“我自己。”

伊维困惑地看了她一眼。

“这部剧大获成功了，不是吗？”

“是的。一切都非常成功。我觉得我登上了世界之巅。我感觉好极了。我想一个人享受这一切。给伯克利饭店打电话，告诉他们在一个小房间里为我准备一个人的桌子。他们会明白我的意思。”

“你到底怎么了？”

“我这辈子再也不会有这样的时刻了。我不会跟任何人分享这一刻。”

朱莉娅将脸洗干净后，没有再进行任何修饰。她既没有涂口红，也没有扑腮红。她又穿上了她来剧院时穿的棕色大衣和裙子，帽子也没换。那是一顶有帽檐的毡帽，她将帽子压下来盖住一只眼，尽可能地挡住自己的脸。准备好后，她看了看镜子中的自己。

“我看起来像一个被丈夫抛弃的裁缝，而且这并非他的错。我相信没人能认出我来。”

伊维从剧院后门处打了电话，她回来后，朱莉娅问，那里有没有许多人在等自己。

“大概有三百人吧。”

“可恶。”她突然有谁都不想见，也不想被任何人看到的欲望。她想要消失一个小时。“告诉消防人员让我从正门出去，我会搭辆出租车走，一旦我离开了，就告诉大伙别等了。”

“只有上帝知道我得忍受什么。”伊维生气地说道。

“你这头老母牛。”

朱莉娅双手捧着伊维的脸，亲吻了她皱巴巴的双颊；然后溜出了她的化妆间，穿过舞台和铁门，走进了漆黑的观众席。

朱莉娅简单的伪装显然颇为奏效，因为当她进入伯克利饭店那间她非常喜欢的小屋子时，那里的领班侍者并没有立刻认出她来。

“你能不能在角落给我安排个位置？”她踌躇地问道。

侍者听到她的声音，又看了一眼，就知道她是谁了。

“您最喜欢的桌子已经为您准备好了，兰伯特小姐。电话里说只有您一人用餐？”朱莉娅点点头，侍者领着她去了角落里的位置。“我听说今晚您的表演大获成功，兰伯特小姐。”好消息传得可真快。“我能点些什么菜？”

领班侍者对朱莉娅独自用晚餐感到十分惊讶，但他的职业允许他向客户们展现的唯一情感就是见到他们时的欣慰。

“我很疲惫，安吉洛。”

“来点鱼子酱作开胃菜吗，夫人，或是牡蛎？”

“牡蛎，安吉洛，要那种很肥的。”

“我会亲自为您挑选的，兰伯特小姐，那主菜呢？”

朱莉娅长长地叹了口气，因为自打她演完第二幕起，她就能够问心无愧地吃一切她想吃的食物。她觉得她应该大吃一顿来庆贺她的胜利，这一次她打算将谨慎全都抛之脑后。

“烤牛排和洋葱，安吉洛，炸薯条，再来一瓶巴斯啤酒。用大银杯装啤酒。”

她可能得有十年没吃过炸薯条了。但这是意义非凡的时刻！今天，她恰好通过一场只能用才华横溢来描述的表演巩固了自己对观众的牢牢把握，巧妙地解决了艾维斯，并让汤姆看到他有多么愚蠢。最关键的是向她自己毫无疑问地证明，她摆脱了那些曾压迫她、让她烦恼的束缚。艾维斯在她脑子里闪现了一下。

“愚蠢的小东西，竟然试图阻挠我的计划。明天我要让她受到人们的嘲笑。”

牡蛎被端了上来，她愉快地享用了它们。她吃了两片涂黄油的黑面包，这可口的滋味使得她觉得可以不惜危及自己不朽的灵魂，然后她大大地喝了一口银杯里的啤酒。

“啤酒，棒极了的啤酒。”她喃喃道。

她能看到迈克尔在知道她的所作所为后拉长的脸。可怜的迈克尔，竟以为她是因为嫉妒他对那个愚蠢的金发小美女太上心才毁了艾维斯的表演。真的，男人们简直愚蠢得让人同情。他们说女人们虚荣，但跟男人比起来，她们简直是谦逊有加的紫罗兰。想到汤姆她止不住想笑。当天下午他想要她，当天晚上他更想得到她。一想到他现在对她来说跟一个舞台工作人员没什么两样，她就觉得浑身自在。不再为感情羁绊让人觉得自信满满。

她所在的饭店房间和大伙吃饭跳舞的大餐厅通过三个拱廊连接；毫无疑问，人群中有不少人去看了今晚的演出。如果他们知道隔壁房间的角落里，那个被毡帽挡住一半脸的女人竟是朱莉娅·兰伯特，他们该感到多么惊讶。坐在那里，没人知道，没人注意，这给了她愉快的独立感。他们在为她表演一出戏，而她成了观众。他们穿过拱廊时，她扫了几眼，年轻的男人和女人，年轻的男人和不那么年轻的女人，秃头的男人和大腹便便的女人，还有涂脂抹粉拼命装成年轻模样的老泼妇。有一些在恋爱，有一些充满嫉妒，还有一些显得漠不关心。

她的牛排上来了。烹饪得正合她意，洋葱清脆，略显焦色。她吃着可口的炸薯条，吸吮着每根指头，就好像这一刻转瞬即逝，她要争取使之延长。

“在牛排和洋葱前面，爱算什么呢？”她问道。独自一人令人陶醉，让她可以尽情神游。她再一次想到汤姆，在心里幽默地耸了耸肩，“真是有趣的经历。”

这段经历必将会对她未来的表演有所帮助。拱廊外的舞者们跟戏里的一幕如此相似，让她想起刚到圣马洛时产生的一个念头。汤姆抛弃她时她所忍受的痛苦，令她回忆起在她还是个小女孩时，她跟随老珍妮·塔特布学习拉辛的《费德尔》。她又读了一遍剧本。提修斯的皇后蒙受的折磨就是她所蒙受的折磨，她不由得感到她们的遭遇惊人的相似。那是她可以演绎的角色；她知道被自己爱慕的年轻男人拒绝是什么感受。天哪，她将给出何等惊艳的表演！她明白为什么今年春天她演得如此糟糕，让迈克尔宁可关掉剧院；因为她在演戏时是在感受那些情感。那可没什么好处。你得拥有那些情感，但你只能在克服它们之后才能进行表演。她想起查尔斯有一次曾对她说诗歌源于平静中所回忆起的那些情感。她对诗歌一无所知，但这话绝对适用于表演。

“可怜的老查尔斯真聪明，能有这样的独到见解。可见贸然评判一个人是多么错误。人们觉得贵族们是一群笨蛋，然后他们之中突然有一个人说出像那样让人惊叹的话。”

但朱莉娅一直觉得，拉辛直到第三幕才让女主角出场是犯了大错。

“如果我演出这部戏，我当然不会照那样胡来。有半幕戏为我的上场烘托就足够了。”

她没有理由不找个剧作家就这个题材为她写一部剧，要么用散文写，要么用简单的诗句，押韵别太频繁。她能念这样的诗句，并且能念得生动形象。这是个不错的主意，毋庸置疑，而且她知道自己该穿什么样的衣服，不是萨拉用来裹着自己的飘垂的布料，而是她和查尔斯在大英博物馆的一尊浮雕上看到的希腊束腰短上衣。

“事情真有趣！你去参观博物馆和画廊，感到十分无聊，但你会在最意想不到的时候发现它们的用处。足以说明艺术并非真的是浪费时间。”

当然，她的双腿很适合穿束腰短上衣，可是穿这个能演悲剧吗？对此她认真地思考了两三分钟。当她为了那冷漠无情的希波吕托斯肝肠寸断时（想到汤姆穿着萨尔维街(1)的高档西服，扮演一个年轻的希腊猎人形象，她不禁咯咯笑起来），她真的能在没有足够的布料的情况下演出悲剧的效果吗？这难题让她激动。然而，她脑海里闪现一个想法，一时间让她心灰意冷。

“这一切都不错，但戏剧家去哪儿找？萨拉有萨尔杜(2)，杜斯有邓南遮(3)，我有谁？‘苏格兰皇后有个好儿子，而我只是个没有子息的光杆儿。’(4)”

然而，她并没有让这一忧伤的想法扰乱她的平静。她兴高采烈，感到自己有能力像丢卡利翁(5)用石头创造人类一样从愚昧的大众中创造剧作家。

“罗杰那天讲的都是一派胡言，可怜的查尔斯似乎把它当真了。他只不过是个自命不凡的小笨蛋，如此而已。”她朝跳舞的房间比了个手势。灯光被调暗了下来，从她坐着的位置看起来这更像一部剧中的一幕。“‘这世界就是个舞台，所有的男人女人都是演员。(6)’但通过那道拱廊，产生了一种假象；我们这些演员们，才是真实。这才是罗杰要寻找的答案。他们就是我们的素材。我们展现他们生活的意义。我们将他们愚蠢的小情感变成艺术，我们创造美，他们的意义在于成为我们实现自己价值所必需的观众。他们是我们演奏的乐器，没有人演奏，乐器有什么用？”

这个想法让她兴奋不已，她心满意足地琢磨了一会儿。她的头脑似乎异常清晰。

“罗杰说我们不存在。哼，只有我们是存在的。他们都只不过是影子，我们给予他们内涵。我们是这一切他们称为生活——混乱无谓的挣扎——的象征，只有这象征才是真实的。他们说表演都是虚假的。这虚假是唯一的真实。”

这样，朱莉娅在自己脑子里重新构架出这柏拉图式的理论，这使她充满了欣喜。突然间，她对那无数匿名观众产生一股亲切之感，他们的存在就是为了给她机会来表现自己。她超然地待在她的山顶上，思考着世人们数不清的活动。她因摆脱了一切世俗的束缚感到无限自由，同这样的狂喜相比，一切都不值一提。她觉得自己像天堂里的精灵。

领班侍者面带奉承的微笑朝她走来。

“一切都还好吗，兰伯特小姐？”

“好极了。你知道，奇妙的是，人与人各不相同。西登斯夫人爱吃排骨；我则一点都不像她，我爱吃牛排。”

————————————————————

(1) 伦敦的高档裁缝街。

(2) 萨尔杜（Victorien Sardou，1831—1908），法国剧作家，代表作为五幕历史剧《祖国》。

(3) 邓南遮（Gabriele D'Annunzio，1863—1938），意大利著名诗人、小说家、剧作家，代表作《玫瑰三部曲》。

(4) 语出伊丽莎白女王一世。

(5) 出自希腊神话，丢卡利翁是普罗米修斯和普罗诺亚之子，他与妻子皮拉逃脱了宙斯所引发的洪水，并从肩头向身后扔石头，石头变成男女，于是重新创造了人类。

(6) 引自莎士比亚喜剧《皆大欢喜》。

PREFACE

It is not very difficult to write a preface to a book that you wrote a long time ago, for the hurrying years have made a different man of you and you can look upon it with a stranger's eyes. You see its faults, and for the reader's delectation you can recall, according to your temperament with toleration or with dismay, the defects in your character as it was then which account for the defects of your book; or you can look back, maybe with the pleasure which distance lends the past, upon the conditions under which you wrote; you can draw a pretty picture of your garret or dwell with modest complacency on the stiff upper lip with which you faced neglect. But when, in order to tempt a reader to buy a book that has no longer the merit of novelty, you set about writing a preface to a work of fiction that you composed no more than two or three years back, it is none too easy to find anything that you want to say, for you have said in your book all you have to say upon the theme with which it deals and having done so have never given it another thought. As nothing is more dead than a love that has burnt itself out, so no subject is less interesting to an author than one upon which he has said his say. Of course you can quarrel with your reviewers, but there is little point in that; what such and such a critic thought of a novel that he read the year before last can only matter to an author of his susceptibility is really too tender for the rough and tumble of this queer world; the critic has long forgotten both the book and his criticism, and the generality of readers never trouble their heads with criticism anyhow.

When first I set up as a professional author I used to paste such reviews as I got in great scrap-books, thinking it would amuse me some day to read them again, and I would carefully head each one with the date and the name of the paper in which it had appeared. But in course of time these unwieldy volumes grew very cumbersome, and because for one reason and another I have seldom lived for long in the same house, I found it necessary at last to get the dustman to rid me of them. Since then I have contented myself with reading my notices, as time wore on with sufficient equanimity not to be unduly perturbed by those that were unfavourable nor unduly elated by those that were laudatory, and throwing them into my waste-paper basket. My recollection is that on the whole the criticisms of Theatre were pretty good. Some critics, however, complained that Julia Lambert, my heroine, was not a creature of high moral character, great intelligence and nobility of soul, and concluded from this that she was a mediocre actress. I have been given to understand that a number of leading ladies were of the same opinion. Indeed one old actress, celebrated for her acting when I was a boy, and still remembered by the middle-aged for the amusingly disagreeable things she so often said, chiefly at the expense of her fellow-players, was quite biting in her references to me; but I think her acrimony was due to a misapprehension. I took pains in my novel to make it clear that my heroine, whatever her other faults, was not a snob, and this naturally enough prevented the old person in question from recognising the fact that my Julia was a fine actress. We are all inclined to think that others can only have our virtues if they also have our vices.

Greatness is rare. During the last fifty years I have seen most of the actresses who have made a name for themselves. I have seen many who had eminent gifts, many who excelled in a domain they had made their own, many who had charm, beauty and knowledge, but I cannot think of more than one to whom I could without hesitation ascribe greatness. This was Eleanora Duse. It may be that Mrs. Siddons had it; it may be that Rachel had it; I do not know; I never saw Sarah Bernhardt till she was past her prime; the glory that surrounded her, the extravagance of her legend, made it difficult to judge her coolly; she was often mannered and she could rant at times like any player queen; at her best she may have had greatness, I only saw its appurtenances, the crown, the sceptre and the ermine cloak—the Emperor of China's new clothes, but no Emperor of China. With the one exception I have mentioned I have only seen actresses who could be good, sometimes very good, in certain parts. I have a notion that one's opinion in this matter depends a good deal on how much one is affected by the glamour of the stage. There are many people whom the theatre fills with an excitement which no familiarity can stale. It is to them a world of mystery and delight; it gives them entry into a realm of the imagination which increases their joy in life, and its illusion colours the ordinariness of their daily round with the golden shimmer of romance. When they watch the celebrated actress, her beauty enhanced by make-up, her significance emphasized by spot-lights, uttering her fine phrases as though they came out of her own head, undergoing remarkable experiences and suffering poignant emotions, they feel that they live more fully; and it is natural enough that they should make a somewhat excessive use of hyperbole when they seek to describe the sensations which the skilful interpreter has given them. It is natural also that they should overlook the fact that the performance which has filled them with rapture owes at least something to the costumier, the scene-painter, the electrician and the author.

Even in my early youth I was never stage-struck; but whether because I am by nature of a somewhat sceptical disposition or whether because my mind was filled with private dreams which satisfied my romantic yearnings, I cannot say; and when I began to have plays acted I lost even the few illusions I had. When I discovered how much effort was put to achieving the gesture that had such a spontaneous look, when I realized how often the perfect intonation which moved an audience to tears was due not to the actress's sensibility but to the producer's experience, when in short I learnt from the inside how complicated was the process by which a play is made ready to set before an audience, I found it impossible to regard even the most brilliant members of the profession with the same awed and admiring wonder as the general public. On the other hand I learnt that they had qualities with which the public is little inclined to credit them. I learnt, for example, that with few exceptions they were hardworking, courageous, patient and conscientious. Though dropping with fatigue after a long day's work, I saw them consent with cheerfulness to go through still once more a difficult scene that they had that very day rehearsed half a dozen times already; I saw them, in illness, give a performance when they could hardly stand on their feet rather than let the company down; and I learnt that for all the frills and airs they might put on, when it came down to the business of getting the best out of the play and themselves, they were as reasonable as anyone could desire. Behind their famous “temperament,” which is a combination of selfishness and nerves more or less consciously emphasized under the erroneous impression that it is a proof of artistic sensibility, there is far oftener than the public imagines an abundance of shrewd, practical sense. I have never known a child that didn't like to show off, and in every actor there remains something of the child; it is to this that he owes many of his most charming gifts. He has more than the normal exhibitionism which is common to all but very few of us, and if he hadn't he would not be an actor; it is wiser to regard this particular trait with humour than with disdain. If I had to put in a phrase the impressions I formed of actors during the long time of my connection with the stage, I should say that their virtues are more solid than they pretend and their failings incidental to the hazardous and exacting profession they follow.

Thirty years elapsed between the production of my first play and the production of my last and in that period I was thrown into intimate contact with a great number of distinguished actresses. Julia Lambert is a portrait of none of them. I have taken a trait here and a trait there and sought to create a living person. Because I was not much affected by the glamour of the brilliant creatures I had known in the flesh I drew the creature of my fancy, I daresay, with a certain coolness. It is this, perhaps, which has disconcerted those readers who cannot separate the actress from the limelight that surrounds her and vexed those actresses who have been so dazzled by the limelight that they honestly think there is no more in them than that. They do themselves an injustice. The quality of the artist depends on the quality of the man and no one can excel in the arts who has not, besides his special gifts, moral rectitude; I would not deny, however, that this may exhibit itself in a form that is surprising and fantastic. I think Julia Lambert is true to life. I should like the reader to notice that though her admirers ascribe greatness to her, and though she accepts the flattery greedily, I, speaking in my own person, have not claimed that she was more than highly successful, very talented, serious and industrious. I should add that for my part I feel a great affection for her; I am not shocked by her naughtiness, nor scandalized by her absurdities; I can only consider her, whatever she does, with fond indulgence.

Before I bring this preface to a close I must tell the reader that in the book which I am now inviting him to peruse I have made two errors in fact. The novelist tries to be accurate in every detail, but sometimes he makes a mistake, and there is generally no lack of persons who are prepared to point it out to him. Once I wrote a novel in which I had occasion to mention a beach called Manly, which is a favourite resort during the bathing season of the inhabitants of Sydney, and unfortunately I spelt it Manley. The superfluous “e” brought me hundreds of angry and derisive letters from New South Wales. You would have thought that the slip, which might after all have been a printer's error, though of course it was due only to my own carelessness, was a deliberate insult that I had offered to the Commonwealth. Indeed one lady told me that it was one more proof of the ignorant superciliousness of the English towards the inhabitants of the English colonies, and that it was people like me who would be responsible if next time Great Britain was embroiled in a Continental war the youth of Australia, instead of flying to her rescue, preferred to stay quietly at home. She ended her letter on a rhetorical note. What, she asked me, would the English say if an Australian novelist, writing about England, should spell Bournmouth with an “e”? My first impulse was to answer that to the best of my belief the English wouldn't turn a hair, even if it were incorrect, which in point of fact it wasn't, but I thought it would better become me to suffer the lady's stern rebuke in silence. Now in this book I have made two mistakes; I have made my heroine put down her failure in Beatrice to the fact that she was not at ease with blank verse, and I have made her, when she speaks of Racine's Phèdre, complain that the heroine did not appear till the third act. Instead of verifying my facts as I should have done, I trusted my memory, and my memory played me false. Beatrice speaks very little verse; all her important scenes are in prose; and if Julia failed in the part it was not for the reason she gave. Phèdre enters upon the stage in the third scene of the first act. I do not know why only two persons, one apiece, pointed out to me these inexcusable blunders; I like to think that most readers did me the credit of supposing that they were due, not to my ignorance, but tomy subtlety, and that in making Julia Lambert speak in this casual and haphazard fashion I was adding a neat touch to my delineation of her character. But I may be unduly flattering myself, and it is just possible that my readers' recollection of the famous plays in which these characters appear was as hazy as my own, and they knew no better.

Chapter 1

The door opened and Michael Gosselyn looked up. Julia came in.

“Hulloa! I won't keep you a minute. I was just signing some letters.”

“No hurry. I only came to see what seats had been sent to the Dennorants. What's that young man doing here?”

With the experienced actress's instinct to fit the gesture to the word, by a movement of her neat head she indicated the room through which she had just passed.

“He's the accountant. He comes from Lawrence and Hamphreys. He's been here three days.”

“He looks very young.”

“He's an articled clerk. He seems to know his job. He can't get over the way our accounts are kept. He told me he never expected a theatre to be run on such businesslike lines. He says the way some of those firms in the city keep their accounts is enough to turn your hair grey.”

Julia smiled at the complacency on her husband's handsome face.

“He's a young man of tact.”

“He finishes today. I thought we might take him back with us and give him a spot of lunch. He's quite a gentleman.”

“Is that a sufficient reason to ask him to lunch?”

Michael did not notice the faint irony of her tone.

“I won't ask him if you don't want him. I merely thought it would be such a treat for him. He admires you tremendously. He's been to see the play three times. He's crazy to be introduced to you.”

Michael touched a button and in a moment his secretary came in.

“Here are the letters, Margery. What appointments have I got for this afternoon?”

Julia with half an ear listened to the list Margery read out and, though she knew the room so well, idly looked about her. It was a very proper room for the manager of a first-class theatre. The walls had been panelled (at cost price) by a good decorator and on them hung engravings of theatrical pictures of Zoffany and de Wilde. The armchairs were large and comfortable. Michael sat in a heavily-carved Chippendale chair, a reproduction but made by a well-known firm, and his Chippendale table, with heavy ball-and-claw feet, was immensely solid. On it stood in a massive silver frame a photograph of herself and to balance it a photograph of Roger, their son. Between these was a magnificent silver inkstand that she had herself given him on one of his birthdays and behind it a rack in red morocco, heavily gilt, in which he kept his private paper in case he wanted to write a letter in his own hand. The paper bore the address, Siddons Theatre, and the envelope his crest, a boar's head with the motto underneath: Nemo me impune lacessit. A bunch of yellow tulips in a silver bowl, which he had got through winning the theatrical golf tournament three times running, showed Margery's care. Julia gave her a reflective glance. Notwithstanding her cropped peroxide hair and her heavily-painted lips she had the neutral look that marks the perfect secretary. She had been with Michael for five years. In that time she must have got to know him inside and out. Julia wondered if she could be such a fool as to be in love with him.

But Michael rose from his chair.

“Now, darling, I'm ready for you.”

Margery gave him his black Homburg hat and opened the door for Julia and Michael to go out. As they entered the office the young man Julia had noticed turned round and stood up.

“I should like to introduce you to Miss Lambert,” said Michael. Then with the air of an ambassador presenting an attaché to the sovereign of the court to which he is accredited: “This is the gentleman who is good enough to put some order into the mess we make of our accounts.”

The young man went scarlet. He smiled stiffly in answer to Julia's warm, ready smile and she felt the palm of his hand wet with sweat when she cordially grasped it. His confusion was touching. That was how people had felt when they were presented to Sarah Siddons. She thought that she had not been very gracious to Michael when he had proposed asking the boy to lunch. She looked straight into his eyes. Her own were large, of a very dark brown, and starry. It was no effort to her, it was as instinctive as brushing away a fly that was buzzing round her, to suggest now a faintly amused, friendly tenderness.

“I wonder if we could persuade you to come and eat a chop with us. Michael will drive you back after lunch.”

The young man blushed again and his Adam's apple moved in his thin neck.

“It's awfully kind of you.” He gave his clothes a troubled look. “I'm absolutely filthy.”

“You can have a wash and brush up when we get home.”

The car was waiting for them at the stage door, a long car in black and chromium, upholstered in silver leather, and with Michael's crest discreetly emblazoned on the doors. Julia got in.

“Come and sit with me. Michael is going to drive.”

They lived in Stanhope Place, and when they arrived Julia told the butler to show the young man where he could wash his hands. She went up to the drawing-room. She was painting her lips when Michael joined her.

“I've told him to come up as soon as he's ready.”

“By the way, what's his name?”

“I haven't a notion.”

“Darling, we must know. I'll ask him to write in our book.”

“Damn it, he's not important enough for that.” Michael asked only very distinguished people to write in their book. “We shall never see him again.”

At that moment the young man appeared. In the car Julia had done all she could to put him at his ease, but he was still very shy. The cocktails were waiting and Michael poured them out. Julia took a cigarette and the young man struck a match for her, but his hand was trembling so much that she thought he would never be able to hold the light near enough to her cigarette, so she took his hand and held it.

“Poor lamb,” she thought, “I suppose this is the most wonderful moment in his whole life. What fun it'll be for him when he tells his people. I expect he'll be a blasted little hero in his office.”

Julia talked very differently to herself and to other people: when she talked to herself her language was racy. She inhaled the first whiff of her cigarette with delight. It was really rather wonderful, when you came to think of it, that just to have lunch with her and talk to her for three quarters of an hour, perhaps, could make a man quite important in his own scrubby little circle.

The young man forced himself to make a remark.

“What a stunning room this is.”

She gave him the quick, delightful smile, with a slight lift of her fine eyebrows, which he must often have seen her give on the stage.

“I'm so glad you like it.” Her voice was rather low and ever so slightly hoarse. You would have thought his observation had taken a weight off her mind. “We think in the family that Michael has such perfect taste.”

Michael gave the room a complacent glance.

“I've had a good deal of experience. I always design the sets myself for our plays. Of course, I have a man to do the rough work for me, but the ideas are mine.”

They had moved into that house two years before, and he knew, and Julia knew, that they had put it into the hands of an expensive decorator when they were going on tour, and he had agreed to have it completely ready for them, at cost price in return for the work they promised him in the theatre, by the time they came back. But it was unnecessary to impart such tedious details to a young man whose name even they did not know. The house was furnished in extremely good taste, with a judicious mixture of the antique and the modern, and Michael was right when he said that it was quite obviously a gentleman's house. Julia, however, had insisted that she must have her bedroom as she liked, and having had exactly the bedroom that pleased her in the old house in Regent's Park which they had occupied since the end of the war she brought it over bodily. The bed and the dressing-table were upholstered in pink silk, the chaise-longue and the armchair in Nattier blue; over the bed there were fat little gilt cherubs who dangled a lamp with a pink shade, and fat little gilt cherubs swarmed all round the mirror on the dressing-table. On satinwood tables were signed photographs, richly framed, of actors and actresses and members of the royal family. The decorator had raised his supercilious eyebrows, but it was the only room in the house in which Julia felt completely at home. She wrote her letters at a satinwood desk, seated on a gilt Hamlet stool.

Lunch was announced and they went downstairs.

“I hope you'll have enough to eat,” said Julia. “Michael and I have very small appetites.”

In point of fact there was grilled sole, grilled cutlets and spinach, and stewed fruit. It was a meal designed to satisfy legitimate hunger, but not to produce fat. The cook, warned by Margery that there was a guest to lunch, had hurriedly made some fried potatoes. They looked crisp and smelt appetizing. Only the young man took them. Julia gave them a wistful look before she shook her head in refusal. Michael stared at them gravely for a moment as though he could not quite tell what they were, and then with a little start, breaking out of a brown study, said No thank you. They sat at a refectory table, Julia and Michael at either end in very grand Italian chairs, and the young man in the middle on a chair that was not at all comfortable, but perfectly in character. Julia noticed that he seemed to be looking at the sideboard and, with her engaging smile, leaned forward.

“What is it?”

He blushed scarlet.

“I was wondering if I might have a piece of bread.”

“Of course.”

She gave the butler a significant glance; he was at that moment helping Michael to a glass of dry white wine, and he left the room.

“Michael and I never eat bread. It was stupid of Jevons not to realize that you might want some.”

“Of course bread is only a habit,” said Michael. “It's wonderful how soon you can break yourself of it if you set your mind to it.”

“The poor lamb's as thin as a rail, Michael.”

“I don't not eat bread because I'm afraid of getting fat. I don't eat it because I see no point in it. After all, with the exercise I take I can eat anything I like.”

He still had at fifty-two a very good figure. As a young man, with a great mass of curling chestnut hair, with a wonderful skin and large deep-blue eyes, a straight nose and small ears, he had been the best-looking actor on the English stage. The only thing that slightly spoiled him was the thinness of his mouth. He was just six foot tall and he had a gallant bearing. It was his obvious beauty that had engaged him to go on the stage rather than to become a soldier like his father. Now his chestnut hair was very grey, and he wore it much shorter; his face had broadened and was a good deal lined; his skin no longer had the soft bloom of a peach and his colour was high. But with his splendid eyes and his fine figure he was still a very handsome man. Since his five years at the war he had adopted a military bearing, so that if you had not known who he was (which was scarcely possible, for in one way and another his photograph was always appearing in the illustrated papers) you might have taken him for an officer of high rank. He boasted that his weight had not changed since he was twenty, and for years, wet or fine, he had got up every morning at eight to put on shorts and a sweater and have a run round Regent's Park.

“The secretary told me you were rehearsing this morning, Miss Lambert,” the young man remarked. “Does that mean you're putting on a new play?”

“Not a bit of it,” answered Michael. “We're playing to capacity.”

“Michael thought we were getting a bit ragged, so he called a rehearsal.”

“I'm very glad I did. I found little bits of business had crept in that I hadn't given them and a good many liberties were being taken with the text. I'm a great stickler for saying the author's exact words, though, God knows, the words authors write nowadays aren't much.”

“If you'd like to come and see our play,” Julia said graciously, “I'm sure Michael will be delighted to give you some seats.”

“I'd love to come again,” the young man answered eagerly. “I've seen it three times already.”

“You haven't?” cried Julia, with surprise, though she remembered perfectly that Michael had already told her so. “Of course it's not a bad little play, it's served our purpose very well, but I can't imagine anyone wanting to see it three times.”

“It's not so much the play I went to see, it was your performance.”

“I dragged that out of him all right,” thought Julia, and then aloud: “When we read the play Michael was rather doubtful about it. He didn't think my part was very good. You know, it's not really a star part. But I thought I could make something out of it. Of course we had to cut the other woman a lot in rehearsals.”

“I don't say we rewrote the play,” said Michael, “but I can tell you it was a very different play we produced from the one the author submitted to us.”

“You're simply wonderful in it,” the young man said.

(“He has a certain charm.”) “I'm glad you liked me,” she answered.

“If you're very nice to Julia I daresay she'll give you a photograph of herself when you go.”

“Would you?”

He blushed again and his blue eyes shone. (“He's really rather sweet.”) He was not particularly good-looking, but he had a frank, open face and his shyness was attractive. He had curly light-brown hair, but it was plastered down and Julia thought how much better he would look if, instead of trying to smooth out the wave with brilliantine, he made the most of it. He had a fresh colour, a good skin and small well-shaped teeth. She noticed with approval that his clothes fitted and that he wore them well. He looked nice and clean.

“I suppose you've never had anything to do with the theatre from the inside before?” she said.

“Never. That's why I was so crazy to get this job. You can't think how it thrills me.”

Michael and Julia smiled on him kindly. His admiration made them feel a little larger than life-size.

“I never allow outsiders to come to rehearsals, but as you're our accountant you almost belong to the theatre, and I wouldn't mind making an exception in your favour if it would amuse you to come.”

“That would be terribly kind of you. I've never been to a rehearsal in my life. Are you going to act in the next play?”

“Oh, I don't think so. I'm not very keen about acting any more. I find it almost impossible to find a part to suit me. You see, at my time of life I can't very well play young lovers, and authors don't seem to write the parts they used to write when I was a young fellow. What the French call a raisonneur. You know the sort of thing I mean, a duke, or a cabinet minister, or an eminent K.C. who says clever, witty things and turns people round his little finger. I don't know what's happened to authors. They don't seem able to write good lines any more. Bricks without straw; that's what we actors are expected to make nowadays. And are they grateful to us? The authors, I mean. You'd be surprised if I told you the terms some of them have the nerve to ask.”

“The fact remains, we can't do without them,” smiled Julia. “If the play's wrong no acting in the world will save it.”

“That's because the public isn't really interested in the theatre. In the great days of the English stage people didn't go to see the plays, they went to see the players. It didn't matter what Kemble and Mrs. Siddons acted. The public went to see them. And even now, though I don't deny that if the play's wrong you're dished, I do contend that if the play's right, it's the actors the public go to see, not the play.”

“I don't think anyone can deny that,” said Julia.

“All an actress like Julia wants is a vehicle. Give her that and she'll do the rest.”

Julia gave the young man a delightful but slightly deprecating smile.

“You mustn't take my husband too seriously. I'm afraid we must admit that he's partial where I'm concerned.”

“Unless this young man is a much bigger fool than I think him he must know that there's nothing in the way of acting that you can't do.”

“Oh, that's only an idea that people have got because I take care never to do anything but what I can do.”

Presently Michael looked at his watch.

“I think when you've finished your coffee, young man, we ought to be going.”

The boy gulped down what was left in his cup and Julia rose from the table.

“You won't forget my photograph?”

“I think there are some in Michael's den. Come along and we'll choose one.”

She took him into a fair-sized room behind the dining-room. Though it was supposed to be Michael's private sitting-room—“a fellow wants a room where he can get away by himself and smoke his pipe”—it was chiefly used as a cloak-room when they had guests. There was a noble mahogany desk on which were signed photographs of George V and Queen Mary. Over the chimney-piece was an old copy of Lawrence's portrait of Kemble as Hamlet. On a small table was a pile of typescript plays. The room was surrounded by bookshelves under which were cupboards, and from one of these Julia took a bundle of her latest photographs. She handed one to the young man.

“This one is not so bad.”

“It's lovely.”

“Then it can't be as like me as I thought.”

“But it is. It's exactly like you.”

She gave him another sort of smile, just a trifle roguish; she lowered her eyelids for a second and then raising them gazed at him for a little with that soft expression that people described as her velvet look. She had no object in doing this. She did it, if not mechanically, from an instinctive desire to please. The boy was so young, so shy, he looked as if he had such a nice nature, and she would never see him again, she wanted him to have his money's worth; she wanted him to look back on this as one of the great moments of his life. She glanced at the photograph again. She liked to think she looked like that. The photographer had so posed her, with her help, as to show her at her best. Her nose was slightly thick, but he had managed by his lighting to make it look very delicate, not a wrinkle marred the smoothness of her skin, and there was a melting look in her fine eyes.

“All right. You shall have this one. You know I'm not a beautiful woman, I'm not even a very pretty one; Coquelin always used to say I had the beauté du diable. You understand French, don't you?”

“Enough for that.”

“I'll sign it for you.”

She sat at the desk and with her bold, flowing hand wrote: Yours sincerely, Julia Lambert.

Chapter 2

When the two men had gone she looked through the photographs again before putting them back.

“Not bad for a woman of forty-six,” she smiled. “They are like me, there's no denying that.” She looked round the room for a mirror, but there wasn't one. “These damned decorators. Poor Michael, no wonder he never uses this room. Of course I never have photographed well.”

She had an impulse to look at some of her old photographs. Michael was a tidy, businesslike man, and her photographs were kept in large cardboard cases, dated and chronologically arranged. His were in other cardboard cases in the same cupboard.

“When someone comes along and wants to write the story of our careers he'll find all the material ready to his hand,” he said.

With the same laudable object he had had all their press cuttings from the very beginning pasted in a series of books.

There were photographs of Julia when she was a child, and photographs of her as a young girl, photographs of her in her first parts, photographs of her as a young married woman, with Michael, and then with Roger, her son, as a baby. There was one photograph of the three of them, Michael very manly and incredibly handsome, herself all tenderness looking down at Roger with maternal feeling, and Roger a little boy with a curly head, which had been an enormous success. All the illustrated papers had given it a full page and they had used it on the programmes. Reduced to picture-postcard size it had sold in the provinces for years. It was such a bore that Roger when he got to Eton refused to be photographed with her any more. It seemed so funny of him not to want to be in the papers.

“People will think you're deformed or something,” she told him. “And it's not as if it weren't good form. You should just go to a first night and see the society people how they mob the photographers, cabinet ministers and judges and everyone. They may pretend they don't like it, but just see them posing when they think the cameraman's got his eye on them.”

But he was obstinate.

Julia came across a photograph of herself as Beatrice. It was the only Shakespearean part she had ever played. She knew that she didn't look well in costume; she could never understand why, because no one could wear modern clothes as well as she could. She had her clothes made in Paris, both for the stage and for private life, and the dressmakers said that no one brought them more orders. She had a lovely figure, everyone admitted that; she was fairly tall for a woman, and she had long legs. It was a pity she had never had a chance of playing Rosalind, she would have looked all right in boy's clothes, of course it was too late now, but perhaps it was just as well she hadn't risked it. Though you would have thought, with her brilliance, her roguishness, her sense of comedy she would have been perfect. The critics hadn't really liked her Beatrice. It was that damned blank verse. Her voice, her rather low rich voice, with that effective hoarseness, which wrung your heart in an emotional passage or gave so much humour to a comedy line, seemed to sound all wrong when she spoke it. And then her articulation; it was so distinct that, without raising her voice, she could make you hear her every word in the last row of the gallery; they said it made verse sound like prose. The fact was, she supposed, that she was much too modern.

Michael had started with Shakespeare. That was before she knew him. He had played Romeo at Cambridge, and when he came down, after a year at a dramatic school, Benson had engaged him. He toured the country and played a great variety of parts. But he realized that Shakespeare would get him nowhere and that if he wanted to become a leading actor he must gain experience in modern plays. A man called James Langton was running a repertory theatre at Middlepool that was attracting a good deal of attention; and after Michael had been with Benson for three years, when the company was going to Middlepool on its annual visit, he wrote to Langton and asked whether he would see him. Jimmie Langton, a fat, bald-headed, rubicund man of forty-five, who looked like one of Rubens' prosperous burghers, had a passion for the theatre. He was an eccentric, arrogant, exuberant, vain and charming fellow. He loved acting, but his physique prevented him from playing any but a few parts, which was fortunate, for he was a bad actor. He could not subdue his natural flamboyance, and every part he played, though he studied it with care and gave it thought, he turned into a grotesque. He broadened every gesture, he exaggerated every intonation. But it was a very different matter when he rehearsed his cast; then he would suffer nothing artificial. His ear was perfect, and though he could not produce the right intonation himself he would never let a false one pass in anyone else.

“Don't be natural,” he told his company. “The stage isn't the place for that. The stage is make-believe. But seem natural.”

He worked his company hard. They rehearsed every morning from ten till two, when he sent them home to learn their parts and rest before the evening's performance. He bullied them, he screamed at them, he mocked them. He underpaid them. But if they played a moving scene well he cried like a child, and when they said an amusing line as he wanted it said he bellowed with laughter. He would skip about the stage on one leg if he was pleased, and if he was angry would throw the script down and stamp on it while tears of rage ran down his cheeks. The company laughed at him and abused him and did everything they could to please him. He aroused a protective instinct in them, so that one and all they felt that they couldn't let him down. Though they said he drove them like slaves, and they never had a moment to themselves, flesh and blood couldn't stand it, it gave them a sort of horrible satisfaction to comply with his outrageous demands. When he wrung an old trouper's hand, who was getting seven pounds a week, and said, by God, laddie, you're stupendous, the old trouper felt like Charles Kean.

It happened that when Michael kept the appointment he had asked for, Jimmie Langton was in need of a leading juvenile. He had guessed why Michael wanted to see him, and had gone the night before to see him play. Michael was playing Mercutio and he had not thought him very good, but when he came into the office he was staggered by his beauty. In a brown coat and grey flannel trousers, even without make-up, he was so handsome it took your breath away. He had an easy manner and he talked like a gentleman. While Michael explained the purpose of his visit Jimmie Langton observed him shrewdly. If he could act at all, with those looks that young man ought to go far.

“I saw your Mercutio last night,” he said. “What d'you think of it yourself?”

“Rotten.”

“So do I. How old are you?”

“Twenty-five.”

“I suppose you've been told you're good-looking?”

“That's why I went on the stage. Otherwise I'd have gone into the army like my father.”

“By gum, if I had your looks what an actor I'd have been.”

The result of the interview was that Michael got an engagement. He stayed at Middlepool for two years. He soon grew popular with the company. He was good-humoured and kindly; he would take any amount of trouble to do anyone a service. His beauty created a sensation in Middlepool and the girls used to hang about the stage door to see him go out. They wrote him love letters and sent him flowers. He took it as a natural homage, but did not allow it to turn his head. He was eager to get on and seemed determined not to let any entanglement interfere with his career. It was his beauty that saved him, for Jimmie Langton quickly came to the conclusion that, notwithstanding his perseverance and desire to excel, he would never be more than a competent actor. His voice was a trifle thin and in moments of vehemence was apt to go shrill. It gave then more the effect of hysteria than of passion. But his gravest fault as a juvenile lead was that he could not make love. He was easy enough in ordinary dialogue and could say his lines with point, but when it came to making protestations of passion something seemed to hold him back. He felt embarrassed and looked it.

“Damn you, don't hold that girl as if she was a sack of potatoes,” Jimmie Langton shouted at him. “You kiss her as if you were afraid you were standing in a draught. You're in love with that girl. You must feel that you're in love with her. Feel as if your bones were melting inside you and if an earthquake were going to swallow you up next minute, to hell with the earthquake.”

But it was no good. Notwithstanding his beauty, his grace and his ease of manner, Michael remained a cold lover. This did not prevent Julia from falling madly in love with him. For it was when he joined Langton's repertory company that they met.

Her own career had been singularly lacking in hardship. She was born in Jersey, where her father, a native of that island, practised as a veterinary surgeon. Her mother's sister was married to a Frenchman, a coal merchant, who lived at St. Malo, and Julia had been sent to live with her while she attended classes at the local lycée. She learnt to speak French like a Frenchwoman. She was a born actress and it was an understood thing for as long as she could remember that she was to go on the stage. Her aunt, Madame Falloux, was “en relations” with an old actress who had been a sociétaire of the Comédie Française and who had retired to St. Malo to live on the small pension that one of her lovers had settled on her when after many years of faithful concubinage they had parted. When Julia was a child of twelve this actress was a boisterous, fat old woman of more than sixty, but of great vitality, who loved food more than anything else in the world. She had a great, ringing laugh, like a man's, and she talked in a deep, loud voice. It was she who gave Julia her first lessons. She taught her all the arts that she had herself learnt at the Conservatoire and she talked to her of Reichenberg who had played ingénues till she was seventy, of Sarah Bernhardt and her golden voice, of Mounet-Sully and his majesty, and of Coquelin the greatest actor of them all. She recited to her the great tirades of Corneille and Racine she had learnt to say them at the Français and taught her to say them in the same way. It was charming to hear Julia in her childish voice recite those languorous, passionate speeches of Phèdre, emphasizing the beat of the Alexandrines and mouthing her words in the manner which is so artificial and yet so wonderfully dramatic. Jane Taitbout must always have been a very stagy actress, but she taught Julia to articulate with extreme distinctness, she taught her how to walk and how to hold herself, she taught her not to be afraid of her own voice, and she made deliberate that wonderful sense of timing which Julia had by instinct and which afterwards was one of her greatest gifts.

“Never pause unless you have a reason for it,” she thundered, banging with her clenched fist on the table at which she sat, “but when you pause, pause as long as you can.”

When Julia was sixteen and went to the Royal Academy of Dramatic Art in Gower Street she knew already much that they could teach her there. She had to get rid of a certain number of tricks that were out of date and she had to acquire a more conversational style. But she won every prize that was open to her, and when she was finished with the school her good French got her almost immediately a small part in London as a French maid. It looked for a while as though her knowledge of French would specialize her in parts needing a foreign accent, for after this she was engaged to play an Austrian waitress. It was two years later that Jimmie Langton discovered her. She was on tour in a melodrama that had been successful in London; in the part of an Italian adventuress, whose machinations were eventually exposed, she was trying somewhat inadequately to represent a woman of forty. Since the heroine, a blonde person of mature years, was playing a young girl, the performance lacked verisimilitude. Jimmie was taking a short holiday which he spent in going every night to the theatre in one town after another. At the end of the piece he went round to see Julia. He was well enough known in the theatrical world for her to be flattered by the compliments he paid her, and when he asked her to lunch with him next day she accepted.

They had no sooner sat down to table than he went straight to the point.

“I never slept a wink all night for thinking of you,” he said.

“This is very sudden. Is your proposal honourable or dis-honourable?”

He took no notice of the flippant rejoinder.

“I've been at this game for twenty-five years. I've been a callboy, a stage-hand, a stage-manager, an actor, a publicity man, damn it, I've even been a critic. I've lived in the theatre since I was a kid just out of a board school, and what I don't know about acting isn't worth knowing. I think you're a genius.”

“It's sweet of you to say so.”

“Shut up. Leave me to do the talking. You've got everything. You're the right height, you've got a good figure, you've got an indiarubber face.”

“Flattering, aren't you?”

“That's just what I am. That's the face an actress wants. The face that can look anything, even beautiful, the face that can show every thought that passes through the mind. That's the face Duse's got. Last night even though you weren't really thinking about what you were doing, every now and then the words you were saying wrote themselves on your face.”

“It's such a rotten part. How could I give it my attention? Did you hear the things I had to say?”

“Actors are rotten, not parts. You've got a wonderful voice, the voice that can wring an audience's heart, I don't know about your comedy, I'm prepared to risk that.”

“What d'you mean by that?”

“Your timing is almost perfect. That couldn't have been taught, you must have that by nature. That's the far, far better way. Now let's come down to brass tacks. I've been making enquiries about you. It appears you speak French like a Frenchwoman and so they give you broken English parts. That's not going to lead you anywhere, you know.”

“That's all I can get.”

“Are you satisfied to go on playing those sort of parts for ever? You'll get stuck in them and the public won't take you in anything else. Seconds, that's all you'll play. Twenty pounds a week at the outside and a great talent wasted.”

“I've always thought that someday or other I should get a chance of a straight part.”

“When? You may have to wait ten years. How old are you now?”

“Twenty.”

“What are you getting?”

“Fifteen pounds a week.”

“That's a lie. You're getting twelve, and it's a damned sight more than you're worth. You've got everything to learn. Your gestures are commonplace. You don't know that every gesture must mean something. You don't know how to get an audience to look at you before you speak. You make up too much. With your sort of face the less make-up the better. Wouldn't you like to be a star?”

“Who wouldn't?”

“Come to me and I'll make you the greatest actress in England. Are you a quick study? You ought to be at your age.”

“I think I can be word-perfect in any part in forty-eight hours.”

“It's experience you want and me to produce you. Come to me and I'll let you play twenty parts a year. Ibsen, Shaw, Barker, Sudermann, Hankin, Galsworthy. You've got magnetism and you don't seem to have an idea how to use it.” He chuckled. “By God, if you had, that old hag would have had you out of the play you're in now before you could say knife. You've got to take an audience by the throat and say, now, you dogs, you pay attention to me. You've got to dominate them. If you haven't got the gift no one can give it to you, but if you have you can be taught how to use it. I tell you, you've got the makings of a great actress. I've never been so sure of anything in my life.”

“I know I want experience. I'd have to think it over of course. I wouldn't mind coming to you for a season.”

“Go to hell. Do you think I can make an actress of you in a season? Do you think I'm going to work my guts out to make you give a few decent performances and then have you go away to play some twopenny-halfpenny part in a commercial play in London? What sort of a bloody fool do you take me for? I'll give you a three years' contract, I'll give you eight pounds a week and you'll have to work like a horse.”

“Eight pounds a week's absurd. I couldn't possibly take that.”

“Oh, yes, you could. It's all you're worth and it's all you're going to get.”

Julia had been on the stage for three years and had learnt a good deal. Besides, Jane Taitbout, no strict moralist, had given her a lot of useful information.

“And are you under the impression, by any chance, that for that I'm going to let you sleep with me as well?”

“My God, do you think I've got time to go to bed with the members of my company? I've got much more important things to do than that, my girl. And you'll find that after you've rehearsed for four hours and played a part at night to my satisfaction, besides a couple of matinées, you won't have much time or much inclination to make love to anybody. When you go to bed all you'll want to do is to sleep.”

But Jimmie Langton was wrong there.

Chapter 3

Julia, taken by his enthusiasm and his fantastic exuberance, accepted his offer. He started her in modest parts which under his direction she played as she had never played before. He interested the critics in her, he flattered them by letting them think that they had discovered a remarkable actress, and allowed the suggestion to come from them that he should let the public see her as Magda. She was a great hit and then in quick succession he made her play Nora in The Doll's House, Ann in Man and Superman, and Hedda Gabler. Middlepool was delighted to discover that it had in its midst an actress who it could boast was better than any star in London, and crowded to see her in plays that before it had gone to only from local patriotism. The London paragraphers mentioned her now and then, and a number of enthusiastic patrons of the drama made the journey to Middlepool to see her. They went back full of praise, and two or three London managers sent representatives to report on her. They were doubtful. She was all very well in Shaw and Ibsen, but what would she do in an ordinary play? The managers had had bitter experiences. On the strength of an outstanding performance in one of these queer plays they had engaged an actor, only to discover that in any other sort of play he was no better than anybody else.

When Michael joined the company Julia had been playing in Middlepool for a year. Jimmie started him with Marchbanks in Candida. It was the happy choice one would have expected him to make, for in that part his great beauty was an asset and his lack of warmth no disadvantage.

Julia reached over to take out the first of the cardboard cases in which Michael's photographs were kept. She was sitting comfortably on the floor. She turned the early photographs over quickly, looking for that which he had had taken when first he came to Middlepool; but when she came upon it, it gave her a pang. For a moment she felt inclined to cry. It had been just like him then. Candida was being played by an older woman, a sound actress who was cast generally for mothers, maiden aunts or character parts, and Julia with nothing to do but act eight times a week attended the rehearsals. She fell in love with Michael at first sight. She had never seen a more beautiful young man, and she pursued him relentlessly. In due course Jimmie put on Ghosts, braving the censure of respectable Middlepool, and Michael played the boy and she played Regina. They heard one another their parts and after rehearsals lunched, very modestly, together so that they might talk of them. Soon they were inseparable. Julia had little reserve; she flattered Michael outrageously. He was not vain of his good looks, he knew he was handsome and accepted compliments, not exactly with indifference, but as he might have accepted a compliment on a fine old house that had been in his family for generations. It was a well-known fact that it was one of the best houses of its period, one was proud of it and took care of it, but it was just there, as natural to possess as the air one breathed. He was shrewd and ambitious. He knew that his beauty was at present his chief asset, but he knew it could not last for ever and was determined to become a good actor so that he should have something besides his looks to depend on. He meant to learn all he could from Jimmie Langton and then go to London.

“If I play my cards well I can get some old woman to back me and go into management. One's got to be one's own master. That's the only way to make a packet.”

Julia soon discovered that he did not much like spending money, and when they ate a meal together, or on a Sunday went for a small excursion, she took care to pay her share of the expenses. She did not mind this. She liked him for counting the pennies, and, inclined to be extravagant herself and always a week or two behind with her rent, she admired him because he hated to be in debt and even with the small salary he was getting managed to save up a little every week. He was anxious to have enough put by so that when he went to London he need not accept the first part that was offered him, but could afford to wait till he got one that gave him a real chance. His father had little more than his pension to live on, and it had been a sacrifice to send him to Cambridge. His father, not liking the idea of his going on the stage, had insisted on this.

“If you want to be an actor I suppose I can't stop you,” he said, “but damn it all, I insist on your being educated like a gentleman.”

It gave Julia a good deal of satisfaction to discover that Michael's father was a colonel, it impressed her to hear him speak of an ancestor who had gambled away his fortune at White's during the Regency, and she liked the signet ring Michael wore with the boar's head on it and the motto: Nemo me impune lacessit.

“I believe you're prouder of your family than of looking like a Greek god,” she told him fondly.

“Anyone can be good-looking,” he answered, with his sweet smile, “but not everyone can belong to a decent family. To tell you the truth I'm glad my governor's a gentleman.”

Julia took her courage in both hands.

“My father's a vet.”

For an instant Michael's face stiffened, but he recovered himself immediately and laughed.

“Of course it doesn't really matter what one's father is. I've often heard my father talk of the vet in his regiment. He counted as an officer of course. Dad always said he was one of the best.”

And she was glad he'd been to Cambridge. He had rowed for his College and at one time there was some talk of putting him in the university boat.

“I should have liked to get my blue. It would have been useful to me on the stage. I'd have got a lot of advertisement out of it.”

Julia could not tell if he knew that she was in love with him. He never made love to her. He liked her society and when they found themselves with other people scarcely left her side. Sometimes they were asked to parties on Sunday, dinner at midday or a cold, sumptuous supper, and he seemed to think it natural that they should go together and come away together. He kissed her when he left her at her door, but he kissed her as he might have kissed the middle-aged woman with whom he had played Candida. He was friendly, good-humoured and kind, but it was distressingly clear that she was no more to him than a comrade. Yet she knew that he was not in love with anybody else. The love-letters that women wrote to him he read out to Julia with a chuckle, and when they sent him flowers he immediately gave them to her.

“What blasted fools they are,” he said. “What the devil do they think they're going to get out of it?”

“I shouldn't have thought it very hard to guess that,” said Julia dryly.

Although she knew he took these attentions so lightly she could not help feeling angry and jealous.

“I should be a damned fool if I got myself mixed up with some woman in Middlepool. After all, they're mostly flappers. Before I knew where I was I'd have some irate father coming along and saying, now you must marry the girl.”

She tried to find out whether he had had any adventures while he was playing with Benson's company. She gathered that one or two of the girls had been rather inclined to make nuisances of themselves, but he thought it was a terrible mistake to get mixed up with any of the actresses a chap was playing with. It was bound to lead to trouble.

“And you know how people gossip in a company. Everyone would know everything in twenty-four hours. And when you start a thing like that you don't know what you're letting yourself in for. I wasn't risking anything.”

When he wanted a bit of fun he waited till they were within a reasonable distance of London and then he would race up to town and pick up a girl at the Globe Restaurant. Of course it was expensive, and when you came to think of it, it wasn't really worth the money; besides, he played a lot of cricket in Benson's company, and golf when he got the chance, and that sort of thing was rotten for the eye.

Julia told a thumping lie.

“Jimmie always says I'd be a much better actress if I had an affair.”

“Don't you believe it. He's just a dirty old man. With him, I suppose. I mean, you might just as well say that I'd give a better performance of Marchbanks if I wrote poetry.”

They talked so much together that it was inevitable for her at last to learn his views on marriage.

“I think an actor's a perfect fool to marry young. There are so many cases in which it absolutely ruins a chap's career. Especially if he marries an actress. He becomes a star and then she's a millstone round his neck. She insists on playing with him, and if he's in management he has to give her leading parts, and if he engages someone else there are most frightful scenes. And of course for an actress it's insane. There's always the chance of her having a baby and she may have to refuse a damned good part. She's out of the public eye for months, and you know what the public is, unless they see you all the time they forget that you ever existed.”

Marriage? What did she care about marriage? Her heart melted within her when she looked into his deep, friendly eyes, and she shivered with delightful anguish when she considered his shining, russet hair. There was nothing that he could have asked her that she would not gladly have given him. The thought never entered his lovely head.

“Of course he likes me,” she said to herself. “He likes me better than anyone, he even admires me, but I don't attract him that way.”

She did everything to seduce him except slip into bed with him, and she only did not do that because there was no opportunity. She began to fear that they knew one another too well for it to seem possible that their relations should change, and she reproached herself bitterly because she had not rushed to a climax when first they came in contact with one another. He had too sincere an affection for her now ever to become her lover. She found out when his birthday was and gave him a gold cigarette case which she knew was the thing he wanted more than anything in the world. It cost a good deal more than she could afford and he smilingly reproached her for her extravagance. He never dreamt what ecstatic pleasure it gave her to spend her money on him. When her birthday came along he gave her half a dozen pairs of silk stockings. She noticed at once that they were not of very good quality, poor lamb, he had not been able to bring himself to spring to that, but she was so touched that he should give her anything that she could not help crying.

“What an emotional little thing you are,” he said, but he was pleased and touched to see her tears.

She found his thrift rather an engaging trait. He could not bear to throw his money about. He was not exactly mean, but he was not generous. Once or twice at restaurants she thought he undertipped the waiter, but he paid no attention to her when she ventured to remonstrate. He gave the exact ten percent, and when he could not make the exact sum to a penny asked the waiter for change.

“‘Neither a borrower nor a lender be,’” he quoted from Polonius.

When some member of the company, momentarily hard up, tried to borrow from him it was in vain. But he refused so frankly, with so much heartiness, that he did not affront.

“My dear old boy, I'd love to lend you a quid, but I'm absolutely stony. I don't know how I'm going to pay my rent at the end of the week.”

For some months Michael was so much occupied with his own parts that he failed to notice how good an actress Julia was. Of course he read the reviews, and their praise of Julia, but he read summarily, without paying much attention till he came to the remarks the critics made about him. He was pleased by their approval, but not cast down by their censure. He was too modest to resent an unfavourable criticism.

“I suppose I was rotten,” he would say ingenuously.

His most engaging trait was his good humour. He bore Jimmie Langton's abuse with equanimity. When tempers grew frayed during a long rehearsal he remained serene. It was impossible to quarrel with him. One day he was sitting in front watching the rehearsal of an act in which he did not appear. It ended with a powerful and moving scene in which Julia had the opportunity to give a fine display of acting. When the stage was being set for the next act Julia came through the pass door and sat down beside Michael. He did not speak to her, but looked sternly in front of him. She threw him a surprised look. It was unlike him not to give her a smile and a friendly word. Then she saw that he was clenching his jaw to prevent its trembling and that his eyes were heavy with tears.

“What's the matter, darling?”

“Don't talk to me. You dirty little bitch, you've made me cry.”

“Angel!”

The tears came to her own eyes and streamed down her face. She was so pleased, so flattered.

“Oh, damn it,” he sobbed. “I can't help it.”

He took a handkerchief out of his pocket and dried his eyes.

(“I love him, I love him, I love him.”)

Presently he blew his nose.

“I'm beginning to feel better now. But, my God, you shattered me.”

“It's not a bad scene, is it?”

“The scene be damned, it was you. You just wrung my heart. The critics are right, damn it, you're an actress and no mistake.”

“Have you only just discovered it?”

“I knew you were pretty good, but I never knew you were as good as all that. You make the rest of us look like a piece of cheese. You're going to be a star. Nothing can stop you.”

“Well then, you shall be my leading man.”

“Fat chance I'd have of that with a London manager.”

Julia had an inspiration.

“Then you must go into management yourself and make me your leading lady.”

He paused. He was not a quick thinker and needed a little time to let a notion sink into his mind. He smiled.

“You know that's not half a bad idea.”

They talked it over at luncheon. Julia did most of the talking while he listened to her with absorbed interest.

“Of course the only way to get decent parts consistently is to run one's own theatre,” he said. “I know that.”

The money was the difficulty. They discussed how much was the least they could start on. Michael thought five thousand pounds was the minimum. But how in heaven's name could they raise a sum like that? Of course some of those Middlepool manufacturers were rolling in money, but you could hardly expect them to fork out five thousand pounds to start a couple of young actors who had only a local reputation. Besides, they were jealous of London.

“You'll have to find your rich old woman,” said Julia gaily.

She only half believed all she had been saying, but it excited her to discuss a plan that would bring her into a close and constant relation with Michael. But he was being very serious.

“I don't believe one could hope to make a success in London unless one were pretty well known already. The thing to do would be to act there in other managements for three or four years first; one's got to know the ropes. And the advantage of that would be that one would have had time to read plays. It would be madness to start in management unless one had at least three plays. One of them out to be a winner.”

“Of course if one did that, one ought to make a point of acting together so that the public got accustomed to seeing the two names on the same bill.”

“I don't know that there's much in that. The great thing is to have good, strong parts. There's no doubt in my mind that it would be much easier to find backers if one had made a bit of a reputation in London.”

Chapter 4

It was getting on for Easter, and Jimmie Langton always closed his theatre for Holy Week. Julia did not quite know what to do with herself; it seemed hardly worth while to go to Jersey. She was surprised to receive a letter one morning from Mrs. Gosselyn, Michael's mother, saying that it would give the Colonel and herself so much pleasure if she would come with Michael to spend the week at Cheltenham. When she showed the letter to Michael he beamed.

“I asked her to invite you. I thought it would be more polite than if I just took you along.”

“You are sweet. Of course I shall love to come.”

Her heart beat with delight. The prospect of spending a whole week with Michael was enchanting. It was just like his good nature to come to the rescue when he knew she was at a loose end. But she saw there was something he wanted to say, yet did not quite like to.

“What is it?”

He gave a little laugh of embarrassment.

“Well, dear, you know, my father's rather old-fashioned, and there are some things he can't be expected to understand. Of course I don't want you to tell a lie or anything like that, but I think it would seem rather funny to him if he knew your father was a vet. When I wrote and asked if I could bring you down I said he was a doctor.”

“Oh, that's all right.”

Julia found the Colonel a much less alarming person than she had expected. He was thin and rather small, with a lined face and close-cropped white hair. His features had a worn distinction. He reminded you of a head on an old coin that had been in circulation too long. He was civil, but reserved. He was neither peppery nor tyrannical as Julia, from her knowledge of the stage, expected a colonel to be. She could not imagine him shouting out words of command in that courteous, rather cold voice. He had in point of fact retired with honorary rank after an entirely undistinguished career, and for many years had been content to work in his garden and play bridge at his club. He read The Times, went to church on Sunday and accompanied his wife to tea-parties. Mrs. Gosselyn was a tall, stoutish, elderly woman, much taller than her husband, who gave you the impression that she was always trying to diminish her height. She had the remains of good looks, so that you said to yourself that when young she must have been beautiful. She wore her hair parted in the middle with a bun on the nape of her neck. Her classic features and her size made her at first meeting somewhat imposing, but Julia quickly discovered that she was very shy. Her movements were stiff and awkward. She was dressed fussily, with a sort of old-fashioned richness which did not suit her. Julia, who was entirely without self-consciousness, found the elder woman's deprecating attitude rather touching. She had never known an actress to speak to and did not quite know how to deal with the predicament in which she now found herself. The house was not at all grand, a small detached stucco house in a garden with a laurel hedge, and since the Gosselyns had been for some years in India there were great trays of brass ware and brass bowls, pieces of Indian embroidery and highly carved Indian tables. It was cheap bazaar stuff and you wondered how anyone had thought it worth bringing home.

Julia was quick-witted. It did not take her long to discover that the Colonel, notwithstanding his reserve, and Mrs. Gosselyn, notwithstanding her shyness, were taking stock of her. The thought flashed through her mind that Michael had brought her down for his parents to inspect her. Why? There was only one possible reason, and when she thought of it her heart leaped. She saw that he was anxious for her to make a good impression. She felt instinctively that she must conceal the actress, and without effort, without deliberation, merely because she felt it would please, she played the part of the simple, modest, ingenuous girl who had lived a quiet country life. She walked round the garden with the Colonel and listened intelligently while he talked of peas and asparagus; she helped Mrs. Gosselyn with the flowers and dusted the ornaments with which the drawing-room was crowded. She talked to her of Michael. She told her howcleverly he acted and how popular he was and she praised his looks. She saw that Mrs. Gosselyn was very proud of him, and with a flash of intuition saw that it would please her if she let her see, with the utmost delicacy, as though she would have liked to keep it a secret but betrayed herself unwittingly, that she was head over ears in love with him.

“Of course we hope he'll do well,” said Mrs. Gosselyn. “We didn't much like the idea of his going on the stage; you see, on both sides of the family, we're army, but he was set on it.”

“Yes, of course I see what you mean.”

“I know it doesn't mean so much as when I was a girl, but after all he was born a gentleman.”

“Oh, but some very nice people go on the stage nowadays, you know. It's not like in the old days.”

“No, I suppose not. I'm so glad he brought you down here. I was a little nervous about it. I thought you'd be made-up and… perhaps a little loud. No one would dream you were on the stage.”

(“I should damn well think not. Haven't I been giving a perfect performance of the village maiden for the last forty-eight hours?”)

The Colonel began to make little jokes with her and sometimes he pinched her ear playfully.

“Now you mustn't flirt with me, Colonel,” she cried, giving him a roguish, delicious glance. “Just because I'm an actress you think you can take liberties with me.”

“George, George,” smiled Mrs. Gosselyn. And then to Julia: “He always was a terrible flirt.”

(“Gosh, I'm going down like a barrel of oysters.”)

Mrs. Gosselyn told her about India, how strange it was to have all those coloured servants, but how nice the society was, only army people and Indian civilians, but still it wasn't like home, and how glad she was to get back to England.

They were to leave on Easter Monday because they were playing that night, and on Sunday evening after supper Colonel Gosselyn said he was going to his study to write letters; a minute or two later Mrs. Gosselyn said she must go and see the cook. When they were left alone Michael, standing with his back to the fire, lit a cigarette.

“I'm afraid it's been very quiet down here; I hope you haven't had an awfully dull time.”

“It's been heavenly.”

“You've made a tremendous success with my people. They've taken an enormous fancy to you.”

“God, I've worked for it,” thought Julia, but aloud said: “How d'you know?”

“Oh, I can see it. Father told me you were very ladylike, and not a bit like an actress, and Mother says you're so sensible.”

Julia looked down as though the extravagance of these compliments was almost more than she could bear. Michael came over and stood in front of her. The thought occurred to her that he looked like a handsome young footman applying for a situation. He was strangely nervous. Her heart thumped against her ribs.

“Julia dear, will you marry me?”

For the last week she had asked herself whether or not he was going to propose to her, and now that he had at last done so, she was strangely confused.

“Michael!”

“Not immediately, I don't mean. But when we've got our feet on the ladder. I know that you can act me off the stage, but we get on together like a house on fire, and when we do go into management I think we'd make a pretty good team. And you know I do like you most awfully. I mean, I've never met anyone who's a patch on you.”

(“The blasted fool, why does he talk all that rot? Doesn't he know I'm crazy to marry him? Why doesn't he kiss me, kiss me, kiss me? I wonder if I dare tell him I'm absolutely sick with love for him.”)

“Michael, you're so handsome. No one could refuse to marry you.”

“Darling!”

(“I'd better get up. He wouldn't know how to sit down. God, that scene that Jimmie made him do over and over again!”)

She got on her feet and put up her face to his. He took her in his arms and kissed her lips.

“I must tell Mother.”

He broke away from her and went to the door.

“Mother, Mother!”

In a moment the Colonel and Mrs. Gosselyn came in. They bore a look of happy expectancy.

(“By God, it was a put-up job.”)

“Mother, Father, we're engaged.”

Mrs. Gosselyn began to cry. With her awkward, lumbering gait she came up to Julia, flung her arms round her, and sobbing, kissed her. The Colonel wrung his son's hand in a manly way and releasing Julia from his wife's embrace kissed her too. He was deeply moved. All this emotion worked on Julia and, though she smiled happily, the tears coursed down her cheeks. Michael watched the affecting scene with sympathy.

“What d'you say to a bottle of pop to celebrate?” he said. “It looks to me as though Mother and Julia were thoroughly upset.”

“The ladies, God bless 'em,” said the Colonel when their glasses were filled.

Chapter 5

Julia now was looking at the photograph of herself in her wedding-dress.

“Christ, what a sight I looked.”

They decided to keep their engagement to themselves, and Julia told no one about it but Jimmie Langton, two or three girls in the company and her dresser. She vowed them to secrecy and could not understand how within forty-eight hours everyone in the theatre seemed to know all about it. Julia was divinely happy. She loved Michael more passionately than ever and would gladly have married him there and then, but his good sense prevailed. They were at present no more than a couple of provincial actors, and to start their conquest of London as a married couple would jeopardize their chances. Julia showed him as clearly as she knew how, and this was very clearly indeed, that she was quite willing to become his mistress, but this he refused. He was too honourable to take advantage of her.

“‘I could not love thee, dear, so much, loved I not honour more,’” he quoted.

He felt sure that when they were married they would bitterly regret it if they had lived together before as man and wife. Julia was proud of his principles. He was a kind and affectionate lover, but in a very short while seemed to take her a trifle for granted; by his manner, friendly but casual, you might have thought they had been married for years. But he showed great good nature in allowing Julia to make love to him. She adored to sit cuddled up to him with his arm round her waist, her face against his, and it was heaven when she could press her eager mouth against his rather thin lips. Though when they sat side by side like that he preferred to talk of the parts they were studying or make plans for the future, he made her very happy. She never tired of praising his beauty. It was heavenly, when she told him how exquisite his nose was and how lovely his russet, curly hair, to feel his hold on her tighten a little and to see the tenderness in his eyes.

“Darling, you'll make me as vain as a peacock.”

“It would be so silly to pretend you weren't divinely handsome.”

Julia thought he was, and she said it because she liked saying it, but she said it also because she knew he liked to hear it. He had affection and admiration for her, he felt at ease with her, and he had confidence in her, but she was well aware that he was not in love with her. She consoled herself by thinking that he loved her as much as he was capable of loving, and she thought that when they were married, when they slept together, her own passion would excite an equal passion in him. Meanwhile she exercised all her tact and all her self-control. She knew she could not afford to bore him. She knew she must never let him feel that she was a burden or a responsibility. He might desert her for a game of golf, or to lunch with a casual acquaintance, but she never let him see for a moment that she was hurt. And with an inkling that her success as an actress strengthened his feeling for her she worked like a dog to play well.

When they had been engaged for rather more than a year an American manager, looking for talent and having heard of Jimmie Langton's repertory company, came to Middlepool and was greatly taken by Michael. He sent him round a note asking him to come to his hotel on the following afternoon.Michael, breathless with excitement, showed it to Julia; it could only mean that he was going to offer him a part. Her heart sank, but she pretended that she was as excited as he, and went with him next day to the hotel. She was to wait in the lobby while Michael saw the great man.

“Wish me luck,” he whispered, as he turned from her to enter the lift. “It's almost too good to be true.”

Julia sat in a great leather armchair willing with all her might the American manager to offer a part that Michael would refuse or a salary that he felt it would be beneath his dignity to accept. Or alternatively that he should get Michael to read the part he had in view and come to the conclusion that he could not touch it. But when she saw Michael coming towards her half an hour later, his eyes bright and his step swinging, she knew he had clicked. For a moment she thought she was going to be sick, and when she forced on her face an eager, happy smile, she felt that her muscles were stiff and hard.

“It's all right. He says it's a damned good part, a boy's part, nineteen. Eight or ten weeks in New York and then on the road. It's a safe forty weeks with John Drew. Two hundred and fifty dollars a week.”

“Oh, darling, how wonderful for you.”

It was quite clear that he had accepted with alacrity. The thought of refusing had never even occurred to him.

“And I—I,” she thought, “if they'd offered me a thousand dollars a week I wouldn't have gone if it meant being separated from Michael.”

Black despair seized her. She could do nothing. She must pretend to be as delighted as he was. He was too much excited to sit still and took her out into the crowded street to walk.

“It's a wonderful chance. Of course America's expensive, but I ought to be able to live on fifty dollars a week at the outside, they say the Americans are awfully hospitable and I shall get a lot of free meals. I don't see why I shouldn't save eight thousand dollars in the forty weeks and that's sixteen hundred pounds.”

(“He doesn't love me. He doesn't care a damn about me. I hate him. I'd like to kill him. Blast that American manager.”)

“And if he takes me on for a second year I'm to get three hundred. That means that in two years I'd have the best part of four thousand pounds. Almost enough to start management on.”

“A second year!” For a moment Julia lost control of herself and her voice was heavy with tears. “D'you mean to say you'll be gone two years?”

“Oh, I should come back next summer of course. They pay my fare back and I'd go and live at home so as not to spend any money.”

“I don't know how I'm going to get on without you.”

She said the words very brightly, so that they sounded polite, but somewhat casual.

“Well, we can have a grand time together in the summer and you know a year, two years at the outside, well, it passes like a flash of lightning.”

Michael had been walking at random, but Julia without his noticing had guided him in the direction she wished, and now they arrived in front of the theatre. She stopped.

“I'll see you later. I've got to pop up and see Jimmie.” His face fell.

“You're not going to leave me now! I must talk to somebody. I thought we might go and have a snack together before the show.”

“I'm terribly sorry. Jimmie's expecting me and you know what he is.”

Michael gave her his sweet, good-natured smile.

“Oh, well, go on then. I'm not going to hold it up against you because for once you've let me down.”

He walked on and she went in by the stage door. Jimmie Langton had arranged himself a tiny flat under the roof to which you gained access through the balcony. She rang the bell of his front door and he opened it himself. He was surprised, but pleased, to see her.

“Hulloa, Julia, come in.”

She walked past him without a word, and when they got into his sitting-room, untidy, littered with typescript plays, books and other rubbish, the remains of his frugal lunch still on a tray by his desk, she turned and faced him. Her jaw was set and her eyes were frowning.

“You devil!”

With a swift gesture she went up to him, seized him by his loose shirt collar with both hands and shook him. He struggled to get free of her, but she was strong and violent.

“Stop it. Stop it.”

“You devil, you swine, you filthy low-down cad.”

He took a swing and with his open hand gave her a great smack on the face. She instinctively loosened her grip on him and put her own hand up to her cheek, for he had hurt her. She burst out crying.

“You brute. You rotten hound to hit a woman.”

“You put that where the monkey put the nuts, dearie. Didn't you know that when a woman hits me I always hit back?”

“I didn't hit you.”

“You damned near throttled me.”

“You deserved it. Oh, my God, I'd like to kill you.”

“Now sit down, duckie, and I'll give you a drop of Scotch to pull you together. And then you can tell me all about it.”

Julia looked round for a big chair into which she could conveniently sink.

“Christ, the place is like a pig-sty. Why the hell don't you get a charwoman in?”

With an angry gesture she swept the books on to the floor from an armchair, threw herself in it, and began to cry in earnest. He poured her out a stiff dose of whisky, added a drop of soda, and made her drink it.

“Now what's all this Tosca stuff about?”

“Michael's going to America.”

“Is he?”

She wrenched herself away from the arm he had round her shoulder. “How could you? How could you?”

“I had nothing to do with it.”

“That's a lie. I suppose you didn't even know that filthy American manager was in Middlepool. Of course it's your doing. You did it deliberately to separate us.”

“Oh, dearie, you're doing me an injustice. In point of fact I don't mind telling you that I said to him he could have anyone in the company he liked with the one exception of Michael Gosselyn.”

Julia did not see the look in Jimmie's eyes when he told her this, but if she had would have wondered why he was looking as pleased as if he had pulled off a very clever little trick.

“Even me?” she said.

“I knew he didn't want women. They've got plenty of their own. It's men they want who know how to wear their clothes and don't spit in the drawing-room.”

“Oh, Jimmie, don't let Michael go. I can't bear it.”

“How can I prevent it? His contract's up at the end of the season. It's a wonderful chance for him.”

“But I love him. I want him. Supposing he sees someone else in America. Supposing some American heiress falls in love with him.”

“If he doesn't love you any more than that I should have thought you'd be well rid of him.”

The remark revived Julia's fury.

“You rotten old eunuch, what do you know about love?”

“These women,” Jimmie sighed. “If you try to go to bed with them they say you're a dirty old man, and if you don't they say you're a rotten old eunuch.”

“Oh, you don't understand. He's so frightfully handsome, they'll fall for him like a row of ninepins, and poor lamb, he's so susceptible to flattery. Anything can happen in two years.”

“What's this about two years?”

“If he's a success he's to stay another year.”

“Well, don't worry your head about that. He'll be back at the end of the season and back for good. That manager only saw him in Candida. It's the only part he's half-way decent in. Take my word for it, it won't be long before they find out they've been sold a pup. He's going to be a flop.”

“What do you know about acting?”

“Everything.”

“I'd like to scratch your eyes out.”

“I warn you that if you attempt to touch me I shan't give you a little bit of a slap, I shall give you such a biff on the jaw that you won't be able to eat in comfort for a week.”

“By God, I believe you'd do it. Do you call yourself a gentleman?”

“Not even when I'm drunk.”

Julia giggled, and Jimmie felt the worst of the scene was over.

“Now you know just as well as I do that you can act him off his head. I tell you, you're going to be the greatest actress since Mrs. Kendal. What do you want to go and hamper yourself with a man who'll always be a mill-stone round your neck? You want to go into management; he'll want to play opposite you. He'll never be good enough, my dear.”

“He's got looks. I can carry him.”

“You've got a pretty good opinion of yourself, haven't you? But you're wrong. If you want to make a success you can't afford to have a leading man who's not up to the mark.”

“I don't care. I'd rather marry him and be a failure than be a success and married to somebody else.”

“Are you a virgin?”

Julia giggled again.

“I don't know that it's any business of yours, but in point of fact I am.”

“I thought you were. Well, unless it means something to you, why don't you go over to Paris with him for a fortnight when we close? He won't be sailing till August. It might get him out of your system.”

“Oh, he wouldn't. He's not that sort of man. You see, he's by way of being a gentleman.”

“Even the upper classes propagate their species.”

“You don't understand,” said Julia haughtily.

“I bet you don't either.”

Julia did not condescend to reply. She was really very unhappy.

“I can't live without him, I tell you. What am I to do with myself when he's away?”

“Stay on with me. I'll give you a contract for another year. I've got a lot of new parts I want to give you and I've got a juvenile in my eye who's a find. You'll be surprised how much easier you'll find it when you've got a chap opposite you who'll really give you something. You can have twelve pounds a week.”

Julia went up to him and stared into his eyes searchingly.

“Have you done all this to get me to stay on for another year? Have you broken my heart and ruined my whole life just to keep me in your rotten theatre?”

“I swear I haven't. I like you and I admire you. And we've done better business the last two years than we've ever done before. But damn it, I wouldn't play you a dirty trick like that.”

“You liar, you filthy liar.”

“I swear it's the truth.”

“Prove it then,” she said violently.

“How can I prove it? You know I'm decent really.”

“Give me fifteen pounds a week and I'll believe you.”

“Fifteen pounds a week? You know what our takings are. How can I? Oh, well, all right. But I shall have to pay three pounds out of my own pocket.”

“A fat lot I care.”

Chapter 6

After a fortnight of rehearsals, Michael was thrown out of the part for which he had been engaged, and for three or four weeks was left to kick his heels about till something else could be found for him. He opened in due course in a play that ran less than a month in New York. It was sent on the road; but languished and was withdrawn. After another wait he was given a part in a costume play where his good looks shone to such advantage that his indifferent acting was little noticed, and in this he finished the season. There was no talk of renewing his contract. Indeed the manager who had engaged him was caustic in his comments.

“Gee, I'd give something to get even with that fellow Langton, the son of a bitch,” he said. “He knew what he was doing all right when he landed me with that stick.”

Julia wrote to Michael constantly, pages and pages of love and gossip, while he answered once a week, four pages exactly in a neat, precise hand. He always ended up by sending her his best love and signing himself hers very affectionately, but the rest of his letter was more informative than passionate. Yet she awaited its coming in an agony of impatience and read it over and over again. Though he wrote cheerfully, saying little about the theatre except that the parts they gave him were rotten and the plays in which he was expected to act beneath contempt, news travels in the theatrical world, and Julia knew that he had not made good.

“I suppose it's beastly of me,” she thought, “but thank God, thank God.”

When he announced the date of his sailing she could not contain her joy. She got Jimmie so to arrange his programme that she might go and meet him at Liverpool.

“If the boat comes in late I shall probably stay the night,” she told Jimmie.

He smiled ironically.

“I suppose you think that in the excitement of homecoming you may work the trick.”

“What a beastly little man you are.”

“Come off it, dear. My advice to you is, get him a bit tight and then lock yourself in a room with him and tell him you won't let him out till he's made a dishonest woman of you.”

But when she was starting he came to the station with her. As she was getting into the carriage he took her hand and patted it.

“Feeling nervous, dear?”

“Oh, Jimmie dear, wild with happiness and sick with anxiety.”

“Well, good luck to you. And don't forget you're much too good for him. You're young and pretty and you're the greatest actress in England.”

When the train steamed out Jimmie went to the station bar and had a whisky and soda. “Lord, what fools these mortals be,” he sighed. But Julia stood up in the empty carriage and looked at herself in the glass.

“Mouth too large, face too puddingy, nose too fleshy. Thank God, I've got good eyes and good legs. Exquisite legs. I wonder if I've got too much make-up on. He doesn't like make-up off the stage. I look bloody without rouge. My eyelashes are all right. Damn it all, I don't look so bad.”

Uncertain till the last moment whether Jimmie would allow her to go Julia had not been able to let Michael know that she was meeting him. He was surprised and frankly delighted to see her. His beautiful eyes beamed with pleasure.

“You're more lovely than ever,” she said.

“Oh, don't be so silly,” he laughed, squeezing her arm affectionately. “You haven't got to go back till after dinner, have you?”

“I haven't got to go back till tomorrow. I've taken a couple of rooms at the Adelphi, so that we can have a real talk.”

“The Adelphi's a bit grand, isn't it?”

“Oh, well, you don't come back from America every day. Damn the expense.”

“Extravagant little thing, aren't you? I didn't know when we'd dock, so I told my people I'd wire when I was getting down to Cheltenham. I'll tell them I'll be coming along tomorrow.”

When they got to the hotel Michael came to Julia's room, at her suggestion, so that they could talk in peace and quiet. She sat on his knees, with her arm round his neck, her cheek against his.

“Oh, it's so good to be home again,” she sighed.

“You don't have to tell me that,” he said, not understanding that she referred to his arms and not to his arrival.

“D'you still like me?”

“Rather.”

She kissed him fondly.

“Oh, you don't know how I've missed you.”

“I was an awful flop in America,” he said. “I didn't tell you in my letters, because I thought it would only worry you. They thought me rotten.”

“Michael,” she cried, as though she could not believe him.

“The fact is, I suppose, I'm too English. They don't want me another year. I didn't think they did, but just as a matter of form I asked them if they were going to exercise their option and they said no, not at any price.”

Julia was silent. She looked deeply concerned, but her heart was beating with exultation.

“I honestly don't care, you know. I didn't like America. It's a smack in the eye of course, it's no good denying that, but the only thing is to grin and bear it. If you only knew the people one has to deal with! Why, compared with some of them, Jimmie Langton's a great gentleman. Even if they had wanted me to stay I should have refused.”

Though he put a brave face on it, Julia felt that he was deeply mortified. He must have had to put up with a good deal of unpleasantness. She hated him to have been made unhappy, but, oh, she was so relieved.

“What are you going to do now?” she asked quietly.

“Well, I shall go home for a bit and think things over. Then I shall go to London and see if I can't get a part.”

She knew that it was no good suggesting that he should come back to Middlepool. Jimmie Langton would not have him.

“You wouldn't like to come with me, I suppose?”

Julia could hardly believe her ears.

“Me? Darling, you know I'd go anywhere in the world with you.”

“Your contract's up at the end of this season, and if you want to get anywhere you've got to make a stab at London soon. I saved every bob I could in America, they all called me a tight-wad but I just let them talk, I've brought back between twelve and fifteen hundred pounds.”

“Michael, how on earth can you have done that?”

“I didn't give much away, you know,” he smiled happily. “Of course it's not enough to start management on, but it's enough to get married on, I mean we'd have something to fall back on if we didn't get parts right away or happened to be out of a job for a few months.”

It took Julia a second or two to understand what he meant.

“D'you mean to say, get married now?”

“Of course it's a risk, without anything in prospect, but one has to take a risk sometimes.”

Julia took his head in both her hands and pressed his lips with hers. Then she gave a sigh.

“Darling, you're wonderful and you're as beautiful as a Greek god, but you're the biggest damned fool I've ever known in my life.”

They went to a theatre that night and at supper drank champagne to celebrate their reunion and toast their future. When Michael accompanied her to her room she held up her face to his.

“D'you want me to say good-night to you in the passage? I'll just come in for a minute.”

“Better not, darling,” she said with quiet dignity.

She felt like a high-born damsel, with all the traditions of a great and ancient family to keep up; her purity was a pearl of great price; she also felt that she was making a wonderfully good impression: of course he was a great gentleman and “damn it all” it behoved her to be a great lady. She was so pleased with her performance that when she had got into her room and somewhat noisily locked the door, she paraded up and down bowing right and left graciously to her obsequious retainers. She stretched out her lily-white hand for the trembling old steward to kiss (as a baby he had often dandled her on his knee), and when he pressed it with his pallid lips she felt something fall upon it. A tear.

Chapter 7

The first year of their marriage would have been stormy except for Michael's placidity. It needed the excitement of getting a part or a first night, the gaiety of a party where he had drunk several glasses of champagne, to turn his practical mind to thoughts of love. No flattery, no allurements, could tempt him when he had an engagement next day for which he had to keep his brain clear or a round of golf for which he needed a steady eye. Julia made him frantic scenes. She was jealous of his friends at the Green Room Club, jealous of the games that took him away from her, and jealous of the men's luncheons he went to under the pretext that he must cultivate people who might be useful to them. It infuriated her that when she worked herself up into a passion of tears he should sit there quite calmly, with his hands crossed and a good-humoured smile on his handsome face, as though she were merely making herself ridiculous.

“You don't think I'm running after any other woman, do you?” he asked.

“How do I know? It's quite obvious that you don't care two straws for me.”

“You know you're the only woman in the world for me.”

“My God!”

“I don't know what you want.”

“I want love. I thought I'd married the handsomest man in England and I've married a tailor's dummy.”

“Don't be so silly. I'm just the ordinary normal Englishman. I'm not an Italian organ-grinder.”

She swept up and down the room. They had a small flat at Buckingham Gate and there was not much space, but she did her best. She threw up her hands to heaven.

“I might be squint-eyed and hump-backed. I might be fifty. Am I so unattractive as all that? It's so humiliating to have to beg for love. Misery, misery.”

“That was a good movement, dear. As if you were throwing a cricket ball. Remember that.”

She gave him a look of scorn.

“That's all you can think of. My heart is breaking, and you can talk of a movement that I made quite accidentally.”

But he saw by the expression of her face that she was registering it in her memory, and he knew that when the occasion arose she would make effective use of it.

“After all love isn't everything. It's all very well at its proper time and in its proper place. We had a lot of fun on our honeymoon, that's what a honeymoon's for, but now we've got to get down to work.”

They had been lucky. They had managed to get fairly good parts together in a play that had proved a success. Julia had one good acting scene in which she had brought down the house, and Michael's astonishing beauty had made a sensation. Michael with his gentlemanly push, with his breezy good-nature, had got them both a lot of publicity and their photographs appeared in the illustrated papers. They were asked to a number of parties and Michael, notwithstanding his thriftiness, did not hesitate to spend money on entertaining people who might be of service. Julia was impressed by his lavishness on these occasions. An actor-manager offered Julia the leading part in his next play, and though there was no part for Michael and she was anxious to refuse it, he would not let her. He said they could not afford to let sentiment stand in the way of business. He eventually got a part in a costume play.

They were both acting when the war broke out. To Julia's pride and anguish Michael enlisted at once, but with the help of his father, one of whose old brother officers was an important personage at the War Office, he very soon got a commission. When he went out to France Julia bitterly regretted the reproaches she had so often heaped upon him, and made up her mind that if he were killed she would commit suicide. She wanted to become a nurse so that she could go out to France too and at least be on the same soil as he, but he made her understand that patriotism demanded that she should go on acting, and she could not resist what might very well be his dying request. Michael thoroughly enjoyed the war. He was popular in the regimental mess, and the officers of the old army accepted him almost at once, even though he was an actor, as one of themselves. It was as though the family of soldiers from which he was born had set a seal on him so that he fell instinctively into the manner and way of thinking of the professional soldier. He had tact and a pleasant manner, and he knew how to pull strings adroitly; it was inevitable that he should get on the staff of some general. He showed himself possessed of considerable organizing capacity and the last three years of the war he passed at G.H.Q. He ended it as a major, with the Military Cross and the Legion of Honour.

Meanwhile Julia had been playing a succession of important parts and was recognized as the best of the younger actresses. Throughout the war the theatre was very prosperous, and she profited by being seen in plays that had long runs. Salaries went up, and with Michael to advise her she was able to extort eighty pounds a week from reluctant managers. Michael came over to England on his leaves and Julia was divinely happy. Though he was in no more danger than if he had been sheep-farming in New Zealand, she acted as though the brief periods he spent with her were the last days the doomed man would ever enjoy on earth. She treated him as though he had just come from the horror of the trenches and was tender, considerate, and unexacting.

It was just before the end of the war that she fell out of love with him.

She was pregnant at the time. Michael had judged it imprudent to have a baby just then, but she was nearly thirty and thought that if they were going to have one at all they ought to delay no longer; she was so well-established on the stage that she could afford not to appear for a few months, and with the possibility that Michael might be killed at any moment—it was true he said he was as safe as a house, he only said that to reassure her, and even generals were killed sometimes—if she was to go on living she must have a child by him. The baby was expected at the end of the year.

She looked forward to Michael's next leave as she had never done before. She was feeling very well, but she had a great yearning to feel his arms around her, she felt a little lost, a little helpless, and she wanted his protective strength. He came, looking wonderfully handsome in his well-cut uniform, with the red tabs and the crown on his shoulder-straps. He had filled out a good deal as the result of the hardships of G.H.Q. and his skin was tanned. With his close-cropped hair, breezy manner and military carriage he looked every inch a soldier. He was in great spirits, not only because he was home for a few days, but because the end of the war was in sight. He meant to get out of the army as quickly as possible. What was the good of having a bit of influence if you didn't use it? So many young men had left the stage, either from patriotism or because life was made intolerable for them by the patriotic who stayed at home, and finally owing to conscription, that leading parts had been in the hands either of people who were inapt for military service or those who had been so badly wounded that they had got their discharge. There was a wonderful opening, and Michael saw that if he were available quickly he could get his choice of parts. When he had recalled himself to the recollection of the public they could look about for a theatre, and with the reputation Julia had now acquired it would be safe to start in management.

They talked late into the night and then they went to bed. She cuddled up to him voluptuously and he put his arms round her. After three months of abstinence he was amorous.

“You're the most wonderful little wife,” he whispered.

He pressed his mouth on hers. She was filled on a sudden with a faint disgust. She had to resist an inclination to push him away. Before, to her passionate nostrils his body, his young beautiful body, had seemed to have a perfume of flowers and honey, and this had been one of the things that had most enchained her to him, but now in some strange way it had left him. She realized that he no longer smelt like a youth, he smelt like a man. She felt a little sick. She could not respond to his ardour, she was eager that he should get his desire satisfied quickly, turn over on his side, and go to sleep. For long she lay awake. She was dismayed. Her heart sank because she knew she had lost something that was infinitely precious to her, and pitying herself she was inclined to cry; but at the same time she was filled with a sense of triumph, it seemed a revenge that she enjoyed for the unhappiness he had caused her; she was free of the bondage in which her senses had held her to him and she exulted. Now she could deal with him on equal terms. She stretched her legs out in bed and sighed with relief.

“By God, it's grand to be one's own mistress.”

They had breakfast in their room, Julia in bed and Michael seated at a little table by her side. She looked at him while he read the paper. Was it possible that three months had made so much difference in him, or was it merely that for years she had still seen him with the eyes that had seen him when he came on the stage to rehearse at Middlepool in the glorious beauty of his youth and she had been stricken as with a mortal sickness? He was wonderfully handsome still, after all he was only thirty-six, but he was not a boy any more; with his close-cropped hair and weather-beaten skin, little lines beginning to mark the smoothness of his forehead and to show under his eyes, he was definitely a man. He had lost his coltish grace and his movements were set. Each difference was very small, but taken altogether they amounted, in her shrewd, calculating eyes, to all the difference in the world. He was a middle-aged man.

They still lived in the small flat that they had taken when first they came to London. Though Julia had been for some time earning a good income it had not seemed worth while to move while Michael was on active service, but now that a baby was coming the flat was obviously too small. Julia had found a house in Regent's Park that she liked very much. She wanted to be settled down in good time for her confinement.

The house faced the gardens. Above the drawing-room floor were two bedrooms and above these two rooms that could be made into a day and a night nursery. Michael was pleased with everything; even the price seemed to him reasonable. Julia had, during the last four years, been earning so much more money than he that she had offered to furnish the house herself. They stood in one of the bedrooms.

“I can make do with a good deal of what we've got for my bedroom,” she said. “I'll get you a nice suite at Maple's.”

“I wouldn't go to much expense,” he smiled. “I don't suppose I shall use it much, you know.”

He liked to share a bed with her. Though not passionate he was affectionate, and he had an animal desire to feel her body against his. For long it had been her greatest comfort. The thought now filled her with irritation.

“Oh, I don't think there should be any more nonsense till after the baby's born. Until all that's over and done with I'm going to make you sleep by yourself.”

“I hadn't thought of that. If you think it's better for the kid…”

Chapter 8

Michael got himself demobbed the moment the war was finished and stepped straight into a part. He returned to the stage a much better actor than he left it. The breeziness he had acquired in the army was effective. He was a well set-up, normal, high-spirited fellow, with a ready smile and a hearty laugh. He was well-suited to drawing-room comedy. His light voice gave a peculiar effect to a flippant line, and though he never managed to make love convincingly he could carry off a chaffing love scene, making a proposal as if it were rather a joke, or a declaration as though he were laughing at himself, in a manner that the audience found engaging. He never attempted to play anyone but himself. He specialized in men about town, gentlemanly gamblers, guardsmen and young scamps with a good side to them. Managers liked him. He worked hard and was amenable to direction. So long as he could get work he didn't mind much what sort of part it was. He stuck out for the salary he thought he was worth, but if he couldn't get it was prepared to take less rather than be idle.

He was making his plans carefully. During the winter that followed the end of the war there was an epidemic of influenza. His father and mother died. He inherited nearly four thousand pounds, and this with his own savings and Julia's brought up their joint capital to seven thousand. But the rent of theatres had gone up enormously, the salaries of actors and the wages of stage-hands had increased, so that the expense of running a theatre was very much greater than it had been before the war. A sum that would then have been amply sufficient to start management on was now inadequate. The only thing was to find some rich man to go in with them so that a failure or two to begin with would not drive them from the field. It was said that you could always find a mug in the city to write a fat cheque for the production of a play, but when you came down to business you discovered that the main condition was that the leading part should be played by some pretty lady in whom he was interested. Years before, Michael and Julia had often joked about the rich old woman who would fall in love with him and set him up in management. He had long since learnt that no rich old woman was to be found to set up in management a young actor whose wife was an actress to whom he was perfectly faithful. In the end the money was found by a rich woman, and not an old one either, but who was interested not in him but in Julia.

Mrs. de Vries was a widow. She was a short stout woman with a fine Jewish nose and fine Jewish eyes, a great deal of energy, a manner at once effusiveand timid, and a somewhat virile air. She had a passion for the stage. When Julia and Michael had decided to try their luck in London Jimmie Langton, to whose rescue she had sometimes come when it looked as though he would be forced to close his repertory theatre, had written to her asking her to do what she could for them. She had seen Julia act in Middlepool. She gave parties so that the young actors might get to know managers, and asked them to stay at her grand house near Guildford, where they enjoyed a luxury they had never dreamt of. She did not much like Michael. Julia accepted the flowers with which Dolly de Vries filled her flat and her dressing-room, she was properly delighted with the presents she gave her, bags, vanity cases, strings of beads in semiprecious stones, brooches; but appeared to be unconscious that Dolly's generosity was due to anything but admiration for her talent. When Michael went away to the war Dolly pressed her to come and live in her house in Montagu Square, but Julia, with protestations of extravagant gratitude, refused in such a way that Dolly, with a sigh and a tear, could only admire her the more. When Roger was born Julia asked her to be his godmother.

For some time Michael had been turning over in his mind the possibility that Dolly de Vries might put up the money they needed, but he was shrewd enough to know that while she might do it for Julia she would not do it for him. Julia refused to approach her.

“She's already been so kind to us I really couldn't ask her, and it would be so humiliating if she refused.”

“It's a good gamble, and even if she lost the money she wouldn't feel it. I'm quite sure you could get round her if you tried.”

Julia was pretty sure she could too. Michael was very simpleminded in some ways; she did not feel called upon to point out to him the obvious facts.

But he was not a man who let a thing drop when he had set his mind to it. They were going to Guildford to spend the weekend with Dolly, and were driving down after the Saturday night's performance in the new car that Julia had given Michael for his birthday. It was a warm beautiful night. Michael had bought options, though it wrung his heart to write the cheques, on three plays that they both liked, and he had heard of a theatre that they could get on reasonable terms. Everything was ready for the venture except the capital. He urged Julia to seize the opportunity that the weekend presented.

“Ask her yourself then,” said Julia impatiently. “I tell you, I'm not going to.”

“She wouldn't do it for me. You can twist her round your little finger.”

“We know a thing or two about financing plays now. People finance plays for two reasons, either because they want notoriety, or because they're in love with someone. A lot of people talk about art, but you don't often find them paying out hard cash unless they're going to get something out of it for themselves.”

“Well, we'll give Dolly all the notoriety she wants.”

“That doesn't happen to be what she's after.”

“What do you mean?”

“Can't you guess?”

Light dawned on him, and he was so surprised that he slowed down. Was it possible that what Julia suspected was true? He had never even thought that Dolly liked him much, and as for supposing she was in love with him—why, the notion had never crossed his mind. Of course Julia had sharp eyes, not much got by her, but she was a jealous little thing, she was always thinking women were making a dead set at him. It was true that Dolly had given him a pair of cuff links at Christmas, but he thought that was only so that he shouldn't feel left out in the cold because she had given Julia a brooch that much have cost at least two hundred pounds. That might be only her cunning. Well, he could honestly say he'd never done a thing to make her think there was anything doing. Julia giggled.

“No, darling, it's not you she's in love with.”

It was disconcerting the way Julia knew what he was thinking. You couldn't hide a thing from that woman.

“Then why did you put the idea into my head? I wish to goodness you'd express yourself so that a fellow can understand.”

Julia did.

“I never heard such nonsense,” he cried. “What a filthy mind you've got, Julia!”

“Come off it, dear.”

“I don't believe there's a word of truth in it. After all I've got eyes in my head. Do you mean to say I shouldn't have noticed it?” He was more irritable than she had ever known him. “And even if it were true I suppose you can take care of yourself. It's a chance in a thousand, and I think it would be madness not to take it.”

“Claudio and Isabella in Measure for Measure.”

“That's a rotten thing to say, Julia. God damn it, I am a gentleman.”

“‘Nemo me impune lacessit.’”

They drove the rest of the journey in stormy silence. Mrs. de Vries was waiting up for them.

“I didn't want to go to bed till I'd seen you,” she said as she folded Julia in her arms and kissed her on both cheeks. She gave Michael a brisk handshake.

Julia spent a happy morning in bed reading the Sunday papers. She read first the theatrical news, then the gossip columns, after that the woman's pages, and finally cast an eye over the headlines of the world's news. The book reviews she ignored; she could never understand why so much space was wasted on them. Michael, who had the room next hers, had come in to say good-morning, and then gone out into the garden. Presently there was a timid little knock at her door and Dolly came in. Her great black eyes were shining. She sat on the bed and took Julia's hand.

“Darling, I've been talking to Michael. I'm going to put up the money to start you in management.”

Julia's heart gave a sudden beat.

“Oh, you mustn't. Michael shouldn't have asked you. I won't have it. You've been far, far too kind to us already.”

Dolly leant over and kissed Julia on the lips. Her voice was lower than usual and there was a little tremor in it.

“Oh, my love, don't you know there isn't anything in the world I wouldn't do for you? It'll be so wonderful; it'll bring us so close together and I shall be so proud of you.”

They heard Michael come whistling along the passage, and when he came into the room Dolly turned to him with her great eyes misty with tears.

“I've just told her.”

He was brimming over with excitement.

“What a grand woman!” He sat down on the other side of the bed and took Julia's disengaged hand. “What d'you say, Julia?”

She gave him a little reflective look.

“‘Vous l'avez voulu, Georges Dandin.’”

“What's that?”

“Molière.”

As soon as the deed of partnership had been signed and Michael had got his theatre booked for the autumn he engaged a publicity agent. Paragraphs were sent to the papers announcing the new venture and Michael and the publicity agent prepared interviews for him and Julia to give to the Press. Photographs of them, singly and together, with and without Roger, appeared in the weeklies. The domestic note was worked for all it was worth. They could not quite make up their minds which of the three plays they had it would be best to start with. Then one afternoon when Julia was sitting in her bedroom reading a novel, Michael came in with a manuscript in his hand.

“Look here, I want you to read this play at once. It's just come in from an agent. I think it's a knock-out. Only we've got to give an answer right away.”

Julia put down her novel.

“I'll read it now.”

“I shall be downstairs. Let me know when you've finished and I'll come up and talk it over with you. It's got a wonderful part for you.”

Julia read quickly, skimming over the scenes in which she was not concerned, but the principal woman's part, the part of course she would play, with concentration. When she had turned the last page she rang the bell and asked her maid (who was also her dresser) to tell Michael she was ready for him.

“Well, what d'you think?”

“The play's all right. I don't see how it can fail to be a success.”

He caught something doubtful in her tone.

“What's wrong then? The part's wonderful. I mean, it's the sort of thing that you can do better than anyone in the world. There's a lot of comedy and all the emotion you want.”

“It's a wonderful part, I know that; it's the man's part.”

“Well, that's a damned good part too.”

“I know; but he's fifty, and if you make him younger you take all the point out of the play. You don't want to take the part of a middle-aged man.”

“But I wasn't thinking of playing that. There's only one man for that. Monte Vernon. And we can get him. I'll play George.”

“But that's a tiny part. You can't play that.”

“Why not?”

“But I thought the point of going into management was that we should both play leads.”

“Oh, I don't care a hang about that. As long as we can find plays with star parts for you I don't matter. Perhaps in the next play there'll be a good part for me too.”

Julia leant back in her chair and the ready tears filled her eyes and ran down her cheeks.

“Oh, what a beast I am.”

He smiled, and his smile was as charming as ever. He came over to her and kneeling by her side put his arms round her.

“Lor Lumme, what's the matter with the old lady now?”

When she looked at him now she wondered what there was in him that had ever aroused in her such a frenzy of passion. The thought of having sexual relations with him nauseated her. Fortunately he found himself very comfortable in the bedroom she had furnished for him. He was not a man to whom sex was important, and he was relieved when he discovered that Julia no longer made any demands on him. He thought with satisfaction that the birth of the baby had calmed her down, he was bound to say that he had thought it might, and he was only sorry they had not had one before. When he had two or three times,more out of amiability than out of desire, suggested that they should resume marital relations and she had made excuses, either that she was tired, not very well, or had two performances next day, to say nothing of a fitting in the morning, he accepted the situation with equanimity. Julia was much easier to get on with, she never made scenes any more, and he was happier than he had ever been before. It was a damned satisfactory marriage he had made, and when he looked at other people's marriages he couldn't help seeing he was one of the lucky ones. Julia was a damned good sort and clever, as clever as a bagful of monkeys; you could talk to her about anything in the world. The best companion a chap ever had, my boy. He didn't mind saying this, he'd rather spend a day alone with her than play a round of golf.

Julia was surprised to discover in herself a strange feeling of pity for him because she no longer loved him. She was a kindly woman, and she realized that it would be a bitter blow to his pride if he ever had an inkling how little he meant to her. She continued to flatter him. She noticed that for long now he had come to listen complacently to her praise of his exquisite nose and beautiful eyes. She got a little private amusement by seeing how much he could swallow. She laid it on with a trowel. But now she looked more often at his straight thin-lipped mouth. It grew meaner as he grew older, and by the time he was an old man it would be no more than a cold hard line. His thrift, which in the early days had seemed an amusing, rather touching trait, now revolted her. When people were in trouble, and on the stage they too often are, they got sympathy and kind friendly words from Michael, but very little cash. He looked upon himself as devilish generous when he parted with a guinea, and a five-pound note was to him the extreme of lavishness. He had soon discovered that Julia ran the house extravagantly, and insisting that he wanted to save her trouble took the matter in his own hands. After that nothing was wasted. Every penny was accountedfor. Julia wondered why servants stayed with them. They did because Michael was so nice to them. With his hearty, jolly, affable manner he made them anxious to please him, and the cook shared his satisfaction when she had found a butcher from whom they could get meat a penny a pound cheaper than elsewhere. Julia could not but laugh when she thought how strangely his passion for economy contrasted with the devil-may-care, extravagant creatures he portrayed so well on the stage. She had often thought that he was incapable of a generous impulse; and now, as though it were the most natural thing in the world, he was prepared to stand aside so that she might have her chance. She was too deeply moved to speak. She reproached herself bitterly for all the unkind things she had for so long been thinking of him.

Chapter 9

They put on the play, and it was a success. After that they continued to produce plays year after year. Because Michael ran the theatre with the method and thrift with which he ran his home they lost little over the failures, which of course they sometimes had, and made every possible penny out of their successes. Michael flattered himself that there was not a management in London where less money was spent on the productions. He exercised great ingenuity in disguising old sets so that they looked new, and by ringing the changes on the furniture that he gradually collected in the store-room saved the expense of hiring. They gained the reputation of being an enterprising management because Michael, in order not to pay the high royalties of well-known authors, was always willing to give an unknown one a trial. He sought out actors who had never been given a chance and whose salaries were small. He thus made some very profitable discoveries.

When they had been in management for three years they were sufficiently well-established for Michael to be able to borrow from the bank enough money to buy the lease of a theatre that had just been built. After much discussion they decided to call it the Siddons Theatre. They opened with a failure and this was succeeded by another. Julia was frightened and discouraged. She thought that the theatre was unlucky and that the public were getting sick of her. It was then that Michael showed himself at his best. He was unperturbed.

“In this business you have to take the rough with the smooth. You're the best actress in England. There are only three people who bring money into the theatre regardless of the play, and you're one of them. We've had a couple of duds. The next play's bound to be all right and then we shall get back all we've lost and a packet into the bargain.”

As soon as Michael had felt himself safe he had tried to buy Dolly de Vries out, but she would not listen to his persuasion and was indifferent to his coldness. For once his cunning found its match. Dolly saw no reason to sell out an investment that seemed sound, and her half share in the partnership kept her in close touch with Julia. But now with great courage he made another effort to get rid of her. Dolly indignantly refused to desert them when they were in difficulties, and he gave it up as a bad job. He consoled himself by thinking that Dolly might leave Roger, her godson, a great deal of money. She had no one belonging to her but nephews in South Africa, and you could not look at her without suspecting that she had a high blood pressure. Meanwhile it was convenient to have the house near Guildford to go to whenever they wished. It saved the expense of having a country house of their own. The third play was a winner, and Michael did not hesitate to point out how right he had been. He spoke as though he was directly responsible for its success. Julia could almost have wished that it had failed like the others in order to take him down a peg or two. For his conceit was outrageous. Of course you had to admit that he had a sort of cleverness, shrewdness rather, but he was not nearly so clever as he thought himself. There was nothing in which he did not think that he knew better than anybody else.

As time went on he began to act less frequently. He found himself much more interested in management.

“I want to run my theatre in as businesslike a way as a city office,” he said.

And he felt that he could more profitably spend his evenings, when Julia was acting, by going to outlying theatres and trying to find talent. He kept a little book in which he made a note for every actor who seemed to show promise. Then he had taken to directing. It had always grizzled him that directors should ask so much money for rehearsing a play, and of late some of them had even insisted on a percentage on the gross. At last an occasion came when the two directors Julia liked best were engaged and the only other one she trusted was acting and thus could not give them all his time.

“I've got a good mind to have a shot at it myself,” said Michael.

Julia was doubtful. He had no fantasy and his ideas were commonplace. She was not sure that he would have authority over the cast. But the only available director demanded a fee that they both thought exorbitant and there was nothing left but to let Michael try. He made a much better job of it than Julia expected. He was thorough; he worked hard. Julia, strangely enough, felt that he was getting more out of her than any other director had done. He knew what she was capable of, and, familiar with her every inflection, every glance of her wonderful eyes, every graceful movement of her body, he was able to give hersuggestions out of which she managed to build up the best performance of her career. With the cast he was at once conciliatory and exacting. When tempers were frayed his good-humour, his real kindliness, smoothed things over. After that there was no question but that he should continue to direct their plays. Authors liked him because, being unimaginative, he was forced to let the plays speak for themselves and often not being quite sure what they meant he was obliged to listen to them.

Julia was now a rich woman. She could not but admit that Michael was as careful of her money as of his own. He watched her investments and was as pleased when he could sell stocks at a profit on her account as if he had made the money for himself. He put her down for a very large salary, and was proud to be able to say that she was the most highly-paid actress in London, but when he himself acted he never put himself down for a higher salary than he thought the part was worth. When he directed a play he put down on the expense account the fee that a director of the second rank would have received. They shared the expenses of the house and the cost of Roger's education. Roger had been entered for Eton within a week of his birth. It was impossible to deny that Michael was scrupulously fair and honest. When Julia realized how much richer she was than he she wanted to pay all these expenses herself.

“There's no reason why you should,” said Michael. “As long as I can pay my whack I'll pay it. You earn more than I do because you're worth more. I put you down for a good salary because you draw it.”

No one could do other than admire the self-abnegation with which he sacrificed himself for her sake. Any ambition he may have had for himself he had abandoned in order to foster her career. Even Dolly, who did not like him, acknowledged his unselfishness. A sort of modesty had always prevented Julia from discussing him with Dolly, but Dolly, with her shrewdness, had long seen how intensely Michael exasperated his wife, and now and then took the trouble to point out how useful he was to her. Everybody praised him. A perfect husband. It seemed to her that none but she knew what it was like to live with a man who was such a monster of vanity. His complacency when he had beaten an opponent at golf or got the better of someone in a business deal was infuriating. He gloried in his artfulness. He was a bore, a crashing bore. He liked to tell Julia everything he did and every scheme that passed through his head; it had been charming when merely to have him with her was a delight, but for years she had found his prosiness intolerable. He could describe nothing without circumstantial detail. Nor was he only vain of his business acumen; with advancing years he had become outrageously vain of his person. As a youth he had taken his beauty for granted: now he began to pay more attention to it and spared no pains to keep what was left of it. It became an obsession. He devoted anxious care to his figure. He never ate a fattening thing and never forgot his exercises. He consulted hair specialists when he thought his hair was thinning, and Julia was convinced that had it been possible to get the operation done secretly he would have had his face lifted. He had got into the way of sitting with his chin slightly thrust out so that the wrinkles in his neck should not show and he held himself with an arched back to keep his belly from sagging. He could not pass a mirror without looking into it. He hankered for compliments and beamed with delight when he had managed to extract one. They were food and drink to him. Julia laughed bitterly when she remembered that it was she who had accustomed him to them. For years she had told him how beautiful he was and now he could not live without flattery. It was the only chink in his armour. An actress out of a job had only to tell him to his face that he was too handsome to be true for him to think that she might do for a part he had in mind. For years, so far as Julia knew, Michael had not bothered with women, but when he reached the middle forties he began to have little flirtations. Julia suspected that nothing much came of them. He was prudent, and all he wanted was admiration. She had heard that when women became pressing he used her as a pretext to get rid of them. Either he couldn't risk doing anything to hurt her, or she was jealous or suspicious and it seemed better that the friendship should cease.

“God knows what they see in him,” Julia exclaimed to the empty room.

She took up half-a-dozen of his later photographs at random and looked at them carefully one by one. She shrugged her shoulders.

“Well, I suppose I can't blame them. I fell in love with him too. Of course he was better-looking in those days.”

It made Julia a little sad to think how much she had loved him. Because her love had died she felt that life had cheated her. She sighed.

“And my back's aching,” she said.

Chapter 10

There was a knock at the door.

“Come in,” said Julia.

Evie entered.

“Aren't you going to bed today, Miss Lambert?” She saw Julia sitting on the floor surrounded by masses of photographs. “Whatever are you doing?”

“Dreaming.” She took up two of the photographs. “Look here upon this picture, and on this.”

One was of Michael as Mercutio in all the radiant beauty of his youth and the other of Michael in the last part he had played, in a white topper and a morning coat, with a pair of field glasses slung over his shoulder. He looked unbelievably self-satisfied.

Evie sniffed.

“Oh, well, it's no good crying over spilt milk.”

“I've been thinking of the past and I'm as blue as the devil.”

“I don't wonder. When you start thinking of the past it means you ain't got no future, don't it?”

“You shut your trap, you old cow,” said Julia, who could be very vulgar when she chose.

“Come on now, or you'll be fit for nothing tonight. I'll clear up all this mess.”

Evie was Julia's dresser and maid. She had come to her first at Middlepool and had accompanied her to London. She was a cockney, a thin, raddled, angular woman, with red hair which was always untidy and looked as if it much needed washing; two of her front teeth were missing but notwithstanding Julia's offer, repeated for years, to provide her with new ones she would not have them replaced.

“For the little I eat I've got all the teeth I want. It'd only fidget me to 'ave a lot of elephant's tusks in me mouth.”

Michael had long wanted Julia at least to get a maid whose appearance was more suitable to their position, and he had tried to persuade Evie that the work was too much for her, but Evie would not hear of it.

“You can say what you like, Mr. Gosselyn, but no one's going to maid Miss Lambert as long as I've got me 'ealth and strength.”

“We're all getting on, you know, Evie. We're not so young as we were.”

Evie drew her forefinger across the base of her nostrils and sniffed.

“As long as Miss Lambert's young enough to play women of twenty-five, I'm young enough to dress 'er. And maid 'er.” Evie gave him a sharp look. “An' what d'you want to pay two lots of wages for, when you can get the work done for one?”

Michael chuckled in his good-humoured way.

“There's something in that, Evie dear.”

She bustled Julia upstairs. When she had no matinée Julia went to bed for a couple of hours in the afternoon and then had a light massage. She undressed now and slipped between the sheets.

“Damn, my hot water bottle's nearly stone cold.”

She looked at the clock on the chimney-piece. It was no wonder. It must have been there an hour. She had no notion that she had stayed so long in Michael's room, looking at those photographs and idly thinking of the past.

“Forty-six. Forty-six. Forty-six. I shall retire when I'm sixty. At fifty-eight South Africa and Australia. Michael says we can clean up there. Twenty thousand pounds. I can play all my old parts. Of course even at sixty I could play women of forty-five. But what about parts? Those bloody dramatists.”

Trying to remember any plays in which there was a first-rate part for a woman of five-and-forty she fell asleep. She slept soundly till Evie came to awake her because the masseuse was there. Evie brought her the evening paper, and Julia, stripped, while the masseuse rubbed her long slim legs and her belly, putting on her spectacles, read the same theatrical intelligence she had read that morning, the gossip column and the woman's page. Presently Michael came in and sat on her bed. He often came at that hour to have a little chat with her.

“Well, what was his name?” asked Julia.

“Whose name?”

“The boy who came to lunch?”

“I haven't a notion. I drove him back to the theatre. I never gave him another thought.”

Miss Phillips, the masseuse, liked Michael. You knew where you were with him. He always said the same things and you knew exactly what to answer. No side to him. And terribly good-looking. My word.

“Well, Miss Phillips, fat coming off nicely?”

“Oh, Mr. Gosselyn, there's not an ounce of fat on Miss Lambert. I think it's wonderful the way she keeps her figure.”

“Pity I can't have you to massage me, Miss Phillips. You might be able to do something about mine.”

“How you talk, Mr. Gosselyn. Why, you've got the figure of a boy of twenty. I don't know how you do it, upon my word I don't.”

“Plain living and high thinking, Miss Phillips.”

Julia was paying no attention to what they said, but Miss Phillips's reply reached her.

“Of course there's nothing like massage, I always say that, but you've got to be careful of your diet. That there's no doubt about at all.”

“Diet!” she thought. “When I'm sixty I shall let myself go. I shall eat all the bread and butter I like. I'll have hot rolls for breakfast, I'll have potatoes for lunch and potatoes for dinner. And beer. God, how I like beer. Pea soup and tomato soup; treacle pudding and cherry tart. Cream, cream, cream. And so help me God, I'll never eat spinach again as long as I live.”

When the massage was finished Evie brought her a cup of tea, a slice of ham from which the fat had been cut, and some dry toast. Julia got up, dressed, and went down with Michael to the theatre. She liked to be there an hour before the curtain rang up. Michael went on to dine at his club. Evie had preceded her in a cab and when she got into her dressing-room everything was ready for her. She undressed once more and put on a dressing-gown. As she sat down at her dressing-table to make up she noticed some fresh flowers in a vase.

“Hulloa, who sent them? Mrs. de Vries?”

Dolly always sent her a huge basket on her first nights, and on the hundredth night, and the two hundredth if there was one, and in between, whenever she ordered flowers for her own house, had some sent to Julia.

“No, miss.”

“Lord Charles?”

Lord Charles Tamerley was the oldest and the most constant of Julia's admirers, and when he passed a florist's he was very apt to drop in and order some roses for her.

“Here's the card,” said Evie.

Julia looked at it. Mr. Thomas Fennell. Tavistock Square.

“What a place to live. Who the hell d'you suppose he is, Evie?”

“Some feller knocked all of a heap by your fatal beauty, I expect.”

“They must have cost all of a pound. Tavistock Square doesn't look very prosperous to me. For all you know he may have gone without his dinner for a week to buy them.”

“I don't think.”

Julia plastered her face with grease paint.

“You're so damned unromantic, Evie. Just because I'm not a chorus girl you can't understand why anyone should send me flowers. And God knows, I've got better legs than most of them.”

“You and your legs,” said Evie.

“Well, I don't mind telling you I think it's a bit of all right having an unknown young man sending me flowers at my time of life. I mean it just shows you.”

“If he saw you now 'e wouldn't, not if I know anything about men.”

“Go to hell,” said Julia.

But when she was made up to her satisfaction, and Evie had put on her stockings and her shoes, having a few minutes still to spare she sat down at her desk and in her straggling bold hand wrote to Mr. Thomas Fennell a gushing note of thanks for his beautiful flowers. She was naturally polite and it was besides a principle with her to answer all fan letters. That was how she kept in touch with her public. Having addressed the envelope she threw the card in the waste-paper basket and was ready to slip into the first-act dress. The call-boy came round knocking at the dressing-room doors.

“Beginners, please.”

Those words, though heaven only knew how often she had heard them, still gave her a thrill. They braced her like a tonic. Life acquired significance. She was about to step from the world of make-believe into the world of reality.

Chapter 11

Next day Julia had lunch with Charles Tamerley. His father, the Marquess of Dennorant, had married an heiress and he had inherited a considerable fortune. Julia often went to the lunch parties he was fond of giving at his house in Hill Street. At the bottom of her heart she had a profound contempt for the great ladies and the noble lords she met there, because she was a working woman and an artist, but she knew the connection was useful. It enabled them tohave first nights at the Siddons which the papers described as brilliant, and when she was photographed at weekend parties among a number of aristocratic persons she knew that it was good publicity. There were one or two leading ladies, younger than she, who did not like her any better because she called at least two duchesses by their first names. This caused her no regret. Julia was not a brilliant conversationalist, but her eyes were so bright, her manner so intelligent, that once she had learnt the language of society she passed for a very amusing woman. She had a great gift of mimicry, which ordinarily she kept in check thinking it was bad for her acting, but in these circles she turned it to good account and by means of it acquired the reputation of a wit. She was pleased that they liked her, these smart, idle women, but she laughed at them up her sleeve because they were dazzled by her glamour. She wondered what they would think if they really knew how unromantic the life of a successful actress was, the hard work it entailed, the constant care one had to take of oneself and the regular, monotonous habits which were essential. But she good-naturedly offered them advice on make-up and let them copy her clothes. She was always beautifully dressed. Even Michael, fondly thinking she got her clothes for nothing, did not know how much she really spent on them.

Morally she had the best of both worlds. Everyone knew that her marriage with Michael was exemplary. She was a pattern of conjugal fidelity. At the same time many people in that particular set were convinced that she was Charles Tamerley's mistress. It was an affair that was supposed to have been going on so long that it had acquired respectability, and tolerant hostesses when they were asked to the same house for a weekend gave them adjoining rooms. This belief had been started by Lady Charles, from whom Charles Tamerley had been long separated, and in point of fact there was not a word of truth in it. The only foundation for it was that Charles had been madly in love with her for twenty years, and it was certainly on Julia's account that the Tamerleys, who had never got on very well, agreed to separate. It was indeed Lady Charles who had first brought Julia and Charles together. They happened, all three, to be lunching at Dolly de Vries' when Julia, a young actress, had made her first great success in London. It was a large party and she was being made much of. Lady Charles, a woman of over thirty then, who had the reputation of being a beauty, though except for her eyes she had not a good feature, but by a sort of brazen audacity managed to produce an effective appearance, leant across the table with a gracious smile.

“Oh, Miss Lambert, I think I used to know your father in Jersey. He was a doctor, wasn't he? He used to come to our house quite often.”

Julia felt a slight sickness in the pit of her stomach; she remembered now who Lady Charles was before she married, and she saw the trap that was being set for her. She gave a rippling laugh.

“Not at all,” she answered. “He was a vet. He used to go to your house to deliver the bitches. The house was full of them.”

Lady Charles for a moment did not quite know what to say.

“My mother was very fond of dogs,” she answered.

Julia was glad that Michael was not there. Poor lamb, he would have been terribly mortified. He always referred to her father as Dr Lambert, pronouncing it as though it were a French name, and when soon after the war he died and her mother went to live with her widowed sister at St. Malo he began to speak of her as Madame de Lambert. At the beginning of her career Julia had been somewhat sensitive on the point, but when once she was established as a great actress she changed her mind. She was inclined, especially among the great, to insist on the fact that her father had been a vet. She could not quite have explained why, but she felt that by so doing she put them in their place.

But Charles Tamerley knew that his wife had deliberately tried to humiliate the young woman, and angered, went out of his way to be nice to her. He asked her if he might be allowed to call and brought her some beautiful flowers.

He was then a man of nearly forty, with a small head on an elegant body, not very good-looking but of distinguished appearance. He looked very well-bred, which indeed he was, and he had exquisite manners. He was an amateur of the arts. He bought modem pictures and collected old furniture. He was a lover of music and exceedingly well-read. At first it amused him to go to the tiny flat off the Buckingham Palace Road in which these two young actors lived. He saw that they were poor and it excited him to get into touch with what he fondly thought was Bohemia. He came several times and he thought it quite an adventure when they asked him to have a lunch with them which was cooked and served by a scarecrow of a woman whom they called Evie. This was life. He did not pay much attention to Michael who seemed to him, notwithstanding his too-obvious beauty, a somewhat ordinary young man, but he was taken by Julia. She had a warmth, a force of character, and a bubbling vitality which were outside his experience. He went to see her act several times and compared her performance with his recollections of the great foreign actresses. It seemed to him that she had in her something quite individual. Her magnetism was incontestable. It gave him quite a thrill to realize on a sudden that she had genius.

“Another Siddons perhaps. A greater Ellen Terry.”

In those days Julia did not think it necessary to go to bed in the afternoons, she was as strong as a horse and never tired, so he used often to take her for walks in the Park. She felt that he wanted her to be a child of nature. That suited her very well. It was no effort for her to be ingenuous, frank and girlishly delighted with everything. He took her to the National Gallery, and the Tate, and the British Museum, and she really enjoyed it almost as much as she said. He liked to impart information and she was glad to receive it. She had a retentive memory and learnt a great deal from him. If later she was able to talk about Proust and Cézanne with the best of them, so that you were surprised and pleased to find so much culture in an actress, it was to him she owed it. She knew that he had fallen in love with her some time before he knew it himself. She found it rather comic. From her standpoint he was a middle-aged man, and she thought of him as a nice old thing. She was madly in love with Michael. When Charles realized that he loved her his manner changed a little, he seemed struck with shyness and when they were together was often silent.

“Poor lamb,” she said to herself, “he's such a hell of a gentleman he doesn't know what to do about it.”

But she had already prepared her course of conduct for the declaration which she felt he would sooner or later bring himself to make. One thing she was going to make quite clear to him. She wasn't going to let him think that because he was a lord and she was an actress he had only to beckon and she would hop into bed with him. If he tried that sort of thing she'd play the outraged heroine on him, with the outflung arm and the index extended in the same line, as Jane Taitbout had taught her to make the gesture, pointed at the door. On the other hand if he was shattered and tongue-tied, she'd be all tremulous herself, sobs in the voice and all that, and she'd say it had never dawned on her that he felt like that about her, and no, no, it would break Michael's heart. They'd have a good cry together and then everything would be all right. With his beautiful manners she could count upon him not making a nuisance of himself when she had once got it into his head that there was nothing doing.

But when it happened it did not turn out in the least as she had expected. Charles Tamerley and Julia had been for a walk in St. James's Park, they had looked at the pelicans, and the scene suggesting it, they had discussed the possibility of her playing Millamant on a Sunday evening. They went back to Julia's flat to have a cup of tea. They shared a crumpet. Then Charles got up to go. He took a miniature out of his pocket and gave it to her.

“It's a portrait of Clairon. She was an eighteenth-century actress and she had many of your gifts.”

Julia looked at the pretty, clever face, with the powdered hair, and wondered whether the stones that framed the little picture were diamonds or only paste.

“Oh, Charles, how can you! You are sweet.”

“I thought you might like it. It's by way of being a parting present.”

“Are you going away?”

She was surprised, for he had said nothing about it. He looked at her with a faint smile.

“No. But I'm not going to see you any more.”

“Why?”

“I think you know just as well as I do.”

Then Julia did a disgraceful thing. She sat down and for a minute looked silently at the miniature. Timing it perfectly, she raised her eyes till they met Charles's. She could cry almost at will, it was one of her most telling accomplishments, and now without a sound, without a sob, the tears poured down her cheeks. With her mouth slightly open, with the look in her eyes of a child that has been deeply hurt and does not know why, the effect was unbearably pathetic. His face was crossed by a twinge of agony. When he spoke his voice was hoarse with emotion.

“You're in love with Michael, aren't you?”

She gave a little nod. She tightened her lips as though she were trying to control herself, but the tears rolled down her cheeks.

“There's no chance for me at all?” He waited for some answer from her, but she gave none, she raised her hand to her mouth and seemed to bite a nail, and still she stared at him with those streaming eyes. “Don't you know what torture it is to go on seeing you? D'you want me to go on seeing you?”

Again she gave a little nod.

“Clara's making me scenes about you. She's found out I'm in love with you. It's only common sense that we shouldn't see one another any more.”

This time Julia slightly shook her head. She gave a sob. She leant back in the chair and turned her head aside. Her whole body seemed to express the hopelessness of her grief. Flesh and blood couldn't stand it. Charles stepped forward and sinking to his knees took that broken woe-begone body in his arms.

“For God's sake don't look so unhappy. I can't bear it. Oh, Julia, Julia, I love you so much, I can't make you so miserable. I'll accept anything. I'll make no demands on you.”

She turned her tear-stained face to him (“God, what a sight I must look now”) and gave him her lips. He kissed her tenderly. It was the first time he had ever kissed her.

“I don't want to lose you,” she muttered huskily.

“Darling, darling!”

“It'll be just as it was before?”

“Just.”

She gave a deep sigh of contentment and for a minute or two rested in his arms. When he went away she got up and looked in the glass.

“You rotten bitch,” she said to herself.

But she giggled as though she were not in the least ashamed and then went into the bathroom to wash her face and eyes. She felt wonderfully exhilarated. She heard Michael come in and called out to him.

“Michael, look at that miniature Charles has just given me. It's on the chimney-piece. Are those diamonds or paste?”

Julia was somewhat nervous when Lady Charles left her husband. She threatened to bring proceedings for divorce, and Julia did not at all like the idea of appearing as intervenor. For two or three weeks she was very jittery. She decided to say nothing to Michael till it was necessary, and she was glad she had not, for in due course it appeared that the threats had been made only to extract more substantial alimony from the innocent husband. Julia managed Charles with wonderful skill. It was understood between them that her great love for Michael made any close relation between them out of the question, but so far as the rest was concerned he was everything to her, her friend, her adviser, her confidant, the man she could rely on in any emergency or go to for comfort in any disappointment. It was a little more difficult when Charles, with his fine sensitiveness, saw that she was no longer in love with Michael. Then Julia had to exercise a great deal of tact. It was not that she had any scruples about being his mistress; if he had been an actor who loved her so much and had loved her so long she would not have minded popping into bed with him out of sheer good-nature; but she just did not fancy him. She was very fond of him, but he was so elegant, so well-bred, so cultured, she could not think of him as a lover. It would be like going to bed with an objet d'art. And his love of art filled her with a faint derision; after all she was a creator, when all was said and done he was only the public. He wished her to elope with him. They would buy a villa at Sorrento on the bay of Naples, with a large garden, and they would have a schooner so that they could spend long days on the beautiful wine-coloured sea. Love and beauty and art; the world well lost.

“The damned fool,” she thought. “As if I'd give up my career to bury myself in some hole in Italy!”

She persuaded him that she had a duty to Michael, and then there was the baby; she couldn't let him grow up with the burden on his young life that his mother was a bad woman. Orange trees or no orange trees, she would never have a moment's peace in that beautiful Italian villa if she was tortured by the thought of Michael's unhappiness and her baby being looked after by strangers. One couldn't only think of oneself, could one? One had to think of others too. She was very sweet and womanly. She sometimes asked Charles why he did not arrange a divorce with his wife and marry some nice woman. She could not bear the thought of his wasting his life over her. He told her that she was the only woman he had ever loved and that he must go on loving her till the end.

“It seems so sad,” said Julia.

All the same she kept her eyes open, and if she noticed that any woman had predatory intentions on Charles she took care to queer her pitch. She did not hesitate if the danger seemed to warrant it to show herself extremely jealous. It had been long agreed, with all the delicacy that might be expected from his good breeding and Julia's good heart, in no definite words, but with guarded hints and remote allusiveness, that if anything happened to Michael, Lady Charles should somehow or other be disposed of and they would then marry. But Michael had perfect health.

On this occasion Julia had much enjoyed lunching at Hill Street. The party had been very grand. Julia had never encouraged Charles to entertain any of the actors or authors he sometimes came across, and she was the only person there who had ever had to earn a living. She had sat between an old, fat, bald and loquacious Cabinet Minister who took a great deal of trouble to entertain her, and a young Duke of Westreys who looked like a stable-boy and who flattered himself that he knew French slang better than a Frenchman. When he discovered that Julia spoke French he insisted on conversing with her in that language. After lunch she was persuaded to recite a tirade from Phèdre as it was done at the Comédie Française and the same tirade as an English student at the Royal Academy of Dramatic Art would deliver it. She made the company laugh very much and came away from the party flushed with success. It was a fine bright day and she made up her mind to walk from Hill Street to Stanhope Place. A good many people recognized her as she threaded her way through the crowd in Oxford Street, and though she looked straight ahead of her she was conscious of their glances.

“What a hell of a nuisance it is that one can't go anywhere without people staring at one.”

She slackened her pace a little. It certainly was a beautiful day.

She let herself into her house with a latch-key and as she got in heard the telephone ringing. Without thinking she took up the receiver.

“Yes?”

She generally disguised her voice when she answered, but for once forgot to.

“Miss Lambert?”

“I don't know if Miss Lambert's in. Who is it please?” she asked, assuming quickly a cockney accent.

The monosyllable had betrayed her. A chuckle travelled over the wire.

“I only wanted to thank you for writing to me. You know, you needn't have troubled. It was so nice of you to ask me to lunch, I thought I'd like to send you a few flowers.”

The sound of his voice and the words told her who it was. It was the blushing young man whose name she did not know. Even now, though she had looked at his card, she could not remember it. The only thing that had struck her was that he lived in Tavistock Square.

“It was very sweet of you,” she answered, in her own voice.

“I suppose you wouldn't come to tea with me one day, would you?”

The nerve of it! She wouldn't go to tea with a duchess; he was treating her like a chorus girl. It was rather funny when you came to think of it.

“I don't know why not.”

“Will you really?” His voice sounded eager. He had a pleasant voice. “When?”

She did not feel at all like going to bed that afternoon.

“Today.”

“OK. I'll get away from the office. Half-past four? 138, Tavistock Square.”

It was nice of him to have suggested that. He might so easily have mentioned some fashionable place where people would stare at her. It proved that he didn't just want to be seen with her.

She took a taxi to Tavistock Square. She was pleased with herself. She was doing a good action. It would be wonderful for him in after years to be able to tell his wife and children that Julia Lambert had been to tea with him when he was just a little insignificant clerk in an accountant's office. And she had been so simple and so natural. No one to hear her prattling away would have guessed that she was the greatest actress in England. And if they didn't believe him he'd have her photograph to prove it, signed yours sincerely. He'd laugh and say that of course if he hadn't been such a kid he'd never have had the cheek to ask her.

When she arrived at the house and had paid off the taxi she suddenly remembered that she did not know his name and when the maid answered the door would not know whom to ask for. But on looking for the bell she noticed that there were eight of them, four rows of two, and by the side of each was a card or a name written in ink on a piece of paper. It was an old house that had been divided up into flats. She began looking, rather hopelessly, at the names wondering whether one of them would recall something, when the door opened and he stood before her.

“I saw you drive up and I ran down. I'm afraid I'm on the third floor. I hope you don't mind.”

“Of course not.”

She climbed the uncarpeted stairs. She was a trifle out of breath when she came to the third landing. He had skipped up eagerly, like a young goat, she thought, and she had not liked to suggest that she would prefer to go more leisurely. The room into which he led her was fairly large, but dingily furnished. On the table was a plate of cakes and two cups, a sugar basin and a milk-jug. The crockery was of the cheapest sort.

“Take a pew,” he said. “the water's just on the boil. I'll only be a minute. I've got a gas-ring in the bathroom.”

He left her and she looked about.

“Poor lamb, he must be as poor as a church mouse.”

The room reminded her very much of some of the lodgings she had lived in when she was first on the stage. She noticed the pathetic attempts he had made to conceal the fact that it was a bedroom as well as a sitting-room. The divan against the wall was evidently his bed at night. The years slipped away from her in fancy and she felt strangely young again. What fun they had had in rooms very like that and how they had enjoyed the fantastic meals they had had, things in paper bags and eggs and bacon fried on the gas-ring! He came in with the tea in a brown pot. She ate a square spongecake with pink icing on it. That was a thing she had not done for years. The Ceylon tea, very strong, with milk and sugar in it, took her back to days she thought she had forgotten. She saw herself as a young, obscure, struggling actress. It was rather delicious. It needed a gesture, but she could only think of one: she took off her hat and gave her head a shake.

They talked. He seemed shy, much shyer than he had seemed over the telephone; well, that was not to be wondered at, now she was there he must be rather overcome, and she set herself to put him at his ease. He told her that his parents lived at Highgate, his father was a solicitor, and he had lived there too, but he wanted to be his own master and now in the last year of his articles he had broken away and taken this tiny flat. He was working for his final examination. They talked of the theatre. He had seen her in every play she had acted in since he was twelve years old. He told her that once when he was fourteen he had stood outside the stage door after a matinée and when she came out had asked her to sign her name in his autograph-book. He was sweet with his blue eyes and pale-brown hair. It was a pity he plastered it down like that. He had a white skin and rather a high colour; she wondered if he was consumptive. Although his clothes were cheap he wore them well, she liked that, and he looked incredibly clean.

She asked him why he had chosen Tavistock Square. It was central, he explained, and he liked the trees. It was quite nice when you looked out of the window. She got up to look, that would be a good way to make a move, then she would put on her hat and say good-bye to him.

“Yes, it is rather charming, isn't it. It's so London; it gives one a sort of jolly feeling.”

She turned to him, standing by her side, as she said this. He put his arm round her waist and kissed her full on the lips. No woman was ever more surprised in her life. She was so taken aback that she never thought of doing anything. His lips were soft and there was a perfume of youth about him which was really rather delightful. But what he was doing was preposterous. He was forcing her lips apart with the tip of his tongue and now he had both arms round her. She did not feel angry, she did not feel inclined to laugh, she did not know what she felt. And now she had a notion that he was gently drawing her along, his lips still pressing hers, she felt quite distinctly the glow of his body, it was as though there was a furnace inside him, it was really remarkable; and then she found herself laid on the divan and he was beside her, kissing her mouth and her neck and her cheeks and her eyes. Julia felt a strange pang in her heart. She took his head in her hands and kissed his lips.

A few minutes later she was standing at the chimney-piece, in front of the looking-glass, making herself tidy.

“Look at my hair.”

He handed her a comb and she ran it through. Then she put on her hat. He was standing just behind her, and over her shoulder she saw his face with those eager blue eyes and a faint smile in them.

“And I thought you were such a shy young man,” she said to his reflection.

He chuckled.

“When am I going to see you again?”

“Do you want to see me again?”

“Rather.”

She thought rapidly. It was too absurd, of course she had no intention of seeing him again, it was stupid of her to have let him behave like that, but it was just as well to temporize. He might be tiresome if she told him that the incident would have no sequel.

“I'll ring up one of these days.”

“Swear.”

“On my honour.”

“Don't be too long.”

He insisted on coming downstairs with her and putting her into a cab. She had wanted to go down alone, so that she could have a look at the cards attached to the bells on the lintel.

“Damn it all, I ought at least to know his name.”

But he gave her no chance. When the taxi drove off she sank into one corner of it and gurgled with laughter.

“Raped, my dear. Practically raped. At my time of life. And without so much as a by-your-leave. Treated me like a tart. Eighteenth-century comedy, that's what it is. I might have been a waiting-maid. In a hoop, with those funny puffy things—what the devil are they called?—that they wore to emphasize their hips, an apron and a scarf round me neck.” Then with vague memories of Farquhar and Goldsmith she invented the dialogue. “La, sir, 'tis shame to take advantage of a poor country girl. What would Mrs. Abigail, her ladyship's woman, say an she knew her ladyship's brother had ravished me of the most precious treasure a young woman in my station of life can possess, videlicet her innocence. Fie, o fie, sir.”

When Julia got home the masseuse was already waiting for her. Miss Phillips and Evie were having a chat.

“Wherever 'ave you been, Miss Lambert?” said Evie. “An' what about your rest, I should like to know.”

“Damn my rest.”

Julia tore off her clothes, and flung them with ample gestures all over the room. Then, stark naked, she skipped on to the bed, stood up on it for a moment, like Venus rising from the waves, and then throwing herself down stretched herself out.

“What's the idea?” said Evie.

“I feel good.”

“Well, if I behaved like that people'd say I'd been drinkin'.”

Miss Phillips began to massage her feet. She rubbed gently, to rest and not to tire her.

“When you came in just now, like a whirlwind,” she said, “I thought you looked twenty years younger. Your eyes were shining something wonderful.”

“Oh, keep that for Mr. Gosselyn, Miss Phillips.” And then as an afterthought, “I feel like a two-year-old.”

And it was the same at the theatre later on. Archie Dexter, who was her leading man, came into her dressing-room to speak about something. She had just finished making-up. He was startled.

“Hulloa, Julia, what's the matter with you tonight? Gosh, you look swell. Why, you don't look a day more than twenty-five.”

“With a son of sixteen it's no good pretending I'm so terribly young any more. I'm forty and I don't care who knows it.”

“What have you done to your eyes? I've never seen them shine like that before.”

She felt in tremendous form. They had been playing the play, it was called The Powder Puff, for a good many weeks, but tonight Julia played it as though it were the first time. Her performance was brilliant. She got laughs that she had never got before. She always had magnetism, but on this occasion it seemed to flow over the house in a great radiance. Michael happened to be watching the last two acts from the corner of a box and at the end he came into her dressing-room.

“D'you know the prompter says we played nine minutes longer tonight, they laughed so much.”

“Seven curtain calls. I thought the public were going on all night.”

“Well, you've only got to blame yourself, darling. There's no one in the world who could have given the performance you gave tonight.”

“To tell you the truth I was enjoying myself. Christ, I'm hungry. What have we got for supper?”

“Tripe and onions.”

“Oh, how divine!” She flung her arms round his neck and kissed him. “I adore tripe and onions. Oh, Michael, Michael, if you love me, if you've got any spark of tenderness in that hard heart of yours, let me have a bottle of beer.”

“Julia.”

“Just this once. It's not often 1 ask you to do anything for me.”

“Oh, well, after the performance you gave tonight I suppose I can't say no, but by God, I'll see that Miss Phillips pitches into you tomorrow.”

Chapter 12

When Julia got to bed and slipped her feet down to the comfort of her hot-water bottle, she took a happy look at her room, rose-pink and Nattier-blue, with the gold cherubs of her dressing-table, and sighed with satisfaction. She thought how very Madame de Pompadour it was. She put out the light but she did not feel at all sleepy. She would have liked really to go to Quag's and dance, but not to dance with Michael, to dance with Louis XV or Ludwig of Bavaria or Alfred de Musset. Clairon and the Bal de l'Opéra. She remembered the miniature Charles had once given her. That was how she felt tonight. Such an adventure had not happened to her for ages. The last time was eight years before. That was an episode that she ought to have been thoroughly ashamed of; goodness, how scared she'd been afterwards, but she had in point of fact never been able to think of it since without a chuckle.

That had been an accident too. She had been acting for a long time without a rest and she badly needed one. The play she was in was ceasing to attract and they were about to start rehearsing a new one when Michael got the chance of letting the theatre to a French company for six weeks. It seemed a good opportunity for Julia to get away. Dolly had rented a house at Cannes for the season and Julia could stay with her. It was just before Easter when she started off, and the trains south were so crowded that she had not been able to get a sleeper, but at Cook's they had said that it would be quite all right and there would be one waiting for her at the station in Paris. To her consternation she found when they got to Paris that nothing seemed to be known about her, and the chef de train told her that every sleeper was engaged. The only chance was that someone should not turn up at the last moment. She did not like the idea of sitting up all night in the corner of a first-class carriage, and went in to dinner with a perturbed mind. She was given a table for two, and soon a man came and sat down opposite her. She paid no attention to him. Presently the chef de train came along and told her that he was very sorry, but he could do nothing for her. She made a useless scene. When the official had gone, the man at her table addressed her. Though he spoke fluent, idiomatic French, she recognized by his accent that he was not a Frenchman. She told him in answer to his polite enquiry the whole story and gave him her opinion of Cook's, the railway company, and the general inefficiency of the human race. He was very sympathetic. He told her that after dinner he would go along the train and see for himself if something could not be arranged. One never knew what one of the conductors could not manage for a tip.

“I'm simply tired out,” she said. “I'd willingly give five hundred francs for a sleeper.”

The conversation thus started, he told her that he was an attaché at the Spanish Embassy in Paris and was going down to Cannes for Easter. Though she had been talking to him for a quarter of an hour she had not troubled to notice what he was like. She observed now that he had a beard, a black curly beard and a black curly moustache, but the beard grew rather oddly on his face; there were two bare patches under the corners of his mouth. It gave him a curious look. With his black hair, drooping eyelids and rather long nose, he reminded her of someone she had seen. Suddenly she remembered, and it was such a surprise that she blurted out:

“D'you know, I couldn't think who you reminded me of. You're strangely like Titian's portrait of Francis I in the Louvre.”

“With his little pig's eyes?”

“No, not them, yours are large, I think it's the beard chiefly.”

She glanced at the skin under his eyes; it was faintly violet and unwrinkled. Notwithstanding the ageing beard he was quite a young man; he could not have been more than thirty. She wondered if he was a Spanish grandee. He was not very well-dressed, but then foreigners often weren't, his clothes might have cost a lot even if they were badly cut, and his tie, though rather loud, she recognised as a Charvet. When they came to the coffee he asked her whether he might offer her a liqueur.

“That's very kind of you. Perhaps it'll make me sleep better.”

He offered her a cigarette. His cigarette-case was silver, that put her off a little, but when he closed it she saw that in the corner was a small crown in gold. He must be a count or something. It was rather chic, having a silver cigarette-case with a gold crown on it. Pity he had to wear those modern clothes! If he'd been dressed like Francis I he would really look very distinguished. She set herself to be as gracious as she knew how.

“I think I should tell you,” he said presently, “that I know who you are. And may I add that I have a great admiration for you?”

She gave him a lingering look of her splendid eyes.

“You've seen me act?”

“Yes, I was in London last month.”

“An interesting little play, wasn't it?”

“Only because you made it so.”

When the man came round to collect the money she had to insist on paying her own bill. The Spaniard accompanied her to the carriage and then said he would go along the train to see if he could find a sleeper for her. He came back in a quarter of an hour with a conductor and told her that he had got her a compartment and if she would give the conductor her things he would take her to it. She was delighted. He threw down his hat on the seat she vacated and she followed him along the corridor. When they reached the compartment he told the conductor to take the portmanteau and the dispatch-case that were in the rack to the carriage madame had just left.

“But it's not your own compartment you're giving up to me?” cried Julia.

“It's the only one on the train.”

“Oh, but I won't hear of it.”

“Allez,” the Spaniard said to the conductor.

“No, no.”

The conductor, on a nod from the stranger, took the luggage away.

“I don't matter. I can sleep anywhere, but I shouldn't sleep a wink if I thought that such a great artist was obliged to spend the night in a stuffy carriage with three other people.”

Julia continued to protest, but not too much. It was terribly sweet of him. She didn't know how to thank him. He would not even let her pay for the sleeper. He begged her, almost with tears in his eyes, to let him have the great privilege of making her that trifling present. She had with her only a dressing-bag, in which were her face creams, her night-dress and her toilet things, and this he put on the table for her. All he asked was that he might be allowed to sit with her and smoke a cigarette or two till she wanted to go to bed. She could hardly refuse him that. The bed was already made up and they sat down on it. In a few minutes the conductor came back with a bottle of champagne and a couple of glasses. It was an odd little adventure and Julia was enjoying it. It was wonderfully polite of him, all that, ah, those foreigners, they knew how to treat a great actress. Of course that was the sort of thing that happened to Bernhardt every day. And Siddons, when she went into a drawing-room everyone stood up as though she were royalty. He complimented her on her beautiful French. Born in Jersey and educated in France? Ah, that explained it. But why hadn't she chosen to act in French rather than in English? She would have as great a reputation as Duse if she had. She reminded him of Duse, the same magnificent eyes and the pale skin, and in her acting the same emotion and the wonderful naturalness.

They half finished the bottle of champagne and Julia realized that it was very late.

“I really think I ought to go to bed now.”

“I'll leave you.”

He got up and kissed her hand. When he was gone Julia bolted the door and undressed. Putting out all the lights except the one just behind her head she began to read. Presently there was a knock at the door.

“Yes?”

“I'm sorry to disturb you. I left my toothbrush in the lavabo. May I get it?”

“I'm in bed.”

“I can't go to sleep unless I brush my teeth.”

“Oh, well, he's clean anyway.”

With a little shrug of her shoulders Julia slipped her hand to the door and drew back the bolt. It would be stupid in the circumstances to be prudish. He came in, went into the lavatory and in a moment came out, brandishing a toothbrush. She had noticed it when she brushed her own teeth, but thought it belonged to the person who had the compartment next door. At that period adjoining compartments shared a lavatory. The Spaniard seemed to catch sight of the bottle.

“I'm so thirsty, do you mind if I have a glass of champagne?”

Julia was silent for a fraction of a second. It was his champagne and his compartment. Oh, well, in for a penny, in for a pound.

“Of course not.”

He poured himself out a glass, lit a cigarette and sat down on the edge of her bed. She moved a little to give him more room. He accepted the situation as perfectly natural.

“You couldn't possibly have slept in that carriage,” he said. “There's a man there who's a heavy breather. I'd almost rather he snored. If he snored one could wake him.”

“I'm so sorry.”

“Oh, it doesn't matter. If the worst comes to the worst I'll curl up in the corridor outside your door.”

“He can hardly expect me to ask him to come and sleep in here,” Julia said to herself. “I'm beginning to think this was all a put-up job. Nothing doing, my lad.” And then aloud: “Romantic, of course, but uncomfortable.”

“You're a terribly attractive woman.”

She was just as glad that her night-dress was pretty and that she had put no cream on her face. She had in point of fact not troubled to take off her make-up. Her lips were brightly scarlet, and with the reading light behind her she well knew that she did not look her worst. But she answered ironically.

“If you think that because you've given up your compartment to me I'm going to let you sleep with me, you're mistaken.”

“Just as you say, of course. But why not?”

“I'm not that sort of terribly attractive woman.”

“What sort of woman are you then?”

“A faithful wife and a devoted mother.”

He gave a little sigh.

“Very well. Then I'll say good-night to you.”

He crushed the stub of his cigarette on the ash tray and took her hand and kissed it. He slowly ran his lips up her arm. It gave Julia a funny little sensation.The beard slightly tickled her skin. Then he leant over and kissed her lips. His beard had a somewhat musty smell, which she found peculiar; she was not sure if it revolted or thrilled her. It was odd when she came to think of it, she had never been kissed by a man with a beard before. It seemed strangely indecent. He snapped out the light.

He did not leave her till a chink of light through the drawn blind warned them that day had broken. Julia was shattered morally and physically.

“I shall look a perfect wreck when we get to Cannes.”

And what a risk to take! He might have murdered her or stolen her pearl necklace. She went hot and cold all over as she pictured to herself the danger she had incurred. He was going to Cannes too. Supposing he claimed acquaintance with her there, how on earth was she going to explain him to her friends? She felt sure Dolly wouldn't like him. He might try to blackmail her. And what should she do if he wanted to repeat the experience? He was passionate, there was no doubt about that, he had asked her where she was staying, and though she had not told him, he could certainly find out if he tried; in a place like Cannes, it would be almost impossible not to run across him. He might pester her. If he loved her as much as he said it was inconceivable that he should let her alone, and foreigners were so unreliable, he might make frightful scenes. The only comfort was that he was only staying over Easter, she would pretend she was tired and tell Dolly that she preferred to stay quietly at the villa.

“How could I have been such a fool?” she cried angrily.

Dolly would be there to meet her at the station, and if he was tactless enough to come up and say good-bye to her she would tell Dolly that he had given up his compartment to her. There was no harm in that. It was always best to tell as much of the truth as you could. But there was quite a crowd of passengers getting out at Cannes, and Julia got out of the station and into Dolly's car without catching a glimpse of him.

“I've arranged nothing for today,” said Dolly. “I thought you'd be tired and I wanted to have you all to myself just for twenty-four hours.”

Julia gave her arm an affectionate squeeze.

“That'll be too wonderful. We'll just sit about the villa and grease our faces and have a good old gossip.”

But next day Dolly had arranged that they should go out to lunch, and they were to meet their hosts at one of the bars on the Croisette to have cocktails. It was a beautiful day, clear, warm and sunny. When they got out of the car Dolly stopped to give the chauffeur instructions about fetching them and Julia waited for her. Suddenly her heart gave a great jump, for there was the Spaniard walking towards her, with a woman on one side of him clinging to his arm and on the other a little girl whose hand he held. She had not time to turn away. At that moment Dolly joined her to walk across the pavement. The Spaniard came, gave her a glance in which there was no sign of recognition, he was in animated conversation with the woman on his arm, and walked on. In a flash Julia understood that he was just as little anxious to see her as she was to see him. The woman and the child were obviously his wife and daughter whom he had come down to Cannes to spend Easter with. What a relief! Now she could enjoy herself without fear. But as she accompanied Dolly to the bar, Julia thought how disgusting men were. You simply couldn't trust them for a minute. It was really disgraceful that a man with a charming wife and such a sweet little girl should be willing to pick up a woman in the train. You would think they'd have some sense of decency.

But as time passed Julia's indignation was mitigated and she had often thought of the adventure since with a good deal of pleasure. After all it had been fun. Sometimes she allowed her reveries to run away with her and she went over in her fancy the incidents of that singular night. He had been a most agreeable lover. It would be something to look back on when she was an old woman. It was the beard that had made such an impression on her, the odd feeling of it on her face and that slightly musty smell which was repulsive and yet strangely exciting. For years she looked out for men with beards, and she had a feeling that if one of them made proposals to her she simply wouldn't be able to resist him. But few men wore beards any more, luckily for her because the sight made her go a little weak at the knees, and none of those that did ever made any advance to her. She would have liked to know who the Spaniard was. She saw him a day or two later playing chemin de fer at the Casino and asked two or three people if they knew him. Nobody did, and he remained in her recollection, and in her bones, without a name. It was an odd coincidence that she didn't know the name either of the young man who had that afternoon behaved in so unexpected a manner. It struck her as rather comic.

“If I only knew beforehand that they were going to take liberties with me I'd at least ask for their cards.”

With this thought she fell happily asleep.

Chapter 13

Some days passed, and one morning, while Julia was lying in bed reading a play, they rang through from the basement to ask if she would speak to Mr. Fennell. The name meant nothing to her and she was about to refuse when it occurred to her that it might be the young man of her adventure. Her curiosity induced her to tell them to connect him. She recognized his voice.

“You promised to ring me up,” he said. “I got tired of waiting, so I've rung you up instead.”

“I've been terribly busy the last few days.”

“When am I going to see you?”

“As soon as I have a moment to spare.”

“What about this afternoon?”

“I've got a matinée today.”

“Come to tea after the matinée.”

She smiled. (“No, young feller-me-lad, you don't catch me a second time like that.”)

“I can't possibly,” she answered. “I always stay in my dressing-room and rest till the evening performance.”

“Can't I come and see you while you're resting?”

She hesitated for an instant. Perhaps the best thing would be to let him come; with Evie popping in and out and Miss Phillips due at seven, there would be no chance of any nonsense, and it would be a good opportunity to tell him, amiably, because he was really a sweet little thing, but firmly, that the incident of the other afternoon was to have no sequel. With a few well-chosen words she would explain to him that it was quite unreasonable and that he must oblige her by erasing the episode from his memory.

“All right. Come at half-past five and I'll give you a cup of tea.”

There was no part of her busy life that she enjoyed more than those three hours that she spent in her dressing-room between the afternoon and the evening performances. The other members of the cast had gone away; and Evie was there to attend to her wants and the door-keeper to guard her privacy. Her dressing-room was like the cabin of a ship. The world seemed a long way off, and she relished her seclusion. She felt an enchanting freedom. She dozed a little, she read a little, or lying on the comfortable sofa she let her thoughts wander. She reflected on the part she was playing and the favourite parts she had played in the past. She thought of Roger her son. Pleasant reveries sauntered through her mind like lovers wandering in a green wood. She was fond of French poetry, and sometimes she repeated to herself verses of Verlaine.

Punctually at half-past five Evie brought her in a card. “Mr. Thomas Fennell,” she read.

“Send him in and bring some tea.”

She had decided how she was going to treat him. She would be amiable, but distant. She would take a friendly interest in his work and ask him about his examination. Then she would talk to him about Roger. Roger was seventeen now and in a year would be going to Cambridge. She would insinuate the fact that she was old enough to be his mother. She would act as if there had never been anything between them and he would go away, never to see her again except across the footlights, half convinced that the whole thing had been a figment of his fancy. But when she saw him, so slight, with his hectic flush and his blue eyes, so charmingly boyish, she felt a sudden pang. Evie closed the door behind him. She was lying on the sofa and she stretched out her arm to give him her hand, the gracious smile of Madame Récamier on her lips, but he flung himself on his knees and passionately kissed her mouth. She could not help herself, she put her arms round his neck, and kissed him as passionately.

(“Oh, my good resolutions. My God, I can't have fallen in love with him.”)

“For goodness' sake, sit down. Evie's coming in with the tea.”

“Tell her not to disturb us.”

“What do you mean?” But what he meant was obvious. Her heart began to beat quickly. “It's ridiculous. I can't. Michael might come in.”

“I want you.”

“What d'you suppose Evie would think? It'd be idiotic to take such a risk. No, no, no.”

There was a knock at the door and Evie came in with the tea. Julia gave her instructions to put the table by the side of her sofa and a chair for the young man on the other side of the table. She kept Evie with unnecessary conversation. She felt him looking at her. His eyes moved quickly, following her gestures and the expression of her face; she avoided them, but she felt their anxiety and the eagerness of his desire. She was troubled. It seemed to her that her voice did not sound quite natural.

(“What the devil's the matter with me? God, I can hardly breathe.”)

When Evie reached the door the boy made a gesture that was so instinctive that her sensitiveness rather than her sight caught it. She could not but look at him. His face had gone quite pale.

“Oh, Evie,” she said. “This gentleman wants to talk to me about a play. See that no one disturbs me. I'll ring when I want you.”

“Very good, miss.”

Evie went out and closed the door.

(“I'm a fool. I'm a bloody fool.”)

But he had moved the table, and he was on his knees, and she was in his arms.

She sent him away a little before Miss Phillips was due, and when he was going rang for Evie.

“Play any good?” asked Evie.

“What play?”

“The play 'e was talkin' to you about.”

“He's clever. Of course he's young.”

Evie was looking down at the dressing-table. Julia liked everything always to be in the same place, and if a pot of grease or her eyeblack was not exactly where it should be made a scene.

“Where's your comb?”

He had used it to comb his hair and had carelessly placed it on the tea-table. When Evie caught sight of it she stared at it for a moment reflectively.

“How on earth did it get there?” cried Julia lightly.

“I was just wondering.”

It gave Julia a nasty turn. Of course it was madness to do that sort of thing in the dressing-room. Why, there wasn't even a key in the lock. Evie kept it. All the same the risk had given it a spice. It was fun to think that she could be so crazy. At all events they'd made a date now. Tom, she'd asked him what they called him at home and he said Thomas, she really couldn't call him that. Tom wanted to take her to supper somewhere so that they could dance, and it happened that Michael was going up to Cambridge for a night to rehearse a series of one-act plays written by undergraduates. They would be able to spend hours together.

“You can get back with the milk,” he'd said.

“And what about my performance next day?”

“We can't bother about that.”

She had refused to let him fetch her at the theatre, and when she got to the restaurant they had chosen he was waiting for her in the lobby. His face lit up as he saw her.

“It was getting so late, I was afraid you weren't coming.”

“I'm sorry, some tiresome people came round after the play and I couldn't get rid of them.”

But it wasn't true. She had been as excited all the evening as a girl going to her first ball. She could not help thinking how absurd she was. But when she had taken off her theatrical make-up and made up again for supper she could not satisfy herself. She put blue on her eyelids and took it off again, she rouged her cheeks, rubbed them clean and tried another colour.

“What are you trying to do?” said Evie.

“I'm trying to look twenty, you fool.”

“If you try much longer you'll look your age.”

She had never seen him in evening clothes before. He shone like a new pin. Though he was of no more than average height his slimness made him look tall. She was a trifle touched to see that for all his airs of the man of the world he was shy with the head-waiter when it came to ordering supper. They danced and he did not dance very well, but she found his slight awkwardness rather charming. People recognized her, and she was conscious that he enjoyed the reflected glory of their glances. A pair of young things who had been dancing came up to their table to say how-do-you-do-to her. When they had left he asked:

“Wasn't that Lord and Lady Dennorant?”

“Yes. I've known George since he was at Eton.”

He followed them with his eyes.

“She was Lady Cecily Laweston, wasn't she?”

“I've forgotten. Was she?”

It seemed a matter of no interest to her. A few minutes later another couple passed them.

“Look, there's Lady Lepard.”

“Who's she?”

“Don't you remember, they had a big party at their place in Cheshire a few weeks ago and the Prince of Wales was there. It was in the Bystander.”

Oh, that was how he got all his information. Poor sweet. He read about grand people in the papers and now and then, at a restaurant or a theatre, saw them in the flesh. Of course it was a thrill for him. Romance. If he only knew how dull they were really! This innocent passion for the persons whose photographs appear in the illustrated papers made him seem incredibly naïve, and she looked at him with tender eyes.

“Have you ever taken an actress out to supper before?”

He blushed scarlet.

“Never.”

She hated to let him pay the bill, she had an inkling that it was costing pretty well his week's salary, but she knew it would hurt his pride if she offered to pay it herself. She asked casually what the time was and instinctively he looked at his wrist.

“I forgot to put on my watch.”

She gave him a searching look.

“Have you pawned it?”

He reddened again.

“No. I dressed in rather a hurry tonight.”

She only had to look at his tie to know that he had done no such thing. He was lying to her. She knew that he had pawned his watch in order to take her out to supper. A lump came into her throat. She could have taken him in her arms then and there and kissed his blue eyes. She adored him.

“Let's go,” she said.

They drove back to his bed-sitting room in Tavistock Square.

Chapter 14

Next day Julia went to Cartier's and bought a watch to send to Tom Fennell instead of the one he had pawned, and two or three weeks later, discovering that it was his birthday, she sent him a gold cigarette-case.

“D'you know, that's the one thing I've wanted all my life.”

She wondered if there were tears in his eyes. He kissed her passionately.

Then, on one excuse and another, she sent him pearl studs and sleeve-links and waistcoat buttons. It thrilled her to make him presents.

“It's so awful that I can't give you anything in return,” he said.

“Give me the watch you pawned to stand me a supper.”

It was a little gold watch that could not have cost more than ten pounds, but it amused her to wear it now and then.

It was not till after that night when they had first supped together that Julia confessed to herself that she had fallen in love with Tom. It came to her as a shock. But she was exhilarated.

“I who thought I could never be in love again. Of course it can't last. But why shouldn't I get what fun out of it I can?”

She decided that he must come again to Stanhope Place. It was not long before an opportunity presented itself.

“You know that young accountant of yours,” she said to Michael. “Tom Fennell's his name. I met him out at supper the other night and I'ved asked him to dinner next Sunday. We want an extra man.”

“Oh, d'you think he'll fit in?”

It was rather a grand party. It was on that account she had asked him. She thought it would please him to meet some of the people he had known only from their pictures. She had realized already that he was a bit of a snob. Well, that was all to the good; she could give him all the smart people he wanted. For Julia was shrewd, and she knew very well that Tom was not in love with her. To have an affair with her flattered his vanity. He was a highly-sexed young man and enjoyed sexual exercise. From hints, from stories that she had dragged out of him, she discovered that since he was seventeen he had had a great many women. He loved the act rather than the person. He looked upon it as the greatest lark in the world. And she could understand why he had so much success. There was something appealing in his slightness, his body was just skin and bone, that was why his clothes sat on him so well, and something charming in his clean freshness. His shyness and his effrontery combined to make him irresistible. It was strangely flattering for a woman to be treated as a little bit of fluff that you just tumbled on to a bed.

“What he's got, of course, is sex appeal.”

She knew that his good looks were due to his youth. He would grow wizened as he grew older, dried up and haggard; that charming flush on his cheeks would turn into a purple glow and his delicate skin would go lined and sallow; but the feeling that what she loved in him would endure so short a time increased her tenderness. She felt a strange compassion for him. He had the high spirits of youth, and she lapped them up as a kitten laps up milk. But he was not amusing. Though he laughed when Julia said a funny thing he never said one himself. She did not mind. She found his dullness restful. She never felt so light-hearted as in his company, and she could be brilliant enough for two.

People kept on telling Julia that she was looking ten years younger and that she had never acted better. She knew it was true and she knew the reason. But it behoved her to walk warily. She must keep her head. Charles Tamerley always said that what an actress needed was not intelligence, but sensibility, and he might be right; perhaps she wasn't clever, but her feelings were alert and she trusted them. They told her now that she must never tell Tom that she loved him.

She was careful to make it plain to him that she laid no claims on him and that he was free to do whatever he liked. She took up the attitude that the whole thing was a bit of nonsense to which neither of them must attach importance. But she left nothing undone to bind him to her. He liked parties and she took him to parties. She got Dolly and Charles Tamerley to ask him to lunch. He was fond of dancing and she got him cards for balls. For his sake she would go to them herself for an hour, and she was conscious of the satisfaction he got out of seeing how much fuss people made of her. She knew that he was dazzled by the great, and she introduced him to eminent persons. Fortunately Michael took a fancy to him. Michael liked to talk, and Tom was a good listener. He was clever at his business. One day Michael said to her:

“Smart fellow, Tom. He knows a lot about income tax. I believe he's shown me a way of saving two or three hundred pounds on my next return.”

Michael, looking for new talent, often took him to the play in the evenings, either in London or the suburbs; they would fetch Julia after the performance, and the three of them supped together. Now and then Michael asked Tom to play golf with him on Sundays and then if there was no party would bring him home to dinner.

“Nice to have a young fellow like that around,” he said. “It keeps one from growing rusty.”

Tom was very pleasant about the house. He would play backgammon with Michael, or patience with Julia, and when they turned on the gramophone he was always there to change the records.

“He'll be a nice friend for Roger,” said Michael. “Tom's got his head screwed on his shoulders the right way, and he's a lot older than Roger. He ought to have a good influence on him. Why don't you ask him to come and spend his holiday with us?”

(“Lucky I'm a good actress.”) But it wanted an effort to keep the joy out of her voice and to prevent her face from showing the exultation that made her heart beat so violently. “That's not a bad idea,” she answered. “I'll ask him if you like.”

Their play was running through August, and Michael had taken a house at Taplow so that they could spend the height of the summer there. Julia was to come up for her performances and Michael when business needed it, but she would have the day in the country and Sundays. Tom had a fortnight's holiday; he accepted the invitation with alacrity.

But one day Julia noticed that he was unusually silent. He looked pale and his buoyant spirits had deserted him. She knew that something was wrong, but he would not tell her what it was; he would only say that he was worried to death. At last she forced him to confess that he had got into debt and was being dunned by tradesmen. The life into which she had led him had made him spend more money than he could afford, and ashamed of his cheap clothes at the grand parties to which she took him, he had gone to an expensive tailor and ordered himself new suits. He had backed a horse hoping to make enough money to get square and the horse was beaten. To Julia it was a very small sum that he owed, a hundred and twenty-five pounds, and she found it absurd that anyone should allow a trifle like that to upset him. She said at once that she would give it to him.

“Oh, I couldn't. I couldn't take money from a woman.”

He went scarlet; the mere thought of it made him ashamed. Julia used all her arts of cajolery. She reasoned, she pretended to be affronted, she even cried a little, and at last as a great favour he consented to borrow the money from her. Next day she sent him a letter in which were bank notes to the value of two hundred pounds. He rang her up and told her that she had sent far more than he wanted.

“Oh, I know people always lie about their debts,” she said with a laugh. “I'm sure you owe more than you said.”

“I promise you I don't. You're the last person I'd lie to.”

“Then keep the rest for anything that turns up. I hate seeing you pay the bill when we go out to supper. And taxis and all that sort of thing.”

“No, really. It's so humiliating.”

“What nonsense! You know I've got more money than I know what do do with. Can you grudge me the happiness it gives me to get you out of a hole?”

“It's awfully kind of you. You don't know what a relief it is. I don't know how to thank you.”

But his voice was troubled. Poor lamb, he was so conventional. But it was true, it gave her a thrill she had never known before to give him money; it excited in her a surprising passion. And she had another scheme in her head which during the fortnight Tom was to spend at Taplow she thought she could easily work. Tom's bedsitting-room in Tavistock Square had at first seemed to her charming in its sordidness, and the humble furniture had touched her heart. But time had robbed it of these moving characteristics. Once or twice she had met people on the stairs and thought they stared at her strangely. There was a slatternly housekeeper who made Tom's room and cooked his breakfast, and Julia had a feeling that she knew what was going on and was spying on her. Once the locked door had been tried while Julia was in the room, and when she went out the housekeeper was dusting the banisters. She gave Julia a sour look. Julia hated the smell of stale food that hung about the stairs and with her quick eyes she soon discovered that Tom's room was none too clean. The dingy curtains, the worn carpet, the shoddy furniture; it all rather disgusted her. Now it happened that a little while before, Michael, always on the look out for a good investment, had bought a block of garages near Stanhope Place. By letting off those he did not want he found that he could get their own for nothing. There were a number of rooms over. He divided them into two small flats, one for their chauffeur and one which he proposed to let. This was still vacant and Julia suggested to Tom that he should take it. It would be wonderful. She could slip along and see him for an hour when he got back from the office; sometimes she could drop in after the theatre and no one would be any the wiser. They would be free there. She talked to him of the fun they would have furnishing it; she was sure they had lots of things in their house that they did not want, and by storing them he would be doing them a kindness. The rest they would buy together. He was tempted by the idea of having a flat of his own, but it was out of the question; the rent, though small, was beyond his means. Julia knew that. She knew also that if she offered to pay it herself he would indignantly refuse. But she had a notion that during that idle, luxurious fortnight by the river she would be able to overcome his scruples. She saw how much the idea tempted him, and she had little doubt that she could devise some means to persuade him that by falling in with her proposal he was really doing her a service.

“People don't want reasons to do what they'd like to,” she reflected. “They want excuses.”

Julia looked forward to Tom's visit to Taplow with excitement. It would be lovely to go on the river with him in the morning and in the afternoon sit about the garden with him. With Roger in the house she was determined that there should be no nonsense between her and Tom; decency forbad. But it would be heaven to spend nearly all day with him. When she had matinées he could amuse himself with Roger.

But things did not turn out at all as she expected. It had never occurred to her that Roger and Tom would take a great fancy to one another. There were five years between them and she thought, or would have if she had thought about it at all, that Tom would look upon Roger as a hobbledehoy, quite nice of course, but whom you treated as such, who fetched and carried for you and whom you told to go and play when you did not want to be bothered with him. Roger was seventeen. He was a nice-looking boy, with reddish hair and blue eyes, but that was the best you could say of him. He had neither his mother's vivacity and changing expression nor his father's beauty of feature. Julia was somewhat disappointed in him. As a child when she had been so constantly photographed with him he was lovely. He was rather stolid now and he had a serious look. Really when you came to examine him his only good features were his teeth and his hair. Julia was very fond of him, but she could not but find him a trifle dull. When she was alone with him the time hung somewhat heavily on her hands. She exhibited a lively interest in the things she supposed must interest him, cricket and such like, but he did not seem to have much to say about them. She was afraid he was not very intelligent.

“Of course he's young,” she said hopefully. “Perhaps he'll improve as he grows older.”

From the time that he first went to his preparatory school she had seen little of him. During the holidays she was always acting at night and he went out with his father or with a boy friend, and on Sundays he and his father played golf together. If she happened to be lunching out it often happened that she did not see him for two or three days together except for a few minutes in the morning when he came to her room. It was a pity he could not always have remained a sweetly pretty little boy who could play in her room without disturbing her and be photographed, smiling into the camera, with his arm round her neck. She went down to see him at Eton occasionally and had tea with him. It flattered her that there were several photographs of her in his room. She was conscious that when she went to Eton it created quite a little excitement, and Mr. Brackenbridge, in whose house he was, made a point of being very polite to her. When the half ended Michael and Julia had already moved to Taplow and Roger came straight there. Julia kissed him emotionally. He was not so much excited at getting home as she had expected him to be. He was rather casual. He seemed suddenly to have grown very sophisticated.

He told Julia at once that he desired to leave Eton at Christmas, he thought he had got everything out of it that he could, and he wanted to go to Vienna for a few months and learn German before going up to Cambridge. Michael had wished him to go into the army, but this he had set his face against. He did not yet know what he wanted to be. Both Julia and Michael had from the first been obsessed by the fear that he would go on the stage, but for this apparently he had no inclination.

“Anyhow he wouldn't be any good,” said Julia.

He led his own life. He went out on the river and lay about the garden reading. On his seventeenth birthday Julia had given him a very smart roadster, and in this he careered about the country at breakneck speeds.

“There's one comfort,” said Julia. “He's no bother. He seems quite capable of amusing himself.”

On Sundays they had a good many people down for the day, actors and actresses, an occasional writer, and a sprinkling of some of their grander friends. Julia found these parties very amusing and she knew that people liked to come to them. On the first Sunday after Roger's arrival there was a great mob. Roger was very polite to the guests. He did his duty as part host like a man of the world. But it seemed to Julia that he held himself in some curious way aloof, as though he were playing a part in which he had not lost himself, and she had an uneasy feeling that he was not accepting all these people, but coolly judging them. She had an impression that he took none of them very seriously.

Tom had arranged to come on the following Saturday and she drove him down after the theatre. It was a moonlit night and at that hour the roads were empty. The drive was enchanting. Julia would have liked it to go on for ever. She nestled against him and every now and then in the darkness he kissed her.

“Are you happy?” she asked.

“Absolutely.”

Michael and Roger had gone to bed, but supper was waiting for them in the dining-room. The silent house gave them the feeling of being there without leave. They might have been a couple of wanderers who had strolled out of the night into a strange house and found a copious repast laid out for them. It was romantic. It had a little the air of a tale in the Arabian Nights. Julia showed him his room, which was next door to Roger's, and then went to bed. She did not wake till late next morning. It was a lovely day. So that she might have Tom all to herself she had not asked anybody down. When she was dressed they would go on the river together. She had her breakfast and her bath. She put on a little white frock that suited the sunny riverside and her, and a large-brimmed red straw hat whose colour threw a warm glow on her face. She was very little made up. She looked at herself in the glass and smiled with satisfaction. She really looked very pretty and young. She strolled down into the garden. There was a lawn that stretched down to the river, and here she saw Michael surrounded by the Sunday papers. He was alone.

“I thought you'd gone to play golf.”

“No, the boys have gone. I thought they'd have more fun if I let them go alone.” He smiled in his friendly way. “They're a bit too active for me. They were bathing at eight o'clock this morning, and as soon as they'd swallowed their breakfast they bolted off in Roger's car.”

“I'm glad they've made friends.”

Julia meant it. She was slightly disappointed that she would not be able to go on the river with Tom, but she was anxious that Roger should like him, she had a feeling that Roger did not like people indiscriminately; and after all she had the next fortnight to be with Tom.

“They make me feel damned middle-aged, I don't mind telling you that,” Michael remarked.

“What nonsense. You're much more beautiful than either of them, and well you know it, my pet.”

Michael thrust out his jaw a little and pulled in his belly.

The boys did not come back till lunch was nearly ready.

“Sorry we're so late,” said Roger. “There was a filthy crowd and we had to wait on nearly every tee. We halved the match.”

They were hungry and thirsty, excited and pleased with themselves.

“It's grand having no one here today,” said Roger. “I was afraid you'd got a whole gang coming and we'd have to behave like little gentlemen.”

“I thought a rest would be rather nice,” said Julia.

Roger gave her a glance.

“It'll do you good, Mummy. You're looking awfully fagged.”

(“Blast his eyes. No, I mustn't show I mind. Thank God, I can act.”)

She laughed gaily.

“I had a sleepless night wondering what on earth we were going to do about your spots.”

“I know, aren't they sickening? Tom says he used to have them too.”

Julia looked at Tom. In his tennis shirt open at the neck, with his hair ruffled, his face already caught by the sun, he looked incredibly young. He really looked no older than Roger.

“Anyhow, his nose is going to peel,” Roger went on with a chuckle. “He'll look a sight then.”

Julia felt slightly uneasy. It seemed to her that Tom had shed the years so that he was become not only in age Roger's contemporary. They talked a great deal of nonsense. They ate enormously and drank tankards of beer. Michael, eating and drinking as sparingly as usual, watched them with amusement. He was enjoying their youth and their high spirits. He reminded Julia of an old dog lying in the sun and gently beating his tail on the ground as he looked at a pair of puppies gambolling about him. They had coffee on the lawn. Julia found it very pleasant to sit there in the shade, looking at the river. Tom was slim and graceful in his long white trousers. She had never seen him smoke a pipe before. She found it strangely touching. But Roger mocked him.

“Do you smoke it because it makes you feel manly or because you like it?”

“Shut up,” said Tom.

“Finished your coffee?”

“Yes.”

“Come on then, let's go on the river.”

Tom gave her a doubtful look. Roger saw it.

“Oh, it's all right, you needn't bother about my respected parents, they've got the Sunday papers. Mummy's just given me a racing punt.”

(“I must keep my temper. I must keep my temper. Why was I such a fool as to give him a racing punt?”)

“All right,” she said, with an indulgent smile, “go on the river, but don't fall in.”

“It won't hurt us if we do. We'll be back for tea. Is the court marked out, Daddy? We're going to play tennis after tea.”

“I daresay your father can get hold of somebody and you can have a four.”

“Oh, don't bother. Singles are better fun really and one gets more exercise.” Then to Tom: “I'll race you to the boathouse.”

Tom leapt to his feet and dashed off with Roger in quick pursuit. Michael took up one of the papers and looked for his spectacles.

“They've clicked all right, haven't they?”

“Apparently.”

“I was afraid Roger would be rather bored alone here with us. It'll be fine for him to have someone to play around with.”

“Don't you think Roger's rather inconsiderate?”

“You mean about the tennis? Oh, my dear, I don't really care if I play or not. It's only natural that those two boys should want to play together. From their point of view I'm an old man, and they think I'll spoil their game. After all the great thing is that they should have a good time.”

Julia had a pang of remorse. Michael was prosy, near with his money, self-complacent, but how extraordinarily kind he was and how unselfish! He was devoid of envy. It gave him a real satisfaction, so long as it did not cost money, to make other people happy. She read his mind like an open book. It was true that he never had any but a commonplace thought; on the other hand he never had a shameful one. It was exasperating that with so much to make him worthy of her affection, she should be so excruciatingly bored by him.

“I think you're a much better man that I am a woman, my sweet,” she said.

He gave her his good, friendly smile and slightly shook his head.

“No, dear, I had a wonderful profile, but you've got genius.”

Julia giggled. There was a certain fun to be got out of a man who never knew what you were talking about. But what did they mean when they said an actress had genius? Julia had often asked herself what it was that had placed her at last head and shoulders above her contemporaries. She had had detractors. At one time people had compared her unfavourably with some actress or other who at the moment enjoyed the public favour, but now no one disputed her supremacy. It was true that she had not the world-wide notoriety of the film-stars; she had tried her luck on the pictures, but had achieved no success; her face on the stage so mobile and expressive for some reason lost on the screen, and after one trial she had with Michael's approval refused to accept any of the offers that were from time to time made her. She had got a good deal of useful publicity out of her dignified attitude. But Julia did not envy the film-stars; they came and went; she stayed. When it was possible she went to see the performance of actresses who played leading parts on the London stage. She was generous in her praise of them and her praise was sincere. Sometimes she honestly thought them so very good that she could not understand why people made so much fuss over her. She was much too intelligent not to know in what estimation the public held her, but she was modest about herself. It always surprised her when people raved over something she had done that came to her so naturally that she had never thought it possible to do anything else. The critics admired her variety. They praised especially her capacity for insinuating herself into a part. She was not aware that she deliberately observed people, but when she came to study a new part vague recollections surged up in her from she knew not where, and she found that she knew things about the character she was to represent that she had had no inkling of. It helped her to think of someone she knew or even someone she had seen in the street or at a party; she combined with this recollection her own personality, and thus built up a character founded on fact but enriched with her experience, her knowledge of technique and her amazing magnetism. People thought that she only acted during the two or three hours she was on the stage; they did not know that the character she was playing dwelt in the back of her mind all day long, when she was talking to others with all the appearance of attention, or in whatever business she was engaged. It often seemed to her that she was two persons, the actress, the popular favourite, the best-dressed woman in London, and that was a shadow; and the woman she was playing at night, and that was the substance.

“Damned if I know what genius is,” she said to herself. “But I know this, I'd give all I have to be eighteen.”

But she knew that wasn't true. If she were given the chance to go back again would she take it? No. Not really. It was not the popularity, the celebrity if you like, that she cared for, nor the hold she had over audiences, the real love they bore her, it was certainly not the money this had brought her; it was the power she felt in herself, her mastery over the medium, that thrilled her. She could step into a part, not a very good one perhaps, with silly words to say, and by her personality, by the dexterity which she had at her finger tips, infuse it with life. There was no one who could do what she could with a part. Sometimes she felt like God.

“And besides,” she chuckled, “Tom wouldn't be born.”

After all it was very natural that he should like to play about with Roger. They belonged to the same generation. It was the first day of his holiday, she must let him enjoy himself; there was a whole fortnight more. He would soon get sick of being all the time with a boy of seventeen. Roger was sweet, but he was dull; she wasn't going to let maternal affection blind her to that. She must be very careful not to show that she was in the least put out. From the beginning she had made up her mind that she would never make any claim on Tom; it would be fatal if he felt that he owed something to her.

“Michael, why don't you let that flat in the mews to Tom? Now that he's passed his exam and is a chartered accountant he can't go on living in a bed-sitting-room.”

“That's not a bad idea. I'll suggest it to him.”

“It would save an agent's fees. We could help him to furnish it. We've got a lot of stuff stored away. We might just as well let him use it as have it moulder away in the attics.”

Tom and Roger came back to eat an enormous tea and then played tennis till the light failed. After dinner they played dominoes. Julia gave a beautiful performance of a still-young mother fondly watching her son and his boy friend. She went to bed early. Presently they too went upstairs. Their rooms were just over hers. She heard Roger go into Tom's room. They began talking, her windows and theirs were open, and she heard their voices in animated conversation. She wondered with exasperation what they found to say to one another. She had never found either of them very talkative. After a while Michael's voice interrupted them.

“Now then, you kids, you go to bed. You can go on talking tomorrow.”

She heard them laugh.

“All right, Daddy,” cried Roger.

“A pair of damned chatterboxes, that's what you are.”

She heard Roger's voice again.

“Well, good-night, old boy.”

And Tom's hearty answer: “So long, old man.”

“Idiots!” she said to herself crossly.

Next morning while she was having her breakfast Michael came into Julia's room.

“The boys have gone off to play golf at Huntercombe. They want to play a couple of rounds and they asked if they need come back to lunch. I told them that was quite all right.”

“I don't know that I particularly like the idea of Tom treating the house as if it was a hotel.”

“Oh, my dear, they're only a couple of kids. Let them have all the fun they can get, I say.”

She would not see Tom at all that day, for she had to start for London between five and six in order to get to the theatre in good time. It was all very well for Michael to be so damned good-natured about it. She was hurt. She felt a little inclined to cry. He must be entirely indifferent to her, it was Tom she was thinking of now; and she had made up her mind that today was going to be quite different from the day before. She had awakened determined to be tolerant and to take things as they came, but she hadn't been prepared for a smack in the face like this.

“Have the papers come yet?” she asked sulkily.

She drove up to town with rage in her heart.

The following day was not much better. The boys did not go off to play golf, but they played tennis. Their incessant activity profoundly irritated Julia. Tom in shorts, with his bare legs, and a cricket shirt, really did not look more than sixteen. Bathing as they did three or four times a day he could not get his hair to stay down, and the moment it was dry it spread over his head in unruly curls. It made him look younger than ever, but oh, so charming. Julia's heart was wrung. And it seemed to her that his demeanour had strangely changed; in the constant companionship of Roger he had shed the young man about town who was so careful of his dress, so particular about wearing the right thing, and was become again a sloppy little schoolboy. He never gave a hint, no glance even betrayed, that he was her lover; he treated her as if she were no more than Roger's mother. In every remark he made, in his mischievousness, in his polite little ways, he made her feel that she belonged to an older generation. His behaviour had nothing of the chivalrous courtesy a young man might show to a fascinating woman; it was the tolerant kindness he might display to a maiden aunt.

Julia was irritated that Tom should docilely follow the lead of a boy so much younger than himself. It indicated lack of character. But she did not blame him; she blamed Roger. Roger's selfishness revolted her. It was all very well to say he was young. His indifference to anyone's pleasure but his own showed a vile disposition. He was tactless and inconsiderate. He acted as though the house, the servants, his father and mother were there for his particular convenience. She would often have been rather sharp with him, but that she did not dare before Tom assume the role of the correcting mother. And when you reproved Rogerhe had a maddening way of looking deeply hurt, like a stricken hind, which made you feel that you had been unkind and unjust. She could look like that too, it was an expression of the eyes that he had inherited from her; she had used it over and over again on the stage with moving effect, and she knew it need not mean very much, but when she saw it in his it shattered her. The mere thought of it now made her feel tenderly towards him. And that sudden change of feeling showed her the truth; she was jealous of Roger, madly jealous. The realization gave her something of a shock; she did not know whether to laugh or to be ashamed. She reflected a moment.

“Well, I'll cook his goose all right.”

She was not going to let the following Sunday pass like the last. Thank God, Tom was a snob. “A woman attracts men by her charm and holds them by their vices,” she murmured and wondered whether she had invented the aphorism or remembered it from some play she had once acted in.

She gave instructions for some telephoning to be done. She got the Dennorants to come for the weekend. Charles Tamerley was staying at Henley and accepted an invitation to come over for Sunday and bring his host, Sir Mayhew Bryanston, who was Chancellor of the Exchequer. To amuse him and the Dennorants, because she knew that the upper classes do not want to meet one another in what they think is Bohemia, but artists of one sort or another, she asked Archie Dexter, her leading man, and his pretty wife who acted under her maiden name of Grace Hardwill. She felt pretty sure that with a marquess and marchioness to hover round and a Cabinet Minister to be impressed by, Tom would not go off to play golf with Roger or spend the afternoon in a punt. In such a party Roger would sink into his proper place of a schoolboy that no one took any notice of, and Tom would see how brilliant she could be when she took the trouble. In the anticipation of her triumph she managed to bear the intervening days with fortitude. She saw little of Roger and Tom. On her matinée days she did not see them at all. If they were not playing some game they were careering about the country in Roger's car.

Julia drove the Dennorants down after the play. Roger had gone to bed, but Michael and Tom were waiting up to have supper with them. It was a very good supper. The servants had gone to bed too and they helped themselves. Julia noticed the shy eagerness with which Tom saw that the Dennorants had everything they wanted, and his alacrity to jump up if he could be of service. His civility was somewhat officious. The Dennorants were an unassuming young couple to whom it had never occurred that their rank could impress anyone, and George Dennorant was a little embarrassed when Tom took away his dirty plate and handed him a dish to help himself to the next course.

“No golf for Roger tomorrow, I think,” said Julia to herself.

They stayed up talking and laughing till three in the morning, and when Tom said good-night to her his eyes were shining; but whether from love or champagne she did not know. He pressed her hand.

“What a lovely party,” he said.

It was late when Julia, dressed in organdie, looking her best, came down into the garden. She saw Roger in a long chair with a book.

“Reading?” she said, lifting her really beautiful eyebrows. “Why aren't you playing golf?”

Roger looked a trifle sulky.

“Tom said it was too hot.”

“Oh?” she smiled charmingly. “I was afraid you thought you ought to stay and entertain my guests. There are going to be so many people, we could easily have managed without you. Where are the others?”

“I don't know. Tom's making chichi with Cecily Dennorant.”

“She's very pretty, you know.”

“It looks to me as though it's going to be a crashing bore today.”

“I hope Tom won't find it so,” she said, as though she were seriously concerned.

Roger remained silent.

The day passed exactly as she had hoped. It was true that she saw little of Tom, but Roger saw less. Tom made a great hit with the Dennorants; he explained to them how they could get out of paying as much income tax as they did. He listened respectfully to the Chancellor while he discoursed on the stage and to Archie Dexter while he gave his views on the political situation. Julia was at the top of her form. Archie Dexter had a quick wit, a fund of stage stories and a wonderful gift for telling them; between the two of them they kept the table during lunch laughing uproariously; and after tea, when the tennis players were tired of playing tennis, Julia was persuaded (not much against her will) to do her imitations of Gladys Cooper, Constance Collier and Gertie Lawrence. But Julia did not forget that Charles Tamerley was her devoted, unrewarded lover, and she took care to have a little stroll alone with him in the gloaming. With him she sought to be neither gay nor brilliant, she was tender and wistful. Her heart ached, notwithstanding the scintillating performance she had given during the day; and it was with almost complete sincerity that with sighs, sad looks and broken sentences she made him understand that her life was hollow and despite the long-continued success of her career she could not but feel that she had missed something. Sometimes she thought of the villa at Sorrento on the bay of Naples. A beautiful dream. Happiness might have been hers for the asking, perhaps; she had been a fool; after all what were the triumphs of the stage but illusion? Pagliacci. People never realized how true that was; Vesti la giubba and all that sort of thing. She was desperately lonely. Of course there was no need to tell Charles that her heart ached not for lost opportunities, but because a young man seemed to prefer playing golf with her son to making love to her.

But then Julia and Archie Dexter got together. After dinner when they were all sitting in the drawing-room, without warning, starting with a few words of natural conversation they burst, as though they were lovers, into a jealous quarrel. For a moment the rest did not realize it was a joke till their mutual accusations became so outrageous and indecent that they were consumed with laughter. Then they played an extempore scene of an intoxicated gentleman picking up a French tart in Jermyn Street. After that, with intense seriousness, while their little audience shook with laughter, they did Mrs. Alving in Ghosts trying to seduce Pastor Manders. They finished with a performance that they had given often enough before at theatrical parties to enable them to do it with effect. This was a Chekhov play in English, but in moments of passion breaking into something that sounded exactly like Russian. Julia exercised all her great gift for tragedy, but underlined it with a farcical emphasis, so that the effect was incredibly funny. She put into her performance the real anguish of her heart, and with her lively sense of the ridiculous made a mock of it. The audience rolled about in their chairs; they held their sides; they groaned in an agony of laughter. Perhaps Julia had never acted before. She was acting for Tom and for him alone.

“I've seen Bernhardt and Réjane,” said the Chancellor; “I've seen Duse and Ellen Terry and Mrs. Kendal. Nunc Dimittis.”

Julia, radiant, sank back into a chair and swallowed at a draught a glass of champagne.

“If I haven't cooked Roger's goose I'll eat my hat,” she thought.

But for all that the two lads had gone off to play golf when she came downstairs next morning. Michael had taken the Dennorants up to town. Julia was tired. She found it an effort to be bright and chatty when Tom and Roger came in to lunch. In the afternoon the three of them went on the river, but Julia had the feeling that they took her, not because they much wanted to, but because they could not help it. She stifled a sigh when she reflected how much she had looked forward to Tom's holiday. Now she was counting the days that must pass till it ended. She drew a deep breath of relief when she got into the car to go to London. She was not angry with Tom, but deeply hurt; she was exasperated with herself because she had so lost control over her feelings. But when she got into the theatre she felt that she shook off the obsession of him like a bad dream from which one awoke; there, in her dressing-rom, she regained possession of herself and the affairs of the common round of daily life faded to insignificance. Nothing really mattered when she had within her grasp this possibility of freedom.

Thus the week went by. Michael, Roger and Tom enjoyed themselves. They bathed, they played tennis, they played golf, they lounged about on the river. There were only four days more. There were only three days more.

(“I can stick it out now. It'll be different when we're back in London again. I mustn't show how miserable I am. I must pretend it's all right.”)

“A snip having this spell of fine weather,” said Michael. “Tom's been a success, hasn't he? Pity he can't stay another week.”

“Yes, a terrible pity.”

“I think he's a nice friend for Roger to have. A thoroughly normal, clean-minded English boy.”

“Oh, thoroughly.” (“Bloody fool, bloody fool.”)

“To see the way they eat is a fair treat.”

“Yes, they seem to have enjoyed their food.” (“My God, I wish it could have choked them.”)

Tom was to go up to town by an early train on Monday morning. The Dexters, who had a house at Bourne End, had asked them all to lunch on Sunday. They were to go down in the launch. Now that Tom's holiday was nearly over Julia was glad that she had never by so much as a lifted eyebrow betrayed her irritation. She was certain that he had no notion how deeply he had wounded her. After all she must be tolerant, he was only a boy, and if you must cross your t's, she was old enough to be his mother. It was a bore that she had a thing about him, but there it was, she couldn't help it; she had told herself from the beginning that she must never let him feel that she had any claims on him. No one was coming to dinner on Sunday. She would have liked to have Tom to herself on his last evening; that was impossible, but at all events they could go for a stroll by themselves in the garden.

“I wonder if he's noticed that he hasn't kissed me since he came here?”

They might go out in the punt. It would be heavenly to lie in his arms for a few minutes; it would make up for everything.

The Dexters' party was theatrical. Grace Hardwill, Archie's wife, played in musical comedy, and there was a bevy of pretty girls who danced in the piece in which she was then appearing. Julia acted with great naturalness the part of a leading lady who put on no frills. She was charming to the young ladies, with their waved platinum hair, who earned three pounds a week in the chorus. A good many of the guests had brought kodaks and she submitted with affability to being photographed. She applauded enthusiastically when Grace Hardwill sang her famous song to the accompaniment of the composer. She laughed as heartily as anyone when the comic woman did an imitation of her in one of her best-known parts. It was all very gay, rather rowdy, and agreeably light-hearted. Julia enjoyed herself, but when it was seven o'clock was not sorry to go. She was thanking her hosts effusively for the pleasant party when Roger came up to her.

“I say, Mum, there's a whole crowd going on to Maidenhead to dine and dance, and they want Tom and me to go too. You don't mind, do you?”

The blood rushed to her cheeks. She could not help answering rather sharply.

“How are you to get back?”

“Oh, that'll be all right. We'll get someone to drop us.”

She looked at him helplessly. She could not think what to say.

“It's going to be a tremendous lark. Tom's crazy to go.”

Her heart sank. It was with the greatest difficulty that she managed not to make a scene. But she controlled herself.

“All right, darling. But don't be too late. Remember that Tom's got to rise with the lark.”

Tom had come up and heard the last words.

“You're sure you don't mind?” he asked.

“Of course not. I hope you'll have a grand time.”

She smiled brightly at him, but her eyes were steely with hatred.

“I'm just as glad those two kids have gone off,” said Michael when they got into the launch. “We haven't had an evening to ourselves for ever so long.”

She clenched her hands in order to prevent herself from telling him to hold his silly tongue. She was in a black rage. This was the last straw. Tom had neglected her for a fortnight, he had not even treated her with civility, and she had been angelic. There wasn't a woman in the world who would have shown such patience. Any other woman would have told him that if he couldn't behave with common decency he'd better get out. Selfish, stupid and common, that's what he was. She almost wished he wasn't going tomorrow so that she could have the pleasure of turning him out bag and baggage. And to dare to treat her like that, a twopenny-halfpenny little man in the city; poets, cabinet ministers, peers of the realm would be only to glad to break the most important engagements to have the chance of dining with her, and he threw her over to go and dance with a pack of peroxide blondes who couldn't act for nuts. That showed what a fool he was. You would have thought he'd have some gratitude. Why, the very clothes he had on she'd paid for. That cigarette-case he was so proud of, hadn't she given him that? And the ring he wore. My God, she'd get even with him. Yes, and she knew how she could do it. She knew where he was most sensitive and how she could most cruelly wound him. That would get him on the raw. She felt a faint sensation of relief as she turned the scheme over in her mind. She was impatient to carry out her part of it at once, and they had no sooner got home than she went up to her room. She got four single pounds out of her bag and a ten-shilling note. She wrote a brief letter.

DEAR TOM,

I'm enclosing the money for your tips as I shan't see you in the morning. Give three pounds to the butler, a pound to the maid who's been valeting you, and ten shillings to the chauffeur.

JULIA.

She sent for Evie and gave instructions that the letter should be given to Tom by the maid who awoke him. When she went down to dinner she felt much better. She carried on an animated conversation with Michael while they dined and afterwards they played six-pack bezique. If she had racked her brains for a week she couldn't have thought of anything that would humiliate Tom more bitterly.

But when she went to bed she could not sleep. She was waiting for Roger and Tom to come home. A notion came to her that made her restless. Perhaps Tom would realize that he had behaved rottenly, if he gave it a moment's thought he must see how unhappy he was making her; it might be that he would be sorry and when he came in, after he had said good-night to Roger, he would creep down to her room. If he did that she would forgive everything. The letter was probably in the butler's pantry; she could easily slip down and get it back. At last a car drove up. She turned on her light to look at the time. It was three. She heard the two young men go upstairs and to their respective rooms. She waited. She put on the light by her bedside so that when he opened the door he should be able to see. She would pretend she was sleeping and then as he crept forward on tiptoe slowly open her eyes and smile at him. She waited. In the silent night she heard him get into bed and switch off the light. She stared straight in front of her for a minute, then with a shrug of the shoulders opened a drawer by her bedside and from a little bottle took a couple of sleeping-tablets.

“If I don't sleep I shall go mad.”

Chapter 15

Julia did not wake till after eleven. Among her letters was one that had not come by post. She recognized Tom's neat, commercial hand and tore it open. It contained nothing but the four pounds and the ten-shilling note. She felt slightly sick. She did not quite know what she had expected him to reply to her condescending letter and the humiliating present. It had not occurred to her that he would return it. She was troubled, she had wanted to hurt his feelings, but she had a fear now that she had gone too far.

“Anyhow I hope he tipped the servants,” she muttered to reassure herself. She shrugged her shoulders. “He'll come round. It won't hurt him to discover that I'm not all milk and honey.”

But she remained thoughtful throughout the day. When she got to the theatre a parcel was waiting for her. As soon as she looked at the address she knew what it contained. Evie asked if she should open it.

“No.”

But the moment she was alone she opened it herself. There were the cuff-links and the waistcoat buttons, the pearl studs, the wrist-watch and the cigarette-case of which Tom was so proud. Not a word of explanation. Her heart sank and she noticed that she was trembling.

“What a damned fool I was! Why didn't I keep my temper?”

Her heart now beat painfully. She couldn't go on the stage with that anguish gnawing at her vitals, she would give a frightful performance; at whatever cost she must speak to him. There was a telephone in his house and an extension to his room. She rang him. Fortunately he was in.

“Tom.”

“Yes?”

He had paused for a moment before answering and his voice was peevish.

“What does this mean? Why have you sent me all those things?

“Did you get the notes this morning?”

“Yes. I couldn't make head or tail of it. Have I offended you?”

“Oh, no,” he answered. “I like being treated like a kept boy. I like having it thrown in my face that even my tips have to be given me. I thought it rather strange that you didn't send me the money for a third-class ticket back to London.”

Although Julia was in a pitiable state of anxiety, so that she could hardly get the words out of her mouth, she almost smiled at his fatuous irony. He was a silly little thing.

“But you can't imagine that I wanted to hurt your feelings. You surely know me well enough to know that's the last thing I should do.”

“That only makes it worse.” (“Damn and curse,” thought Julia.) “I ought never to have let you make me those presents. I should never have let you lend me money.”

“I don't know what you mean. It's all some horrible misunderstanding. Come and fetch me after the play and we'll have it out. I know I can explain.”

“I'm going to dinner with my people and I shall sleep at home.”

“Tomorrow then.”

“I'm engaged tomorrow.”

“I must see you, Tom. We've been too much to one another to part like this. You can't condemn me unheard. It's so unjust to punish me for no fault of mine.”

“I think it's much better that we shouldn't meet again.”

Julia was growing desperate.

“But I love you, Tom. I love you. Let me see you once more and then, if you're still angry with me, we'll call it a day.”

There was a long pause before he answered.

“All right. I'll come after the matinée on Wednesday.”

“Don't think unkindly of me, Tom.”

She put down the receiver. At all events he was coming. She wrapped up again the things he had returned to her, and hid them away where she was pretty sure Evie would not see them. She undressed, put on her old pink dressing-gown and began to make up. She was out of humour: this was the first time she had ever told him that she loved him. It vexed her that she had been forced to humiliate herself by begging him to come and see her. Till then it had always been he who sought her company. She was not pleased to think that the situation between them now was openly reversed.

Julia gave a very poor performance at the matinée on Wednesday. The heat wave had affected business and the house was apathetic. Julia was indifferent. With that sickness of apprehension gnawing at her heart she could not care how the play went. (“What the hell do they want to come to the theatre for on a day like this anyway?”) She was glad when it was over.

“I'm expecting Mr. Fennell,” she told Evie. “While he's here I don't want to be disturbed.”

Evie did not answer. Julia gave her a glance and saw that she was looking grim.

(“To hell with her. What do I care what she thinks!”)

He ought to have been there by now. It was after five. He was bound to come; after all, he'd promised, hadn't he? She put on a dressing-gown, not the one she made up in, but a man's dressing-gown, in plum-coloured silk. Evie took an interminable time to put things straight.

“For God's sake don't fuss, Evie. Leave me alone.”

Evie did not speak. She went on methodically arranging the various objects on the dressing-table exactly as Julia always wanted them.

“Why the devil don't you answer when I speak to you?”

Evie turned round and looked at her. She thoughtfully rubbed her finger along her nostrils.

“Great actress you may be…”

“Get the hell out of here.”

After taking off her stage make-up Julia had done nothing to her face except put the very faintest shading of blue under her eyes. She had a smooth, pale skin and without rouge on her cheeks or red on her lips she looked wan. The man's dressing-gown gave an effect at once helpless, fragile and gallant. Her heart was beating painfully and she was very anxious, but looking at herself in the glass she murmured: Mimi in the last act of Bohème. Almost without meaning to she coughed once or twice consumptively. She turned off the bright lights on her dressing-table and lay down on the sofa. Presently there was a knock at the door and Evie announced Mr. Fennell. Julia held out a white, thin hand.

“I'm lying down. I'm afraid I'm not very well. Find yourself a chair. It's nice of you to come.”

“I'm sorry. What's the matter?”

“Oh, nothing.” She forced a smile to her ashy lips. “I haven't been sleeping very well the last two or three nights.”

She turned her beautiful eyes on him and for a while gazed at him in silence. His expression was sullen, but she had a notion that he was frightened.

“I'm waiting for you to tell me what you've got against me,” she said at last in a low voice.

It trembled a little, she noticed, but quite naturally. (“Christ, I believe I'm frightened too.”)

“There's no object in going back to that. The only thing I wanted to say to you was this: I'm afraid I can't pay you the two hundred pounds I owe you right away, I simply haven't got it, but I'll pay you by degrees. I hate having to ask you to give me time, but I can't help myself.”

She sat up on the sofa and put both her hands to her breaking heart.

“I don't understand. I've lain awake for two whole nights turning it all over in my mind. I thought I should go mad. I've been trying to understand. I can't. I can't.”

(“What play did I say that in?”)

“Oh yes, you can, you understand perfectly. You were angry with me and you wanted to get back on me. And you did. You got back on me all right. You couldn't have shown your contempt for me more clearly.”

“But why should I want to get back on you? Why should I be angry with you?”

“Because I went to Maidenhead with Roger to that party and you wanted me to come home.”

“But I told you to go. I said I hoped you'd have a good time.”

“I know you did, but your eyes were blazing with passion. I didn't want to go, but Roger was keen on it. I told him I thought we ought to come back and dine with you and Michael, but he said you'd be glad to have us off your hands, and I didn't like to make a song and dance about it. And when I saw you were in a rage it was too late to get out of it.”

“I wasn't in a rage. I can't think how you got such an idea in your head. It was so natural that you should want to go to the party. You can't think I'm such a beast as to grudge you a little fun in your fortnight's holiday. My poor lamb, my only fear was that you would be bored. I so wanted you to have a good time.”

“Then why did you send me that money and write me that letter? It was so insulting.”

Julia's voice faltered. Her jaw began to tremble and the loss of control over her muscles was strangely moving. Tom looked away uneasily.

“I couldn't bear to think of you having to throw away your good money on tips. I know that you're not terribly rich and I knew you'd spent a lot on green fees. I hate women who go about with young men and let them pay for everything. It's so inconsiderate. I treated you just as I'd have treated Roger. I never thought it would hurt your feelings.”

“Will you swear that?”

“Of course I will. My God, is it possible that after all these months you don't know me better than that? If what you think were true, what a mean, cruel, despicable woman I should be, what a cad, what a heartless, vulgar beast! Is that what you think I am?”

A poser.

“Anyhow it doesn't matter. I ought never to have accepted valuable presents from you and allowed you to lend me money. It's put me in a rotten position. Why I thought you despised me is that I can't help feeling that you've got a right to. The fact is I can't afford to run around with people who are so much richer than I am. I was a fool to think I could. It's been fun and I've had a grand time, but now I'm through. I'm not going to see you any more.”

She gave a deep sigh.

“You don't care two hoots for me. That's what that means.”

“That's not fair.”

“You're everything in the world to me. You know that. I'm so lonely and your friendship meant a great deal to me. I'm surrounded by hangers-on and parasites and I knew you were disinterested. I felt I could rely on you. I so loved being with you. You were the only person in the world with whom I could be entirely myself. Don't you know what a pleasure it was to me to help you a little? It wasn't for your sake I made you little presents, it was for my own; it made me so happy to see you using the things I'd given you. If you'd cared for me at all they wouldn't have humiliated you, you'd have been touched to owe me something.”

She turned her eyes on him once more. She could always cry easily, and she was really so miserable now that she did not have to make even a small effort. He had never seen her cry before. She could cry, without sobbing, her wonderful dark eyes wide open, with a face that was almost rigid. Great heavy tears ran down it. And her quietness, the immobility of the tragic body, were terribly moving. She hadn't cried like that since she cried in The Stricken Heart. Christ, how that play had shattered her. She was not looking at Tom, she was looking straight in front of her; she was really distracted with grief, but, what was it? Another self within her knew what she was doing, a self that shared in her unhappiness and yet watched its expression. She felt him go white. She felt a sudden anguish wring his heartstrings, she felt that his flesh and blood could not support the intolerable pain of hers.

“Julia.”

His voice was broken. She slowly turned her liquid eyes on him. It was not a woman crying that he saw, it was all the woe of human kind, it was the immeasurable, the inconsolable grief that is the lot of man. He threw himself down on his knees and took her in his arms. He was shattered.

“Dearest, dearest.”

For a minute she did not move. It was as if she did not know that he was there. He kissed her streaming eyes and with his mouth sought hers. She gave it to him as though she were powerless, as though, scarcely conscious of what was befalling her, she had no will left. With a scarcely perceptible movement she pressed her body to his and gradually her arms found their way round his neck. She lay in his arms, not exactly inert, but as though all the strength, all the vitality, had gone out of her. In his mouth he tasted the saltness of her tears. At last, exhausted, clinging to him with soft arms she sank back on the sofa. His lips clung to hers.

You would never have thought had you seen her a quarter of an hour later, so quietly gay, flushed a little, that so short a while before she had passed through such a tempest of weeping. They each had a whisky and soda and a cigarette and looked at one another with fond eyes.

“He's a sweet little thing,” she thought.

It occurred to her that she would give him a treat.

“The Duke and Duchess of Rickaby are coming to the play tonight and we're going to have supper at the Savoy. I suppose you wouldn't come, would you? I want a man badly to make a fourth.”

“If you'd like me to, of course I will.”

The heightened colour on his cheeks told her how excited he was to meet such distinguished persons. She did not tell him that the Rickabys would go anywhere for a free meal. Tom took back the presents that he had returned to her rather shyly, but he took them. When he had gone she sat down at the dressing-table and had a good look at herself.

“How lucky I am that I can cry without my eyelids swelling,” she said. She massaged them a little. “All the same, what mugs men are.”

She was happy. Everything would be all right now. She had got him back. But somewhere, at the back of her mind or in the bottom of her heart, was a feeling of ever so slight contempt for Tom because he was such a simple fool.

Chapter 16

Their quarrel, destroying in some strange way the barrier between them, brought them closer together. Tom offered less resistance than she had expected when she mooted once more the question of the flat. It looked as though, after their reconciliation, having taken back her presents and consented to forget the loan,he had put aside his moral scruples. They had a lot of fun furnishing it. The chauffeur's wife kept it clean for him and cooked his breakfast. Julia had a key and would sometimes let herself in and sit by herself in the little sitting-room till he came back from his office. They supped together two or three times a week and danced, then drove back to the flat in a taxi. Julia enjoyed a happy autumn. The play they put on was a success. She felt alert and young. Roger was coming home at Christmas, but only for a fortnight, and was then going to Vienna. Julia expected him to monopolize Tom and she was determined not to mind. Youth naturally appealed to youth and she told herself that there was no reason for her to feel anxious if for a few days the two of them were so wrapped up in one another that Tom had no thought for her. She held him now. He was proud to be her lover, it gave him confidence in himself, and he was pleased to be on familiar terms with a large number of more or less distinguished persons whom after all he only knew through her. He was anxious now to join a good club and Julia was preparing the ground. Charles had never refused her anything, and with tact she was certain that she could wheedle him into proposing Tom for one of those to which he belonged. It was a new and delicious sensation for Tom to have money to spend; she encouraged him to be extravagant; she had a notion that he would get used to living in a certain way and then would realize that he could not do without her.

“Of course it can't last,” she told herself, “but when it comes to an end it will have been a wonderful experience for him. It'll really have made a man of him.”

But though she told herself that it could not last she did not see really why it shouldn't. As the years went by and he grew older there wouldn't be any particular difference between them. He would no longer be so very young in ten or fifteen years and she would be just the same age as she was now. They were very comfortable together. Men were creatures of habit; that gave women such a hold on them. She did not feel a day older than he, and she was convinced that the disparity in their ages had never even occurred to him. It was true that on this point she had once had a moment's disquietude. She was lying on his bed. He was standing at the dressing-table, in his shirt sleeves, brushing his hair. She was stark naked and she lay in the position of a Venus by Titian that she remembered to have seen in a country house at which she had stayed. She felt that she made really a lovely picture, and in complete awareness of the charming sight she offered, held the pose. She was happy and satisfied.

“This is romance,” she thought, and a light, quick smile hovered over her lips.

He caught sight of her in the mirror, turned round and without a word, twitched the sheet over her. Though she smiled at him affectionately, it gave her quitea turn. Was he afraid that she would catch cold, or was it that his English modesty was shocked at her nakedness? Or could it be that, his boyish lust satisfied, he was a trifle disgusted at the sight of her ageing body? When she got home she again took all her clothes off and examined herself in the looking-glass. She determined not to spare herself. She looked at her neck, there was no sign of age there, especially when she held her chin up; and her breasts were small and firm; they might have been a girl's. Her belly was flat, her hips were small, there was a very small roll of fat there, like a long sausage, but everyone had that, and anyhow Miss Phillips could have a go at it. No one could say that her legs weren't good, they were long and slim and comely; she passed her hands over her body, her skin was as soft as velvet and there wasn't a blemish on it. Of course there were a few wrinkles under her eyes, but you had to peer to see them; they said there was an operation now by which you could get rid of them, it might be worth while to inquire into that; it was lucky that her hair had retained its colour; however well hair was dyed, to dye hardened the face; hers remained a rich, deep brown. Her teeth were all right too.

“Prudishness, that's all it was.”

She had a moment's recollection of the Spaniard with the beard in the wagon-lit and she smiled roguishly at herself in the glass.

“No damned modesty about him.”

But all the same from that day on she took care to act up to Tom's standards of decency.

Julia's reputation was so good that she felt she need not hesitate to show herself with Tom in public places. It was a new experience for her to go to night-clubs, she enjoyed it, and though no one could have been better aware than she that she could go nowhere without being stared at, it never entered her head that such a change in her habits must excite comment. With twenty years of fidelity behind her, for of course she did not count the Spaniard, an accident that might happen to any woman, Julia was confident that no one would imagine for a moment that she was having an affair with a boy young enough to be her son. It never occurred to her that perhaps Tom was not always so discreet as he might have been. It never occurred to her that the look in her eyes when they danced together betrayed her. She looked upon her position as so privileged that it never occurred to her that people at last were beginning to gossip.

When this gossip reached the ears of Dolly de Vries she laughed. At Julia's request she had invited Tom to parties and once or twice had him down for a weekend in the country, but she had never paid any attention to him. He seemed a nice little thing, a useful escort for Julia when Michael was busy, but perfectly insignificant. He was one of those persons who everywhere pass unnoticed, and even after you had met him you could not remember what he was like. He was the extra man you invited to dinner to make an odd number even. Julia talked of him gaily as “me boy friend” or as “my young man”; she could hardly have been so cool about it, so open, if there were anything in it. Besides, Dolly knew very well that the only two men there had ever been in Julia's life were Michael and Charles Tamerley. But it was funny of Julia, after taking so much care of herself for years, suddenly to start going to night-clubs three or four times a week. Dolly had seen little of her of late and indeed had been somewhat piqued by her neglect. She had many friends in theatrical circles and she began to make enquiries. She did not at all like what she heard. She did not know what to think. One thing was evident, Julia couldn't know what was being said about her, and someone must tell her. Not she; she hadn't the courage. Even after all these years she was a little frightened of Julia. Julia was a very good-tempered woman, and though her language was often brusque it was hard to ruffle her; but there was something about her that prevented you from taking liberties with her; you had a feeling that if once you went too far you would regret it. But something must be done. Dolly turned the matter over in her mind for a fortnight, anxiously; she tried to put her own wounded feelings aside and look at it only from the point of view of Julia's career, and at last she came to the conclusion that Michael must speak to her. She had never liked Michael, but after all he was Julia's husband and it was her duty to tell him at least enough to make him put a stop to whatever was going on.

She rang Michael up and made an appointment with him at the theatre. Michael liked Dolly as little as she liked him, though for other reasons, and when he heard that she wanted to see him he swore. He was annoyed that he had never been able to induce her to sell out her shares in the management, and he resented whatever suggestions she made as an unwarrantable interference. But when she was shown in to his office he greeted her with cordiality. He kissed her on both cheeks.

“Sit down and make yourself comfy. Come to see that the old firm's still raking in dividends for you?”

Dolly de Vries was now a woman of sixty. She was very fat, and her face, with its large nose and heavy red lips, seemed larger than life. There was a slightly masculine touch in her black satin dress, but she wore a double string of pearls round her neck, a diamond brooch at her waist and another in her hat. Her short hair was dyed a rich copper. Her lips and her fingernails were bright red. Her voice was loud and deep, but when she got excited the words were apt to tumble over one another and a slight cockney accent revealed itself.

“Michael, I'm upset about Julia.”

Michael, always the perfect gentleman, slightly raised his eyebrows and compressed his thin lips. He was not prepared to discuss his wife even with Dolly.

“I think she's doing a great deal too much. I don't know what's come over her. All these parties she's going to now. These nightclubs and things. After all,she's not a young woman any more; she'll just wear herself out.”

“Oh, nonsense. She's as strong as a horse and she's in the best of health. She's looking younger than she has for years. You're not going to grudge her a bit of fun when her day's work is over. The part she's playing just now doesn't take it out of her; I'm very glad that she should want to go out and amuse herself. It only shows how much vitality she has.”

“She never cared for that sort of thing before. It seems so strange that she should suddenly take to dancing till two in the morning in the horrible atmosphere of those places.”

“It's the only exercise she gets. I can't expect her to put on shorts and come for a run with me in the park.”

“I think you ought to know that people are beginning to talk. It's doing her reputation a lot of harm.”

“What the devil d'you mean by that?”

“Well, it's absurd that at her age she should make herself so conspicuous with a young boy.”

He looked at her for a moment without understanding, and when he caught what she meant he laughed loud.

“Tom? Don't be such a fool, Dolly.”

“I'm not a fool. I know what I'm talking about. When anyone's as well known as Julia and she's always about with the same man naturally people talk.”

“But Tom's just as much my friend as hers. You know very well that I can't take Julia out dancing. I have to get up every morning at eight to get my exercise in before my day's work. Hang it all, I do know something about human nature after thirty years on the stage. Tom's a very good type of clean, honest English boy and he's by way of being a gentleman. I daresay he admires Julia, boys of that age often think they're in love with women older than themselves, well, it won't do him any harm, it'll do him good; but to think Julia could possibly give him a thought—my poor Dolly, you make me laugh.”

“He's boring, he's dull, he's common and he's a snob.”

“Well, if you think he's all that doesn't it strike you as rather strange that Julia should be so wrapped up in him as you seem to think?”

“Only a woman knows what a woman can do.”

“That's not a bad line, Dolly. We shall have you writing a play next. Now let's get this straight. Can you look me in the face and tell me that you really think Julia is having an affair with Tom?”

She looked him in the face. Her eyes were anguished. For though at first she had only laughed at what was being said about Julia she had not been able altogether to suppress the doubts that soon assailed her; she remembered a dozen little incidents that at the time had escaped her notice, but when considered in cold blood looked terribly suspicious. She had suffered such torture as she had never thought it possible to endure. Proof? She had no proof; she only had an intuition that she could not mistrust; she wanted to say yes, the impulse to do so was almost uncontrollable; she controlled it. She could not give Julia away. The fool might go and tell her and Julia would never speak to her again. He might have Julia watched and catch her out. No one could tell what might happen if she told the truth.

“No, I don't.”

Her eyes filled with tears and began to roll down her massive cheeks. Michael saw her misery. He thought her ridiculous, but he realized that she was suffering and in the kindness of his heart sought to console her.

“I was sure you didn't really. You know how fond Julia is of you, you mustn't be jealous, you know, if she has other friends.”

“God knows I don't grudge her anything,” she sobbed. “She's been so different to me lately. She's been so cold. I've been such a loyal friend to her, Michael.”

“Yes, dear, I know you have.”

“Had I but served my God with half the zeal I served my King…”

“Oh, come now, it's not so bad as that. You know, I'm not the sort of chap to talk about his wife to other people. I always think that's such frightfully bad form. But you know, honestly you don't know the first thing about Julia. Sex doesn't mean a thing to her. When we were first married it was different, and I don't mind telling you after all these years that she made life a bit difficult for me. I don't say she was a nymphomaniac or anything like that, but she was inclined to be rather tiresome sometimes. Bed's all very well in its way, but there are other things in life. But after Roger was born she changed completely. Having a baby settled her. All those instincts went into her acting. You've read Freud, Dolly; what does he call it when that happens?”

“Oh, Michael, what do I care about Freud?”

“Sublimation. That's it. I often think that's what's made her such a great actress. Acting's a whole-time job, and if you want to be really good you've got to give your whole self to it. I'm so impatient with the public who think actors and actresses lead a devil of a life. We haven't got the time for that sort of nonsense.”

What Michael was saying made her so angry that she recovered her self-control.

“But Michael, it may be that you and I know that there's nothing wrong in Julia's going about all the time with that miserable little pip-squeak. It's so bad for her reputation. After all, one of your great assets has been your exemplary married life. Everyone has looked up to you. The public has loved to think of you as such a devoted and united couple.”

“And so we are, damn it.”

Dolly was growing impatient.

“But I tell you people are talking. You can't be so stupid as not to see that they're bound to. I mean, if Julia had had one flagrant affair after another, nobody would take any notice, but after the life she's led for so many years suddenly to break out like this— naturally everybody starts chattering. It's so bad for business.”

Michael gave her a swift glance. He smiled a little.

“I see what you mean, Dolly. I daresay there's something in what you say and in the circumstances I feel that you have a perfect right to say it. You were awfully good to us when we started and I should hate to see you let down now. I'll tell you what, I'll buy you out.”

“Buy me out?”

Dolly straightened herself and her face, a moment ago rumpled and discomposed, hardened. She was seized with indignation. He went on suavely.

“I see your point. If Julia's gadding about all night it must tell on her performances. That's obvious. She's got a funny sort of public, a lot of old ladies come to our matinées because they think she's such a sweet good woman. I don't mind admitting that if she gets herself unpleasantly talked about it might have some effect on the takings. I know Julia well enough to know that she wouldn't put up with any interference with her liberty of action. I'm her husband and I've got to put up with it. But you're in a different position altogether. I shouldn't blame you if you wanted to get out while the going was good.”

Dolly was alert now. She was far from a fool and when it came to business was a match for Michael. She was angry, but her anger gave her self-control.

“I should have thought after all these years, Michael, that you knew me better than that. I thought it my duty to warn you, but I'm prepared to take the rough with the smooth. I'm not the woman to desert a sinking ship. I daresay I can afford to lose my money better than you can.”

It gave her a great deal of satisfaction to see the disappointment that was clearly expressed on Michael's face. She knew how much money meant to him and she had a hope that what she had said would rankle. He pulled himself together quickly.

“Well, think it over, Dolly.”

She gathered up her bag and they parted with mutual expressions of affection and good will.

“Silly old bitch,” he said when the door was closed behind her.

“Pompous old ass,” she hissed as she went down in the lift.

But when she got into her magnificent and very expensive car and drove back to Montagu Square she could not hold back the heavy, painful tears that filled her eyes. She felt old, lonely, unhappy, and desperately jealous.

Chapter 17

Michael flattered himself on his sense of humour. On the Sunday evening that followed his conversation with Dolly he strolled into Julia's room while she was dressing. They were going to the pictures after an early dinner.

“Who's coming tonight besides Charles?” he asked her.

“I couldn't find another woman. I've asked Tom.”

“Good! I wanted to see him.”

He chuckled at the thought of the joke he had up his sleeve. Julia was looking forward to the evening. At the cinema she would arrange the seating so that Tom sat next to her and he would hold her hand while she chatted in undertones to Charles on the other side of her. Dear Charles, it was nice of him to have loved her so long and so devotedly; she would go out of her way to be very sweet to him. Charles and Tom arrived together. Tom was wearing his new dinner-jacket for the first time and he and Julia exchanged a little private glance, of satisfaction on his part and of compliment on hers.

“Well, young feller,” said Michael heartily, rubbing his hands, “do you know what I hear about you? I hear that you're compromising my wife.”

Tom gave him a startled look and went scarlet. The habit of flushing mortified him horribly, but he could not break himself of it.

“Oh, my dear,” cried Julia gaily, “how marvellous! I've been trying to get someone to compromise me all my life. Who told you, Michael?”

“A little bird,” he said archly.

“Well, Tom, if Michael divorces me you'll have to marry me, you know.”

Charles smiled with his gentle, rather melancholy eyes.

“What have you been doing, Tom?” he asked.

Charles was gravely, Michael boisterously, diverted by the young man's obvious embarrassment. Julia, though she seemed to share their amusement, was alert and watchful.

“Well, it appears that the young rip has been taking Julia to night-clubs when she ought to have been in bed and asleep.”

Julia crowed with delight.

“Shall we deny it, Tom, or shall we brazen it out?”

“Well, I'll tell you what I said to the little bird,” Michael broke in. “I said to her, as long as Julia doesn't want me to go to nightclubs with her…”

Julia ceased to listen to what he said. Dolly, she thought, and oddly enough she described her to herself in exactly the words Michael had used a couple of days before. Dinner was announced and their bright talk turned to other things. But though Julia took part in it with gaiety, though she appeared to be giving her guests all her attention and even listened with a show of appreciation to one of Michael's theatrical stories that she had heard twenty times before, she was privately holding an animated conversation with Dolly. Dolly cowered before her while she told her exactly what she thought of her.

“You old cow,” she said to her. “How dare you interfere with my private concerns? No, don't speak. Don't try to excuse yourself. I know exactly what you said to Michael. It was unpardonable. I thought you were a friend of mine. I thought I could rely on you. Well, that finishes it. I'll never speak to you again. Never. Never. D'you think I'm impressed by your rotten old money? Oh, it's no good saying you didn't mean it. Where would you be except for me, I should like to know. Any distinction you've got, the only importance you have in the world, is that you happen to know me. Who's made your parties go all these years? D'you think that people came to them to see you? They came to see me. Never again. Never.”

It was in point of fact a monologue rather than a conversation.

Later on, at the cinema, she sat next to Tom as she had intended and held his hand, but it seemed to her singularly unresponsive. Like a fish's fin. She suspected that he was thinking uncomfortably of what Michael had said. She wished that she had had an opportunity of a few words with him so that she might have told him not to worry. After all no one could have carried off the incident with more brilliance than she had. Aplomb; that was the word. She wondered what it was exactly that Dolly had told Michael. She had better find out. It would not do to ask Michael, that would look as though she attached importance to it; she must find out from Dolly herself. It would be much wiser not to have a row with her. Julia smiled as she thought of the scene she would have with Dolly. She would be sweetness itself, she would wheedle it all out of her, and never give her an inkling that she was angry. It was curious that it should send a cold shiver down her back to think that people were talking about her. After all if she couldn't do what she liked who could? Her private life was nobody's business. All the same one couldn't deny that it wouldn't be very nice if people were laughing at her. She wondered what Michael would do if he found out the truth. He couldn't very well divorce her and continue to manage for her. If he had any sense he'd shut his eyes. But Michael was funny in some ways; every now and then he would get up on his hind legs and start doing his colonel stuff. He was quite capable of saying all of a sudden that damn it all, he must behave like a gentleman. Men were such fools; there wasn't one of them who wouldn't cut off his nose to spite his face. Of course it wouldn't really matter very much to her. She could go and act in America for a year till the scandal had died down and then go into management with somebody else. But it would be a bore. And then there was Roger to consider; he'd feel it, poor lamb; he'd be humiliated, naturally; it was no good shutting one's eyes to the fact, at her age she'd look a perfect fool being divorced on account of a boy of three-and-twenty. Of course she wouldn't be such a fool as to marry Tom. Would Charles marry her? She turned and in the half-light looked at his distinguished profile. He had been madly in love with her for years; he was one of those chivalrous idiots that a woman could turn round her little finger; perhaps he wouldn't mind being co-respondent instead of Tom. That might be a very good way out. Lady Charles Tamerley. It sounded all right. Perhaps she had been a little imprudent. She had always been very careful when she went to Tom's flat, but it might be that one of the chauffeurs in the mews had seen her go in or come out and had thought things. That class of people had such filthy minds. As far as the night-clubs were concerned, she'd have been only too glad to go with Tom to quiet little places where no one would see them, but he didn't like that. He loved a crowd, he wanted to see smart people, and be seen. He liked to show her off.

“Damn,” she said to herself. “Damn, damn.”

Julia didn't enjoy her evening at the cinema as much as she had expected.

Chapter 18

Next day Julia got Dolly on her private number.

“Darling, it seems ages since I've seen you. What have you been doing with yourself all this time?”

“Nothing very much.”

Dolly's voice sounded cold.

“Now listen, Roger's coming home tomorrow. You know he's leaving Eton for good. I'm sending the car for him early and I want you to come to lunch. Not a party; only you and me, Michael and Roger.”

“I'm lunching out tomorrow.”

In twenty years Dolly had never been engaged when Julia wanted her to do something with her. The voice at the other end of the telephone was hostile.

“Dolly, how can you be so unkind? Roger'll be terribly disappointed. His first day at home; besides, I want to see you. I haven't seen you for ages and I miss you terribly. Can't you break your engagement, just for this once, darling, and we'll have a good old gossip after lunch, just you and me?”

No one could be more persuasive than Julia when she liked, no one could put more tenderness into her voice, nor a more irresistible appeal. There was a moment's pause and Julia knew that Dolly was struggling with her wounded feelings.

“All right, darling, I'll manage.”

“Darling.” But when she rang off Julia through clenched teeth muttered: “The old cow.”

Dolly came. Roger listened politely while she told him that he had grown and with his grave smile answered her suitably when she said the sort of things she thought proper to a boy of his age. Julia was puzzled by him. Without talking much he listened, apparently with attention, to what the rest of them were saying, but she had an odd feeling that he was occupied with thoughts of his own. He seemed to observe them with a detached curiosity like that with which he might have observed animals in a zoo. It was faintly disquieting. When the opportunity presented itself she delivered the little bit of dialogue she had prepared for Dolly's benefit.

“Oh, Roger darling, you know your wretched father's busy tonight. I've got a couple of seats for the second house at the Palladium and Tom wants you to dine with him at the Café Royal.”

“Oh!” He paused for a second. “All right.”

She turned to Dolly.

“It's so nice for Roger to have somebody like Tom to go about with. They're great friends, you know.”

Michael gave Dolly a glance. There was a twinkle in his eyes. He spoke.

“Tom's a very decent sort of boy. He won't let Roger get into any mischief.”

“I should have thought Roger would prefer to go about with his Eton friends,” said Dolly.

“Old cow,” thought Julia. “Old cow.”

But when lunch was over she asked her to come up to her room.

“I'll get into bed and you can talk to me while I'm resting. A good old girls' gossip, that's what I want.”

She put her arm affectionately round Dolly's vast waist and led her upstairs. For a while they spoke of indifferent things, clothes and servants, make-up and scandal; then Julia, leaning on her elbow, looked at Dolly with confiding eyes.

“Dolly, there's something I want to talk to you about. I want advice and you're the only person in the world whose advice I would take. I know I can trust you.”

“Of course, darling.”

“It appears that people are saying rather disagreeable things about me. Someone's been to Michael and told him that there's a lot of gossip about me and poor Tom Fennell.”

Though her eyes still wore the charming and appealing look that she knew Dolly found irresistible, she watched her closely for a start or for some change in her expression. She saw nothing.

“Who told Michael?”

“I don't know. He won't say. You know what he is when he starts being a perfect gentleman.”

She wondered if she only imagined that Dolly's features at this slightly relaxed.

“I want the truth, Dolly.”

“I'm so glad you've asked me, darling. You know how I hate to interfere in other people's business and if you hadn't brought the matter up yourself nothing would have induced me to mention it.”

“My dear, if I don't know that you're a loyal friend, who does?”

Dolly slipped off her shoes and settled down massively in her chair. Julia never took her eyes off her.

“You know how malicious people are. You've always led such a quiet, regular life. You've gone out so little, and then only with Michael or Charles Tamerley. He's different; of course everyone knows he's adored you for ages. It seems so funny that all of a sudden you should run around all over the place with a clerk in the firm that does your accounts.”

“He isn't exactly that. His father has bought him a share in the firm and he's a junior partner.”

“Yes, he gets four hundred a year.”

“How d'you know?” asked Julia quickly.

This time she was certain that Dolly was disconcerted.

“You persuaded me to go to his firm about my income tax. One of the head partners told me. It seems a little strange that on that he should be able to have a flat, dress the way he does and take people to night clubs.”

“For all I know his father may make him an allowance.”

“His father's a solicitor in the North of London. You know very well that if he's bought him a partnership he isn't making him an allowance as well.”

“Surely you don't imagine that I'm keeping him,” said Julia, with a ringing laugh.

“I don't imagine anything, darling. Other people do.”

Julia liked neither the words Dolly spoke nor the way she said them. But she gave no sign of her uneasiness.

“It's too absurd. He's Roger's friend much more than mine. Of course I've been about with him. I felt I was getting too set. I'm tired of just going to the theatre and taking care of myself. It's no life. After all if I don't enjoy myself a little now I never shall. I'm getting on, you know, Dolly, it's no good denying it. You know what Michael is; of course he's sweet, but he is a bore.”

“No more a bore than he's ever been,” said Dolly acidly.

“I should have thought I was the last person anyone would dream would have an affair with a boy twenty years younger than myself.”

“Twenty-five,” corrected Dolly. “I should have thought so too. Unfortunately he's not very discreet.”

“What do you mean by that?”

“Well, he's told Avice Crichton that he'll get her a part in your next play.”

“Who the devil is Avice Crichton?”

“Oh, she's a young actress I know. She's as pretty as a picture.”

“He's only a silly kid. I suppose he thinks he can get round Michael. You know what Michael is with his little bits.”

“He says he can get you to do anything he wants. He says you just eat out of his hand.”

It was lucky for Julia that she was a good actress. For a second her heart stood still. How could he say a thing like that? The fool. The blasted fool. But recovering herself at once she laughed lightly.

“What nonsense! I don't believe a word of it.”

“He's a very commonplace, rather vulgar young man. It's not surprising if all the fuss you've made of him has turned his head.”

Julia, smiling good-naturedly, looked at her with ingenuous eyes.

“But, darling, you don't think he's my lover, do you?”

“If I don't, I'm the only person who doesn't.”

“And do you?”

For a minute Dolly did not answer. They looked at one another steadily, their hearts were black with hatred; but Julia still smiled.

“If you give me your solemn word of honour that he isn't, of course I'll believe you.”

Julia dropped her voice to a low, grave note. It had a true ring of sincerity:

“I've never told you a lie yet, Dolly, and I'm too old to begin now. I give you my solemn word of honour that Tom has never been anything more to me than just a friend.”

“You take a great weight off my mind.”

Julia knew that Dolly did not believe her and Dolly was aware that Julia knew it. She went on.

“But in that case, for your own sake, Julia dear, do be sensible. Don't go about with this young man any more. Drop him.”

“Oh, I couldn't do that. That would be an admission that people were right in what they thought. After all, my conscience is clear. I can afford to hold my head high. I should despise myself if I allowed my behaviour to be influenced by malicious gossip.”

Dolly slipped her feet back into he shoes and getting her lipstick out of her bag did her lips.

“Well, dear, you're old enough to know your own mind.”

They parted coldly.

But one or two of Dolly's remarks had been somewhat of a shock to Julia. They rankled. It was disconcerting that gossip had so nearly reached the truth. But did it matter? Plenty of women had lovers and who bothered? And an actress. No one expected an actress to be a pattern of propriety.

“It's my damned virtue. That's at the bottom of the trouble.”

She had acquired the reputation of a perfectly virtuous woman, whom the tongue of scandal could not touch, and now it looked as though her reputation was a prison that she had built round herself. But there was worse. What had Tom meant by saying that she ate out of his hand? That deeply affronted her. Silly little fool. How dare he? She didn't know what to do about it either. She would have liked to tax him with it. What was the good? He would deny it. The only thing was to say nothing; it had all gone too far now, she must accept everything. It was no good not facing the truth, he didn't love her, he was her lover because it gratified his self-esteem, because it brought him various things he cared for and because in his own eyes at least it gave him a sort of position.

“If I had any sense I'd chuck him.” She gave an angry laugh. “It's easy to say that. I love him.”

The strange thing was that when she looked into her heart it was not Julia Lambert the woman who resented the affront, she didn't care for herself, it was the affront to Julia Lambert the actress that stung her. She had often felt that her talent, genius the critics called it, but that was a very grand word, her gift, if you like, was not really herself, not even part of her, but something outside that used her, Julia Lambert the woman, in order to express itself. It was a strange, immaterial personality that seemed to descend upon her and it did things through her that she did not know she was capable of doing. She was an ordinary, prettyish, ageing woman. Her gift had neither age nor form. It was a spirit that played on her body as the violinist plays on his violin. It was the slight to that that galled her.

She tried to sleep. She was so accustomed to sleeping in the afternoon that she could always drop off the moment she composed herself, but on this occasion she turned restlessly from side to side and sleep would not come. At last she looked at the clock. Tom often got back from his office soon after five. She yearned for him; in his arms was peace, when she was with him nothing else mattered. She dialled his number.

“Hulloa? Yes. Who is it?”

She held the receiver to her ear, panic-stricken. It was Roger's voice. She hung up.

Chapter 19

Nor did Julia sleep well that night. She was awake when she heard Roger come in and, turning on her light she saw that it was four. She frowned. He came clattering down the stone stairs next morning just when she was beginning to think of getting up.

“Can I come in, Mummy?”

“Come in.”

He was still in his pyjamas and dressing-gown. She smiled at him because he looked so fresh and young.

“You were very late last night.”

“No, not very. I was in by one.”

“Liar. I looked at my clock. It was four.”

“All right. It was four then,” he agreed cheerfully.

“What on earth were you doing?”

“We went on to some place after the show and had supper. We danced.”

“Who with?”

“A couple of girls we picked up. Tom knew them before.”

“What were their names?”

“One was called Jill and one was called Joan. I don't know what their other names were. Joan's on the stage. She asked me if I couldn't get her an understudy in your next play.”

At all events neither of them was Avice Crichton. That name had been in her thoughts ever since Dolly had mentioned it.

“But those places aren't open till four.”

“No, we went back to Tom's flat. Tom made me promise I wouldn't tell you. He said you'd be furious.”

“Oh, my dear, it takes a great deal more than that to make me furious. I promise you I won't say a word.”

“If anyone's to blame I am. I went to see Tom yesterday afternoon and we arranged it then. All this stuff about love that one hears about in plays and reads in novels. I'm nearly eighteen. I thought I ought to see for myself what it was all about.”

Julia sat up in bed and looked at Roger with wide, enquiring eyes.

“Roger, what do you mean?”

He was composed and serious.

“Tom said he knew a couple of girls who were all right. He's had them both himself. They live together and so we phoned and asked them to meet us after the show. He told them I was a virgin and they'd better toss up for me. When we got back to the flat he took Jill into the bedroom and left me the sitting-room and Joan.”

For the moment she did not think of Tom, she was so disturbed at what Roger was saying.

“I don't think it's so much really. I don't see it's anything to make all that fuss about.”

She could not speak. The tears filled her eyes and ran quickly down her face.

“Mummy, what's the matter? Why are you crying?”

“But you're a little boy.”

He came over to her and sitting on the side of her bed took her in his arms.

“Darling, don't cry. I wouldn't have told you if I'd thought it was going to upset you. After all it had to happen sooner or later.”

“But so soon. So soon. It makes me feel so old.”

“Not you, darling. ‘Age cannot wither her, nor custom stale her infinite variety.’”

She giggled through her tears.

“You fool, Roger, d'you think Cleopatra would have liked what that silly old donkey said of her? You might have waited a little longer.”

“It's just as well I didn't. I know all about it now. To tell you the truth I think it's rather disgusting.”

She sighed deeply. It was a comfort to feel him holding her so tenderly. But she felt terribly sorry for herself.

“You're not angry with me, darling?” he asked.

“Angry? No. But if it had to come I wish it hadn't been quite so matter of fact. You talk as though it had just been a rather curious experiment.”

“I suppose it was in a way.”

She gave him a little smile.

“And you really think that was love?”

“Well, it's what most people mean by it, isn't it?”

“No, they don't, they mean pain and anguish, shame, ecstasy, heaven and hell; they mean the sense of living more intensely, and unutterable boredom; they mean freedom and slavery; they mean peace and unrest.”

Something in the stillness with which he listened to her made her give him a glance through her eyelashes. There was a curious expression in his eyes. She did not know what it meant. It was as though he were gravely listening to a sound that came from a long way off.

“It doesn't sound as though it were much fun,” he murmured.

She took his smooth face in her hands and kissed his lips.

“I'm a fool, aren't I? You see, I still see you as a little baby boy that I'm holding in my arms.”

A twinkle shone in his eyes.

“What are you grinning at, you ape?”

“It made a damned good photograph, didn't it?”

She could not but laugh.

“You pig. You filthy pig.”

“I say, about the understudy, is there any chance for Joan?”

“Tell her to come and see me one day.”

But when Roger left her she sighed. She was depressed. She felt very lonely. Her life had always been so full and so exciting that she had never had the time to busy herself much with Roger. She got in a state, of course, when he had whooping-cough or measles, but he was for the most part in robust health, and then he occupied a pleasant place in the background of her consciousness. But she had always felt that he was there to be attended to when she was inclined and she had often thought it would be nice when he was old enough really to share her interests. It came to her as a shock now to realize that, without ever having really possessed him, she had lost him. Her lips tightened when she thought of the girl who had taken him from her.

“An understudy. My foot.”

Her pain absorbed her so that she could not feel the grief she might have felt from her discovery of Tom's perfidy. She had always known in her bones that he was unfaithful to her. At his age, with his wanton temperament, with herself tied down by her performances at the theatre, by all manner of engagements which her position forced upon her, it was plain that he had ample opportunity to gratify his inclinations. She had shut her eyes. All she asked was that she should not know. This was the first time that an actual fact had been thrust upon her notice.

“I must just put up with it,” she sighed. Thoughts wandered through her mind. “It's like lying and not knowing you're lying, that's what's fatal; I suppose it's better to be a fool and know it than a fool and not know it.”

Chapter 20

Tom went to Eastbourne with his family for Christmas. Julia had two performances on Boxing Day, so the Gosselyns stayed in town; they went to a large party at the Savoy that Dolly de Vries gave to see the New Year in; and a few days later Roger set off for Vienna. While he was in London Julia saw little of Tom. She did not ask Roger what they did when they tore about the town together, she did not want to know, she steeled herself not to think and distracted her mind by going to as many parties as she could. And there was always her acting; when once she got into the theatre her anguish, her humiliation, her jealousy were allayed. It gave her a sense of triumphant power to find, as it were in her pot of grease paint, another personality that could be touched by no human griefs. With that refuge always at hand she could support anything.

On the day that Roger left, Tom rang her up from his office.

“Are you doing anything tonight? What about going out on the binge?”

“No, I'm busy.”

It was not true, but the words slipped out of her mouth independent of her will.

“Oh, are you? Well, what about tomorrow?”

If he had expressed disappointment, if he had asked her to cut the date he supposed she had, she might have had strength to break with him then and there. His casualness defeated her.

“Tomorrow's all right.”

“O.K. I'll fetch you at the theatre after the show. Bye-bye.”

Julia was ready and waiting when he was shown into her dressing-room. She was strangely nervous. His face lit up when he saw her, and when Evie went out of the room for a moment he caught her in his arms and warmly kissed her on the lips.

“I feel all the better for that,” he laughed.

You would never have thought to look at him, so young, fresh and ingenuous, in such high spirits, that he was capable of giving her so much pain. You would never have thought that he was so deceitful. It was quite plain that he had not noticed that for more than a fortnight he had hardly seen her.

(“Oh, God, if I could only tell him to go to hell.”)

But she looked at him with a gay smile in her lovely eyes.

“Where are we going?”

“I've got a table at Quag's. They've got a new turn there, an American conjurer, who's grand.”

She talked with vivacity all through supper. She told him about the various parties she had been to, and the theatrical functions she had not been able to get out of, so that it seemed only on account of her engagements that they had not met. It disconcerted her to perceive that he took it as perfectly natural. He was glad to see her, that was plain, he was interested in what she had been doing and in the people she had seen, but it was plain also that he had not missed her. To see what he would say she told him that she had had an offer to take the play in which she was acting to New York. She told him the terms that had been suggested.

“They're marvellous,” he said, his eyes glittering. “What a snip! You can't lose and you may make a packet.”

“The only thing is, I don't much care for leaving London.”

“Why on earth not? I should have thought you'd jump at it. The play's had a good long run, for all you know it'll be pretty well through by Easter, and if you want to make a stab at America you couldn't have a better vehicle.”

“I don't see why it shouldn't run through the summer. Besides, I don't like strangers very much. I'm fond of my friends.”

“I think that's silly. Your friends'll get along without you all right. And you'll have a grand time in New York.”

Her gay laugh was very convincing.

“One would think you were terribly anxious to get rid of me.”

“Of course I should miss you like hell. But it would only be for a few months. If I had a chance like that I'd jump at it.”

But when they had finished supper and the commissionaire had called up a taxi for them he gave the address of the flat as if it were an understood thing that they should go back to it. In the taxi he put his arm round her waist and kissed her, and later, when she lay in his arms, in the little single bed, she felt that all the pain she had suffered during that last fortnight was not too great a price to pay for the happy peace that filled her heart.

Julia continued to go to the smart supper places and to nightclubs with Tom. If people wanted to think he was her lover, let them; she was past caring. But it happened more than once that he was engaged when she wanted him to go somewhere with her. It had spread around among Julia's grander friends that Tom was very clever at helping one with one's income-tax returns. The Dennorants had asked him down to the country for a weekend, and here he had met a number of persons who were glad to take advantage of his technical knowledge. He began to get invitations from people whom Julia did not know. Acquaintances would mention him to her.

“You know Tom Fennell, don't you? He's very clever, isn't he? I hear he's saved the Gillians hundreds of pounds on their income-tax.”

Julia was none too pleased. It was through her that he had got asked to parties that he wanted to go to. It began to look as if in this respect he could do without her. He was pleasant and unassuming, very well-dressed now, and with a fresh, clean look that was engaging; he was able to save people money; Julia knew the world which he was so anxious to get into well enough to realize that he would soon establish himself in it. She had no very high opinion of the morals of the women he would meet there and she could name more than one person of title who would be glad to snap him up. Julia's comfort was that they were all as mean as cat's meat. Dolly had said he was only earning four hundred a year; he certainly couldn't live in those circles on that.

Julia had with decision turned down the American offer before ever she mentioned it to Tom; their play was playing to very good business. But one of those inexplicable slumps that occasionally affect the theatre now swept over London and the takings suddenly dropped. It looked as though they would not be able to carry on long after Easter. They had a new play on which they set great hopes. It was called Nowadays, and the intention had been to produce it early in the autumn. It had a great part for Julia and the advantage of one that well suited Michael. It was the sort of play that might easily run a year. Michael did not much like the idea of producing it in May, with the summer coming on, but there seemed no help for it and he began looking about for a cast.

One afternoon, during the interval at a matinée, Evie brought a note in to Julia. She was surprised to see Roger's handwriting.

DEAR MOTHER,

This is to introduce to you Miss Joan Denver who Italked to you about. She's awfully keen on getting in theSiddons Theatre and would be quite satisfied with anunderstudy however small.

Your affectionate son,

ROGER.

Julia smiled at the formal way in which he wrote; she was tickled because he was so grown up as to try to get jobs for his girl friends. Then she suddenly remembered who Joan Denver was. Joan and Jill. She was the girl who had seduced poor Roger. Her face went grim. But she was curious to see her.

“Is George there?” George was the doorkeeper. Evie nodded and opened the door.

“George.”

He came in.

“Is the lady who brought this letter here now?”

“Yes, miss.”

“Tell her I'll see her after the play.”

She wore in the last act an evening dress with a train; it was a very grand dress and showed her beautiful figure to advantage. She wore diamonds in her dark hair and diamond bracelets on her arms. She looked, as indeed the part required, majestic. She received Joan Denver the moment she had taken her last call. Julia could in the twinkling of an eye leap from her part into private life, but now without an effort she continued to play the imperious, aloof, stately and well-bred woman of the play.

“I've kept you waiting so long I thought I wouldn't keep you till I'd got changed.”

Her cordial smile was the smile of a queen; her graciousness kept you at a respectful distance. In a glance she had taken in the young girl who entered her dressing-room. She was young, with a pretty little face and a snub nose, a good deal made-up and not very well made-up.

“Her legs are too short,” thought Julia. “Very second-rate.”

She had evidently put on her best clothes and the same glance had told Julia all about them.

(“Shaftesbury Avenue. Off the rail.”)

The poor thing was at the moment frightfully nervous. Julia made her sit down and offered her a cigarette.

“There are matches by your side.”

She saw her hands tremble when she tried to strike one. It broke and she rubbed a second three times against the box before she could get it to light.

(“If Roger could only see her now! Cheap rouge, cheap lipstick, and scared out of her wits. Gay little thing, he thought she was.”)

“Have you been on the stage long, Miss—I'm so sorry I've forgotten your name.”

“Joan Denver.” Her throat was dry and she could hardly speak. Her cigarette went out and she held it helplessly. She answered Julia's question. “Two years.”

“How old are you?”

“Nineteen.”

(“That's a lie. You're twenty-two if you're a day.”) “You know my son, don't you?”

“Yes.”

“He's just left Eton. He's gone to Vienna to learn German. Of course he's very young, but his father and I thought it would be good for him to spend a few months abroad before going up to Cambridge. And what parts have you played? Your cigarette's gone out. Won't you have another?”

“Oh, it's all right, thanks. I've been playing on tour. But I'm frightfully anxious to be in town.” Despair gave her courage and she uttered the speech she had evidently prepared. “I've got the most tremendous admiration for you, Miss Lambert. I always say you're the greatest actress on the stage. I've learnt more from you than I did all the years I was at the R.A.D.A. My greatest ambition is to be in your theatre, Miss Lambert, and if you could see your way to giving me a little something, I know it would be the most wonderful chance a girl could have.”

“Will you take off your hat?”

Joan Denver took the cheap little hat off her head and with a quick gesture shook out her close-cropped curls.

“What pretty hair you have,” said Julia.

Still with that slightly imperious, but infinitely cordial smile, the smile that a queen in royal procession bestows on her subjects, Julia gazed at her. She did not speak. She remembered Jane Taitbout's maxim: don't pause unless it's necessary, but then pause as long as you can. She could almost hear the girl's heart beating and she felt her shrinking in her ready-made clothes, shrinking in her skin.

“What made you think of asking my son to give you a letter to me?”

Joan grew red under her make-up and she swallowed before she answered.

“I met him at a friend's house and I told him how much I admired you and he said he thought perhaps you'd have something for me in your next play.”

“I'm just turning over the parts in my mind.”

“I wasn't thinking of a part. If I could have an understudy—I mean, that would give me a chance of attending rehearsals and studying your technique. That's an education in itself. Everyone agrees about that.”

(“Silly little fool, trying to flatter me. As if I didn't know that. And why the hell should I educate her?”) “It's very sweet of you to put it like that. I'm only a very ordinary person really. The public is so kind, so very kind. You're a pretty little thing. And young. Youth is so beautiful. Our policy has always been to give the younger people a chance. After all we can't go on for ever, and we look upon it as a duty we owe the public to train up actors and actresses to take our place when the time comes.”

Julia said these words so simply, in her beautifully modulated voice, that Joan Denver's heart was warmed. She'd got round the old girl and the understudy was as good as hers. Tom Fennell had said that if she played her cards well with Roger it might easily lead to something.

“Oh, that won't be for a long while yet, Miss Lambert,” she said, her eyes, her pretty dark eyes, glowing.

(“You're right there, my girl, dead right. I bet I could play you off the stage when I was seventy.”)

“I must think it over. I hardly know yet what understudies we shall want in our next play.”

“I hear there's some talk of Avice Crichton for the girl's part. I thought perhaps I could understudy her.”

Avice Crichton. No flicker of the eyes showed that the name meant anything to Julia.

“My husband has mentioned her, but nothing is settled yet. I don't know her at all. Is she clever?”

“I think so. I was at the Academy with her.”

“And pretty as a picture, they tell me.” Rising to her feet to show that the audience was at an end, Julia put off her royalty. She changed her tone and became on a sudden the jolly, good-natured actress who would do a good turn to anyone if she could. “Well, dear, leave me your name and address and if there's anything doing I'll let you know.”

“You won't forget me, Miss Lambert?”

“No, dear, I promise you I won't. It's been so nice to see you. You have a very sweet personality. You'll find your way out, won't you? Good-bye.”

“A fat chance she's got of ever setting foot in this theatre,” said Julia to herself when she was gone. “Dirty little bitch to seduce my son. Poor lamb. It's a shame, that's what it is; women like that oughtn't to be allowed.”

She looked at herself in the glass as she slipped out of her beautiful gown. Her eyes were hard and her lips had a sardonic curl. She addressed her reflection.

“And I may tell you this, old girl: there's one person who isn't going to play in Nowadays and that's Miss Avice Crichton.”

Chapter 21

But a week or so later Michael mentioned her.

“I say, have you ever heard of a girl called Avice Crichton?”

“Never.”

“I'm told she's rather good. A lady and all that sort of thing. Her father's in the army. I was wondering if she'd do for Honor.”

“How did you hear about her?”

“Through Tom. He knows her, he says she's clever. She's playing in a Sunday-night show. Next Sunday, in point of fact. He says he thinks it might be worth while to go and have a look-see.”

“Well, why don't you?”

“I was going down to Sandwich to play golf. Would it bore you awfully to go? I expect the play's rotten, but you'd be able to tell if it was worth while letting her read the part. Tom'll go with you.”

Julia's heart was beating nineteen to the dozen.

“Of course I'll go.”

She phoned to Tom and asked him to come round and have a snack before they went to the theatre. He arrived before she was ready.

“Am I late or were you early?” she said, when she came into the drawing-room.

She saw that he had been waiting impatiently. He was nervous and eager.

“They're going to ring up sharp at eight,” he said. “I hate getting to a play after it's begun.”

His agitation told her all she wanted to know. She lingered a little over the cocktails.

“What is the name of this actress we're going to see tonight?” she asked.

“Avice Crichton. I'm awfully anxious to know what you think about her. I think she's a find. She knows you're coming tonight. She's frightfully nervous, but I told her she needn't be. You know what these Sunday-night plays are; scratch rehearsals and all that; I said you'd quite understand and you'd make allowances.”

All through dinner he kept looking at his watch. Julia acted the woman of the world. She talked of one thing and another and noticed that he listened with distraction. As soon as he could he brought the conversation back to Avice Crichton.

“Of course I haven't said anything to her about it, but I believe she'd be all right for Honor.” He had read Nowadays, as he read, before they were produced, all Julia's plays. “She looks the part all right, I'm sure of that. She's had a struggle and of course it would be a wonderful chance for her. She admires you tremendously and she's terribly anxious to get into a play with you.”

“That's understandable. It means the chance of a year's run and a lot of managers seeing her.”

“She's the right colour, she's very fair; she'd be a good contrast to you.”

“What with platinum and peroxide there's no lack of blondes on the stage.”

“But hers is natural.”

“Is it? I had a long letter from Roger this morning. He seems to be having quite a good time in Vienna.”

Tom's interest subsided. He looked at his watch. When the coffee came Julia said it was undrinkable. She said she must have some more made.

“Oh, Julia, it isn't worth while. We shall be awfully late.”

“I don't suppose it matters if we miss the first few minutes.”

His voice was anguished.

“I promised we wouldn't be late. She's got a very good scene almost at the beginning.”

“I'm sorry, but I can't go without my coffee.”

While they waited for it she maintained a bright flow of conversation. He scarcely answered. He looked anxiously at the door. And when the coffee came she drank it with maddening deliberation. By the time they got in the car he was in a state of cold fury and he stared silently in front of him with a sulky pout on his mouth. Julia was not dissatisfied with herself. They reached the theatre two minutes before the curtain rose and as Julia appeared there was a burst of clapping from the audience. Julia, apologizing to the people she disturbed, threaded her way to her seat in the middle of the stalls. Her faint smile acknowledged the applause that greeted her beautifully-timed entrance, but her downcast eyes modestly disclaimed that it could have any connection with her.

The curtain went up and after a short scene two girls came in, one very pretty and young, the other much older and plain. In a minute Julia turned to Tom and whispered:

“Which is Avice Crichton, the young one or the old one?”

“The young one.”

“Oh, of course, you said she was fair, didn't you?”

She gave his face a glance. He had lost his sulky look; a happy smile played on his lips. Julia turned her attention to the stage. Avice Crichton was very pretty, no one could deny that, with lovely golden hair, fine blue eyes and a little straight nose; but it was a type that Julia did not care for.

“Insipid,” she said to herself. “Chorus-girly.”

She watched her performance for a few minutes. She watched intently; then she leant back in her stall with a little sigh.

“She can't act for toffee,” she decided.

When the curtain fell Tom turned to her eagerly. He had completely got over his bad temper.

“What do you think of her?”

“She's as pretty as a picture.”

“I know that. But her acting. Don't you think she's good?”

“Yes, clever.”

“I wish you'd come round and tell her that yourself. It would buck her up tremendously.”

“I?”

He did not realize what he was asking her to do. It was unheard-of that she, Julia Lambert, should go behind and congratulate a small-part actress.

“I promised I'd take you round after the second act. Be a sport, Julia. It'll please her so much.”

(“The fool. The blasted fool. All right, I'll go through with it.”) “Of course if you think it'll mean anything to her, I'll come with pleasure.”

After the second act they went through the iron door and Tom led her to Avice Crichton's dressing-room. She was sharing it with the plain girl with whom she had made her first entrance. Tom effected the introductions. She held out a limp hand in a slightly affected manner.

“I'm so glad to meet you, Miss Lambert. Excuse this dressing-room, won't you? But it was no good trying to make it look nice just for one night.”

She was not in the least nervous. Indeed, she seemed self-assured.

(“Hard as nails. And with an eye to the main chance. Doing the colonel's daughter on me.”)

“It's awfully nice of you to come round. I'm afraid it's not much of a play, but when one's starting like I am one has to put up with what one can get. I was rather doubtful about it when they sent it me to read, but I took a fancy to the part.”

“You play it charmingly,” said Julia.

“It's awfully nice of you to say so. I wish we could have had a few more rehearsals. I particularly wanted to show you what I could do.”

“Well, you know, I've been connected with the profession a good many years. I always think, if one has talent one can't help showing it. Don't you?”

“I know what you mean. Of course I want a lot more experience, I know that, but it's only a chance I want really. I know I can act. If I could only get a part that I could really get my teeth into.”

She waited a little in order to let Julia say that she had in her new play just the part that would suit her, but Julia continued to look at her smilingly. Julia was grimly amused to find herself treated like a curate's wife to whom the squire's lady was being very kind.

“Have you been on the stage long?” she said at last. “It seems funny I should never have heard of you.”

“Well, I was in revue for a while, but I felt I was just wasting my time. I was out on tour all last season. I don't want to leave London again if I can help it.”

“The profession's terribly overcrowded,” said Julia.

“Oh, I know. It seems almost hopeless unless you've got influence or something. I hear you're putting a new play on soon.”

“Yes.”

Julia continued to smile with an almost intolerable sweetness.

“If there's a part for me in it, I'd most awfully like to play with you. I'm so sorry Mr. Gosselyn couldn't come tonight.”

“I'll tell him about you.”

“D'you really think there's a chance for me?” Through her self-assurance, through the country-house manner she assumed in order to impress Julia, there pierced an anxious eagerness. “If you'd put in a word for me it would help so much.”

Julia gave her a reflective look.

“I take my husband's advice more often than he takes mine,” she smiled.

When they left the dressing-room so that Avice Crichton might change for the third act, Julia caught the questioning glance she gave Tom as she said good-bye to him. Julia was conscious, though she saw no movement, that he slightly shook his head. Her sensibility at that moment was extraordinarily acute and she translated the mute dialogue into words.

“Coming to supper afterwards?”

“No, damn it, I can't, I've got to see her home.”

Julia listened to the third act grimly. That was in order since the play was serious. When it was over and a pale, shattered author had made a halting speech, Tom asked her where she would like to go for supper.

“Let's go home and talk,” she said. “If you're hungry I'm sure we can find you something to eat in the kitchen.”

“D'you mean to Stanhope Place?”

“Yes.”

“All right.”

She felt his relief that she did not want to go back to the flat. He was silent in the car and she knew that it irked him to have to come back with her. She guessed that someone was giving a supper party to which Avice Crichton was going and he wanted to be there. The house was dark and empty when they reached it. The servants were in bed. Julia suggested that they should go down to the basement and forage.

“I don't want anything to eat unless you do,” he said. “I'll just have a whisky and soda and go to bed. I've got a very heavy day tomorrow at the office.”

“All right. Bring it up to the drawing-room. I'll go and turn on the lights.”

When he came up she was doing her face in front of a mirror and she continued till he had poured out the whisky and sat down. Then she turned round. He looked very young, and incredibly charming, in his beautiful clothes, sitting there in the big armchair, and all the bitterness she had felt that evening, all the devouring jealousy of the last few days, were dissipated on a sudden by the intensity of her passion. She sat down on the arm of his chair and caressingly passed her hand over his hair. He drew back with an angry gesture.

“Don't do that,” he said. “I do hate having my hair mussed about.”

It was like a knife in her heart. He had never spoken to her in that tone before. But she laughed lightly and getting up took the whisky he had poured out for her and sat down in a chair opposite him. The movement he had made, the words he had spoken, were instinctive and he was a trifle abashed. He avoided her glance and his face once more bore a sulky look. The moment was decisive. For a while they were silent. Julia's heart beat painfully, but at last she forced herself to speak.

“Tell me,” she said, smiling, “have you been to bed with Avice Crichton?”

“Of course not,” he cried.

“Why not? She's pretty.”

“She's not that sort of girl. I respect her.”

Julia let none of her feelings appear on her face. Her manner was wonderfully casual; she might have been talking of the fall of empires or the death of kings.

“D'you know what I should have said? I should have said you were madly in love with her.” He still avoided her eyes. “Are you engaged to her by anychance?”

“No.”

He looked at her now, but the eyes that met Julia's were hostile.

“Have you asked her to marry you?”

“How could I? A damned rotter like me.”

He spoke so passionately that Julia was astonished.

“What are you talking about?”

“Oh, what's the good of beating about the bush? How could I ask a decent girl to marry me? I'm nothing but a kept boy, and, God knows, you have good reason to know it.”

“Don't be so silly. What a fuss to make over a few little presents I've given you.”

“I oughtn't to have taken them. I knew all the time it was wrong. It all came so gradually that I didn't realize what was happening till I was in it up to my neck. I couldn't afford to lead the life you made me lead; I was absolutely up against it. I had to take money from you.”

“Why not? After all, I'm a very rich woman.”

“Damn your money.”

He was holding a glass in his hands and yielding to a sudden impulse, he flung it into the fireplace. It shattered.

“You needn't break up the happy home,” said Julia ironically.

“I'm sorry. I didn't mean to do that.” He sank back into his chair and turned his head away. “I'm so ashamed of myself. It's not very nice to have lost one's self-respect.”

Julia hesitated. She did not quite know what to say.

“It seemed only natural to help you when you were in a hole. It was a pleasure to me.”

“I know, you were wonderfully tactful about it. You almost persuaded me that I was doing you a service when you paid my debts. You made it easy for me to behave like a cad.”

“I'm sorry you should feel like that about it.”

She spoke rather tartly. She was beginning to feel a trifle irritated.

“There's nothing for you to be sorry about. You wanted me and you bought me. If I was such a skunk as to let myself be bought that was no business of yours.”

“How long have you been feeling like this?”

“From the beginning.”

“That isn't true.”

She knew that what had awakened his conscience was the love that had seized him for a girl who he believed was pure. The poor fool! Didn't he know that Avice Crichton would go to bed with an assistant stage manager if she thought it would get her a part?

“If you're in love with Avice Crichton why don't you tell me so?” He looked at her miserably, but did not answer. “Are you afraid it'll crab her chances of getting a part in the new play? You ought to know me well enough by now to know that I would never let sentiment interfere with business.”

He could hardly believe his ears.

“What do you mean by that?”

“I think she's rather a find. I'm going to tell Michael that I think she'll do very well.”

“Oh, Julia, you are a brick. I never knew what a wonderful woman you were.”

“You should have asked me and I'd have told you.”

He gave a sigh of relief.

“My dear, I'm so terribly fond of you.”

“I know, and I'm terribly fond of you. You're great fun to go about with and you're always so well turned out, you're a credit to any woman. I've liked going to bed with you and I've a sort of notion you've liked going to bed with me. But let's face it, I've never been in love with you any more than you've been in love with me. I knew it couldn't last. Sooner or later you were bound to fall in love and that would end it. And you have fallen in love, haven't you?”

“Yes.”

She was determined to make him say it, but when he did the pang it gave her was dreadful. Notwithstanding, she smiled goodhumouredly. “We've had some very jolly times together, but don't you think the moment has come to call it a day?”

She spoke so naturally, almost jestingly, that no one could have guessed that the pain at her heart seemed past bearing. She waited for her answer with sickening dread.

“I'm awfully sorry, Julia; I must regain my self-respect.” He looked at her with troubled eyes. “You aren't angry with me?”

“Because you've transferred your volatile affections from me to Avice Crichton?” Her eyes danced with mischievous laughter. “My dear, of course not. After all they stay in the profession.”

“I'm very grateful to you for all you've done for me. I don't want you to think I'm not.”

“Oh, my pet, don't talk such nonsense. I've done nothing for you.” She got up. “Now you really must go. You've got a heavy day at the office tomorrow and I'm dog-tired.”

It was a load off his mind. But he wasn't quite happy for all that, he was puzzled by her tone, which was so friendly and yet at the same time faintly ironical; he felt a trifle let down. He went up to her to kiss her good-night. She hesitated for the fraction of a second, then with a friendly smile gave him first one cheek and then the other.

“You'll find your way out, won't you?” She put her hand to her mouth to hide an elaborate yawn. “Oh, I'm so sleepy.”

The moment he had gone she turned out the lights and went to the window. She peered cautiously through the curtains. She heard him slam the front door and saw him come out. He looked right and left. She guessed at once that he was looking for a taxi. There was none in sight and he started to walk in the direction of the Park. She knew that he was going to join Avice Crichton at the supper party and tell her the glad news. Julia sank into a chair. She had acted, she had acted marvellously, and now she felt all in. Tears, tears that nobody could see, rolled down her cheeks. She was miserably unhappy. There was only one thing that enabled her to bear her wretchedness, and that was the icy contempt that she could not but feel for the silly boy who could prefer to her a small-part actress who didn't even begin to know how to act. It was grotesque. She couldn't use her hands; why, she didn't even know how to walk across the stage.

“If I had any sense of humour I'd just laugh my head off,” she cried. “It's the most priceless joke I've ever heard.”

She wondered what Tom would do now. The rent of the flat would be falling due on quarter day. A lot of the things in it belonged to her. He wouldn't much like going back to his bed-sitting-room in Tavistock Square. She thought of the friends he had made through her. He'd been clever with them. They found him useful and he'd keep them. But it wouldn't be so easy for him to take Avice about. She was a hard, mercenary little thing, Julia was sure of that, she wouldn'tbe much inclined to bother about him when his money flowed less freely. The fool to be taken in by her pretence of virtue! Julia knew the type. It was quite obvious, she was only using Tom to get a part at the Siddons and the moment she got it she would give him the air. Julia started when this notion crossed her mind. She had promised Tom that Avice should have the part in Nowadays because it fell into the scene she was playing, but she had attached no importance to her promise. Michael was always there to put his foot down.

“By God, she shall have the part,” she said out loud. She chuckled maliciously. “Heaven knows, I'm a good-natured woman, but there are limits to everything.”

It would be a satisfaction to turn the tables on Tom and Avice Crichton. She sat on, in the darkness, grimly thinking how she would do it. But every now and then she started to cry again, for from the depths of her subconscious surged up recollections that were horribly painful. Recollections of Tom's slim, youthful body against hers, his warm nakedness and the peculiar feel of his lips, his smile, at once shy and roguish, and the smell of his curly hair.

“If I hadn't been a fool I'd have said nothing. I ought to know him by now. It's only an infatuation. He'd have got over it and then he'd have come hungrily back to me.”

Now she was nearly dead with fatigue. She got up and went to bed. She took a sleeping-draught.

Chapter 22

But she woke early next morning, at six, and began to think of Tom. She repeated to herself all she had said to him and all he had said to her. She was harassed and unhappy. Her only consolation was that she had carried the rupture through with so careless a gaiety that he could not guess how miserable he had made her.

She spent a wretched day, unable to think of anything else, and angry with herself because she could not put Tom out of her mind. It would not have been so bad if she could have confided her grief to a friend. She wanted someone to console her, someone to tell her that Tom was not worth troubling about and to assure her that he had treated her shamefully. As a rule she took her troubles to Charles or to Dolly. Of course Charles would give her all the sympathy she needed, but it would be a terrible blow to him, after all he had loved her to distraction for twenty years, and it would be cruel to tell him that she had given to a very ordinary young man what he would gladly have sacrificed ten years of his life for. She was his ideal and it would be heartless on her part to shatter it. It certainly did her good at that moment to be assured that Charles Tamerley, so distinguished, so cultured, so elegant, loved her with an imperishable devotion. Of course Dolly would be delighted if she confided in her. They had not seen much of one another lately, but Julia knew that she had only to call up and Dolly would come running. Even though she more than suspected the truth already she'd be shocked and jealous when Julia made a clean breast of it, but she'd be so thankful that everything was over, she'd forgive. It would be a comfort to both of them to tear Tom limb from limb. Of course it wouldn't be very nice to admit that Tom had chucked her, and Dolly was so shrewd, she would never get away with the lie that she had chucked him. She wanted to have a good cry with somebody, and there didn't seem to be any reason for it if she had made the break herself. It would be a score for Dolly, and however sympathetic she was it was asking too much of human nature to expect that she would be altogether sorry that Julia had been taken down a peg or two. Dolly had always worshipped her. She wasn't going to give her a peep at her feet of clay.

“It almost looks as if the only person I can go to is Michael,” she giggled. “But I suppose it wouldn't do.”

She knew exactly what he would say.

“My dear girl, I'm really not the sort of feller you ought to come to with a story like that. Damn it all, you put me in a very awkward position. I flatter myself I'm pretty broad-minded, I may be an actor, but when all's said and done I am a gentleman, and well, I mean, I mean it's such damned bad form.”

Michael did not get home till the afternoon, and when he came into her room she was resting. He told her about his weekend and the result of his matches. He had played very well, some of his recoveries had been marvellous, and he described them in detail.

“By the way, what about that girl you saw last night, is she any good?”

“I really think she is, you know. She's very pretty. You're sure to fall for her.”

“Oh, my dear, at my time of life. Can she act?”

“She's inexperienced of course, but I think she's got it in her.”

“Oh, well, I'd better have her up and give her the once-over. How can I get hold of her?”

“Tom's got her address.”

“I'll phone him right away.”

He took off the receiver and dialled Tom's number. Tom was in and Michael wrote down the address on a pad.

The conversation went on.

“Oh, my dear old chap, I'm sorry to hear that. What rotten luck!”

“What's the matter?” asked Julia.

He motioned her to be quiet.

“Oh, well, I don't want to be hard on you. Don't you worry. I'm sure we can come to some arrangement that will be satisfactory to you.” He put his hand over the receiver and turned to Julia. “Shall I ask him to dinner next Sunday?”

“If you like.”

“Julia says, will you come and dine on Sunday? Oh, I'm sorry. Well, so long, old man.”

He put down the receiver.

“He's got a date. Is the young ruffian having an affair with this girl?”

“He assures me not. He respects her. She's a colonel's daughter.”

“Oh, she's a lady.”

“I don't know that that follows,” said Julia acidly. “What were you talking to him about?”

“He says they've cut his salary. Bad times. He wants to give up the flat.” Julia's heart gave a sudden sickening beat. “I've told him not to worry. I'll let him stay there rent free till times improve.”

“I don't know why you should do that. After all it was a purely business arrangement.”

“It seems rather tough luck on a young chap like that. And you know he's very useful to us; if we want an extra man we can always call upon him, and it's convenient having him round the corner when I want someone to play golf with me. It's only twenty-five pounds a quarter.”

“You're the last person I should expect to see indulge in indiscriminate generosity.”

“Oh, don't you be afraid, if I lose on the swings I'll get back on the roundabouts.”

The masseuse came in and put an end to the conversation. Julia was thankful that it would soon be time to go down to the theatre and so put an end for a while to the misery of that long day; when she got back she would take a sleeping-draught again and so get some hours of forgetfulness. She had a notion that in a few days the worst of her pain would be over; the important thing was to get through them as best she could. She must distract her mind. When she left for the theatre she told the butler to ring up Charles Tamerley and see if she could lunch with him at the Ritz next day.

He was extraordinarily nice at luncheon. His look, his manner, bespoke the different world he lived in, and she felt a sudden abhorrence for the circle in which on Tom's account she had moved during the last year. He spoke of politics, of art, of books; and peace entered into her soul. Tom had been an obsession and she saw now that it had been hurtful; but she would escape from it. Her spirits rose. She did not want to be alone, she knew that even though she went home after lunch she would not sleep, so she asked Charles if he would take her to the National Gallery. She could give him no greater pleasure; he liked to talk about pictures and he talked of them well. It took them back to the old days when she had made her first success in London and they used to spend so many afternoons together, walking in the park or sauntering through museums. The day after that she had a matnée and the next a lunch-party, but when they separated they arranged to lunch again together on the Friday and go to the Tate.

A few days later Michael told her that he had engaged Avice Crichton.

“She has the looks for the part, there's no doubt about that, and she'll be a good contrast to you. I'm taking her acting on the strength of what you said.”

Next morning they rang through from the basement to say that Mr. Fennell was on the telephone. It seemed to her that her heart stopped beating.

“Put him through.”

“Julia, I wanted to tell you, Michael has engaged Avice.”

“Yes, I know.”

“He told her he was engaging her on what you'd told him. You are a brick.”

Julia, her heart now beating nineteen to the dozen, made an effort to control her voice.

“Oh, don't talk such nonsense,” she answered gaily. “I told you it would be all right.”

“I'm awfully glad it's fixed up. She's accepted the part on what I've told her about it. Ordinarily she won't take anything unless she's read the play.”

It was just as well he could not see Julia's face when she heard him say this. She would have liked to answer tartly that it was not their habit when they engaged small-part actresses to let them read the play, but instead she said mildly:

“Well, I think she'll like it, don't you? It's quite a good part.”

“And you know, she'll play it for all it's worth. I believe she'll make a sensation.”

Julia took a long breath.

“It'll be wonderful, won't it? I mean, it may make her.”

“Yes, I've told her that. I say, when am I going to see you again?”

“I'll phone you, shall I? It's such a bore, I'm terribly full of engagements for the next few days.”

“You're not going to drop me just because…”

She gave a low, rather hoarse chuckle, that chuckle which so delighted audiences.

“Don't be so silly. Oh lord, there's my bath running. I must go and have it. Good-bye, my sweet.”

She put down the receiver. The sound of his voice! The pain in her heart was unendurable. Sitting up in her bed she rocked to and fro in an agony.

“What shall I do? What shall I do?”

She had thought she was getting over it, and now that brief, silly conversation had shown her that she loved him as much as ever. She wanted him. She missed him every minute of the day. She could not do without him.

“I shall never get over it,” she moaned.

Once again the theatre was her only refuge. By an ironic chance the great scene of the play in which she was then acting, the scene to which the play owed its success, showed the parting of two lovers. It was true that they parted from a sense of duty; and Julia, in the play, sacrificed her love, her hopes of happiness, all that she held dear, to an ideal of uprightness. It was a scene that had appealed to her from the beginning. She was wonderfully moving in it. She put into it now all the agony of her spirit; it was no longer the broken heart of a character that she portrayed but her own. In ordinary life she tried to stifle a passion that she knew very well was ridiculous, a love that was unworthy of the woman she was, and she steeled herself to think as little as possible of the wretched boy who had wrought such havoc with her; but when she came to this scene she let herself go. She gave free rein to her anguish. She was hopeless with her own loss, and the love she poured out on the man who was playing opposite to her was the love she still felt, the passionate, devouring love, for Tom. The prospect of the empty life that confronted the woman of the play was the prospect of her own empty life. There was at least that solace, she felt she had never played so magnificently.

“My God, it's almost worth while to suffer so frightfully to give such a performance.”

She had never put more of herself into a part.

One night a week or two later when she came into her dressing-room at the end of the play, exhausted by all the emotion she had displayed, but triumphant after innumerable curtain calls, she found Michael sitting there.

“Hulloa? You haven't been in front, have you?”

“Yes.”

“But you were in front two or three days ago.”

“Yes, I've sat through the play for the last four nights.”

She started to undress. He got up from his chair and began to walk up and down. She gave him a glance and saw that he was frowning slightly.

“What's the matter?”

“That's what I want to know.”

She gave a start. The thought flashed through her mind that he had once more heard something about Tom.

“Why the devil isn't Evie here?” she asked.

“I told her to get out. I've got something to say to you, Julia. It's no good your flying in a temper. You've just got to listen.”

A cold shiver ran down her spine.

“Well, what is it?”

“I heard something was up and I thought I'd better see for myself. At first I thought it was just an accident. That's why I didn't say anything till I was quite sure. What's wrong with you, Julia?”

“With me?”

“Yes. Why are you giving such a lousy performance?”

“Me?” That was the last thing she expected to hear him say. She faced him with blazing eyes. “You damned fool, I've never acted better in my life.”

“Nonsense. You're acting like hell.”

Of course it was a relief that he was talking about her acting, but what he was saying was so ridiculous that, angry as she was, she had to laugh.

“You blasted idiot, you don't know what you're talking about. Why, what I don't know about acting isn't worth knowing. Everything you know about it I've taught you. If you're even a tolerable actor, it's due to me. After all, the proof of the pudding's in the eating. D'you know how many curtain calls I got tonight? The play's never gone better in all its run.”

“I know all about that. The public are a lot of jackasses. If you yell and scream and throw yourself about you'll always get a lot of damned fools to shout themselves silly. Just barn-storming, that's what you've been doing the last four nights. It was false from beginning to end.”

“False? But I felt every word of it.”

“I don't care what you felt, you weren't acting it. Your performance was a mess. You were exaggerating; you were over-acting; you didn't carry conviction for a moment. It was about as rotten a piece of ham-acting as I've ever seen in my life.”

“You bloody swine, how dare you talk to me like that? It's you the ham.”

With her open hand she gave him a great swinging blow on the face. He smiled.

“You can hit me, you can swear at me, you can yell your head off, but the fact remains that your acting's gone all to hell. I'm not going to start rehearsing Nowadays with you acting like that.”

“Find someone who can act the part better than I can then.”

“Don't be silly, Julia. I may not be a very good actor myself, I never thought I was, but I know good acting from bad. And what's more there's nothing about you I don't know. I'm going to put up the notices on Saturday and then I want you to go abroad. We'll make Nowadays our autumn production.”

The quiet, decisive way in which he spoke calmed her. It was true that when it came to acting Michael knew everything there was to know about her.

“Is it true that I'm acting badly?”

“Rottenly.”

She thought it over. She knew exactly what had happened. She had let her emotion run away with her; she had been feeling, not acting. Again a cold shiver ran down her spine. This was serious. It was all very fine to have a broken heart, but if it was going to interfere with her acting…no, no, no. That was quite another pair of shoes. Her acting was more important than any love affair in the world.

“I'll try and pull myself together.”

“It's no good trying to force oneself. You're tired out. It's my fault, I ought to have insisted on your taking a holiday long ago. What you want is a good rest.”

“What about the theatre?”

“If I can't let it, I'll revive some play that I can play in. There's Hearts Are Trumps. You always hated your part in that.”

“Everyone says the season's going to be wonderful. You can't expect much of a revival, with me out of the cast; you won't make a penny.”

“I don't care a hang about that. The only thing that matters is your health.”

“Oh, Christ, don't be so magnanimous,” she cried. “I can't bear it.”

Suddenly she burst into a storm of weeping.

“Darling!”

He took her in his arms and sat her down on the sofa with himself beside her. She clung to him desperately.

“You're so good to me, Michael, and I hate myself. I'm a beast, I'm a slut, I'm just a bloody bitch. I'm rotten through and through.”

“All that may be,” he smiled, “but the fact remains that you're a very great actress.”

“I don't know how you can have the patience you have with me. I've treated you foully. You've been too wonderful and I've sacrificed you heartlessly.”

“Now, dear, don't say a lot of things that you'll regret later. I shall only bring them up against you another time.”

His tenderness melted her and she reproached herself bitterly because for years she had found him so boring.

“Thank God, I've got you. What should I do without you?”

“You haven't got to do without me.”

He held her close and though she sobbed still she began to feel comforted.

“I'm sorry I was so beastly to you just now.”

“Oh, my dear.”

“Do you really think I'm a ham actress?”

“Darling, Duse couldn't hold a candle to you.”

“Do you honestly think that? Give me your hanky. You never saw Sarah Bernhardt, did you?”

“No, never.”

“She ranted like the devil.”

They sat together for a little while, in silence, and Julia grew calmer in spirit. Her heart was filled with a great love for Michael.

“You're still the best-looking man in England,” she murmured at last. “No one will ever persuade me to the contrary.”

She felt that he drew in his belly and thrust out his chin, and it seemed to her rather sweet and touching.

“You're quite right. I'm tired out. I feel low and miserable. I feel all empty inside. The only thing is to go away.”

Chapter 23

After Julia had made up her mind to that she was glad. The prospect of getting away from the misery that tormented her at once made it easier to bear. The notices were put up; Michael collected his cast for the revival and started rehearsals. It amused Julia to sit idly in a stall and watch the actress who had been engaged rehearse the part which she had played herself. She had never lost the thrill it gave her when she first went on the stage to sit in the darkened playhouse, under dust-sheets, and see the characters grow in the actors' hands. Merely to be inside a theatre rested her; nowhere was she so happy. Watching the rehearsals she was able to relax so that when at night she had her own performance to give she felt fresh. She realized that all Michael had said was true. She took hold of herself. Thrusting her private emotion into the background and thus getting the character under control, she managed once more to play with her accustomed virtuosity. Her acting ceased to be a means by which she gave release to her feelings and was again the manifestation of her creative instinct. She got a quiet exhilaration out of thus recovering mastery over her medium. It gave her a sense of power and of liberation.

But the triumphant effort she made took it out of her and when she was not in the theatre she felt listless and discouraged. She lost her exuberant vitality. A new humility overcame her. She had a feeling that her day was done. She sighed as she told herself that nobody wanted her any more. Michael suggested that she should go to Vienna to be near Roger, and she would have liked that, but she shook her head.

“I should only cramp his style.”

She was afraid he would find her a bore. He was enjoying himself and she would only be in the way. She could not bear the thought that he would find it an irksome duty to take her here and there and occasionally have lunch or dinner with her. It was only natural that he should have more fun with the friends of his own age that he had made. She decided to go and stay with her mother. Mrs. Lambert—Madame de Lambert, as Michael insisted on calling her—had lived for many years now with her sister, Madame Falloux, at St. Malo. She spent a few days every year in London with Julia, but this year had not been well enough to come. She was an old lady, well over seventy, and Julia knew that it would be a great joy for her to have her daughter on a long visit. Who cared about an English actress in Vienna? She wouldn't be anyone there. In St. Malo she would be something of a figure, and it would be fun for the two old women to be able to show her off to their friends.

“Ma fille, la plus grande actrice d'Angleterre,” and all that sort of thing.

Poor old girls, they couldn't live much longer and they led drab, monotonous lives. Of course it would be fearfully boring for her, but it would be a treat for them. Julia had a feeling that perhaps in the course of her brilliant and triumphant career she had a trifle neglected her mother. She could make up for it now. She would lay herself out to be charming. Her tenderness for Michael and her everpresent sense of having been for years unjust to him filled her with contrition. She felt that she had been selfish and overbearing, and she wanted to atone for all that. She was eager to sacrifice herself, and so wrote to her mother to announce her imminent arrival.

She managed in the most natural way in the world to see nothing of Tom till her last day in London. The play had closed the night before and she was starting for St. Malo in the evening. Tom came in about six o'clock to say good-bye to her. Michael was there, Dolly, Charles Tamerley and one or two others, so that there was no chance of their being left even for a moment by themselves. Julia found no difficulty in talking to him naturally. To see him gave her not the anguish she had feared but no more than a dull heartache. They had kept the date and place of her departure secret, that is to say, the press representative of the theatre had only rung up a very few newspapers, so that when Julia and Michael reached the station there were not more than half-a-dozen reporters and three cameramen. Julia said a few gracious words to them, and Michael a few more, then the press representative took the reporters aside and gave them asuccinct account of Julia's plans. Meanwhile Julia and Michael posed while the cameramen to the glare of flashes photographed them arm in arm, exchanging a final kiss, and at last Julia, half out of the carriage window, giving her hand to Michael who stood on the platform.

“What a nuisance these people are,” she said. “One simply cannot escape them.”

“I can't imagine how they knew you were going.”

The little crowd that had assembled when they realized that something was going on stood at a respectful distance. The press representative came up and told Michael he thought he'd given the reporters enough for a column. The train steamed out.

Julia had refused to take Evie with her. She had a feeling that in order to regain her serenity she must cut herself off completely for a time from her old life. Evie in that French household would be out of place. For Madame Falloux, Julia's Aunt Carrie, married as a girl to a Frenchman, now as an old, old lady spoke French more easily than English. She had been a widow for many years and her only son had been killed in the war. She lived in a tall, narrow stone house on a hill, and when you crossed its threshold from the cobbled street you entered upon the peace of a by-gone age. Nothing had been changed for half a century. The drawing-room was furnished with a Louis XV suite under covers, and the covers were only taken off once a month to give the silk underneath a delicate brushing. The crystal chandelier was shrouded in muslin so that the flies should not spot it. In front of the chimney-piece was a fire-screen of peacocks' feathers artfully arranged and protected by glass. Though the room was never used Aunt Carrie dusted it herself every day. The dining-room was panelled and here too the chairs were under dust-covers. On the sideboard was a silver épergne, a silver coffee-pot, a silver teapot and a silver tray. Aunt Carrie and Julia's mother, Mrs. Lambert, lived in the morning-room, a long narrow room, with Empire furniture. On the walls in oval frames were oil portraits of Aunt Carrie and her deceased husband, of his father and mother, and a pastel of the dead son as a child. Here they had their work-boxes, here they read their papers, the Catholic La Croix, the Revue des Deux Mondes and the local daily, and here they played dominoes in the evening. Except on Thursday evenings when the Abbé and the Commandant La Garde, a retired naval officer, came to dinner they had their meals there; but when Julia arrived they decided that it would be more convenient to eat in the dining-room.

Aunt Carrie still wore mourning for her husband and her son. It was seldom warm enough for her to leave off the little black tricot that she crocheted herself. Mrs. Lambert wore black too, but when Monsieur L'Abbé and the Commandant came to dinner she put over her shoulders a white lace shawl that Julia had given her. After dinner they played plafond for two sous a hundred. Mrs. Lambert, because she had lived for so many years in Jersey and still went to London, knew all about the great world, and she said that a game called contract was much played, but the Commandant said it was all very well for Americans, but he was content to stick to plafond, and the Abbé said that for his part he thought it a pity that whist had been abandoned. But there, men were never satisfied with what they had; they wanted change, change, change all the time.

Every Christmas Julia gave her mother and her aunt expensive presents, but they never used them. They showed them to their friends with pride, these wonderful things that came from London, and then wrapped them up in tissue paper and put them away in cupboards. Julia had offered her mother a car, but she refused it. For the little they went out, they could go on foot; a chauffeur would steal their petrol, if he had his meals out it would be ruinous and if he had them in it would upset Annette. Annette was cook, housekeeper and housemaid. She had been with Aunt Carrie for five-andthirty years. Her niece was there to do the rough work, but Angèle was young, she wasn't forty yet, and it would hardly do to have a man constantly about the house.

They put Julia in the same room she had had as a girl when she was living with Aunt Carrie for her education. It gave her a peculiar, heart-rending sensation, indeed for a little it made her quite emotional. But she fell into the life very easily. Aunt Carrie had become a Catholic on her marriage and Mrs. Lambert, when on losing her husband she settled down in St. Malo, having received instructions from the Abbé, in due course took the same step. The two old ladies were very devout. They went to Mass every morning and to High Mass on Sundays. Otherwise they seldom went out. When they did it was to pay a ceremonious call on some old lady who had had a bereavement in the family or one of whose grandchildren was become engaged. They read their papers, and their magazine, did a great deal of sewing for charitable purposes, played dominoes and listened to the radio that Julia had given them. Though the Abbé and the Commandant had dined with them every Thursday for many years they were always in a flutter when Thursday came. The Commandant, with the sailor's downrightness that they expected of him, did not hesitate to say so if something was not cooked to his liking, and even the Abbé, though a saint, had his likes and dislikes. For instance, he was very fond of sole normande, but he insisted on its being cooked with the best butter, and with butter at the price it was since the war that was very expensive. Every Thursday morning Aunt Carrie took the cellar key from the place where she had hidden it and herself fetched a bottle of claret from the cellar. She and her sister finished what was left of it by the end of the week.

They made a great fuss of Julia. They dosed her with tisanes and were anxious that she should not sit in anything that might be thought a draught. Indeed a great part of their lives was devoted to avoiding draughts. They made her lie on sofas and were solicitous that she should cover her feet. They reasoned with her about the clothes she wore. Those silk stockings that were so thin you could see through them; and what did she wear next to her skin? Aunt Carrie would not have been surprised to learn that she wore nothing but a chemise.

“She doesn't even wear that,” said Mrs. Lambert.

“What does she wear then?”

“Panties,” said Julia.

“And a soutien-gorge, I suppose.”

“Certainly not,” cried Julia tartly.

“Then, my niece, under your dress you are naked?”

“Practically.”

“C'est de la folie,” said Aunt Carrie.

“C'est vraiment pas raisonnable, ma fille,” said Mrs. Lambert.

“And without being a prude,” added Aunt Carrie, “I must say that it is hardly decent.”

Julia showed them her clothes, and on the first Thursday after her arrival they discussed what she should wear for dinner. Aunt Carrie and Mrs. Lambert grew rather sharp with one another. Mrs. Lambert thought that since her daughter had evening dresses with her she ought to wear one, but Aunt Carrie considered it quite unnecessary.

“When I used to come and visit you in Jersey, my dear, and gentlemen were coming to dinner, I remember you would put on a tea-gown.”

“Of course a tea-gown would be very suitable.”

They looked at Julia hopefully. She shook her head.

“I would sooner wear a shroud.”

Aunt Carrie wore a high-necked dress of heavy black silk, with a string of jet, and Mrs. Lambert a similar one, but with her lace shawl and a paste necklace. The Commandant, a sturdy little man with a much-wrinkled face, white hair cut en brosse and an imposing moustache dyed a deep black, was very gallant,and though well past seventy pressed Julia's foot under the table during dinner. On the way out he seized the opportunity to pinch her bottom.

“Sex appeal,” Julia murmured to herself as with dignity she followed the two old ladies into the parlour.

They made a fuss of her, not because she was a great actress, but because she was in poor health and needed rest. Julia to her great amazement soon discovered that to them her celebrity was an embarrassment rather than an asset. Far from wanting to show her off, they did not offer to take her with them to pay calls. Aunt Carrie had brought the habit of afternoon tea with her from Jersey, and had never abandoned it. One day, soon after Julia's arrival, when they had invited some ladies to tea, Mrs. Lambert at lunch thus addressed her daughter:

“My dear, we have some very good friends at St. Malo, but of course they still look upon us as foreigners, even after all these years, and we don't like to do anything that seems at all eccentric. Naturally we don't want you to tell a lie, but unless you are forced to mention it, your Aunt Carrie thinks it would be better if you did not tell anyone that you are an actress.”

Julia was taken aback, but, her sense of humour prevailing, she felt inclined to laugh.

“If one of the friends we are expecting this afternoon happens to ask you what your husband is, it wouldn't be untrue, would it, to say that he was in business?”

“Not at all,” said Julia, permitting herself to smile.

“Of course, we know that English actresses are not like French ones,” Aunt Carrie added kindly. “It's almost an understood thing for a French actress to have a lover.”

“Dear, dear,” said Julia.

Her life in London, with its excitements, its triumphs and its pains, began to seem very far away. She found herself able soon to consider Tom and her feeling for him with a tranquil mind. She realized that her vanity had been more wounded than her heart. The days passed monotonously. Soon the only thing that recalled London to her was the arrival on Monday of the Sunday papers. She got a batch of them and spent the whole day reading them. Then she was a trifle restless. She walked on the ramparts and looked at the islands that dotted the bay. The grey sky made her sick for the grey sky of England. But by Tuesday morning she had sunk back once more into the calmness of the provincial life. She read a good deal, novels, English and French, that she bought at the local bookshop, and her favourite Verlaine. There was a tender melancholy in his verses that seemed to fit the grey Breton town, the sad old stone houses and the quietness of those steep and tortuous streets. The peaceful habits of the two old ladies, the routine of their uneventful existence and their quiet gossip, excited her compassion. Nothing had happened to them for years, nothing now would ever happen to them till they died, and then how little would their lives have signified. The strange thing was that they were content. They knew neither malice nor envy. They had achieved the aloofness from the common ties of men that Julia felt in herself when she stood at the footlights bowing to the applause of an enthusiastic audience. Sometimes she had thought that aloofness her most precious possession. In her it was born of pride; in them of humility. In both cases it brought one precious thing, liberty of spirit; but with them it was more secure.

Michael wrote to her once a week, brisk, businesslike letters in which he told her what the takings were at the Siddons and the preparations he was making for the next production; but Charles Tamerley wrote to her every day. He told her the gossip of the town, he talked in his charming, cultivated way of the pictures he saw and the books he read. He was tenderly allusive and playfully erudite. He philosophized without pedantry. He told her that he adored her. They were the most beautiful love-letters Julia had ever received, and for the sake of posterity she made up her mind to keep them. One day perhaps someone would publish them and people would go to the National Portrait Gallery and look at her portrait, the one McEvoy had painted, and sigh when they thought of the sad, romantic love-story of which she had been the heroine.

Charles had been wonderful to her during the first two weeks of her bereavement, she did not know what she would have done without him. He had always been at her beck and call. His conversation, by taking her into a different world, had soothed her nerves. Her soul had been muddied, and in his distinction of spirit she had washed herself clean. It had rested her wonderfully to wander about the galleries with him and look at pictures. She had good reason to be grateful to him. She thought of all the years he had loved her. He had waited for her now for more than twenty years. She had not been very kind to him. It would have given him so much happiness to possess her and really it would not have hurt her. She wondered why she had resisted him so long. Perhaps because he was so faithful, because his devotion was so humble, perhaps only because she wanted to preserve in his mind the ideal that he had of her. It was stupid really and she had been selfish. It occurred to her with exultation that she could at last reward him for all his tenderness, his patience and his selflessness. She had not lost the sense of unworthiness which Michael's great kindness had aroused in her, and she was remorseful still because she had been for so long impatient of him. The desire for self-sacrifice with which she left England burnt still in her breast with an eager flame. She felt that Charles was a worthy object for its exercise. She laughed a little, kindly and compassionately, as she thought of his amazement when he understood what she intended; for a moment he would hardly be able to believe it, and then what rapture, then what ecstasy! The love that he had held banked up for so many years would burst its sluices like a great torrent and in a flood o'erwhelm her. Her heart swelled at the thought of his infinite gratitude. But still he could hardly believe in his good fortune; and when it was all over and she lay in his arms she would nestle up to him and whisper tenderly:

“Was it worth waiting for?”

“Like Helen, you make me immortal with a kiss.”

It was wonderful to be able to give so much happiness to a human being.

“I'll write to him just before I leave St. Malo,” she decided.

The spring passed into summer, and at the end of July it was time for Julia to go to Paris and see about her clothes. Michael wanted to open with the new play early in September and rehearsals were to start in August. She had brought the play with her to St. Malo, intending to study her part, but the circumstances in which she lived had made it impossible. She had all the leisure she needed, but in that grey, austere and yet snug little town, in the constant company of those two old ladies whose interests were confined to the parish church and their household affairs, though it was a good play, she could take but little interest in it.

“It's high time I was getting back,” she said. “It would be hell if I really came to the conclusion that the theatre wasn't worth the fuss and bother they make about it.”

She said good-bye to her mother and to Aunt Carrie. They had been very kind to her, but she had an inkling that they would not be sorry when her departure allowed them to return to the life she had interrupted. They were a little relieved besides to know that now there was no more danger of some eccentricity, such as you must always run the risk of with an actress, which might arouse the unfavourable comment of the ladies of St. Malo.

She arrived in Paris in the afternoon, and when she was shown into her suite at the Ritz, she gave a sigh of satisfaction. It was a treat to get back to luxury. Three or four people had sent her flowers. She had a bath and changed. Charley Deveril, who always made her clothes for her, an old friend, called to take her to dinner at the Bois.

“I had a wonderful time,” she told him, “and of course, it was a grand treat for those old girls to have me there, but I have a feeling that if I'd stayed a day longer I should have been bored.”

To drive up the Champs Elysées on that lovely evening filled her with exhilaration. It was good to smell once more the smell of petrol. The cars, the taxis, the hooting of horns, the chestnut trees, the street lights, the crowd on the pavement and the crowd sitting outside the cafés; it was an enchantment. And when they got to the Château de Madrid, so gay, so civilized and so expensive, it was grand to see once more well-dressed women, decently made up, and tanned men in dinner-jackets.

“I feel like a queen returning from exile.”

Julia spent several happy days choosing her clothes and having the first fittings. She enjoyed every moment of them. But she was a woman of character, and when she had come to a decision she adhered to it; before leaving for London she wrote a note to Charles. He had been to Goodwood and Cowes and was spending twenty-four hours in London on his way to Salzburg.

CHARLES DEAR,

How wonderful that I shall see you so soon. Of course I am free on Wednesday. Shall we dine together and do you love me still?

Your JULIA.

As she stuck down the envelope she murmured: Bis dat qui cito dat. It was a Latin tag that Michael always quoted when, asked to subscribe to a charity, he sent by return of post exactly half what was expected of him.

Chapter 24

On Wednesday morning Julia had her face massaged and her hair waved. She could not make up her mind whether to wear for dinner a dress of flowered organdie, very pretty and spring-like with its suggestion of Botticelli's “Primavera,” or one of white satin beautifully cut to show off her slim young figure, and virginal; but while she was having her bath she decided on the white satin: it indicated rather delicately that the sacrifice she intended was in the nature of an expiation for her long ingratitude to Michael. She wore no jewels but a string of pearls and a diamond bracelet; besides her wedding-ring only one square-cut diamond. She would have liked to put on a slight brown tan, it looked open-air girl and suited her, but reflecting on what lay before her she refrained. She could not very well, like the actor who painted himself black all over to play Othello, tan her whole body. Always a punctual woman, she came downstairs as the front door was being opened for Charles. She greeted him with a look into which she put tenderness, a roguish charm and intimacy. Charles now wore his thinning grey hair rather long, and with advancing years his intellectual, distinguished features had sagged a little; he was slightly bowed and his clothes looked as though they needed pressing.

“Strange world we live in,” thought Julia. “Actors do their damnedest to look like gentlemen and gentlemen do all they can to look like actors.”

There was no doubt that she was making a proper effect on him. He gave her the perfect opening.

“Why are you looking so lovely tonight?” he asked.

“Because I'm looking forward to dining with you.”

With her beautiful, expressive eyes she looked deep into his. She parted her lips in the manner that she found so seductive in Romney's portraits of Lady Hamilton.

They dined at the Savoy. The head-waiter gave them a table on the gangway so that they were admirably in view. Though everyone was supposed to be out of town the grill-room was well filled. Julia bowed and smiled to various friends of whom she caught sight. Charles had much to tell her; she listened to him with flattering interest.

“You are the best company in the world, Charles,” she told him.

They had come late, they dined well, and by the time Charles had finished his brandy people were already beginning to come in for supper.

“Good gracious, are the theatres out already?” he said, glancing at his watch. “How quickly the time flies when I'm with you. D'you imagine they want to get rid of us?”

“I don't feel a bit like going to bed.”

“I suppose Michael will be getting home presently?”

“I suppose so,”

“Why don't you come back to my house and have a talk?”

That was what she called taking a cue.

“I'd love it,” she answered, putting into her tone the slight blush which she felt would have well become her cheek.

They got into his car and drove to Hill Street. He took her into his study. It was on the ground floor and looked on a tiny garden. The french windows were wide open. They sat down on a sofa.

“Put out some of the lights and let the night into the room,” said Julia. “She quoted from The Merchant of Venice. ‘In such a night as this, when the sweet wind did gently kiss the trees…’”

Charles switched off everything but one shaded lamp, and when he sat down again she nestled up to him. He put his arm round her waist and she rested her head on his shoulder.

“This is heaven,” she murmured.

“I've missed you terribly all these months.”

“Did you get into mischief?”

“Well, I bought an Ingres drawing and paid a lot of money for it. I must show it to you before you go.”

“Don't forget. Where have you put it?”

She had wondered from the moment she got into the house whether the seduction would take place in the study or upstairs.

“In my bedroom,” he answered.

“That's much more comfortable really,” she reflected.

She laughed in her sleeve as she thought of poor old Charles devising a simple little trick like that to get her into his bedroom. What mugs men were! Shy, that was what was the matter with them. A sudden pang shot through her heart as she thought of Tom. Damn Tom. Charles really was very sweet and she was determined to reward him at last for his long devotion.

“You've been a wonderful friend to me, Charles,” she said in her low, rather husky voice. She turned a little so that her face was very near his, her lips, again like Lady Hamilton's, slightly open. “I'm afraid I haven't always been very kind to you.”

She looked so deliciously yielding, a ripe peach waiting to be picked, that it seemed inevitable that he should kiss her. Then she would twine her soft white arms round his neck. But he only smiled.

“You mustn't say that. You've been always divine.”

(“He's afraid, poor lamb.”) “I don't think anyone has ever been so much in love with me as you were.”

He gave her a little squeeze.

“I am still. You know that. There's never been any woman but you in my life.”

Since, however, he did not take the proffered lips she slightly turned. She looked reflectively at the electric fire. Pity it was unlit. The scene wanted a fire.

“How different everything would have been if we'd bolted that time. Heigh-ho.”

She never quite knew what heigh-ho meant, but they used it a lot on the stage, and said with a sigh it always sounded very sad.

“England would have lost its greatest actress. I know now how dreadfully selfish it was of me ever to propose it.”

“Success isn't everything. I sometimes wonder whether to gratify my silly little ambition I didn't miss the greatest thing in the world. After all, love is the only thing that matters.” And now she looked at him again with eyes more beautiful than ever in their melting tenderness. “D'you know, I think that now, if I had my time over again, I'd say take me.”

She slid her hand down to take his. He gave it a graceful pressure.

“Oh, my dear.”

“I've so often thought of that dream villa of ours. Olive trees and oleanders and the blue sea. Peace. Sometimes I'm appalled by the dullness and vulgarity of my life. What you offered was beauty. It's too late now, I know; I didn't know then how much I cared for you, I never dreamt that as the years went on you would mean more and more to me.”

“It's heavenly to hear you say that, my sweet. It makes up for so much.”

“I'd do anything in the world for you, Charles. I've been selfish. I've ruined your life, I didn't know what I was doing.”

Her voice was low and tremulous and she threw back her head so that her neck was like a white column. Her décolleté showed part of her small firm breasts and with her hands she pressed them forward a little.

“You mustn't say that, you mustn't think that,” he answered gently. “You've been perfect always. I wouldn't have had you otherwise. Oh, my dear, life is so short and love is so transitory. The tragedy of life is that sometimes we get what we want. Now that I look back on our long past together I know that you were wiser than I. ‘What leaf-fringed legend haunts about thy shape?’ Don't you remember how it goes? ‘Never, never canst thou kiss, though winning near the goal—yet, do not grieve; she cannot fade, though thou hast not thy bliss. For ever wilt thou love, and she be fair!’”

(“Idiotic.”) “Such lovely lines,” she sighed. “Perhaps you're right. Heigh-ho.”

He went on quoting. That was a trick of his that Julia had always found somewhat tiresome.

“‘Ah, happy, happy boughs! that cannot shed
Your leaves, nor ever bid the Spring adieu;
And, happy melodist, unwearied,
For ever piping songs for ever new!…’”

It gave Julia an opportunity to think. She stared in the unlit fire, her gaze intent, as though she were entranced by the exquisite beauty of those words. It was quite obvious that he just hadn't understood. It could hardly be wondered at. She had been deaf to his passionate entreaties for twenty years, and it was very natural if he had given up his quest as hopeless. It was like Mount Everest; if those hardy mountaineers who had tried for so long in vain to reach the summit finally found an easy flight of steps that led to it, they simply would not believe their eyes: they would think there was a catch in it. Julia felt that she must make herself a little plainer; she must, as it were, reach out a helping hand to the weary pilgrim.

“It's getting dreadfully late,” she said softly. “Show me your new drawing and then I must go home.”

He rose and she gave him both her hands so that he should help her up from the sofa. They went upstairs. His pyjamas and dressing-gown were neatly arranged on a chair.

“How well you single men do yourselves. Such a cosy, friendly bedroom.”

He took the framed drawing off the wall and brought it over for her to look at under the light. It was a portrait in pencil of a stoutish woman in a bonnet and a low-necked dress with puffed sleeves. Julia thought her plain and the dress ridiculous.

“Isn't it ravishing?” she cried.

“I knew you'd like it. A good drawing, isn't it?”

“Amazing.”

He put the little picture back on its nail. When he turned round again she was standing near the bed with her hands behind her back, a little like a Circassian slave introduced by the chief eunuch to the inspection of the Grand Vizier; there was a hint of modest withdrawal in her bearing, a delicious timidity, and at the same time the virgin's anticipation that she was about to enter into her kingdom. Julia gave a sigh that was ever so slightly voluptuous.

“My dear, it's been such a wonderful evening. I've never felt so close to you before.”

She slowly raised her hands from behind her back and with the exquisite timing that came so naturally to her moved them forwards, stretching out her arms, and held them palms upward as though there rested on them, invisibly, a lordly dish, and on the dish lay her proffered heart. Her beautiful eyes were tender and yielding and on her lips played a smile of shy surrender.

She saw Charles's smile freeze on his face. He had understood all right.

(“Christ, he doesn't want me. It was all a bluff.”) The revelation for a moment staggered her. (“God, how am I going to get out of it? What a bloody fool I must look.”)

She very nearly lost her poise. She had to think like lightning. He was standing there, looking at her with an embarrassment that he tried hard to conceal. Julia was panic-stricken. She could not think what to do with those hands that held the lordly dish; God knows, they were small, but at the moment they felt like legs of mutton hanging there. Nor did she know what to say. Every second made her posture and the situation more intolerable.

(“The skunk, the dirty skunk. Codding me all these years.”)

She did the only thing possible. She continued the gesture. Counting so that she should not go too fast, she drew her hands towards one another, till she could clasp them, and then throwing back her head, raised them, very slowly, to one side of her neck. The attitude she reached was as lovely as the other, and it was the attitude that suggested to her what she had to say. Her deep, rich voice trembled a little with emotion.

“I'm so glad when I look back to think that we have nothing to reproach ourselves with. The bitterness of life is not death, the bitterness of life is that love dies. (She'd heard something like that said in a play.) If we'd been lovers you'd have grown tired of me long ago, and what should we have now to look back on but regret for our own weakness? What was that line of Shelley's that you said just now about fading?”

“Keats,” he corrected. “‘she cannot fade though thou hast not thy bliss.’”

“That's it. Go on.”

She was playing for time.

“‘For ever wilt thou love, and she be fair.’”

She threw her arms wide in a great open gesture and tossed her curly head. She'd got it.

“It's true, isn't it? ‘For ever wilt thou love and I be fair.’ What fools we should have been if for a few moments' madness we had thrown away the wonderful happiness our friendship has brought us. We have nothing to be ashamed of. We're clean. We can walk with our heads held high and look the whole world in the face.”

She instinctively felt that this was an exit line, and suiting her movements to the words, with head held high, backed to the door and flung it open. Her power was such that she carried the feeling of the scene all the way down the stairs with her. Then she let it fall and with the utmost simplicity turned to Charles who had followed her.

“My cloak.”

“The car is there,” he said as he wrapped it round her. “I'll drive you home.”

“No, let me go alone. I want to stamp this hour on my heart. Kiss me before I go.”

She held up her lips to him. He kissed them. But she broke away from him, with a stifled sob, and tearing open the door ran to the waiting car.

When she got home and stood in her own bedroom she gave a great whoof of relief.

“The bloody fool. Fancy me being taken in like that. Thank God, I got out of it all right. He's such an ass, I don't suppose he began to see what I was getting at.” But that frozen smile disconcerted her. “He may have suspected, he couldn't have been certain, and afterwards he must have been pretty sure he'd made a mistake. My God, the rot I talked. It seemed to go down all right, I must say. Lucky I caught on when I did. In another minute I'd have had me dress off. That wouldn't have been so damned easy to laugh away.”

Julia began to titter. The situation was mortifying, of course, he had made a damned fool of her, but if you had any sense of humour you could hardly help seeing that there was a funny side to it. She was sorry that there was nobody to whom she could tell it; even if it was against herself it would make a good story. What she couldn't get over was that she had fallen for the comedy of undying passion that he had played all those years; for of course it was just a pose; he liked to see himself as the constant adorer, and the last thing he wanted, apparently, was to have his constancy rewarded.

“Bluffed me, he did, completely bluffed me.”

But an idea occurred to Julia and she ceased to smile. When a woman's amorous advances are declined by a man she is apt to draw one or two conclusions; one is that he is homosexual and the other is that he is impotent. Julia reflectively lit a cigarette. She asked herself if Charles had used his devotion to her as a cover to distract attention from his real inclinations. But she shook her head. If he had been homosexual she would surely have had some hint of it; after all, in society since the war they talked of practically nothing else. Of course it was quite possible he was impotent. She reckoned out his age. Poor Charles. She smiled again. And if that were the case it was he, not she, who had been placed in an embarrassing and even ridiculous position. He must have been scared stiff, poor lamb. Obviously it wasn't the sort of thing a man liked to tell a woman, especially if he were madly in love with her; the more she thought of it the more probable she considered the explanation. She began to feel very sorry for him, almost maternal in fact.

“I know what I'll do,” she said, as she began to undress, “I'll send him a huge bunch of white lilies tomorrow.”

Chapter 25

Julia lay awake next morning for some time before she rang her bell. She thought. When she reflected on her adventure of the previous night she could not but be pleased that she had shown so much presence of mind. It was hardly true to say that she had snatched victory from defeat, but looking upon it as a strategic retreat her conduct had been masterly. She was, notwithstanding, ill at ease. There might be yet another explanation for Charles's singular behaviour. It was possible that he did not desire her because she was not desirable. The notion had crossed her mind in the night, and though she had at once dismissed it as highly improbable, there was no denying it, at that hour of the morning it had a nasty look. She rang. As a rule, since Michael often came in while Julia had breakfast, Evie, when she had drawn the curtains, handed her a mirror and a comb, her powder and lipstick. On this occasion, instead of running the comb rapidly through her hair and giving her face a perfunctory dab with the puff, Julia took some trouble. She painted her lips with care and put on some rouge; she arranged her hair.

“Speaking without passion or prejudice,” she said, still looking at herself in the glass, when Evie placed the breakfast tray on her bed, “would you say I was by way of being a good-looking woman, Evie?”

“I must know what I'm letting myself in for before answering that question.”

“You old bitch,” said Julia.

“You're no beauty, you know.”

“No great actress ever has been.”

“When you're all dolled up posh like you was last night, and got the light be'ind you, I've seen worse, you know.”

(“Fat lot of good it did me last night.”) “What I want to say is, if I really set my mind on getting off with a man, d'you think I could?”

“Knowing what men are, I wouldn't be surprised. Who d'you want to get off with now?”

“Nobody. I was only talking generally.”

Evie sniffed and drew her forefinger along her nostrils.

“Don't sniff like that. If your nose wants blowing, blow it.”

Julia ate her boiled egg slowly. She was busy with her thoughts. She looked at Evie. Funny-looking old thing of course, but one never knew.

“Tell me, Evie, do men ever try to pick you up in the street?”

“Me? I'd like to see 'em try.”

“So would I, to tell you the truth. Women are always telling me how men follow them in the street and if they stop and look in at a shop window come up and try to catch their eye. Sometimes they have an awful bother getting rid of them.”

“Disgusting, I call it.”

“I don't know about that. It's rather flattering. You know, it's a most extraordinary thing, no one ever follows me in the street. I don't remember a man ever having tried to pick me up.”

“Oh, well, you walk along Edgware Road one evening. You'll get picked up all right.”

“I shouldn't know what to do if I was.”

“Call a policeman,” said Evie grimly.

“I know a girl who was looking in a shop window in Bond Street, a hat shop, and a man came up and asked her if she'd like a hat. I'd love one, she said, and they went in and she chose one and gave her name and address, he paid for it on the nail, and then she said, thank you so much, and walked out while he was waiting for the change.”

“That's what she told you.” Evie's sniff was sceptical. She gave Julia a puzzled look. “What's the idea?”

“Oh, nothing. I was only wondering why in point of fact I never have been accosted by a man. It's not as if I had no sex appeal.”

But had she? She made up her mind to put the matter to the test.

That afternoon, when she had had her sleep, she got up, made up a little more than usual, and without calling Evie put on a dress that was neither plain nor obviously expensive and a red straw hat with a wide brim.

“I don't want to look like a tart,” she said as she looked at herself in the glass. “On the other hand I don't want to look too respectable.”

She tiptoed down the stairs so that no one should hear her and closed the door softly behind her. She was a trifle nervous, but pleasantly excited; she felt that she was doing something rather shocking. She walked through Connaught Square into the Edgware Road. It was about five o'clock. There was a dense line of buses, taxis and lorries, bicyclists dangerously threaded their way through the traffic. The pavements were thronged. She sauntered slowly north. At first she walked with her eyes straight in front of her, looking neither to the right nor to the left, but soon realized that this was useless. She must look at people if she wanted them to look at her. Two or three times when she saw half a dozen persons gazing at a shop window she paused and gazed too, but none of them took any notice of her. She strolled on. People passed her in one direction and another. They seemed in a hurry. No one paid any attention to her. When she saw a man alone coming towards her she gave him a bold stare, but he passed on with a blank face. It occurred to her that her expression was too severe, and she let a slight smile hover on her lips. Two or three men thought she was smiling at them and quickly averted their gaze. She looked back as one of them passed her and he looked back too, but catching her eye he hurried on. She felt a trifle snubbed and decided not to look round again. She walked on and on. She had always heard that the London crowd was the best behaved in the world, but really its behaviour on this occasion was unconscionable.

“This couldn't happen to one in the streets of Paris, Rome or Berlin,” she reflected.

She decided to go as far as the Marylebone Road, and then turn back. It would be too humiliating to have to go home without being once accosted. She was walking so slowly that passers-by sometimes jostled her. This irritated her.

“I ought to have tried Oxford Street,” she said. “That fool Evie. The Edgware Road's obviously a wash-out.”

Suddenly her heart gave an exultant leap. She had caught a young man's eye and she was sure that there was a gleam in it. He passed, and she had all she could do not to turn round. She started, for in a moment he passed her again, he had retraced his steps, and this time he gave her a stare. She shot him a glance and then modestly lowered her eyes. He fell back and she was conscious that he was following her. It was all right. She stopped to look into a shop window and he stopped too. She knew how to behave now. She pretended to be absorbed in the goods that were displayed, but just before she moved on gave him a quick flash of her faintly-smiling eyes. He was rather short, he looked like a clerk or a shop-walker, he wore a grey suit and a brown soft hat. He was not the man she would have chosen to be picked up by, but there it was, he was evidently trying to pick her up. She forgot that she was beginning to feel tired. She did not know what would happen next. Of course she wasn't going to let the thing go too far, but she was curious to see what his next step would be. She wondered what he would say to her. She was excited and pleased; it was a weight off her mind. She walked on slowly and she knew he was close behind her. She stopped at another shop window, and this time when he stopped he was close beside her. Her heart began to beat wildly. It was really beginning to look like an adventure.

“I wonder if he'll ask me to go to a hotel with him. I don't suppose he could afford that. A cinema. That's it. It would be rather fun.”

She looked him full in the face now and very nearly smiled. He took off his hat.

“Miss Lambert, isn't it?”

She almost jumped out of her skin. She was indeed so taken aback that she had not the presence of mind to deny it.

“I thought I recognized you the moment I saw you, that's why I turned back, to make sure, see, and I said to meself, if that's not Julia Lambert I'm Ramsay Macdonald. Then you stopped to look in that shop window and that give me the chance to 'ave a good look at you. What made me 'esitate was seeing you in the Edgware Road. It seems so funny, if you know what I mean.”

It was much funnier than he imagined. Anyhow it didn't matter if he knew who she was. She ought to have guessed that she couldn't go far in London without being recognized. He had a cockney accent and a pasty face, but she gave him a jolly, friendly smile. He mustn't think she was putting on airs.

“Excuse me talking to you, not 'aving been introduced and all that, but I couldn't miss the opportunity. Will you oblige me with your autograph?”

Julia caught her breath. It couldn't be that this was why he had followed her for ten minutes. He must have thought that up as an excuse for speaking to her. Well, she would play up.

“I shall be delighted. But I can't very well give it you in the street. People would stare so.”

“That's right. Look here, I was just going along to 'ave my tea. There's a Lyons at the next corner. Why don't you come in and 'ave a cup too?”

She was getting on. When they'd had tea he'd probably suggest going to the pictures.

“All right,” she said.

They walked along till they came to the shop and took their places at a small table.

“Two teas, please, miss,” he ordered. “Anything to eat?” And when Julia declined: “Scone and butter for one, miss.”

Julia was able now to have a good look at him. Though stocky and short he had good features, his black hair was plastered down on his head and he had fine eyes, but his teeth were poor and his pale skin gave him an unhealthy look. There was a sort of impudence in his manner that Julia did not much like, but then, as she sensibly reflected, you could hardly expect the modesty of the violet in a young man who picked you up in the Edgware Road.

“Before we go any further let's 'ave this autograph, eh? Do it now, that's my motto.”

He took a fountain pen from his pocket and from a bulging pocket-book a large card.

“One of our trade cards,” he said. “That'll be O.K.”

Julia thought it silly to carry the subterfuge to this length, but she good-humouredly signed her name on the back of the card.

“Do you collect autographs?” she asked him with a subtle smile.

“Me? Noa. I think it's a lot of tommyrot. My young lady does. She's got Charlie Chaplin and Douglas Fairbanks and I don't know what all. Show you 'er photo if you like.”

From his pocket-book he extracted a snapshot of a rather pert-looking young woman showing all her teeth in a cinema smile.

“Pretty,” said Julia.

“And how. We're going to the pictures tonight. She will be surprised when I give her your autograph. The first thing I said to meself when I knew it was you was, I'll get Julia Lambert's autograph for Gwen or die in the attempt. We're going to get married in August, when I 'ave my 'oliday, you know; we're going to the Isle of Wight for the 'oneymoon. I shall 'ave a rare lot of fun with 'er over this. She won't believe me when I tell her you an' me 'ad tea together, she'll think I'm kidding, and then I'll show 'er the autograph, see?”

Julia listened to him politely, but the smile had left her face.

“I'm afraid I shall have to go in a minute,” she said. “I'm late already.”

“I 'aven't got too much time meself. You see, meeting my young lady, I want to get away from the shop on the tick.”

The check had been put on the table when the girl brought their tea, and when they got up Julia took a shilling out of her bag.

“What are you doing that for? You don't think I'm going to let you pay. I invited you.”

“That's very kind of you.”

“But I'll tell you what you can do, let me bring my young lady to see you in your dressing-room one day. Just shake 'ands with her, see? It would mean a rare lot to her. Why, she'd go on talking about it the rest of her life.”

Julia's manner had been for some minutes growing stiffer and now, though gracious still, it was almost haughty.

“I'm sorry, but we never allow strangers behind.”

“Oh, sorry. You don't mind my asking though, do you? I mean, it's not as if it was for meself.”

“Not at all. I quite understand.”

She signalled to a cab crawling along the curb and gave her hand to the young man.

“Good-bye, Miss Lambert. So long, good luck and all that sort of thing. And thanks for the autograph.”

Julia sat in the corner of the taxi raging.

“Vulgar little beast. Him and his young lady. The nerve of asking if he could bring her to see me.”

When she got home she went upstairs to her room. She snatched her hat off her head and flung it angrily on the bed. She strode over to the looking-glass and stared at herself.

“Old, old, old,” she muttered. “There are no two ways about it; I'm entirely devoid of sex appeal. You wouldn't believe it, would you? You'd say it was preposterous. What other explanation is there? I walk from one end of the Edgware Road to the other and God knows I'd dressed the part perfectly, and not a man pays the smallest attention to me except a bloody little shop-assistant who wants my autograph for his young lady. It's absurd. A lot of sexless bastards. I don't know what's coming to the English. The British Empire!”

The last words she said with a scorn that would have withered a whole front bench of cabinet ministers. She began to gesticulate.

“It's ridiculous to suppose that I could have got to my position if I hadn't got sex appeal. What do people come to see an actress for? Because they want to go to bed with her. Do you mean to tell me that I could fill a theatre for three months with a rotten play if I hadn't got sex appeal? What is sex appeal anyway?”

She paused, looking at herself reflectively.

“Surely I can act sex appeal. I can act anything.”

She began to think of the actresses who notoriously had it, of one especially, Lydia Mayne, whom one always engaged when one wanted a vamp. She was not much of an actress, but in certain parts she was wonderfully effective. Julia was a great mimic, and now she began to do an imitation of Lydia Mayne. Her eyelids drooped sensually over her eyes as Lydia's did and her body writhed sinuously in her dress. She got into her eyes the provoking indecency of Lydia's glance and into her serpentine gestures that invitation which was Lydia's speciality. She began to speak in Lydia's voice, with the lazy drawl that made every remark she uttered sound faintly obscene.

“Oh, my dear man, I've heard that sort of thing so often. I don't want to make trouble between you and your wife. Why won't men leave me alone?”

It was a cruel caricature that Julia gave. It was quite ruthless. It amused her so much that she burst out laughing.

“Well, there's one thing, I may not have any sex appeal, but after seeing my imitation there aren't many people who'd think Lydia had either.”

It made her feel much better.

Chapter 26

Rehearsals began and distracted Julia's troubled mind. The revival that Michael put on when she went abroad had done neither very well nor very badly, but rather than close the theatre he was keeping it in the bill till Nowadays was ready. Because he was acting two matinées a week, and the weather was hot, he determined that they should take rehearsals easy. They had a month before them.

Though Julia had been on the stage so long she had never lost the thrill she got out of rehearsing, and the first rehearsal still made her almost sick with excitement. It was the beginning of a new adventure. She did not feel like a leading lady then, she felt as gay and eager as if she were a girl playing her first small part. But at the same time she had a delicious sense of her own powers. Once more she had the chance to exercise them.

At eleven o'clock she stepped on to the stage. The cast stood about idly. She kissed and shook hands with the artists she knew and Michael with urbanity introduced to her those she did not. She greeted Avice Crichton with cordiality. She told her how pretty she was and how much she liked her hat; she told her about the lovely frocks she had chosen for her in Paris.

“Have you seen Tom lately?” she asked.

“No, I haven't. He's away on his holiday.”

“Oh, yes. He's a nice little thing, isn't he?”

“Sweet.”

The two women smiled into one another's eyes. Julia watched her when she read her part and listened to her intonations. She smiled grimly. It was exactly what she had expected. Avice was one of those actresses who were quite sure of themselves from the first rehearsal. She didn't know what was coming to her. Tom meant nothing to Julia any more, but she had a score to settle with Avice and she wasn't going to forget it. The slut!

The play was a modern version of The Second Mrs. Tanqueray, but with the change of manners of this generation it had been treated from the standpoint of comedy. Some of the old characters were introduced, and Aubrey Tanqueray, now a very old man, appeared in the second act. After Paula's death he had married for the third time. Mrs. Cortelyon had undertaken to compensate him for his unfortunate experience with his second wife, and she was now a cantankerous and insolent old lady. Ellean, his daughter, and Hugh Ardale had agreed to let bygones be bygones, for Paula's tragic death had seemed to wipe out the recollection of his lapse into extraconjugal relations; and they had married. He was now a retired brigadier-general who played golf and deplored the decline of the British Empire—“Gad, sir, I'd stand those damned socialists against a wall and shoot 'em if I had my way”; whereas Ellean, by this time an elderly woman, after a prudish youth had become gay, modem and plain-spoken. The character that Michael played was called Robert Humphreys, and like the Aubrey of Pinero's play he was a widower with an only daughter; he had been a consul in China for many years, and having come into money had retired and was settling on the estate, near where the Tanquerays still lived, which a cousin had left him. His daughter, Honor (this was the part for which Avice Crichton had been engaged), was studying medicine with the intention of practising in India. Alone in London, and friendless after so many years abroad, he had picked up a well-known woman of the town called Mrs. Marten. Mrs. Marten belonged to the same class as Paula, but she was less exclusive; she “did” the summer and the winter season at Cannes and in the intervals lived in a flat in Albermarle Street where she entertained the officers of His Majesty's brigade. She played a good game of bridge and an even better game of golf. The part well suited Julia.

The author followed the lines of the old play closely. Honor announced to her father that she was abandoning her medical studies and until her marriage wished to live with him, for she had just become engaged to Ellean's son, a young guardsman. Somewhat disconcerted, Robert Humphreys broke to her his intention of marrying Mrs. Marten. Honor took the information with composure.

“Of course you know she's a tart, don't you?” she said coolly.

He, much embarrassed, spoke of the unhappy life she had led and how he wanted to make up to her for all she had suffered.

“Oh, don't talk such rot,” she answered. “It's grand work if you can get it.”

Ellean's son had been one of Mrs. Marten's numerous lovers just as Ellean's husband had been one of Paula Tanqueray's. When Robert Humphreys brought his wife down to his home in the country and this fact was discovered, they decided that Honor must be informed. To their consternation Honor did not turn a hair. She knew already.

“I was as pleased as Punch when I found out,” she told her stepmother. “You see, darling, you can tell me if he's all right in bed.”

This was Avice Crichton's best scene, it lasted a full ten minutes, and Michael had realized from the beginning that it was effective and important. Avice's cold, matter-of-fact prettiness had been exactly what he had thought would be so telling in the circumstances. But after half-a-dozen rehearsals he began to think that that was all she had to give. He talked it over with Julia.

“How d'you think Avice is shaping?”

“It's early days to tell yet.”

“I'm not happy about her. You said she could act. I've seen no sign of it yet.”

“It's a cast-iron part. She can't really go wrong in it.”

“You know just as well as I do that there's no such thing as a cast-iron part. However good a part is, it has to be acted for all it's worth. I'm not sure if it wouldn't be better to kick her out and get somebody else.”

“That wouldn't be so easy. I think you ought to give her a chance.”

“She's so awkward, her gestures are so meaningless.”

Julia reflected. She had her reasons for wishing to keep Avice in the cast. She knew her well enough to be sure that if she were dismissed she would tell Tom that it was because Julia was jealous of her. He loved her and would believe anything she said. He might even think that Julia had put this affront on her in revenge for his desertion. No, no, she must stay. She must play the part, and fail; and Tom must see with his own eyes what a bad actress she was. They both of them thought the play would make her. Fools. It would kill her.

“You know how clever you are, Michael, I'm sure you can train her if you're willing to take a little trouble.”

“But that's just it, she doesn't seem able to take direction. I show her exactly how to say a line and then she goes and says it in her own way. You wouldn't believe it, but sometimes I can hardly help thinking she's under the delusion that she knows better than I do.”

“You make her nervous. When you tell her to do something she's in such a dither she doesn't know what she's up to.”

“Good lord, no one could be more easy than I am. I've never even been sharp with her.”

Julia gave him an affectionate smile.

“Are you going to pretend that you really don't know what's the matter with her?”

“No, what?”

He looked at her with a blank face.

“Come off it, darling. Haven't you noticed that she's madly in love with you?”

“With me? But I thought she was practically engaged to Tom. Nonsense. You're always fancying things like that.”

“But it's quite obvious. After all she isn't the first who's fallen for your fatal beauty, and I don't suppose she'll be the last.”

“Heaven knows, I don't want to queer poor Tom's pitch.”

“It's not your fault, is it?”

“What d'you want me to do about it then?”

“Well, I think you ought to be nice to her. She's very young, you know, poor thing. What she wants is a helping hand. If you took her alone a few times and went through the part with her I believe you could do wonders. Why don't you take her out to lunch one day and have a talk to her?”

She saw the gleam in Michael's eyes as he considered the proposition and the shadow of a smile that was outlined on his lips.

“Of course the great thing is to get the play as well acted as we can.”

“I know it'll be a bore for you, but honestly, for the sake of the play I think it'll be worth while.”

“You know that I would never do anything to upset you, Julia. I mean, I'd much sooner fire the girl and get someone else in her place.”

“I think that would be such a mistake. I'm convinced that if you'll only take enough trouble with her she'll give a very good performance.”

He walked up and down the room once or twice. He seemed to be considering the matter from every side.

“Well, I suppose it's my job to get the best performance I can out of every member of my cast. In every case you have to find out which is the best method of approach.”

He threw out his chin and drew in his belly. He straightened his back. Julia knew that Avice Crichton would hold the part, and next day at rehearsal he took her aside and had a long talk with her. She knew by his manner exactly what he was saying and, watching them out of the corner of her eye, presently she saw Avice nod and smile. He had asked her to lunch with him. With a contented mind Julia went on studying her part.

Chapter 27

They had been rehearsing for a fortnight when Roger arrived from Austria. He had been spending a few weeks on a Carinthian lake, and after a day or two in London was to go and stay with friends in Scotland. Since Michael had to dine early to go to the theatre Julia went to meet him by herself. When she was dressing, Evie, sniffing as usual, told her that she was taking as much pains to make herself look nice as if she were going to meet a young man. She wanted Roger to be proud of her, and certainly she looked very young and pretty in her summer frock as she strolled up and down the platform. You would have thought, but wrongly, that she was perfectly unconscious of the attention she attracted. Roger, after a month in the sun, was very brown, but he was still rather spotty and he seemed thinner than when he had left London at the New Year. She hugged him with exuberant affection. He smiled slightly.

They were to dine by themselves. Julia asked him if he would like to go to a play afterwards or to the pictures, but he said he preferred to stay at home.

“That'll be much nicer,” she answered, “and we'll just talk.”

There was indeed a subject that Michael had invited her to discuss with Roger when the opportunity arose. Now that he was going to Cambridge so soon he ought to make up his mind what he wanted to do. Michael was afraid that he would drift through his time there and then go into a broker's office or even on the stage. Thinking that Julia had more tact than he, and more influence with the boy, he had urged her to put before him the advantages of the Foreign Office and the brilliant possibilities of the Bar. Julia thought it would be strange if in the course of two or three hours' conversation she could not find a way to lead to this important topic. At dinner she tried to get him to talk about Vienna. But he was reticent.

“Oh, I just did the usual things, you know. I saw the sights and worked hard at my German. I knocked about in beer places. I went to the opera a good deal.”

She wondered if he had had any love affairs.

“Anyhow, you haven't come back engaged to a Viennese maiden,” she said, thinking to draw him out.

He gave her a reflective, but faintly amused look. You might almost have thought that he had seen what she was driving at. It was strange; though he was her own son she did not feel quite at home with him.

“No,” he answered, “I was too busy to bother with that sort of thing.”

“I suppose you went to all the theatres.”

“I went two or three times.”

“Did you see anything that would be any use to me?”

“You know, I never thought about that.”

His answer might have seemed a little ungracious but that it was accompanied by a smile, and his smile was very sweet. Julia wondered again how it was that he had inherited so little of Michael's beauty and of her charm. His red hair was nice, but his pale lashes gave his face a sort of empty look. Heaven only knew where with such a father and such a mother he had got his rather lumpy figure. He was eighteen now; it was time he fined down. He seemed a trifle apathetic; he had none of her sparkling vitality; she could picture the vividness with which she would have narrated her experiences if she had just spent six months in Vienna. Why, already she had made a story about her stay at St. Malo with Aunt Carrie and her mother that made people roar with laughter. They all said it was as good as a play, and her own impression was that it was much better than most. She told it to Roger now. He listened with his slow, quiet smile; but she had an uneasy feeling that he did not think it quite so funny as she did. She sighed in her heart. Poor lamb, he could have no sense of humour. Then he made some remark that led her to speak of Nowadays. She told him its story, and explained what she was doing with her part; she talked to him of the cast and described the sets. At the end of dinner it suddenly struck her that she had been talking entirely of herself and her own interests. She did not know how she had been led to do this, and the suspicion flashed across her mind that Roger had guided the conversation in that direction so that it should be diverted from him and his affairs. But she put it aside. He really wasn't intelligent enough for that. It was later when they sat in the drawing-room listening to the radio and smoking, that Julia found the chance to slip in, apparently in the most casual fashion, the question she had prepared.

“Have you made up your mind what you're going to be yet?”

“No. Is there any hurry?”

“You know how ignorant I am about everything. Your father says that if you're going to be a barrister you ought to work at law when you go to Cambridge. On the other hand, if you fancy the Foreign Office, you should take up modern languages.”

He looked at her for so long, with that queer, reflective air of his, that Julia had some difficulty in holding her light, playful and yet affectionate expression.

“If I believed in God I'd be a priest,” he said at last.

“A priest?”

Julia could hardly believe her ears. She had a feeling of acute discomfort. But his answer sank into her mind and in a flash she saw him as a cardinal, inhabiting a beautiful palazzo in Rome, filled with wonderful pictures, and surrounded by obsequious prelates; and then again as a saint, in a mitre and vestments heavily embroidered with gold, with benevolent gestures distributing bread to the poor. She saw herself in a brocaded dress and a string of pearls. The mother of the Borgias.

“That was all right in the sixteenth century,” she said. “It's too late in the day for that.”

“Much.”

“I can't think what put such an idea in your head.” He did not answer, so that she had to speak again. “Aren't you happy?”

“Quite,” he smiled.

“What is it you want?”

Once again he gave her his disconcerting stare. It was hard to know if he was serious, for his eyes faintly shimmered with amusement.

“Reality.”

“What do you mean?”

“You see, I've lived all my life in an atmosphere of makebelieve. I want to get down to brass tacks. You and father are all right breathing this air, it's the only air you know and you think it's the air of heaven. It stifles me.”

Julia listened to him attentively, trying to understand what he meant.

“We're actors, and successful ones. That's why we've been able to surround you with every luxury since you were born. You could count on the fingers of one hand the actors who've sent their son to Eton.”

“I'm very grateful for all you've done for me.”

“Then what are you reproaching us for?”

“I'm not reproaching you. You've done everything you could for me. Unfortunately for me you've taken away my belief in everything.”

“We've never interfered with your beliefs. I know we're not religious people, we're actors, and after eight performances a week one wants one's Sundays to oneself. I naturally expected they'd see to all that at school.”

He hesitated a little before he spoke again. One might have thought that he had to make a slight effort over himself to continue.

“When I was just a kid, I was fourteen, I was standing one night in the wings watching you act. It must have been a pretty good scene, you said the things you had to say so sincerely, and what you were saying was so moving, I couldn't help crying. I was all worked up. I don't know how to say it quite, I was uplifted; I felt terribly sorry for you, I felt a bloody little hero; I felt I'd never do anything again that was beastly or underhand. And then you had to come to the back of the stage, near where I was standing, the tears were streaming down your face; you stood with your back to the audience and in your ordinary voice you said to the stage manager: what the bloody hell is that electrician doing with the lights? I told him to leave out the blue. And then in the same breath you turned round and faced the audience with a great cry of anguish and went on with the scene.”

“But, darling, that was acting. If an actress felt the emotions she represented she'd tear herself to pieces. I remember the scene well. It used to bring down the house. I've never heard such applause in my life.”

“I suppose I was a fool to be taken in by it. I believed you meant what you said. When I saw that it was all pretence it smashed something. I've never believed in you since. I'd been made a fool of once; I made up my mind that I wouldn't ever be made a fool of again.”

She gave him her delightful and disarming smile.

“Darling, I think you're talking nonsense.”

“Of course you do. You don't know the difference between truth and make-believe. You never stop acting. It's second nature to you. You act when there's a party here. You act to the servants, you act to Father, you act to me. To me you act the part of the fond, indulgent, celebrated mother. You don't exist, you're only the innumerable parts you've played. I've often wondered if there was ever a you or if you were never anything more than a vehicle for all these other people that you've pretended to be. When I've seen you go into an empty room I've sometimes wanted to open the door suddenly, but I've been afraid to in case I found nobody there.”

She looked up at him quickly. She shivered, for what he said gave her an eerie sensation. She listened to him attentively, with a certain anxiety, for he was so serious that she felt he was expressing something that had burdened him for years. She had never in his whole life heard him talk so much.

“D'you think I'm only sham?”

“Not quite. Because sham is all you are. Sham is your truth. Just as margarine is butter to people who don't know what butter is.”

She had a vague feeling of guilt. The Queen in Hamlet: “And let me wring your heart; for so I shall, if it be made of penetrable stuff.” Her thoughts wandered.

(“I wonder if I'm too old to play Hamlet. Siddons and Sarah Bernhardt played him. I've got better legs than any of the men I've seen in the part. I'll ask Charles what he thinks. Of course there's that bloody blank verse. Stupid of him not to write it in prose. Of course I might do it in French at the François. God,what a stunt that would be.”)

She saw herself in a black doublet, with long silk hose. “Alas, poor Yorick.” But she bethought herself.

“You can hardly say that your father doesn't exist. Why, he's been playing himself for the last twenty years.” (“Michael could play the King, not in French, of course, but if we decided to have a shot at it in London.”)

“Poor father, I suppose he's good at his job, but he's not very intelligent, is he? He's so busy being the handsomest man in England.”

“I don't think it's very nice of you to speak of your father like that.”

“Have I told you anything you don't know?” he asked coolly.

Julia wanted to smile, but would not allow the look of somewhat pained dignity to leave her face.

“It's our weakness, not our strength, that endears us to those who love us,” she replied.

“In what play did you say that?”

She repressed a gesture of annoyance. The words had come naturally to her lips, but as she said them she remembered that they were out of a play. Little brute! But they came in very appositely.

“You're hard,” she said plaintively. She was beginning to feel more and more like Hamlet's mother. “Don't you love me?”

“I might if I could find you. But where are you? If one stripped you of your exhibitionism, if one took your technique away from you, if one peeled you as one peels an onion of skin after skin of pretence and insincerity, of tags of old parts and shreds of faked emotions, would one come upon a soul at last?” He looked at her with his grave sad eyes and then he smiled a little. “I like you all right.”

“Do you believe I love you?”

“In your way.”

Julia's face was suddenly discomposed.

“If you only knew the agony I suffered when you were ill! I don't know what I should have done if you'd died!”

“You would have given a beautiful performance of a bereaved mother at the bier of her only child.”

“Not nearly such a good performance as if I'd had the opportunity of rehearsing it a few times,” Julia answered tartly. “You see, what you don't understand is that acting isn't nature; it's art, and art is something you create. Real grief is ugly; the business of the actor is to represent it not only with truth but with beauty. If I were really dying as I've died in half-a-dozen plays, d'you think I'd care whether my gestures were graceful and my faltering words distinct enough to carry to the last row of the gallery? If it's a sham it's no more a sham than a sonata of Beethoven's, and I'm no more of a sham than the pianist who plays it. It's cruel to say that I'm not fond of you. I'm devoted to you. You've been the only thing in my life.”

“No. You were fond of me when I was a kid and you could have me photographed with you. It made a lovely picture and it was fine publicity. But since then you haven't bothered much about me. I've bored you rather than otherwise. You were always glad to see me, but you were thankful that I went my own way and didn't want to take up your time. I don't blame you; you hadn't got time in your life for anyone but yourself.”

Julia was beginning to grow a trifle impatient. He was getting too near the truth for her comfort.

“You forget that young things are rather boring.”

“Crashing, I should think,” he smiled. “But then why do you pretend that you can't bear to let me out of your sight? That's just acting too.”

“You make me very unhappy. You make me feel as if I hadn't done my duty to you.”

“But you have. You've been a very good mother. You've done something for which I shall always be grateful to you, you've left me alone.”

“I don't understand what you want.”

“I told you. Reality.”

“But where are you going to find it?”

“I don't know. Perhaps it doesn't exist. I'm young still; I'm ignorant. I thought perhaps that at Cambridge, meeting people and reading books, I might discover where to look for it. If they say it only exists in God, I'm done.”

Julia was disturbed. What he said had not really penetrated to her understanding, his words were lines and the important thing was not what they meant, but whether they “got over”, but she was sensitive to the emotion she felt in him. Of course he was only eighteen, and it would be silly to take him too seriously, she couldn't help thinking he'd got all that from somebody else, and that there was a good deal of pose in it. Did anyone have ideas of his own and did anyone not pose just a wee, wee bit? But of course it might be that at the moment he felt everything he said, and it wouldn't be very nice of her to make light of it.

“Of course I see what you mean,” she said. “My greatest wish in the world is that you should be happy. I'll manage your father, and you can do as you like. You must seek your own salvation, I see that. But I think you ought to make sure that all these ideas of yours aren't just morbid. Perhaps you were too much alone in Vienna and I daresay you read too much. Of course your father and I belong to a different generation and I don't suppose we can help you. Why don't you talk it over with someone more of your own age? Tom, for instance.”

“Tom? A poor little snob. His only ambition in life is to be a gentleman, and he hasn't the sense to see that the more he tries the more hopeless it is.”

“I thought you liked him so much. Why, at Taplow last summer you just lived in his pocket.”

“I didn't dislike him. I made use of him. He could tell me a lot of things that I wanted to know. But I thought him an insignificant, silly little thing.”

Julia remembered how insanely jealous she had been of their friendship. It made her angry to think of all the agony she had wasted.

“You've dropped him, haven't you?” he asked suddenly.

She was startled.

“I suppose I have more or less.”

“I think it's very wise of you. He wasn't up to your mark.”

He looked at her with his calm, reflective eyes, and on a sudden Julia had a sickening fear that he knew that Tom had been her lover. It was impossible, she told herself, it was only her guilty conscience that made her think so; at Taplow there had been nothing; it was incredible that any of the horrid gossip had reached his ears; and yet there was something in his expression that made her certain that he knew. She was ashamed.

“I only asked him to come down to Taplow, because I thought it would be nice for you to have a boy of that age to play around with.”

“It was.”

There was in his eyes a faint twinkle of amusement. She felt desperate. She would have liked to ask him what he was grinning at, but dared not; for she knew; he was not angry with her, she could have borne that, he was merely diverted. She was bitterly hurt. She would have cried, but that he would only laugh. And what could she say to him? He believed nothing she said. Acting! For once she was at a loss how to cope with a situation. She was up against something that she did not know, something mysterious and rather frightening. Could that be reality? At that moment they heard a car drive up.

“There's your father,” she exclaimed.

What a relief! The scene was intolerable, and she was thankful that his arrival must end it. In a moment Michael, very hearty, with his chin thrust out and his belly pulled in, looking for all his fifty odd years incredibly handsome, burst into the room and, in his manly way, thrust out his hand to greet after a six months' absence his only begotten son.

Chapter 28

Three days later Roger went up to Scotland. By the exercise of some ingenuity Julia had managed that they should not again spend any length of time alone together. When they happened to be by themselves for a few minutes they talked of indifferent things. Julia was not really sorry to see him go. She could not dismiss from her mind the curious conversation she had had with him. There was one point in particular that unaccountably worried her; this was his suggestion that if she went into an empty room and someone suddenly opened the door there would be nobody there. It made her feel very uncomfortable.

“I never set out to be a raving beauty, but the one thing no one has ever denied me is personality. It's absurd to pretend that because I can play a hundred different parts in a hundred different ways I haven't got an individuality of my own. I can do that because I'm a bloody good actress.”

She tried to think what happened to her when she went alone into an empty room.

“But I never am alone, even in an empty room. There's always Michael, or Evie, or Charles, or the public; not in the flesh, of course, but in the spirit, as it were. I must speak to Charles about Roger.”

Unfortunately he was away. But he was coming back for the dress-rehearsal and the first night; he had not missed these occasions for twenty years, and they had always had supper together after the dress-rehearsal. Michael would remain in the theatre, busy with the lights and so on, so that they would be alone.They would be able to have a good talk.

She studied her part. Julia did not deliberately create the character she was going to act by observation; she had a knack of getting into the shoes of the woman she had to portray so that she thought with her mind and felt with her senses. Her intuition suggested to her a hundred small touches that afterwards amazed people by their verisimilitude; but when they asked her where she had got them she could not say. Now she wanted to show the courageous yet uneasy breeziness of the Mrs. Marten who played golf and could talk to a man like one good chap to another and yet, essentially a respectable, middle-class woman, hankered for the security of the marriage state.

Michael never liked to have a crowd at a dress-rehearsal, and this time, anxious to keep the secret of the play till the first night, he had admitted besides Charles only the people, photographers and dressmakers, whose presence was necessary. Julia spared herself. She had no intention of giving all she had to give till the first night. It was enough if her performance was adequate. Under Michael's businesslike direction everything went off without a hitch and by ten o'clock Julia and Charles were sitting in the grill-room of the Savoy. The first thing she asked him was what he thought of Avice Crichton.

“Not at all bad and wonderfully pretty. She really looked lovely in that second-act dress.”

“I'm not going to wear the dress I wore in the second act. Charley Deverill has made me another.”

He did not see the slightly humorous glance she gave him, and if he had would not have guessed what it meant. Michael, having taken Julia's advice, had gone to a good deal of trouble with Avice. He had rehearsed her by herself upstairs in his private room and had given her every intonation and every gesture. He had also, Julia had good reason to believe, lunched with her several times and taken her out to supper. The result of all this was that she was playing the part uncommonly well. Michael rubbed his hands.

“I'm very pleased with her. I think she'll make quite a hit. I've half a mind to give her a contract.”

“I wouldn't,” said Julia. “Not till after the first night. You can never really tell how a performance is going to pan out till you've got an audience.”

“She's a nice girl and a perfect lady.”

“A nice girl, I suppose, because she's madly in love with you, and a perfect lady because she's resisting your advances till she's got a contract.”

“Oh, my dear, don't be silly. Why, I'm old enough to be her father.”

But he smiled complacently. She knew very well that his lovemaking went no farther than holding hands and a kiss or two in a taxi, but she knew also that it flattered him to imagine that she suspected him capable of infidelity.

But now Julia, having satisfied her appetite with proper regard for her figure, attacked the subject which was on her mind.

“Charles dear, I want to talk to you about Roger.”

“Oh yes, he came back the other day, didn't he? How is he?”

“My dear, a most terrible thing has happened. He's come back a fearful prig and I don't know what to do about it.”

She gave him her version of the conversation. She left out one or two things that it seemed inconvenient to mention, but what she told was on the whole accurate.

“The tragic thing is that he has absolutely no sense of humour,” she finished.

“After all he's only eighteen.”

“You could have knocked me down with a feather when he said all those things to me. I felt just like Balaam when his ass broke into light conversation.”

She gave him a gay look, but he did not even smile. He did not seem to think her remark as funny as she did.

“I can't imagine where he got his ideas. It's absurd to think that he could have thought out all that nonsense for himself.”

“Are you sure that boys of that age don't think more than we older people imagine? It's a sort of puberty of the spirit and its results are often strange.”

“It seems so deceitful of Roger to have harboured thoughts like those all these years and never breathed a word about them. He might have been accusing me.” She gave a chuckle. “To tell you the truth, when Roger was talking to me I felt just like Hamlet's mother.” Then with hardly a break: “I wonder if I'm too old to play Hamlet?”

“Gertrude isn't a very good part, is it?”

Julia broke into a laugh of frank amusement.

“Don't be idiotic, Charles. I wouldn't play the Queen. I'd play Hamlet.”

“D'you think it's suited to a woman?”

“Mrs. Siddons played it and so did Sarah Bernhardt. It would set a seal on my career, if you know what I mean. Of course there's the difficulty of the blank verse.”

“I have heard actors speak it so that it was indistinguishable from prose,” he answered.

“Yes, but that's not quite the same, is it?”

“Were you nice to Roger?”

She was surprised at his going back to that subject so suddenly, but she returned to it with a smile.

“Oh, charming.”

“It's hard not to be impatient with the absurdity of the young; they tell us that two and two make four as though it had never occurred to us, and they're disappointed if we can't share their surprise when they have just discovered that a hen lays an egg. There's a lot of nonsense in their ranting and raving, but it's not all nonsense. One ought to sympathize with them; one ought to do one's best to understand. One has to remember how much has to be forgotten and how much has to be learnt when for the first time one faces life. It's not very easy to give up one's ideals, and the brute facts of every day are bitter pills to swallow. The spiritual conflicts of adolescence can be very severe and one can do so little to resolve them.”

“But you don't really think there's anything in all this stuff of Roger's? I believe it's all a lot of communist nonsense that he's learnt in Vienna. I wish we'd never sent him there.”

“You may be right. It may be that in a year or two he'll lose sight of the clouds of glory and accept the chain. It may be that he'll find what he's looking for, if not in God, then in art.”

“I should hate him to be an actor if that's what you mean.”

“No, I don't think he'll fancy that.”

“And of course he can't be a playwright, he hasn't a sense of humour.”

“I daresay he'll be quite content to go into the Foreign Office. It would be an asset to him there.”

“What would you advise me to do?”

“Nothing. Let him be. That's probably the greatest kindness you can do him.”

“But I can't help being worried about him.”

“You needn't be. Be hopeful. You thought you'd only given birth to an ugly duckling; perhaps he's going to turn into a white-winged swan.”

Charles was not giving Julia what she wanted. She had expected him to be more sympathetic.

“I suppose he's getting old, poor dear,” she reflected. “He's losing his grip of things. He must have been impotent for years; I wonder it never struck me before.”

She asked what the time was.

“I think I ought to go. I must get a long night's rest.”

Julia slept well and when she awoke had at once a feeling of exultation. Tonight was the first night. It gave her a little thrill of pleasure to recollect that people had already been assembling at the pit and gallery doors when she left the theatre after the dress-rehearsal, and now at ten in the morning there was probably already a long queue.”

“Lucky it's a fine day for them, poor brutes.”

In bygone years she had been intolerably nervous before a first night. She had felt slightly sick all day and as the hours passed got into such a state that she almost thought she would have to leave the stage. But by now, after having passed through the ordeal so many times, she had acquired a certain nonchalance. Throughout the early part of the day she felt only happy and mildly excited; it was not till late in the afternoon that she began to feel ill at ease. She grew silent and wanted to be left alone. She also grew irritable, and Michael, having learnt from experience, took care to keep out of her way. Her hands and feet got cold and by the time she reached the theatre they were like lumps of ice. But still the apprehension that filled her was not unpleasant.

Julia had nothing to do that morning but go down to the Siddons for a word-rehearsal at noon, so she lay in bed till late. Michael did not come back to lunch, having last things to do to the sets, and she ate alone. Then she went to bed and for an hour slept soundly. Her intention was to rest all the afternoon; Miss Phillips was coming at six to give her a light massage, and by seven she wanted to be at the theatre. But when she awoke she felt so much refreshed that it irked her to stay in bed, so she made up her mind to get up and go for a walk. It was a fine, sunny day. Liking the town better than the country and streets more than trees, she did not go into the Park, but sauntered round the neighbouring squares, deserted at that time of year, idly looking at the houses, and thought how much she preferred her own to any of them. She felt at ease and light-hearted. Then she thought it time to go home. She had just reached the corner of Stanhope Place when she heard her name called in a voice that she could not but recognize.

“Julia.”

She turned round and Tom, his face all smiles, caught her up. She had not seen him since her return from France. He was very smart in a neat grey suit and a brown hat. He was tanned by the sun.

“I thought you were away.”

“I came back on Monday. I didn't ring up because I knew you were busy with the final rehearsals. I'm coming tonight; Michael gave me a stall.”

“Oh, I'm glad.”

It was plain that he was delighted to see her. His face was eager and his eyes shone. She was pleased to discover that the sight of him excited no emotion in her. She wondered as they went on talking what there was in him that had ever so deeply affected her.

“What on earth are you wandering about like this for?”

“I've been for a stroll. I was just going in to tea.”

“Come and have tea with me.”

His flat was just round the corner. Indeed he had caught sight of her just as he was going down the mews to get to it.

“How is it you're back so early?”

“Oh, there's nothing much on at the office just now. You know, one of our partners died a couple of months ago, and I'm getting a bigger share. It means I shall be able to keep on the flat after all. Michael was jolly decent about it, he said I could stay on rent free till things got better. I hated the idea of turning out. Do come. I'd love to make you a cup of tea.”

He rattled on so vivaciously that Julia was amused. You would never have thought to listen to him that there had ever been anything between them. He seemed perfectly unembarrassed.

“All right. But I can only stay a minute.”

“O.K.”

They turned into the mews and she preceded him up the narrow staircase.

“You toddle along to the sitting-room and I'll put the water on to boil.”

She went in and sat down. She looked round the room that had been the scene of so many emotions for her. Nothing was changed. Her photograph stood in its old place, but on the chimney-piece was a large photograph also of Avice Crichton. On it was written for Tom from Avice. Julia took everything in. The room might have been a set in which she had once acted; it was vaguely familiar, but no longer meant anything to her. The love that had consumed her then, the jealousy she had stifled, the ecstasy of surrender, it had no more reality than one of the innumerable parts she had played in the past. She relished her indifference. Tom came in, with the tea-cloth she had given him, and neatly set out the tea-service which she had also given him. She did not know why the thought of his casually using still all her little presents made her inclined to laugh. Then he came in with the tea and they drank it sitting side by side on the sofa. He told her more about his improved circumstances. In his pleasant, friendly way he acknowledged that it was owing to the work that through her he had been able to bring the firm that he had secured a larger share in the profits. He told her of the holiday from which he had just returned. It was quite clear to Julia that he had no inkling how much he had made her suffer. That too made her now inclined to laugh.

“I hear you're going to have an enormous success tonight.”

“It would be nice, wouldn't it?”

“Avice says that both you and Michael have been awfully good to her. Take care she doesn't romp away with the play.”

He said it chaffingly, but Julia wondered whether Avice had told him that this was what she expected to do.

“Are you engaged to her?”

“No. She wants her freedom. She says an engagement would interfere with her career.”

“With her what?” The words slipped out of Julia's mouth before she could stop them, but she immediately recovered herself. “Yes, I see what she means of course.”

“Naturally, I don't want to stand in her way. I mean, supposing after tonight she got a big offer for America I can quite see that she ought to be perfectly free to accept.”

Her career! Julia smiled quietly to herself.

“You know, I do think you're a brick, the way you've behaved to her.”

“Why?”

“Oh, well, you know what women are!”

As he said this he slipped his arm round her waist and kissed her. She laughed outright.

“What an absurd little thing you are.”

“How about a bit of love?”

“Don't be so silly.”

“What is there silly about it? Don't you think we've been divorced long enough?”

“I'm all for irrevocable divorce. And what about Avice?”

“Oh, she's different. Come on.”

“Has it slipped your memory that I've got a first night tonight?”

“There's plenty of time.”

He put both arms round her and kissed her softly. She looked at him with mocking eyes. Suddenly she made up her mind.

“All right.”

They got up and went into the bedroom. She took off her hat and slipped out of her dress. He held her in his arms as he had held her so often before. He kissed her closed eyes and the little breasts of which she was so proud. She gave him her body to do what he wanted with, but her spirit held aloof. She returned his kisses out of amiability, but she caught herself thinking of the part she was going to play that night. She seemed to be two persons, the mistress in her lover's embrace, and the actress who already saw in her mind's eye the vast vague dark audience and heard the shouts of applause as she stepped on to the stage. When, a little later, they lay side by side, he with his arm round her neck, she forgot about him so completely that she was quite surprised when he broke a long silence.

“Don't you care for me any more?”

She gave him a little hug.

“Of course, darling. I dote on you.”

“You're so strange today.”

She realized that he was disappointed. Poor little thing, she didn't want to hurt his feelings. He was very sweet really.

“With the first night before me I'm not really myself today. You mustn't mind.”

When she came to the conclusion, quite definitely now, that she no longer cared two straws for him she could not help feeling a great pity for him. She stroked his cheek gently.

“Sweetie pie.” (“I wonder if Michael remembered to have tea sent along to the queues. It doesn't cost much and they do appreciate it so enormously.”) “You know, I really must get up. Miss Phillips is coming at six. Evie will be in a state, she won't be able to think what's happened to me.”

She chattered brightly while she dressed. She was conscious, although she did not look at him, that Tom was vaguely uneasy. She put her hat on, then she took his face in both her hands and gave him a friendly kiss.

“Good-bye, my lamb. Have a good time tonight.”

“Best of luck.”

He smiled with some awkwardness. She perceived that he did not quite know what to make of her. Julia slipped out of the flat, and if she had not been England's leading actress, and a woman of hard on fifty, she would have hopped on one leg all the way down Stanhope Place till she got to her house. She was as pleased as Punch. She let herself in with her latchkey and closed the front door behind her.

“I daresay there's something in what Roger said. Love isn't worth all the fuss they make about it.”

Chapter 29

Four hours later it was all over. The play went well from the beginning; the audience, notwithstanding the season a fashionable one, were pleased after the holidays to find themselves once more in a playhouse, and were ready to be amused. It was an auspicious beginning for the theatrical season. There had been great applause after each act and at the end a dozen curtains calls; Julia took two by herself and even she was startled by the warmth of her reception. She had made the little halting speech, prepared beforehand, which the occasion demanded. There had been a final call of the entire company and then the orchestra had struck up the National Anthem. Julia, pleased, excited and happy, went to her dressing-room. She had never felt more sure of herself. She had never acted with greater brilliance, variety and resource. The play ended with a long tirade in which Julia, as the retired harlot, castigated the flippancy, the uselessness, the immorality of the idle set into which her marriage had brought her. It was two pages long and there was not another actress in England who could have held the attention of the audience while she delivered it. With her exquisite timing, with the modulation of her beautiful voice, with her command of the gamut of emotions, she had succeeded by a miracle of technique in making it a thrilling, almost spectacular climax to the play. A violent action could not have been more exciting nor an unexpected dénouement more surprising. The whole cast had been excellent with the exception of Avice Crichton. Julia hummed in an undertone as she went into her dressing-room.

Michael followed her in almost at once.

“It looks like a winner all right.” He threw his arms round her and kissed her. “By God, what a performance you gave.”

“You weren't so bad yourself, dear.”

“That's the sort of part I can play on my head,” he answered carelessly, modest as usual about his own acting. “Did you hear them during your long speech? That ought to knock the critics.”

“Oh, you know what they are. They'll give all their attention to the blasted play and then three lines at the end to me.”

“You're the greatest actress in the world, darling, but by God, you're a bitch.”

Julia opened her eyes very wide in an expression of the most naïve surprise.

“Michael, what do you mean?”

“Don't look so innocent. You know perfectly well. Do you think you can cod an old trooper like me?”

He was looking at her with twinkling eyes and it was very difficult for her not to burst out laughing.

“I am as innocent as a babe unborn.”

“Come off it. If anyone ever deliberately killed a performance you killed Avice's. I couldn't be angry with you, it was so beautifully done.”

Now Julia simply could not conceal the little smile that curled her lips. Praise is always grateful to the artist. Avice's one big scene was in the second act. It was with Julia, and Michael had rehearsed it so as to give it all to the girl. This was indeed what the play demanded and Julia, as always, had in rehearsals accepted his direction. To bring out the colour of her blue eyes and to emphasize her fair hair they had dressed Avice in pale blue. To contrast with this Julia had chosen a dress of an agreeable yellow. This she had worn at the dress rehearsal. But she had ordered another dress at the same time, of sparkling silver, and to the surprise of Michael and the consternation of Avice it was in this that she made her entrance in the second act. Its brilliance, the way it took the light, attracted the attention of the audience. Avice's blue looked drab by comparison. When the reached the important scene they were to have together Julia produced, as a conjurer produces a rabbit from his hat, a large handkerchief of scarlet chiffon and with this she played. She waved it, she spread it out as though to look at it, she screwed it up, she wiped her brow with it, she delicately blew her nose. The audience fascinated could not take their eyes away from the red rag. And she moved upstage so that Avice to speak to her had to turn her back on the audience, and when they were sitting on a sofa together she took her hand, in an impulsive way that seemed to the public exquisitely natural, and sitting well back herself forced Avice to turn her profile to the house. Julia had noticed early in rehearsals that in profile Avice had a sheep-like look. The author had given Avice lines to say that had so much amused the cast at the first rehearsal that they had all burst out laughing. Before the audience had quite realized how funny they were Julia had cut in with her reply, and the audience anxious to hear it suppressed their laughter. The scene which was devised to be extremely amusing took on a sardonic colour, and the character Avice played acquired a certain odiousness. Avice in her inexperience, not getting the laughs she had expected, was rattled; her voice grew hard and her gestures awkward. Julia took the scene away from her and played it with miraculous virtuosity. But her final stroke was accidental. Avice had a long speech to deliver, and Julia nervously screwed her red handkerchief into a ball; the action almost automatically suggested an expression; she looked at Avice with troubled eyes and two heavy tears rolled down her cheeks. You felt the shame with which the girl's flippancy affected her, and you saw her pain because her poor little ideals of uprightness, her hankering for goodness, were so brutally mocked. The episode lasted no more than a minute, but in that minute, by those tears and by the anguish of her look, Julia laid bare the sordid misery of the woman's life. That was the end of Avice.

“And I was such a damned fool, I thought of giving her a contract,” said Michael.

“Why don't you?”

“When you've got your knife into her? Not on your life. You're a naughty little thing to be so jealous. You don't really think she means anything to me, do you? You ought to know by now that you're the only woman in the world for me.”

Michael thought that Julia had played this trick on account of the rather violent flirtation he had been having with Avice, and though, of course, it was hard luck on Avice he could not help being a trifle flattered.

“You old donkey,” smiled Julia, knowing exactly what he was thinking and tickled to death at his mistake. “After all, you are the handsomest man in London.”

“All that's as it may be. But I don't know what the author'll say. He's a conceited little ape and it's not a bit the scene he wrote.”

“Oh, leave him to me. I'll fix him.”

There was a knock at the door and it was the author himself who came in. With a cry of delight, Julia went up to him, threw her arms round his neck and kissed him on both cheeks.

“Are you pleased?”

“It looks like a success,” he answered, but a trifle coldly.

“My dear, it'll run for a year.” She placed her hands on his shoulders and looked him full in the face. “But you're a wicked, wicked man.”

“I?”

“You almost ruined my performance. When I came to that bit in the second act and suddenly saw what it meant I nearly broke down. You knew what was in that scene, you're the author; why did you let us rehearse it all the time as if there was no more in it than appeared on the surface? We're only actors, how can you expect us to—to fathom your subtlety? It's the best scene in your play and I almost bungled it. No one in the world could have written it but you. Your play's brilliant, but in that scene there's more than brilliance, there's genius.”

The author flushed. Julia looked at him with veneration. He felt shy and happy and proud.

(“In twenty-four hours the mug'll think he really meant the scene to go like that.”)

Michael beamed.

“Come along to my dressing-room and have a whisky and soda. I'm sure you need a drink after all that emotion.”

They went out as Tom came in. Tom's face was red with excitement.

“My dear, it was grand. You were simply wonderful. Gosh, what a performance.”

“Did you like it? Avice was good, wasn't she?”

“No, rotten.”

“My dear, what do you mean? I thought she was charming.”

“You simply wiped the floor with her. She didn't even look pretty in the second act.”

Avice's career!

“I say, what are you doing afterwards?”

“Dolly's giving a party for us.”

“Can't you cut it and come along to supper with me? I'm madly in love with you.”

“Oh, what nonsense. How can I let Dolly down?”

“Oh, do.”

His eyes were eager. She could see that he desired her as he had never done before, and she rejoiced in her triumph. But she shook her head firmly. There was a sound in the corridor of a crowd of people talking, and they both knew that a troop of friends were forcing their way down the narrow passage to congratulate her.

“Damn all these people. God, how I want to kiss you. I'll ring you up in the morning.”

The door burst open and Dolly, fat, perspiring and bubbling over with enthusiasm, swept in at the head of a throng that packed the dressing-room to suffocation. Julia submitted to being kissed by all and sundry. Among others were three or four well-known actresses, and they were prodigal of their praise. Julia gave a beautiful performance of unaffected modesty. The corridor was packed now with people who wanted to get at least a glimpse of her. Dolly had to fight her way out.

“Try not to be too late,” she said to Julia. “It's going to be a heavenly party.”

“I'll come as soon as ever I can.”

At last the crowd was got rid of and Julia, having undressed, began to take off her make-up. Michael came in, wearing a dressing-gown.

“I say, Julia, you'll have to go to Dolly's party by yourself. I've got to see the libraries and I can't manage it. I'm going to sting them.”

“Oh, all right.”

“They're waiting for me now. See you in the morning.”

He went out and she was left alone with Evie. The dress she had arranged to wear for Dolly's party was placed over a chair. Julia smeared her face with cleansing cream.

“Evie, Mr. Fennell will be ringing up tomorrow. Will you say I'm out?”

Evie looked in the mirror and caught Julia's eyes.

“And if he rings up again?”

“I don't want to hurt his feelings, poor lamb, but I have a notion I shall be very much engaged for some time now.”

Evie sniffed loudly and with that rather disgusting habit of hers drew her forefinger across the bottom of her nose.

“I understand,” she said dryly.

“I always said you weren't such a fool as you looked.” Julia went on with her face. “What's that dress doing on that chair?”

“That? That's the dress you said you'd wear for the party.

“Put it away. I can't go to the party without Mr. Gosselyn.”

“Since when?”

“Shut up, you old hag. Phone through and say that I've got a bad headache and had to go home to bed, but Mr. Gosselyn will come if he possibly can.”

“The party's being given special for you. You can't let the poor old gal down like that?”

Julia stamped her feet.

“I don't want to go to a party. I won't go to a party.”

“There's nothing for you to eat at home.”

“I don't want to go home. I'll go and have supper at a restaurant.”

“Who with?”

“By myself.”

Evie gave her a puzzled glance.

“The play's a success, isn't it?”

“Yes. Everything's a success. I feel on top of the world. I feel like a million dollars. I want to be alone and enjoy myself. Ring up the Berkeley and tell them to keep a table for one in the little room. They'll know what I mean.”

“What's the matter with you?”

“I shall never in all my life have another moment like this. I'm not going to share it with anyone.”

When Julia had got her face clean she left it. She neither painted her lips nor rouged her cheeks. She put on again the brown coat and skirt in which she had come to the theatre and the same hat. It was a felt hat with a brim, and this she pulled down over one eye so that it should hide as much of her face as possible. When she was ready she looked at herself in the glass.

“I look like a working dressmaker whose husband's left her, and who can blame him? I don't believe a soul would recognize me.”

Evie had had the telephoning done from the stage door, and when she came back Julia asked her if there were many people waiting for her there.

“About three 'undred I should say.”

“Damn.” She had a sudden desire to see nobody and be seen by nobody. She wanted just for one hour to be obscure. “Tell the fireman to let me out at the front and I'll take a taxi, and then as soon as I've got out let the crowd know there's no use in their waiting.”

“God only knows what I 'ave to put up with,” said Evie darkly.

“You old cow.”

Julia took Evie's face in her hands and kissed her raddled cheeks; then slipped out of her dressing-room, on to the stage and through the iron door into the darkened auditorium.

Julia's simple disguise was evidently adequate, for when she came into the little room at the Berkeley of which she was peculiarly fond, the head-waiter did not immediately know her.

“Have you got a corner that you can squeeze me into?” she asked diffidently.

Her voice and a second glance told him who she was.

“Your favourite table is waiting for you, Miss Lambert. The message said you would be alone?” Julia nodded and he led her to a table in the corner of the room. “I hear you've had a big success tonight, Miss Lambert.” How quickly good news travelled. “What can I order?”

The head-waiter was surprised that Julia should be having supper by herself, but the only emotion that it was his business to show clients was gratification at seeing them.

“I'm very tired, Angelo.”

“A little caviare to begin with, madame, or some oysters?”

“Oysters, Angelo, but fat ones.”

“I will choose them myself, Miss Lambert, and to follow?”

Julia gave a long sigh, for now she could, with a free conscience, order what she had had in mind ever since the end of the second act. She felt she deserved a treat to celebrate her triumph, and for once she meant to throw prudence to the winds.

“Grilled steak and onions, Angelo, fried potatoes, and a bottle of Bass. Give it me in a silver tankard.”

She probably hadn't eaten fried potatoes for ten years. But what an occasion it was! By a happy chance on this day she had confirmed her hold on the public by a performance that she could only describe as scintillating, she had settled an old score, by one ingenious devise disposing of Avice and making Tom see what a fool he had been, and best of all had proved to herself beyond all question that she was free from the irksome bonds that had oppressed her. Her thoughts flickered for an instant round Avice.

“Silly little thing to try to put a spoke in my wheel. I'll let her have her laughs tomorrow.”

The oysters came and she ate them with enjoyment. She ate two pieces of brown bread and butter with the delicious sense of imperilling her immortal soul, and she took a long drink from the silver tankard.

“Beer, glorious beer,” she murmured.

She could see Michael's long face if he knew what she was doing. Poor Michael who imagined she had killed Avice's scene because she thought he was too attentive to that foolish little blonde. Really, it was pitiful how stupid men were. They said women were vain; why, they were modest violets in comparison with men. She could not but laugh when she thought of Tom. He had wanted her that afternoon, he had wanted her still more that night. It was wonderful to think that he meant no more to her than a stage-hand. It gave one a grand feeling of confidence to be heart-whole.

The room in which she sat was connected by three archways with the big dining-room where they supped and danced; amid the crowd doubtless were a certain number who had been to the play. How surprised they would be if they knew that the quiet little woman in the corner of the adjoining room, her face half hidden by a felt hat, was Julia Lambert. It gave her a pleasant sense of independence to sit there unknown and unnoticed. They were acting a play for her and she was the audience. She caught brief glimpses of them as they passed the archway, young men and young women, young men and women not so young, men with bald heads and men with fat bellies, old harridans clinging desperately to their painted semblance of youth. Some were in love, and some were jealous, and some were indifferent.

Her steak arrived. It was cooked exactly as she liked it, and the onions were crisp and brown. She ate the fried potatoes delicately, with her fingers, savouring each one as though it were the passing moment that she would bid delay.

“What is love beside steak and onions?” she asked. It was enchanting to be alone and allow her mind to wander. She thought once more of Tom and spiritually shrugged a humorous shoulder. “It was an amusing experience.”

It would certainly be useful to her one of these days. The sight of the dancers seen through the archway was so much like a scene in a play that she was reminded of a notion that she had first had in St. Malo. The agony that she had suffered when Tom deserted her recalled to her memory Racine's Phèdie which she had studied as a girl with old Jane Taitbout. She read the play again. The torments that afflicted Theseus' queen were the torments that afflicted her, and she could not but think that there was a striking similarity in their situations. That was a part she could act; she knew what it felt like to be turned down by a young man one had a fancy for. Gosh, what a performance she could give! She knew why in the spring she had acted so badly that Michael had preferred to close down; it was because she was feeling the emotions she portrayed. That was no good. You had to have had the emotions, but you could only play them when you had got over them. She remembered that Charles had once said to her that the origin of poetry was emotion recollected in tranquillity. She didn't know anything about poetry, but it was certainly true about acting.

“Clever of poor old Charles to get hold of an original idea like that. It shows how wrong it is to judge people hastily. One thinks the aristocracy are a bunch of nit-wits, and then one of them suddenly comes out with something like that that's so damned good it takes your breath away.”

But Julia had always felt that Racine had made a great mistake in not bringing on his heroine till the third act.

“Of course I wouldn't have any nonsense like that if I played it. Half an act to prepare my entrance if you like, but that's ample.”

There was no reason why she should not get some dramatist to write her a play on the subject, either in prose or in short lines of verse with rhymes at not too frequent intervals. She could manage that, and effectively. It was a good idea, there was no doubt about it, and she knew the clothes she would wear, not those flowing draperies in which Sarah swathed herself, but the short Greek tunic that she had seen on a bas-relief when she went to the British Museum with Charles.

“How funny things are! You go to those museums and galleries and think what a damned bore they are and then, when you least expect it, you find that something you've seen comes in useful. It shows art and all that isn't really waste of time.”

Of course she had the legs for a tunic, but could one be tragic in one? This she thought about seriously for two or three minutes. When she was eating outher heart for the indifferent Hippolytus (and she giggled when she thought of Tom, in his Savile Row clothes, masquerading as a young Greek hunter) could she really get her effects without abundant draperies? The difficulty excited her. But then a thought crossed her mind that for a moment dashed her spirits.

“It's all very well, but where are the dramatists? Sarah had her Sardou, Duse her D'Annunzio. But who have I got? ‘The Queen of Scots hath a bonnie bairn and I am but a barren stock.’”

She did not, however, let this melancholy reflection disturb her serenity for long. Her elation was indeed such that she felt capable of creating dramatists from the vast inane as Deucalion created men from the stones of the field.

“What nonsense that was that Roger talked the other day, and poor Charles, who seemed to take it seriously. He's a silly little prig, that's all.” She indicated a gesture towards the dance room. The lights had been lowered and from where she sat it looked more than ever like a scene in a play. “‘All the world's a stage, and all the men and women merely players.’ But there's the illusion, through that archway; it's we, the actors, who are the reality. That's the answer to Roger. They are our raw materials. We are the meaning of their lives. We take their silly little emotions and turn them into art, out of them we create beauty, and their significance is that they form the audience we must have to fulfil ourselves. They are the instruments on which we play, and what is an instrument without somebody to play on it?”

The notion exhilarated her, and for a moment or two she savoured it with satisfaction. Her brain seemed miraculously lucid.

“Roger says we don't exist. Why, it's only we who do exist. They are the shadows and we give them substance. We are the symbols of all this confused, aimless struggling that they call life, and it's only the symbol which is real. They say acting is only make-believe. That make-believe is the only reality.”

Thus Julia out of her own head framed anew the Platonic theory of ideas. It filled her with exultation. She felt a sudden wave of friendliness for that immense anonymous public who had being only to give her opportunity to express herself. Aloof on her mountain top she considered the innumerable activities of men. She had a wonderful sense of freedom from all earthly ties, and it was such an ecstasy that nothing in comparison with it had any value. She felt like a spirit in heaven.

The head-waiter came up to her with a ingratiating smile.

“Everything all right, Miss Lambert?”

“Lovely. You know, it's strange how people differ. Mrs. Siddons was a rare one for chops; I'm not a bit like her in that; I'm a rare one for steaks.”

盖房记[1]

我妻子索菲娅、我自己，以及我们一群孩子里的头一个，最早住在伦敦郊区一种号称是“梦寐以求的半独立式别墅”里。但事实上我们的住处跟我们梦想的样子完全相反。我们连招待来访朋友的地方都没有；燃煤也不得不放在屋外，靠着后墙堆成一堆。假如某天我们硬塞了几个熟人进来一起共进晚餐的话，上菜就成了一大难题。因为没有餐柜间，这种时候女仆就会习惯性地把盘子放在楼梯上或过道的凳子椅子上。假如我们就座后又有客人来的话，来人就会看到剩饭剩菜杯盘狼藉地摆放在这些地方，可能旁边还有待上桌的芹菜，于是通常便嫌弃地离开。在下雨天、扫烟囱，以及大扫除的时候，你会看到椅子四腿朝天，水桶挡在门口，人需要侧身才能在这些障碍物中间穿行。我们自然对这个别墅牢骚满腹，并下定决心：一旦条件成熟——当然是指跟钱有关的条件——我们就要将心头盘算已久的一个念头付诸实践。

这个念头就是要在比我们当时住所离城更远一点的地方盖一座我们自己的房子。这个新住宅在所有方面都将完美无缺。它的大小和比例虽然尚未可知，但足以让我们从此无比幸福快乐地生活在一起，这一点我们早已确定。盖房的花费既不能太多也不能太少，要刚刚好，能配得上我们新得的幸福。它的选址要在一个有益健康的地点，底土得是一层干沙砾，在泉水上游约九十英尺[2]处。北面需有树林，南边需有风景，还要交通便利、铁路直达。

十八个月前，蒙上天恩赐我们有了第三个孩子，我们决定要将以上想法付诸行动了。我想详细地介绍一下房子本身，而不是它的地理位置，至于我克服了多少困难最后才找到一个合适的地点，在此恕不赘述。对那些蜿蜒的路旁标记着粉红或绿色小长方形的地图我早已了如指掌。那些张贴在火车站和房产中介窗上“建筑用租地”的多姿多彩的规划图我也都谙熟于心：草图里那一行行的，或是富有艺术感的不规则的卷心菜，指的其实是大树，种下去长大后就可以提供阴凉；那一块块蓝色指的是鱼塘和喷泉；直抵地图边缘那又宽又直的一条是通往火车站的路，有时火车站的一角也会入图，以假装此地离火车站很近，有的地主大概是想以此掩盖事实。

经过相当长一段时间的仔细研究之后，我意识到我们在选址这个问题上的一些想法必须得放弃。最先放弃的是北面的树林，经过短暂的挣扎后，位于泉水上游九十英尺的要求也随之而去了。索菲娅像所有妻子一样无比执着，坚持她对南边要有优美风景的要求，而我则早早被打败不再想着沙砾底土的事了。最后我们终于定下了一块地，假装那里交通便利、有益健康，除此之外再无任何可称道之处。约定的租期是九十九年。

我们接下来要考虑的是找一位建筑设计师。我有个时不时写点艺术和科学方面的文章向杂志社投稿的朋友，他向我倾情推荐了一位彭尼先生，说这位先生在建筑方面是个全才，要说他在专业上有哪方面更为出色，那就是为普通收入的家庭设计高性价比的房子。我马上跟索菲娅提议，先好好计划一下最适合我们的房间安排，然后去拜访这位设计师，好让他把我们的计划变成现实。

我画了个草图，索菲娅也画了一个。她画的客厅和餐厅很大，几乎是我画的两倍，不过她的门窗大小还算合理。我们很快就发现无论怎么努力都不可能达成一致。争论很久都无果之后，我们就直接去了彭尼先生的办公室。我告诉了他我的来意，他拿出一张大图纸，做了一些气势十足的笔记，还标上大大的括号和破折号。坐在他的办公室里，四周环绕的是一卷卷的图纸、圆形、正方形、三角板、圆规以及其他各种被人类时不时想出来的新发明，我意识到这些我在数年前才从欧几里得几何学里隐约知道的东西原来都是真实存在的，于是我顺理成章地变成了任由他摆布的傀儡。他奇迹般地摆平了一切问题：我们被告知每一个房间只能是多大面积，上楼梯只能采用某一种方法，以及我们一次只能订多少红酒，才能放得进他脑中设想的酒窖。在他辅以实例力劝之下，不管我想不想接受，他专业的意见都在我的脑海中自动浮现出来。索菲娅当时一直保持沉默，所以我认为她也跟我一样身不由己；但她事后跟我说根本不是这么回事，她只不过是那会儿有点疲惫罢了。

在整个过程中我一直急于想说明讲定的千八百英镑不能超支，于是我又跟彭尼先生重申了一遍。

“我会把我预想的房子给您做一个大致的估算，”他呼唤他的职员，“莱能！”

“先生，请讲。”

“四十九乘五十四乘二十八，十四的两倍乘三十一乘十一，还有其他一些小地方我们大概算个一百六十。”

“八万两千四百——”

“但是最多一千八百，”我说，“是我们能给——”

“英尺，我亲爱的先生，英尺，立方英尺，”彭尼先生接着说，“莱能，就算一英尺六个便士，余数忽略不计。”

“两千两百镑。”这实在是太多了。

“这样，试试再少一点，把所有一百以下的全都减掉。”

“大概一千八百七十镑。”

“在我看来这非常令人满意，”彭尼先生说着转过身来问我，“您觉得呢？”

“约翰，你别太吹毛求疵了。”我妻子插进来说，“我相信这已经是非常非常公道的价格了，又要讲究又要便宜，二者兼得是不可能的。”

（顺便说一句，索菲娅在人前从来不会以“亲爱的”来称呼我。她的理由是，这种行为就跟古代被围城时故意把面包扔到城墙外面去一样，它其实意味着内在的匮乏而不是富足。）

我没有再跟设计师纠缠下去，然后我俩便站起身来准备告辞。

“彭尼先生，请你一定要建一个很棒的花房，”我的妻子说，“要别具特色的。最好能是中国园林风格的，在角落有些漂亮的装饰，就像史密斯夫人家的一样，或者比她的更好。”她补充了一句，转头瞥了我一眼，我在那一瞥中仿佛看见被打破了的摩西第十诫。[3]

“我们会把设计草图给您送过去，相信会非常适合您的。”彭尼先生亲切地回答，就好像对所有打算盖房的人的想法他早已拥有一本指南大全似的。

至于盖房规划的全过程我就不赘述了。有一天早上我们到现场查看房子的地基，这时建筑施工队已经选定，房子结构也已经在地上标了出来。

说起来真是奇怪。新房子画在地上的轮廓不知为何看上去真是小得荒谬又恼人。看到它，想想每天会在墙板、门柱和壁炉上撞出多少瘀青来，就觉得下半生都要在这样的狭小空间里度过将是多么凄惨。在我看来，画线标记出的起居室就跟个牢房差不多；厨房看起来就像个大盒子，而书房好像只能装下一个壁炉和一扇门。我们被告知房子画在地上看起来都是这个样子，但是索菲娅看到客厅小成这样，厌恶之情无论讲什么科学道理都没法减弱半分。得再加长六英尺——或者四英尺——至少得三英尺，她理论了半天，于是客厅相应加长了。我好不容易把她哄离现场踏上回家的路，这才大大地松了口气。

房子一天天垒高了，烟囱也竖起来了。一天，我们正站在一旁看着工人们在屋顶上忙活，施工队的工头向我们走来。

“先生，这是您自己的房子，而且我们正在做最后一根烟囱，您要不要上去看一看呢？”他说。

“我要是个男人的话，肯定上去了，”我妻子对我说，“从那么高的地方望去，周围的风景一定很美吧！”

这回答使我陷入了一种两难境地，因为我必须承认我对登高并不热衷。每次看到那种人容易失足滑落，却没有防护栏的高处，无论是悬崖峭壁、屋顶、脚手架还是其他高处，我都会觉得站在地面上远比站在这些地方更合我意。但是我的房子无论如何都算不上很高，而且也就只需要上去这么一次，所以我还是回答说我打算上去看看。

我在爬梯子的时候膝盖就已经颇感压力了，但这还不算什么；当我跟着工头踏上两条窄窄的木板，每走一步木板就向下弯一下的时候，所经受的恐惧才真正让人难以忍受。但是既然已经开始就只好继续下去，于是我接下来又爬上了另一个梯子，看起来又细又不坚固，而且顶端也没有用绳索固定。我看着梯子踏板之间的地平线，忍不住假想万一梯子某一部分突然断裂，将是多么骇人的场景。为了驱逐这个念头，我赶紧在脑海中批判起当天早上《泰晤士报》的头条社论来，可是这个方法并不奏效。于是我又开始想象，虽然看上去出奇的高，其实我离地面不过四英尺而已，但这个方法也失败了。当我正准备开始想象地面上铺着无数羽绒褥垫的时候，我发现自己已经到达了脚手架顶端。

“这儿可真高啊。”我对工头说，竭力想显得镇定自若，但显然并不成功。

“嗯，不，我们有时候盖的建筑比这个高多了。”他回答，“我得提醒您别踩到那块木板的顶端，因为它会翻转——当然，您要是从这儿掉下去，跟从纪念碑上掉下去是一样的效果，等他们把您抬起来的时候，您的小命早就玩儿完了。”他边说边眺望四下里的庄稼和天气，说得就跟这件事真的发生了一样。

这时一个工人把一摞砖放在了前面提到过的木板上，木板就在我脚边翻转了，于是我就像私家马车后面那些小个子男仆一般，被颠得上下晃动不已。我战战兢兢地问这些砖这么重会不会导致危险，同时脑中浮现出一段报纸新闻，题为“脚手架超重酿成的惨剧”。

“我正想说这个事儿呢。阿丹放的砖确实有点太多了。”工头回答，“不过只要我们不上下乱蹦，不打喷嚏，架子是不会断的。虽然那次那个拌砂浆的小子百日咳实在是太厉害，导致我可怜的兄弟吉姆挂掉了。”他语气是那么轻描淡写，就好像他自个儿长了好几个脖子，所以摔断一两个不足为虑似的。

我的妻子在远处摘雏菊，很显然她毫不在意我是在脚手架顶端，还是在底端，或是躺在圣乔治医院里；于是我打起精神准备下来，并再次踏上那个瘦小的梯子。我没法准确描述自己是怎么下来的，但整个过程中我觉得身上就像是被打了无数个孔，风从四面八方贯穿而过。待我离地面越来越近时，这种感觉终于消失了。我妻子对于高度的认知显然和我相去甚远，她仔细地询问在上面看周围风景如何，而我压根儿就忘了这件事。即便如此，我也不会再来一次。我已经下定决心再也不去打扰我的烟囱了。

接下来就是持续的焦虑以及在老住所、新房子和建筑设计事务所之间来回奔波。除此之外一切还算顺利，直到房子即将落成之际。索菲娅在建房之初热情满满，但现在她的热情已燃烧殆尽，只留下我独自面对后期遇到的种种麻烦。其中一个问题就是门廊。我本人很讨厌下雨天在别人门外等候还要经受风雨侵袭，所以我一直打算如果有朝一日要盖房就一定要有一个堪称典范的门廊。结果当工人们已经进入收尾阶段时，我才懊恼地想起我一直忘了跟彭尼先生提这件事，而他也从来没有跟我建议过要建个门廊。

“要不要门廊这纯属个人感觉和品味，”他听到我的抱怨以后如是回答，“所以，当然您要是不提，我是不会放上去的。不过这一回正好，您的房子加个门廊的话外观上会有所改善。不过这会有个问题，就是门廊的顶部会把原来楼梯平台那儿的窗子给堵住；当然我们可以在高一点的地方开个口保证通风，只要您不介意屋内有些许黑暗，或者说昏暗。”

我的第一反应就是这很可能会让我和家人患上慢性忧郁症；但是我又想起来在广告里看到过一种反射镜，据说能把阳光反射到屋子里任何一个角落，于是为了梦想中的门廊，我决定忍受窗户被遮挡的不便。不过后来我发现昏暗是全天候的——那个所谓的专利反射镜只能把一团圆圆的亮光反射到我们压根儿不想要它照到的对面墙上，而我们想要它照到的楼梯平台那里黑暗如故。

跟建筑施工队以规定好的金额签合同建房的过程中有一种陷阱，稍不留神你就会中招，这种事故有个学名叫作“产生额外费用”。如果你不想被左邻右舍说闲话，那么唯一的办法就是付给施工队一大笔远远超过合同金额的钱，中间的差额当然就是额外费用。就我的情况而言，虽然我一开始就很清楚最后肯定要付一些额外的钱，但我的常识显然还是不足；也许彭尼先生本人也应该更明确地告诉我，但凡我回答了“是”的所有问题我都得付钱。比如某个窗子，我想不想要比原设计的更大一些？而另一个窗子，考虑到门的位置，要不要比原计划的小一点点？诸如此类。此外还有一大堆的“未包含在内”的东西：餐具洗涤室的水槽、集雨箱和水泵、屋顶的天窗、刮泥板、屋顶的风向标以及东西南北四个字，还有育儿室的换气设备、厨房的换气设备，虽然这些设备运转良好，但方向却正好弄反了；还有获专利的神奇的门铃拉绳，以及皇家特许的非凡的厨房炉灶——只需三便士三法寻就能让火持续燃烧十二小时，还可以用各种方式烹制大块肉骨头，加热头一天的剩饭剩菜，煮得了蔬菜，熨得了衣服。我没有严格地把每笔花费都记个账，而且太过信任彭尼先生，认为在他手里可以放心，不会有太过分的超支。结果当我发现所有这些额外花费加起来有好几百镑时，整个人都不好了。我有种想再盖一座房子的冲动，哪怕要再经受一次所有的担忧焦虑，以证明这次我会殚精竭虑避免产生任何额外费用！

最后一切总要结束，于是不知从哪儿冒出来了一位房屋监察员。传说中监察员的职责就是要确保你不会被建筑商以附加费用形式多收哪怕半个便士。建筑商先对房子某一部分报个价，可能比实际价值贵一倍，监察员又再报一个价，只有实际价值的一半。然后他们再通过打嘴仗来解决争端，把估价的差距逐渐缩小，一直到最后取个中间价。我所有的账目都经过了此种操作。

搬家车把我们的家具和财物送到了新房子，其间还算顺利；但是在安顿下来的过程中又发生了一些恼人的小事，要不是因为索菲娅对此事的态度如同圣马丁节[4]前的和煦小阳春，估计我的感受会更加糟糕。烟就是其中一件烦心事。书房的壁炉一生火，所有的烟尘就全都灌进了屋子。我们在困扰中只好叫来了设计师彭尼先生，他第一句话就是问我们有没有试过把烟道排气阀打开来解决这个问题。我们之前确实没打开，一打开后，烟尘立刻就都被抽走了。最后，我还记得一天晚上索菲娅突然跳起来大喊，把我三魂都吓掉了两魂：“天哪，那个该死的施工队！育儿室的窗子连一根铁栅都没有装！约翰，说不定哪天我可怜的孩子们一不留神就掉出去了——他们哪里懂什么危不危险？——然后就会摔得粉身碎骨！你当初为什么要把育儿室放到三楼啊？”你们可以确信，第二天一早铁栅就钉上去了。

一八六五年

[1]本文是哈代在伦敦和布鲁姆菲尔德建筑事务所担任助理建筑师时写成，于1865年发表在《钱伯斯杂志》上，是他发表的第一篇文学类文章。此前哈代曾投稿过几首诗歌，但均被退回未录用。哈代称本文为一篇“幽默小品”，为给事务所同事和学徒取乐，并非严肃的文学作品。但本文得以发表给了哈代激励，让他开始考虑散文类写作。

[2]一英尺约为零点三零五米，九十英尺则约为二十七点四米。

[3]摩西第十诫为：“不可贪恋邻人的房屋；不可贪恋邻人的妻子、仆婢、牛驴，并他的一切所有。”

[4]圣马丁节，天主教节日，设于每年十一月十一日，大部分欧洲国家会庆祝这个节日，其性质类似美国的感恩节。

喷嚏不止的贼

许多年前，当这些老态龙钟的橡树还只有年长绅士的手杖那么粗的时候，在威塞克斯住着一个自耕农的儿子，名叫休伯特。他那时年方十四，个性坦诚直率，无忧无虑，而且很有胆量，他本人对此也颇为自得。

一个寒冷的圣诞前夕，他父亲因为找不到帮手，只得打发他到离家数英里之外的小镇上去办一趟重要差事。他骑着马去了镇上，办事耽搁了许久，直到很晚才终于办完。他回到客栈，装好马鞍，立刻动身上路。回家的路要经过布莱克摩尔山谷，那里土地肥沃但人烟稀少，沿途都是难走的黏土路和弯曲的小道。那时候跟现在一样，大部分的山谷都被茂密的树林覆盖。

当时应该已是晚上九点，休伯特正骑着他壮实的矮脚马杰里穿行在树枝交错的密林中，嘴里唱着圣诞颂歌应景。突然他觉得似乎听到树枝间传来什么声音，这让他想起他正经过的地点素有恶名：有人曾在此处被打劫。他看看杰里，真希望它的毛色是种别的颜色，因为浅灰色让这头温顺的牲畜在这浓荫暗处都十分显眼。“怕什么呀？”沉思了几分钟以后，他大声说，“杰里的腿脚又轻又快，才不会让拦路的强盗追上我。”

“嗬嗬！真的嘛！”一个低沉的声音响起来；下一秒钟一个男人从休伯特右边的树丛里窜出来，另一个男人从左边冲过来，还有一个从他前面几码[1]远的一棵树干后跳出来。他们抢走了缰绳，把休伯特拖下马来。尽管他用尽全身力气又踢又打，尽显一个英勇男孩的本色，但还是被制服了。他的胳膊被反绑起来，双腿被紧紧捆在一块儿。强盗们把他扔进了壕沟，随即牵马离开了，他只能隐约看到他们的脸被刻意涂黑了。

休伯特惊魂初定后，费了很大的劲儿终于把双腿从绳索中解救出来；但是无论怎么努力，双臂依然被紧紧绑着无法挣脱。他只好站起身来反背着手继续赶路，解不解得开只能看运气了。虽然他知道在这种情形下，光靠双脚根本不可能在当晚赶到家，但还是继续前行。不过突如其来的遇袭让他头脑有些混乱，所以走着走着就迷了路。要不是因为深知在这严寒霜冻的天气不盖铺盖睡着的后果实在太严重，他真想倒在枯叶堆里一觉睡到天亮。现在他只好向前漫游，胳膊被绳索反绑到已经麻木，心里为失去了杰里而哀痛：可怜的杰里，它从不曾踢人、咬人或表现出任何一点不端行为，现在却平白被抢走了！就连看到树丛里透出远处的灯光，也无法让他高兴起来。他朝着灯光处走去，一会儿就走到了一座大宅前，侧翼、三角阁、塔楼、城垛和烟囱在星空下依稀可见。

四下里悄无声息，但宅门却大敞着，吸引休伯特走到这里来的灯光就是从这门内传来的。他走进去，发现自己进了一个巨大的房间，应该是作宴会厅之用的，厅内灯火通明。四面墙壁被大块儿的暗色护墙板覆盖，上有凹凸纹造型、雕花、壁橱门以及这种豪宅常见的各种装饰。最吸引他的还是大厅正中那巨大的餐桌，上面摆满了丰盛的晚餐，尚未动过。餐椅已围着餐桌摆好了，看起来像是有什么突发事件导致正准备开始的宴会突然中断了。

休伯特双手被缚，就算是想吃也有心无力，除非他像猪或牛一样直接把嘴凑到盘子里去。他的第一个想法是找人帮忙。当他正要继续往里屋走去找人的时候，突然听到了门廊外传来急匆匆的脚步声和说话声，“快点！”声音低沉，跟他被拖下马时听到的那个声音一样。他刚钻到桌子底下，三个男人就进了大厅。他悄悄从垂下来的桌布底下窥视，看到了他们那涂黑的脸，对于这三人是不是打劫他的那一伙人的最后一点怀疑也立刻烟消云散了。

“好啦，”第一个人（就是声音低沉的那个）说，“我们先躲起来。他们马上就会回来的。我把他们引开的把戏还不错吧，是不是？”

“是啊，你模仿遇难的人的号叫声模仿得很像。”第二个人说。

“太棒了！”第三个人说。

“但是他们很快就会发现这是假警报。快，我们躲哪儿呢？我们得找个能待上两三个小时的地方，等到所有人都上床睡觉了再出来。哈！我知道了。这边来！我听说那里头的橱柜一年到头都开不了一次，我们正好躲里面去。”

三个人走进一条与大厅相连的走廊。休伯特往前匍匐爬了一小段，看到了走廊尽头面朝着宴会厅有一个大橱柜。窃贼们钻了进去，关上了柜门。休伯特屏住呼吸，悄悄溜过去，想看看能不能探听到他们更多的计划。他慢慢靠近，听到强盗们在低声讨论宅子里哪个房间有珠宝，哪个房间有餐具，哪个房间有其他贵重物品，很显然他们打算要大捞一把。

他们藏起来不久后，就听到外面的阳台传来一阵女士先生们欢快的闲聊声。休伯特心想可不能被他们发现自己在屋子里头晃荡，不然肯定会被当成强盗的，于是他赶紧轻手轻脚溜回大厅，走到门外，在门廊的一个黑暗的角落站定。这样他就能眼观四方但又不会被发现。过了片刻，一大群人从他旁边经过，进了房子：有一对年长的绅士和夫人、八九位年轻的女士和八九位年轻的先生，以及半打男女仆人。看来刚才宅子里的人全都出动了。

“好啦，孩子们，年轻人，我们继续晚宴吧！”年长的绅士说道，“刚才那声音到底是什么，我实在不太明白。我当时简直确信无疑是有个人就在我家门口被谋杀了。”

接着女士们开始议论，说她们当时是如何给吓坏了，如何预期会有一场大冒险，又如何发现最后什么事都没有。

“等着吧，女士们，”休伯特在心里说，“你们很快就会来一场大冒险的。”

看起来这些年轻的先生和女士是这对年长夫妇的已婚的儿女，特地在这一天赶回来陪父母一起过圣诞节。

大门已经关上了，休伯特一人留在外面门廊里。他觉得现在时机已到，可以找人帮忙了。既然没法用手敲门，他便大胆地用脚踢门。

“嘿！你在这儿捣什么乱？”门房开了门，抓住休伯特的肩膀把他扯进大厅里，报告说：“西蒙爵士，我抓到这个小子在门廊里吵吵闹闹。”

所有人都转过身来。

“把他带到前面来吧。”西蒙爵士就是上面提到的那位年长的绅士。“孩子，你在这儿做什么？”

“呀，他的胳膊被绑住了！”有一位女士惊呼。

“可怜的人！”另一位女士说。

休伯特赶紧开始解释他在回家的路上被打劫了，马也被抢走了，还被强盗们无情地丢弃，弄成现在这副惨状。

“想想都好惨！”西蒙爵士感叹道。

“说得倒像真的一样！”一位男宾带着怀疑的语气说。

“你觉得很可疑？”西蒙爵士问。

“说不定他自己就是个强盗呢！”又有一位女士提议。

“现在我仔细地一看，他的面相果然是有些凶狠邪恶呀。”老母亲说。

休伯特羞愤得脸都红了，没有再继续说下去，告诉他们这些贼现在就躲在这座房子里，而是固执地不再开口说话，心里已半打定主意等他们自己去以身涉险算了。

“好了，把他的绳子解开，”西蒙爵士说，“这样吧，今天是圣诞前夕，我们还是要好好地招待他。来吧孩子，坐到餐桌末尾的那个空位上去，想吃什么就尽情地吃吧。等你吃饱了，我们再来听你说说详情。”

宴会继续进行。休伯特现在双手重获自由，也毫不后悔自己加入了这场宴会。大家吃吃喝喝，情绪越来越高涨。酒杯不停被斟满，壁炉里木头熊熊燃烧，女士们听着先生们的逸闻趣事笑得乐不可支。聚会欢乐喧闹，正是从前的圣诞聚会该有的样子。

虽然一开始休伯特因为他们怀疑自己的诚实而颇为受伤，但身处热闹情境，听着欢声笑语，看着身边人人兴高采烈，他的身体和头脑也渐渐热和起来。到后来他听到他们说的趣闻和他们妙语连珠的对话，也笑得跟老西蒙爵士一样开怀。宴会快结束时，西蒙爵士的一个儿子，显然有些喝多了——当然在那个年代对男人来说这是常态——他对休伯特说：“嘿，孩子，你还好吧？要不要来一撮鼻烟？”他递过来一个鼻烟壶，那是当时全国上下老老少少都很时兴用的玩意儿。

“谢谢先生。”休伯特取了一撮鼻烟。

“跟我们的女士们说说，你是谁，来自何处，有些什么本事吧！”那位年轻人继续说，边说边用力拍了拍休伯特的肩膀。

“好的，”我们的主人公挺直身子站起来，觉得这个时候最好做出一副信心十足的样子，“我是一个旅行魔术师。”

“不可能吧！”

“下面还有更离奇的故事吗？”

“小巫师，你能把魂灵从地狱深处召唤出来不？”

“我能在橱柜里召唤出暴风雨。”休伯特回答。

“哈哈！”老爵士开心地搓了搓手，“我们一定得看看他的表演。姑娘们别走，有好戏可看啦。”

“不会有什么危险吧？”老夫人问。

休伯特离开餐桌，对刚才让他任意取用鼻烟的年轻人说：“请把您的鼻烟壶递给我。现在，请大家跟我来，可不能发出一点声音。要是有任何人说话，咒语可就不灵了。”

大家都同意遵守规矩。休伯特走进长廊，脱掉鞋子，蹑手蹑脚走到橱柜跟前，其他人则保持一小段距离默默地跟在他身后。休伯特接着搬了一张凳子放到柜门前，站上去，高度正好够得到柜顶。然后他悄无声息地把鼻烟壶里所有的鼻烟沿着柜门上方边缘倒了一圈，再短促地吹了几口气，把鼻烟从门缝吹进橱柜里去。他对围观的人群举起手指示意，让他们保持安静。

“天哪，那是什么声音？”过了一两分钟后，老妇人惊问道。

橱柜里头响起了一声压抑的喷嚏声。

休伯特再次举起手指让他们噤声。

“真离奇啊！”西蒙爵士悄声低语，“实在是太有意思了。”

休伯特借此机会把橱柜的门闩轻轻地拨回原位，然后镇定地说：“再给我一些鼻烟。”

“再给他一些鼻烟。”西蒙爵士下令。两三位先生把鼻烟壶递了过去，里面的鼻烟全被从柜门顶吹进了柜子里。又传来一声喷嚏声，这次可没能像第一次那样压住。接着又是一声，明显地宣告着喷嚏是无论如何都压制不住了。最后橱柜里响起了一阵惊天动地的喷嚏风暴。

“了不起！这么年轻就有这样的本事真是了不起！”西蒙爵士说，“我自己对这种隔物传声的把戏也很感兴趣——我想这个应该是叫腹语吧？”

“再给我一些鼻烟。”休伯特说。

“再给他一些鼻烟！”西蒙爵士又下令。仆人端上来一罐上好的苏格兰调香鼻烟。

休伯特再一次把柜门上沿堆满鼻烟，再吹进柜子里。如此循环往复，直到把满满一罐子鼻烟全部倾空。柜里的喷嚏声这会儿已经是不绝于耳，无比壮观。听上去就像是狂风呼啸、暴雨倾盆、飓风过境、海浪翻腾。

“我敢说柜子里是真的有人，这不是在变戏法！”西蒙爵士如梦初醒，大声说。

“的确是有人，”休伯特说，“他们是打算来打劫这座宅子的，就是他们抢走了我的马。”

喷嚏声变成了断断续续的呻吟声。一个贼听出了休伯特的声音，大喊：“啊！饶命啊！饶命啊！放我们出去吧！”

“我的马在哪儿？”休伯特问。

“拴在肖茨绞刑场后面洼地的树旁了。饶命啊！饶命啊！放我们出去吧，我们要被憋死了啊！”

现在所有宾客都看出来这不是玩闹，而是真格儿的了。所有男仆都被唤来，手持火枪或短棍在橱柜外摆好队形严阵以待。休伯特打了个手势，把门闩打开，然后站定，做好了防御的姿势。但是三个强盗并没有发起进攻。大家发现他们蜷缩在橱柜的角落里，上气不接下气地喘息着。他们压根儿没有抵抗，被捆起来扔到外屋里待到天亮。

休伯特现在才把他开始没讲完的故事讲给众人听，大家都对他的慷慨相助感激不尽。西蒙爵士极力劝说他留下来过夜，住在这座宅子最好的房间里。当年伊丽莎白女王和查尔斯国王相继到此地巡访时都曾在该房间下榻。休伯特谢绝了，他着急要找回他的杰里，想要赶快确认一下强盗们所说的是否属实。

于是，依着三个贼所指的杰里的藏身之处，数位男宾陪同休伯特一起去了绞刑场后面。他们来到土堆后面四下里张望，呀！他的马果然就拴在那儿，毫发无伤，而且一副满不在乎的模样。看到休伯特后它欢快地嘶叫起来。休伯特找回了杰里，心里的快乐真是无以复加。他翻身上马，和他刚认识的朋友们道了声“晚安”，沿着他们所指的回家最近的路骑马慢跑离去，并在凌晨四点时安全抵达。

一八七七年

[1]码（yard），长度单位。一码为三英尺，约零点九一四米。

牧羊人的四个月夜见闻

第一夜

那位和蔼可亲的治安官[1]——可惜现在已不在人世了——宣称对这个故事的真实性负责。他喜欢以一个明亮的月夜和一个神秘的身影这样老套的方式来做开场白。这种开头就算在今天看来也是很巧妙的，如果后面展开得好的话。

他会这么开始：圣诞之月将她清冷的面容向着山地，山地下了霜，反射着月亮的光辉——光芒极其微弱，只有靠得很近的眼睛才能看清。这眼睛，他说，是一个牧羊少年的眼睛，他的年纪做牧羊人还太年轻了些。此时他正站在一个带轮子的小茅屋里，心不在焉地从墙上的窗洞望向外面。这种茅屋多是牧羊人在产羔季节早期居住。

这个地方叫作产羔角，是广袤的马尔布里丘山地牧场有天然屏障的一块区域。从伦敦穿过奥德布里克汉姆通往巴斯和布里斯托尔有一条大路，沿着这条大路横跨中威塞克斯的途中正好路过此地。茅屋所在之处，除北面之外，地势高且干爽，非常开阔，方圆几英里连绵起伏的山丘可尽收眼底。北面是一片高高的荆豆，茎秆粗壮巨大。前面还有单独的一丛，与那一大片不相连。这丛荆豆是中空的，里头被巧妙地加以利用来放置前面提到的小茅屋，这样既挡风又隐蔽，不到跟前几乎看不见。不过，茅屋的两个小窗前的荆豆枝已被砍去，以方便屋里的人观察羊群的动静。

茅屋后方的一长带荆豆丛所提供的庇护又被人为地改进，钉上了笔直的木桩圈成一个围场，围栏加以多刺的荆豆枝相互缠绕，围场里躺着八百头闻名遐迩的马尔布里丘品种的母羊。

年少的牧羊人漫不经心地望向南面，沐浴在月光下看起来别无二致的高地之上矗立着一个显眼的物体，而且只有一个。那是一个德鲁伊巨石牌坊，三块长条形的大石构成了一个门的形状，两块直立着做门框，一块横在上方做门梁。每一块石头都已饱经沧桑，被无数风雨打磨、擦刮、冲刷、啃噬、劈裂。但现在月光给它们镀上了一层美丽的银色，让它们看上去不觉破落反觉有型。当地人把这废墟称为“恶魔之门”。

这时一个老牧羊人从羊群的方向走来，进了小屋，在阴暗中四下望了望。“你现在渴不渴睡？”他问道，听起来很不客气。

少年怯生生地给了个否定的回答。

“好，”牧羊人说，“那我就回家去睡两个钟头。我看现在这儿也没啥事要干的了。母羊应该要到天亮以后才需要照顾——晚上还需要照顾就怪咯。但是上头说我们一定要有人待在这儿，所以你就留下来，听到没有？反正你白天可以睡觉，我又睡不成。万一有啥事你就赶快跑下来找我，十分钟就到我家。我买不起蜡烛给你，但是现在是圣诞周，大家都在过节，所以你可以在椅子上眯一下，不用整个晚上睁起眼睛。但是小心点，一次不能眯太久，不要超过恶魔之门的影子移动两格的时间，你还要注意下那些母羊。”[2]

男孩没有明确地回答，老牧羊人用他的手杖拨了拨炉子里的火，关上门离开了。

这是产羔季开始以来每晚的例行公事，所以男孩对这命令并不惊讶。他在炉子上烧稻草自娱自乐了一会儿，再出去看了看母羊和刚出生的小羊，回来，坐下，然后睡着了。这是他履行职责的惯常方式。虽然他只在这一周被允许打个盹儿，但事实上之前的每个晚上他都会打盹儿，直到凌晨三四点的时候肩膀上挨一记老牧羊人的手杖给打醒。

他醒来时大约是晚上十一点。他很惊讶没人叫也没被打怎么会自己醒来，但转念一想，很可能是有人叫过他，虽然他没看见。于是他从窗口往羊群的方向望去。羊群安静地躺着，跟他上次去看的时候一样，听不到什么羊叫声，也没有任何人打扰。他又从另一头的窗子望出去，发现了不同寻常的情况。地上的霜依然在月光下闪着微光，中间间或夹杂着一丛荆豆的黑影，最显眼的则是巨石牌坊幽灵般的形状。不同之处在于，牌坊前站着一个男人。

仔细看看就可以确定他不是牧羊人或者附近的庄稼汉。他穿着深色的外套，身形修长，仪态优雅，在巨石牌坊前走来走去。

牧羊少年正在猜测这个陌生人为何会在这个时间出现在这里，突然发现另一个身影正穿过开阔的草地，朝着巨石牌坊以及被荆豆丛掩盖的茅屋方向走来。这是个女子。陌生男子一看到她就急匆匆走上前来，正好在茅屋窗前迎上了她。没等她弄明白他的意图，他已经把她紧紧搂在怀里。

女子挣脱了他，庄重地退后两步。

“哈丽特，你终于来了——愿上帝为此保佑你！”他热切地喊。

“希望不是为这个而保佑我，”她有些愠怒地回答，接着她缓和了一下语气，“弗莱德，我来是因为你恳求我！你写这样一封信到底是什么意思？我怕如果我不来，可能会对你造成什么严重的伤害。你是怎么过来的？”

“我从父亲的住处一路走过来的。”

“这是怎么回事？上次分别以后你过得还好吗？”

“过得很是艰难，也许你不用问也能猜得到。自从上次离开这片山丘之后，我到过许多地方，见过许多人，但我心里只想着你。”

“你用这种奇怪的方式把我叫到这儿来就是为了告诉我这个吗？”

一阵微风吹过，掩盖了男子轻声的回答和接下来的几句话，之后他的声音又传了过来，“哈丽特——我们俩实话实说吧！我听说，公爵对你并——不——好！”

“他脾气是有些急躁，但他是个好丈夫。”

“他对你说话粗暴，有时候还威胁要把你关在门外。”

“只有一次，弗莱德！我发誓只有一次。我再说一遍，公爵是个很好的丈夫。而你应该为今晚耍这样的把戏把我叫出来受到惩罚！你到底想做什么？”

“我最亲爱的哈丽特！你这样说公平吗？诚实吗？你跟他生活在一起很悲惨，这难道不是尽人皆知的吗？你性情温和，他却脾气乖张，让你过得苦不堪言。我来是想问问，有没有什么我可以帮忙的。你是一位公爵夫人，而我不过是个小小的弗莱德·奥格本；但是我并不是完全没有可能帮到你……上帝啊！你那甜蜜的言语，再加上你那甜美的容貌，难道还不足以让他斯文一点吗！”

“奥格本上尉！”她低喊，带着半开玩笑的惊恐口吻强调说，“你作为我年少时的好朋友怎么能这样对我？不要这样对我说话，也不要这样瞪着我！你要说的真的就只有这些吗？看来我不应该来这儿。我真是太轻率了。”

又来了一阵风，吹走了一段对话。

“好吧。我看出来了，对我来说你已经死了，我已经失去了你。”接下来听到他如是说，“‘奥格本上尉’这个称呼证明了这一点。哈丽特，我曾经深爱过你，现在也一样，没有一丝一毫的减少。但你已经不是当初的那个你了——你曾经对我诚实而坦白，而现在你却捏造谎言，隐藏你的心意。就这样吧，我再也不能见你了。”

“不要用这么悲凉的语气说这样的话，傻瓜。你可以用正常的方式来见我——为什么不呢？但是，不能再像今天这样了。要不是公爵正好出门去了，没人能让我控制自己反复无常的冲动的话，我本来是不会来的。”

“他什么时候回来？”

“后天，或者大后天。”

“那你明天晚上再来跟我见面吧。”

“不行，弗莱德，我不能来。”

“如果你明天晚上来不了的话，你可以后天晚上来。请把他回来之前的两个晚上赐一个给我吧。请发誓一定要来！明天或后天晚上你一定要来跟我道别！”他握住了这位公爵夫人的手。

“不，弗莱德——放开我的手！你怎么还胆敢这样搂着我？难道你弗雷德里克所谓的爱，就是只记得一个女人的过去，而忘记了她现在的处境，对她完全没有一丝尊重了吗？你利用我对你的同情把我哄到这里来，然后还这样紧紧搂着我，实在是太过分、太不绅士了！”

“求你再来见我一次吧！我赶了两千英里的路来这里，只为了这一个请求！”

“不，我不能答应你！人们会造谣的——天知道他们会怎么捏造！我不能再见你。看在从前的情分上不要再提了。”

“那你就承认两件事：一是你曾经爱过我，二是你的丈夫对你很不好，所以你常常会想起你曾经爱我的时候。”

“好吧——我两件事都承认。”她含糊地回答，“但是承认这样的事对我很不利。我发誓你由此得出的推论是不成立的。”

“请别这么说。毕竟你还是来见我了——至于原因，让我爱怎么想就怎么想吧，反正对你也不会有什么危害。请再来见我一次吧！”

他仍然拉着她的手，搂着她的腰。“好吧，”她说，“你的这种哀求方式说服了我。我答应明天或者后天晚上再来见你。现在请你放开我！”

他松开了手，两人就此分别。公爵夫人飞快地跑下了山坡，朝着远处的抖森塔公爵府奔去。他望着她的身影消失在远处，转过身向着相反的方向大步离开了。一切又重归寂静空旷。

但这寂静空旷只保持了一小会儿。他们刚离开，又一个身影出现了。他从巨石牌坊后面走了出来，体形看上去比第一个男子要健壮，身着骑手的马靴和马刺。从这情形来看有两件事显而易见：一是他目睹了上尉和公爵夫人私会的全过程；二是虽然他能看见两人的一举一动，包括拥抱，但是距离太远他不可能听到女士的抗议，或是任何只言片语，所以在他看来更像是一对恋人两情相悦的幽会。可惜牧羊少年还要再过些年才足够成熟，能得出这样的结论。

第三个人定定地站了一会儿，似乎陷入了沉思。然后他走到了之前女士和先生站的地方，低头看着地面，接着转身朝第三个方向走了，似乎想离前两个人走的路越远越好。他朝着大路的方向走去。几分钟之后，似乎传来了一阵马蹄踏在寒霜覆盖的路面上的声音，逐渐远去，直到再也听不见。

少年在茅屋内继续一动不动地面朝着巨石牌坊，似乎期待着有更多演员登场表演，但之后再没有人来。不知道他小脸贴着窗站了有多久，突然背上挨了重重的一击将他从恍惚中惊醒。他立刻辨认出这熟悉的感觉来自老牧羊人的手杖。

“比尔·米尔斯！你个没长眼睛没长手脚的臭小子！都怪你，把火都搞熄了，你明明晓得我需要火一直燃着！我就晓得你一个人在这儿肯定要出问题，害得我在床上都睡不稳，就跟蓟花毛毛遇到风一样，待都待不住！哪，发生啥事了，你个呆瓜？”

“没啥事。”

“母羊都还好吗？”

“好。”

“有没有小羊崽儿要抱进来嘞？”

“没有。”

老牧羊人重新生着了火，提着灯走进羊群。这时月亮已渐渐西沉。他很快又回来了。

“要死咯——你说没啥事发生，结果有一头母羊生了对双胞胎差点要挂了，另外一头没人看也快不行咯！比尔·米尔斯，我给你说过有啥事马上跑下来喊我，结果你就是这个样子做事情哇！”

“你说了现在是过节我可以睡一下，所以我就睡了。”

“小伙子，不要这个样子跟老人家说话，不然你要上绞刑架！你肯定不是一直都在睡觉，不然你不可能会站在窗子那儿偷看！现在你先回家，吃早餐的时候再回来。唉，我是个老人家咯，有些老人家可以享清福，而我——算咯，能睡一下是一下！”

老牧羊人在茅屋里躺下来，少年往山下他住的小村庄走去。

第二夜

第二个夜晚到来时，少年的举动明显表明他在想着头一晚目睹的约会，以及女士被迫做出的还会再来的承诺。至于照料羊群，今晚不过是重复之前的惯例：十到十一点之间老牧羊人像往常一样离开，回家睡觉去了，希望能不受打扰地睡上一会儿，但其实睡不睡得着要碰运气；不行就只有在白天偶尔补一觉。少年又一个人留在小屋里了。

寒霜几乎跟前一晚一样，也许更重了些。月亮一如既往地照耀着，只是比平时晚出来三刻钟。少年的情形也同往常一样，只是今晚他睡意全无。他其实心里也很害怕，但是总的来说，他宁愿冒被老牧羊人发现自己玩忽职守的风险，也不想错过那对陌生人的幽会。

在远处的抖森塔敲响十一点的钟声之前，他看到午夜剧场的第二幕开始上演。但是率先出现的既不是那位情人也不是公爵夫人，而是第三个人——那个穿着马靴和马刺的壮硕男子，他从东边走上来，头一晚他也是从那里离开的。他绕着巨石牌坊走了一圈，然后朝隐藏着茅屋的荆豆丛大步走过来。月光照亮了他的脸，牧羊少年认出了他就是公爵，顿时被恐惧牢牢攫住。对当地的农人来说，公爵就是上帝。冒犯了他就意味着挨饿、丧家、死亡；看他一眼就会呆若木鸡、心受创伤。牧羊少年封上炉子，以免有光线透出来，然后迅速钻进了角落的稻草堆里。

公爵走到了荆豆丛跟前，站在头一晚他妻子与上尉谈话的地点。他仔细打量了一下荆豆丛，似乎是想找个藏身之处，然后发现了茅屋的存在。他绕着屋子转了转，又往里面张望了一下，发现屋里似乎空无一人，便钻了进来，关上门，把脸贴在少年的脸刚贴过的圆形小窗上。

如果公爵此举的目的是要藏起来的话，那么他的速度真是恰到好处。他刚刚藏好，十一点的钟声就响起了，头一晚光临过的那个身材修长的年轻人立刻出现在山丘北面。由于他昨晚情不自禁地往前奔跑迎接，约会之处便自动从恶魔之门转移到了荆豆丛旁。他本能地朝着这方向走来，在头一晚见面的地方等候公爵夫人。

然而，今晚等待着他，以及角落里瑟瑟发抖的少年的，却是可怕的意外。自他出现后，公爵的呼吸就越来越急促，呼吸声连蜷缩着的少年都能听得清清楚楚。年轻人才刚刚停下脚步，机敏的公爵就轻手轻脚推开了茅屋的门，绕过荆豆丛，突然从正面迎上了弗莱德上尉。

“你玷污了她的名誉，必须为此去死！”严厉低沉的私语声穿过茅屋的板壁传到牧羊少年耳里。

牧羊少年一向沉默寡言，对外界无动于衷，但此刻内心也激荡不已。他冒险站起身来向窗外张望，但除了荆豆枝什么也看不见，外面两个人已经转到侧面去了。接下来的一段时间发生了什么他一直不敢确定。地上有个影子迅速有力地动了一下，但他只能看到影子的一部分。接着传来什么东西倒地的声音，之后是一片死寂。

两三分钟后，公爵出现在茅屋的一角，攥着第二个人的衣领，那个人此刻已经一动不动了。公爵拖着他穿过空地，朝巨石牌坊而去。这废墟后面有个凹凸不平的洼地，那里荆豆和荆棘丛生，里头布满孔洞，是獾群的旧巢，这些动物现在不是迁离就是灭绝了。公爵拖着重负消失在洼地里，不一会儿又出现了。他回来时已经没有拖着东西了。

他走回茅屋侧面，把草地上的什么东西清理了一下，然后又开始蹲守，但这次他没有进茅屋，而是站在屋外的暗处。“现在轮到第二个了！”他说。

就算是不谙世事的少年也明白，他是在等约会的另一方——他的妻子，公爵夫人——等候的目的是什么，少年简直不敢去想。公爵看上去是个意志如钢的人，复仇时绝不心慈手软，定会赶尽杀绝。而且——虽然牧羊少年那时候还不太明白——更合理的可能是，头一晚看到的哑剧给坏脾气的公爵传达了错误的信息，夸大了事实，从而令他走上了极端。

妒火中烧的守望者等了许久却一无所获。男孩在茅屋里都能听到他间或发出的讶异的感叹声，似乎他那有罪的公爵夫人没有如他所想前来赴约令他很是失望一般。他隔一阵就从荆豆丛的阴影里走到月光下，举起怀表看看时间。

到了十一点半，他似乎终于放弃了等候。他又去了一趟巨石牌坊后面的洼地，在那里待了差不多一刻钟。接着他沿着山肩的斜坡迅速地往靠左的地方走去，很快骑着马回来了，证明他的马一直就拴在底下某个隐蔽之处。他再一次穿过巨石牌坊和茅屋之间的山坡，仔细地四下查看，像是要最后一次确定她没有来。然后他便骑着马缓缓下山，朝着抖森塔驰去。

牧羊少年想到了躺在远处洼地里的东西，一秒钟也不想一个人在山上待着了，就算是老牧羊人的牧羊手杖也强迫不了他。他宁愿与最可怕的活人同行，也不愿与死人做伴。于是他像野兔一样急奔下山去追赶那位骑马人，并在第二个下坡处赶上了报复心大炽的公爵。（宽阔的西行大路就在这里穿过中威塞克斯，这里离庄园的一个侧门不远——现在这个门已经封闭，看门人的小屋也拆掉了，虽然拆除时大家都不明就里，因为这本是庄园最方便的一个出入口。）

一听到马蹄声，比尔·米尔斯就觉得好过一些了。因为公爵虽然位高权重令他心存畏惧，不过他对与公爵同路并没有道德上的反感。虽然公爵刚刚干了一件可怕的事，但他认为贵族有权在自己的领地里为所欲为。公爵稳稳地骑着马，头顶上是祖辈留下的大树，马蹄踏在石板铺就的车道上，敲击出清脆的声音。很快他就来到了府邸大门前，大门上方是护墙，方方的城垛在砾石铺成的平台上投下锯齿状的阴影。小比尔·米尔斯对这些轮廓很熟悉，虽然从未有机会见识里面是什么样子。

当骑马人走近府邸时，一个小塔楼的门很快开了，一个女人走了出来。她一看到骑手的身形，就立刻跑出府，在月光下迎接他。

“啊！亲爱的——你回来啦？”她说，“你翻过小山丘的时候，我听到了希罗的蹄声，就知道是你回来了。我本来想再走远一点去迎接你的，要是我知道——”

“见到我很高兴吧？嗯？”

“这还用问吗？”

“嗯，这是个可爱的夜晚，很适合约会啊。”

“是的，这是个可爱的夜晚。”

公爵下马站到她身旁，问道：“你既然不是在等我，那为什么这个时辰了还在竖着耳朵倾听？”

“是啊，为什么呢！其实这后面有个离奇的故事，我必须得马上告诉你。但是你为什么比之前说的提前了一个晚上回来呢？这让我很遗憾——真的好遗憾！”她顽皮地摇了摇头，“因为我本来想给你个惊喜，叫人堆好了一个篝火堆，打算等你明天回来的时候点燃，结果现在白费心思了。你看那边还有篝火堆的影子呢。”

公爵望向树林间一块略高的空地，看到了一堆柴火。他垂下眼帘望着地面，眼神里半是冷漠半是不解。“让你辗转难眠的离奇故事是什么？”他低声问。

“是这样的——事情还挺严重的。我的表弟弗莱德·奥格本——现在是奥格本上尉啦——在他少年时代曾是我的忠实倾慕者，我想我以前告诉过你吧，虽然我比他要大六岁。说实话，他喜欢我到了有些荒谬的地步了。”

“你以前从来没跟我提过这事。”

“那我应该是跟你姐姐说过——是的，是跟她说的。我已经很多年没有见他了，所以我几乎都忘记了他过去对我的仰慕之情了。前天我收到一封没写寄信地址的神秘来信，打开一看发现是他写的，你可以猜到我有多惊讶。信的内容真是把我吓坏了。他从加拿大回来了，住在他父亲家中，他想尽各种方法恳求我马上去见他。我可以先跟你原文复述一遍信的内容，等我们进门了我再给你看信。

“他的信是这样的：‘我亲爱的哈丽特表姐，很久没见了，我这样突然出现一定让你大吃一惊吧。而我的请求会让你更吃惊。可是，如果你对我的生命和未来还有一点点的关切的话，求你答应我。亲爱的哈丽特，求你今晚十一点到马尔布里丘的德鲁伊巨石那儿来见我，从你的住处到那里大约有一英里多。除了恳求你来见我之外，我不能再多说了。等你到了，我会跟你解释清楚的。重要的是，我想见你。请你独自一人前来。相信我，要不是我的幸福——上帝啊，我全部的幸福——都寄托于此，我是不会提这样的要求的！我太激动，没法再写下去了——你的弗莱德。’

“这封信就是这么写的。当然，事后证明我不该去的，但是当时我没想到会是这样。我记得他性格鲁莽冲动，很担心他遇到了什么可怕的事，却找不到一个朋友能帮忙，而他又只愿意把麻烦向我一个人倾诉。于是我就把自己裹得暖暖的，在他指定的时间去了马尔布里丘。我是不是很勇敢呀？”

“非常勇敢。”

“等我到了那儿——我们要不要进去呀，外面有点冷了呢？”但是公爵没有动。“等我到了那儿，他来了。当然啦，他已经不是我记忆中的少年模样了，已经是个成年人，一个军官了。我一见到他就后悔去了。我都不知道该怎么跟你说他的所作所为。我到现在也不明白他到底想干什么，但我感觉他就只是想要跟我见面。他握着我的手，搂着我的腰——搂得紧紧的——不肯放手，直到我答应再去见他才放开。在那么偏僻的地方，他的举止那么古怪又那么热切，我实在有点害怕了，于是我就答应再去见他，然后就赶紧逃走——赶紧跑回家了——就是这样。今晚，随着约好见面的时间越来越近——当然我根本没打算去见他——我有点不安，怕他发现我不打算赴约之后会来家里找我，所以我实在睡不着。你怎么这么沉默呀！”

“我赶了很长时间的路。”

“那我们快进屋吧。你怎么一个人回来，连个随从都没带呢？”

“我喜欢这样。”

两人沉默着向里走了一会儿，她又说：“我想到一件事，虽然我也许不该跟你提。但他说，如果我今晚没去见他的话，他明晚会继续在那里等候。要不，明晚我们一起去山那边——去看看他还在不在那儿吧？如果在的话，你就好好地训斥他一顿，告诉他旧爱重燃的念头是多么愚蠢，而且不好好来府上做客却把我那样哄出去，是多么不合情理！”

“我们为什么要去看他还在不在那儿？”她的丈夫阴郁地问。

“因为我觉得我们应该做点什么。可怜的弗莱德！如果你好好跟他讲讲道理，再把我们俩真实的想法和立场告诉他，他会听你的劝告的。对一个显然是由于某种原因遭受了打击的人，我们这样做也只是出于基督徒应有的仁慈。他的神志似乎有点错乱了。”

说话间他们已经走到了门口，打了门铃等候。整个府邸似乎都在沉睡，但很快出来了一个仆人迎接他们，牵走了马，公爵同公爵夫人迈进了大门。

第三夜

这是没办法的事。老牧羊人离开以后，比尔·米尔斯必须得留下来看羊，今晚也一样，不然他就只有失去工作丢了饭碗。他想到魔鬼之门后面躺着的东西，尽量让自己勇敢一点，但是并不成功。所以当他看到公爵和公爵夫人的身影，看到他们沿着下了霜的草地慢慢走上来时，虽然依然充满敬畏，但同时也松了口气。公爵夫人步履轻快地走在丈夫前面几码远的地方。

“我跟你说过了，他肯定觉得不值得再来一趟了！”公爵停下脚步，不愿意再继续走了。

“他很可能会来，而且会等一晚上的。让他再这么空等一次有点残忍了。”

“他不在这儿，我们还是回家吧。”

“他看起来确实不在这儿。我在想他会不会出了什么事。万一出了事，我永远都不能原谅我自己！”

公爵有些不自在地说：“哦，不会的。他可能有别的事要办。”

“那不太可能。”

“要么就是他觉得距离太远了。”

“那也不可能。”

“那就是他终于想通了。”

“是的，也许他终于想通了。其实，也有可能他一直都在这儿——就在恶魔之门后面的洼地里藏着。我们过去看看吧，说不定我们会吓他一跳，不过那也是他活该。”

“哦，他不在那儿。”

“说不定就是因为你，所以他正静悄悄地躺在那里呢。”她狡黠地说。

“哦不——不是因为我！”

“那就跟我来吧。亲爱的，我觉得你今天晚上就像是个不肯去上学的孩子，而且反应还那么迟钝！你是在嫉妒那个可怜的孩子，这样做太傻啦。”

“好吧好吧，我跟你去！别说了，哈丽特！”他们穿过了草地。

牧羊少年想知道他们会做什么，于是出了茅屋，弓着身子藏在那一片荆豆丛后面，打算悄悄靠近巨石牌坊再站起身来窥看。但当他穿过一小段空地的时候暴露了自己。

“啊！我终于看到他了！”公爵夫人说。

“看到他！在哪？！”公爵问。

“在恶魔之门旁边。你没看到那儿有个人影吗？唉，我可怜的‘恋人’表弟呀，这次你可要挨一顿骂了！”她半带怜悯地笑着说，“咦，你怎么了？”她转头问丈夫。

“那不是他！”公爵哑着嗓子说。

“啊，确实不可能是他！”

“不，不是他。这个太小了，是个男孩。”

“我也是这么想的！孩子，你过来。”

牧羊少年提心吊胆地走上前来。

“你在这儿干什么？”

“我在看羊，公爵大人。”

“啊，你认识我！你每天晚上都在这儿看羊吗？”

“有时候在，公爵大人。”

“那么今晚或昨晚你有没有看到什么？”公爵夫人问，“有人在这里等候或转悠么？”

少年沉默不语。

“他什么都没看见。”她的丈夫插话，双眼死死盯住男孩，眼神令人生畏，眼中似乎有火在燃烧，“好了，我们走吧。天气太冷不宜久留。”

他们离开后，少年回了茅屋，然后又去到羊群中，不像开始那么恐惧了——熟悉的环境逐渐占据了他的思绪，让他不再时刻想着附近埋着的那具尸体。但是他独处的时间并不长。待到从这里到抖森塔一个来回的时间过去后，抖森塔那个方向又出现了公爵壮硕的身影。这次他是一个人来的。

这位贵族的眼力似乎同牧羊少年的一样敏锐，因为他一眼就看见了羊群中间的少年，然后径直向他走来。

“你就是我刚才问过话的那个牧羊孩子吗？”

“就是我，公爵大人。”

“听着。公爵夫人之前问你今晚和这几晚你在这儿看到过什么，而你没有回答。现在我问你同样的问题，你不要害怕，老实回答。这几天晚上你在这里看羊的时候有看见什么奇怪的事吗？”

“公爵大人，我是个粗心大意的穷小子，看到啥都记不得了。”

“我再问你一次，”公爵走近两步，“这几天晚上你看羊的时候看见过什么奇怪的事吗？”

“啊，我的大人啊！我只是个刚开始学放羊的小子，我爸就是给大人您种篱笆的，我妈就是您后院里头扫煤渣的！我一个人待着的时候就是睡觉，我啥都没看见！”

公爵抓住了男孩的肩膀，逼近他的脸，死死盯着他的眼睛。“说，你昨天晚上看到了什么？”

“天哪，公爵大人饶命啊！不要拿刀捅我啊！”男孩哭喊着，跪了下来，“我没看见您在这儿走过，或骑马经过，或者埋伏等人，或者拖了个重东西！”

“嗯！”审问者森森地说，放开了他，“你没有看见过这些事情，这很好。那现在你是想看我做一遍这些事呢，还是想终生保守秘密？”

“保守秘密，公爵大人！”

“你确定你能守得住？”

“肯定，大人，您可以随便考验我！”

“非常好。我问你，你喜不喜欢放羊？”

“一点都不喜欢。对喜欢热闹的人来说，放羊太孤单了。而且我还老是遭欺负。”

“我相信你。你还年幼，不适合做牧羊人。我得做点事让你过得更好。你会换下罩衫和粗胶靴，穿上真正的细布上衣和锃亮的皮鞋。你会被送进学校，学习你从未听说过的东西，度假的时候就打打球，你将被培养成一个男子汉。但是，你绝不能说出你曾经当过放羊娃，晚上在山上守过夜。因为没人愿意跟放羊娃交朋友。”

“相信我，公爵大人。”

“假如什么时候你得意忘形了，提起了你放羊的日子——不管是今年还是明年，不管是在学校里还是已经毕业，哪怕是二十年以后你坐在马车里——我对你的资助就会立刻撤销，你就会被打回原形，跟以前一样回来放羊。我记得你刚才说过你有父母？”

“只剩一个寡母了，公爵大人。”

“我会出钱供养她，让她过上舒适的生活，除非你说起——什么来着？”

“我放羊的日子，还有我在这儿看到的事情。”

“嗯。如果你真的提起了呢？”

“她也会被打回原形，跟以前一样当她的寡妇！”

“好——很好。不过这还不够。你跟我来。”他带着少年来到了巨石牌坊前，让他跪下。

“喏，这里曾是一个圣地，”公爵继续说，“这个祭坛是为供奉一个神明家族而建的。在人们还没听说过上帝的远古时代，这些神明就已被人们广为传颂，所以在这里立下的誓言会具有双倍的效力。现在你跟着我一起说：‘神明在上——天使、大天使、权天使和力天使做证，假如我跟别人提起我放羊的日子，或是我在马尔布里丘上的所见所闻，则必遭天谴！我将受尽折磨，无论在屋内还是花园，在田野还是路上，教堂还是礼拜堂，故乡还是他乡，陆地还是海洋。我将身患恶疾，无论是进餐还是宴饮，成人还是老朽，鲜活还是弥留，我身心都必遭苦痛，直到永远。我愿如此，此乃我愿。阿门，阿门。’现在，亲吻这块石头。”

男孩浑身发抖地重复了这些话，并亲吻了石头。

公爵松开了抓着他的手。那天晚上牧羊少年住在抖森塔府里。第二天，他被送去一个遥远的村庄上学，后来又去了一个预备学校，念完之后接着去了公学。

第四夜

这是很多年之后的一个冬夜，曾经的牧羊少年正坐在抖森塔北翼的一间陈设得当的办公室里，穿着打扮看上去是个受过教育的普通办事员。他看上去大约三十八到四十岁，但实际上并没这么大。当他偶尔抬起头，寻找放错地方的信件或文件时，那疲惫不安的眼神似乎说明他有些心绪不宁，虽然他四周环境都很祥和。他肤色苍白，完全不像个农人。他声称自己在写东西，却一字未著。他只坐了几分钟后就放下笔，将椅子推后，不安地把双手搭在扶手上，眼望着地板。

很快，他站起身离开了房间。他穿过一段走廊，经过一个八角形的中央大厅，来到一扇门前敲了敲门。一个虚弱而低沉的声音让他进去。这是个书房，里面只有一个人——他的恩主，公爵大人。

这么多年过去，公爵已不复当初的壮硕。他现在几乎只剩皮包骨头了，白发稀疏，双手几近透明。“啊，是米尔斯？坐下吧，什么事？”

“没什么特别的，公爵大人。没什么重要的来信，也没有访客。”

“噢——那是什么事呢？你看起来有点忧虑。”

“往昔旧事重新复活了，有情况唤醒了它们。”

“见鬼的往昔旧事——你说的是哪些旧事？”

“二十二年前的圣诞周，已故公爵夫人的表弟弗雷德里克请求与她在马尔布里丘见面。我目睹了他们那次的会面——那天晚上就跟今天一样——而且我，您也知道，还看到了更多。她见了他一面，但再没有见过第二面。”

“米尔斯，需不需要我提醒你一些话——有个放羊娃在那座山上立誓时说的话？”

“不需要。他一直信守着他的誓言和承诺。自那一晚以后，他从未有只言片语提起过他牧羊的日子——就连跟您也不曾提起。大人，您想不想听我继续说下去？”

“我不想听你再说下去了。”公爵愠怒地说。

“好的，如您所愿。不过，似乎时辰已到——也许已迫在眉睫——就算我守口如瓶，纸可能也包不住火了。”

“我不想再听你说这个了！”公爵重复了一遍。

“您不必担心我会背叛您，”管家说，语气中颇有些苦涩，“我是您的人，您对我恩重如山——没有哪位恩主会比您更好了。您供我吃穿，送我读书，又让我在府里做管家为您效劳，我绝不是忘恩负义的人。但是那又怎样呢？我守口如瓶，大人您因此得到什么好处了吗？我觉得并没有。奥格本上尉的失踪引起了轩然大波，我一个字也没有说。他的遗体至今没有下落。二十二年来我一直在想，您究竟把他怎么处置了。现在我知道了。今天下午发生的一件事迫使我回想起了当年。为了确定那一切都不是梦，我带着一把铁锹去了那里。我搜寻了一遍，看到了我想知道的事。在一个封闭的獾洞里，有东西在腐烂。”

“米尔斯，你觉得公爵夫人猜到了吗？”

“她从没猜到过，我敢保证，到死都没有。”

“你离开的时候把一切都恢复原样了吗？”

“是的。”

“是什么事让你非得今天下午上那儿去？”

“就是刚才大人您说您不想听的那件事。”

公爵沉默了。这个夜晚安静得出奇，远处响起了丧钟的声音，清清楚楚传到他们耳里。

“这钟是为何而鸣？”这位贵族问道。

“为了我想来告诉您的事，大人。”

“你在折磨我——你就喜欢这样！”公爵大声吼道，“村子里谁死了？”

“最年长的人——那位老牧羊人。”

“终于死了——他多大了？”

“九十四。”

“我才七十岁，所以我还有二十四年可以活呢！”

“我在马尔布里丘上放羊的时候在那位老牧羊人手下当差。那件事的隔天晚上，也就是当我第一次同大人您说话的时候，他就在山上。他一直都在山上，只是我不知道他在场——您也不知道。”

“啊！”公爵惊跳起来，“说下去——我让步了——你可以说出来。”

“今天下午我听说他已到弥留之际。这让我想起了过去——促使我去山上搜寻，正如我告诉您的一样。回来的时候我听人说，他提出要见牧师，说要忏悔并坦白一个他已经保守了二十多年的秘密——据他说是‘出于对公爵大人的尊敬’——是他在二十二年前十二月的一个晚上回去看羊时发生的事。我仔细地回想了一遍，那天晚上他把我留下看羊，但他通常都会中途突然回来，以免我睡着了出娄子。那天晚上我没有见到他，虽然他说了他会回来。他肯定回来过了，而且——因为某种原因躲起来了。一切都很明显了。另一件事是，牧师两小时前去了他的住处。除此之外我还没有听到更多的消息。”

“这已经够了。让牧师明天天亮时来见我。”

“做什么呢？”

“让他在接下来的二十四年里闭嘴——直到我跟老牧羊人一样在九十四岁入土。”

“我的大人——您命令我保持沉默，我就绝不说出去，哪怕要砍头我也不会说。我发誓为您效劳，我就会为您效劳。但是这样的坚持真的有用吗？”

“我说了，我要让他闭上嘴！”公爵喊着，口气里带着几分过去的粗鲁与强硬，“现在，你回家休息去吧，米尔斯，我自己来对付他。”

谈话结束了，管家起身离开。这个夜晚，正如他所说，就跟二十二年前的那个夜晚一样。正是那一晚发生的事让他从此无法再把这个时节看成一个欢乐与友爱的季节。他回到庄园边上自己的屋里，这些年他一直独自一人，无亲无故。十一点钟他准备就寝——但并未上床。他坐下，沉思了半天。十二点的钟声响起，他望着窗外惨白的月亮，不知为何，突然起身戴上帽子走出家门。比尔·米尔斯走啊走，一直来到了马尔布里丘的顶端。他已经整整二十多年都不曾在晚上这个时间来这里了。

他估摸着当初小茅屋所在之处，尽量走近些。现在这里没有产羔的羊群了，当初粗暴待他的老牧羊人昨天也已经咽了气。但是巨石牌坊还一如既往地矗立在那里，反射着银白的月光。他穿过中间的草地走近牌坊，有些迷乱地将嘴唇贴在了石头上。虽然他内心充满不安与自责，但是想到当初在这个远古异教神庙前立下的可怕誓词，还亲吻巨石以示将永守誓言，他还是忍不住笑了一下。他的确一直信守诺言，但不是当作宗教誓言，而是当作承诺。他也因此获得了许多实际的好处，虽然并没有得到幸福。随着时间的推移，年岁的增长，他心中反叛的情绪逐渐滋长，以至于今晚听到的消息几乎让他如释重负。

就在他靠着恶魔之门思绪万千之际，他突然意识到自己并不是山丘上唯一的人。一个穿白衣的身影在他对面无声地迈着大步走来。米尔斯一动不动，等人影走近，他发现来人正是公爵本人，还穿着睡衣——很显然是在梦游。米尔斯不想惊动他，紧紧地贴在石头的阴影里。公爵径直走进了洼地，跪到地上，开始像獾一样用双手刨土。几分钟后，他站起身来，沉重地叹了口气，沿着来时的路往回走。

管家怕他路上伤到自己，但又不想惊醒他，于是便悄无声息地一路尾随。公爵准确无误地沿原路返回，进了庄园，走近宅子，钻进了一扇开着的窗——他大概就是从这扇窗里出来的。米尔斯觉得没必要惊动屋子里的人，于是便轻轻地把窗户关上，然后回到住处，等待着第二天一早真相被揭露。

不过，整个晚上他都感到心神不宁，不仅担心第二天即将到来的事，也担忧公爵的身体状况。他一大早就去了抖森塔。百叶窗还紧闭着，门房来开门时神色有些怪异。管家说想求见公爵大人。

门房压低了声音郁郁地回答：“先生，很抱歉，公爵大人过世了！昨晚不知道什么时候他离开了房间，也不知道他去了哪儿。他回来时，上楼梯失足摔了下去。”

没等牧师开口，管家米尔斯就坦白了马尔布里丘上发生的故事。米尔斯早就决定，等到公爵一死他就要让真相大白。他可以欣然接受这么做给自己带来的后果，但他并没有因此活得更久。他死的时候还不到四十九岁，正在开普郡务农。

马尔布里丘品种的羊群依然闻名遐迩，看上去也跟从前毫无差别。但是现在这些羊经过了许多代繁衍，跟已故治安官讲述的故事中的那些羊其实已相差甚远。产羔角已经许久不做产羔之用了，虽然这个名字沿用至今。之所以弃用，部分是因为当时给牧羊人提供了许多便利的高大的荆豆丛被清除掉了。还有部分原因，可能跟另一件事有关。据当地现在的牧羊人说，在圣诞周的夜晚，巨石牌坊附近的空地上会看见有影子掠过，武器的寒光一闪，然后一个男人拖着一个重物走进洼地。不过这些都只是未经证实的传言罢了。

一八八一年圣诞节

[1]治安官（magistrate），又称太平绅士（Justice of the Peace），是源自英国的职衔。在维多利亚时期，乡村地区的治安官通常由当地的乡绅担任，以维持社会治安，并处理一些不严重的违法乱纪行为。治安官并无俸禄，属于绅士应尽的义务，也不需要有法律或理政方面的专业训练或资格认证。

[2]英文中作者是通过语法错误、拼写错误以及用词和句子结构等来表现威塞克斯地区的劳动者说的方言。威塞克斯原为盎格鲁—撒克逊人于公元519年建立的王国名，至十世纪初被诺曼王朝取代。哈代借用了“威塞克斯”指代其小说中描绘的英格兰的西南部，实际上是以哈代所在的故乡多塞特为中心，包括伯克郡（北威塞克斯）、汉普郡（上威塞克斯）、威尔特郡（中威塞克斯）、多塞特（南威塞克斯）、萨默塞特（外威塞克斯）和德文郡（下威塞克斯）。因语法错误、拼写错误不能以中文表示出来，所以译者在译文中作了处理，用某些方言表示，便于读者理解。

三个陌生人

在英格兰农业区，历经世纪更迭却几乎原貌未改的大概要算广袤无际、青草茂密、荆豆丛生的牧场了。牧场根据种类不同分别被称为丘陵牧场、峡谷牧场和草场，主要集中在南部和西南部几个郡的大片地区。因此在这些地区如果偶尔看到有人烟，通常都是某个牧羊人孤零零的小屋。

五十年前，在这个地区的某个丘陵牧场上，就矗立着这么个孤单的小屋，也许现在还在那儿。尽管它孑然独立，但实地测量一下就会发现它距离最近的小镇还不到三英里。不过这于事无补：三英里崎岖不平的山路，加上一年中大部分时间天气恶劣——冰雹、降雪、大雨、迷雾——就算是豪爽好客的泰门或尼布甲尼撒王到了这里也会落得形影相吊；即便是在气候宜人的时节，那些喜爱亲近自然的人——诗人、哲人、艺术家，以及其他那些专事“酝酿与思考美好事物”的人——也会对这山路望而却步。

通常这些偏僻的住所在修建之初都会将某处废弃的土泥营地或古冢、某簇树丛，至少也是一截干枯的古老树篱利用起来就近搭建。不过，本故事里说到的这个牧羊人的住处却未用此法。这所房子叫作“高报晓梯”，可谓是茕茕孑立、毫无遮挡。选址于此的唯一原因大概就是附近正好有两条小路垂直交叉，可能五百年来一直如此。因此屋子四面都全然暴露于自然的威力之下。不过，尽管此处刮风时一定挨吹，下雨时一定遭淋，但这丘陵上冬季的种种天气并不像低处居民们想象的那般可怕。这里的霜降没有峡谷里那么有害，霜冻也极少那么恶劣。不明就里的人怜悯牧羊人一家住在这里受尽风刀霜剑，他们自己却说，总的来讲，原来住在附近温暖山谷里的一条小溪边时总是“又齁又堵”（即嗓子沙哑、咳嗽痰多），现在反而好得多了。

一八二几年三月二十八日那晚，正是最容易唤起这种怜悯之情的时节。暴风雨猛烈拍打着墙壁、斜坡和篱笆，就像森拉克之战和克雷西之战中长弓射出的箭雨一般。[1]羊群和其他户外养的牲口无处躲藏，只得转身用屁股迎着风；栖息在参差不齐的荆棘枝上的小鸟，尾巴被风吹得翻起来，像一把张开的伞。牧羊人小屋的山墙顶已有浸水的痕迹，屋檐的滴水直拍打到了墙上。但怜悯牧羊人绝对是大错特错。因为这位乡下人正兴高采烈在家中招待客人，庆祝他的二女儿受洗命名。

客人们是在落雨之前到达的，此刻大家都聚在房子的主屋，又叫客厅。在这个意义重大的夜晚八点时分，看看屋内就会觉得，在这狂暴的天气里有这么个温暖舒适的安乐窝真是别无所求了。屋子主人做什么行当，只要看看壁炉上方挂着做装饰用的一排牧羊手杖便一目了然了。这些手杖去掉了棍把，只留下曲柄，磨得锃亮，每一个曲柄的样式都不同，从旧时家庭圣经图片里画的最古老的样式到最近当地羊市流行的时新样式应有尽有。屋内点了半打蜡烛照明，烛芯只比包着它们的蜡油略细一点，都插在只有节日、圣日和家庭聚餐等重要日子才会使用的烛台上。蜡烛遍布整个房间，有两支摆放于壁炉架上。这个位置是有讲究的，家里有聚会时才会把蜡烛摆在壁炉架上。

壁炉里有一根粗大的木头慢慢燃着垫底，木头前的荆棘在熊熊燃烧，发出噼啪的爆裂声，就像是“愚人的笑声”[2]。

在座一共有十九人，其中有五位妇人，穿着各色鲜艳的长裙，在靠墙的椅子上就座，或娇羞或大方的姑娘们坐在靠窗的长凳上。四位男子正懒懒地坐在高背长椅上，其中包括篱笆匠查理·杰克、教区执事以利亚·纽，以及附近奶牛场的场主、牧羊人的岳父约翰·皮彻。一个小伙子坐在墙角的碗橱前正对一个姑娘说着要缔结良缘的绵绵情话，姑娘听得脸颊绯红。还有一个五十多岁上了年纪的男子，他刚订婚不久，正心神不定地晃悠着，慢慢朝他未婚妻所在之处挪过去。聚会整体来说非常愉快，可以自由自在不受世俗限制使得大家更加兴高采烈。人人都相互信赖、互怀善意，因此更加放松。而他们最好的一点就是没人表现出想飞黄腾达，或欲增进心智，或要鹤立鸡群的样子，因而显得平和从容，几近高贵。如今除了社会阶层的两极之外，似乎其余所有人都患上了此种病症，因而大大破坏了温柔敦厚之风气。

牧羊人菲诺结了门好亲，他的妻子是奶牛场主的女儿，娘家就在稍远一些的一个山谷里。她出嫁时带来了五十基尼[3]的陪嫁——到现在还留着，待到养育后代有急需时才动用。这位节俭的妇人对于聚会究竟该如何安排颇费了些心思。倘若以静坐为主，虽然也有好处，但在椅子上或坐或靠，一放松就很容易让男人们开怀畅饮起来，最后把所有酒都喝个精光。办成舞会也不是不可以，但舞会虽可避免酗酒，却另有坏处：大运动量会导致胃口大开，他们的食物储藏室又会惨遭洗劫。菲诺太太于是决定采取折中方案，最好是先跳一会儿舞，然后聊会儿天，再唱几首歌，这样穿插进行，以避免出现不可控制的狂饮或饕餮。其实这不过是她自己脑中的盘算罢了，牧羊人菲诺可是一心一意想要好好展示一下主人家的热情好客。

提琴手是当地的一个男孩，大约十二岁，拉起吉格舞曲和里尔舞曲来可谓相当熟练。但他毕竟手小指头短，左手不停地在高音把位和第一把位间变换，有时难以应付，于是间或会发出一些杂音。晚上七点，男孩便开始奏响欢快的音乐，教区执事以利亚·纽周到地带上了他最中意的乐器蛇形号，吹出呜呜的低音为提琴伴奏。大家即刻闻声起舞。菲诺太太私底下嘱咐两位演奏者，跳舞的时间一定不要超过一刻钟。

但是以利亚和男孩演奏得正畅快，完全忘了她的叮嘱。加上在场有一个十七岁的小伙子奥利弗·盖尔斯，被他的舞伴，一个三十三岁的美貌姑娘迷得神魂颠倒，不假思索地塞了一个崭新的克朗银币[4]给乐师们作为贿赂，希望他们不到力气用光千万别停。菲诺太太看到客人们脸上开始热气腾腾，赶紧走上去扯了扯小提琴手的胳膊肘，又用手堵了堵蛇形号的喇叭口，但两人却置若罔闻。菲诺太太怕如果干涉得太明显，会让别人闲话自己这个女主人不够亲切好客，只得退回坐下，无计可施。舞会于是继续欢快地进行，越来越狂热；跳舞的人们如同行星沿既定轨道运行一般，上前、退后、靠近、拉远，直到房间尽头那嘀嗒作响的时钟的指针转了整整一个圆周。

正当牧羊人菲诺的乡村小屋里宾客皆欢之际，外面阴沉的夜里一件与这场聚会颇为相关的事也正在进行中。在菲诺太太对越来越激烈的舞会的担忧逐渐加剧的同时，有一个人正从三英里外的小镇方向朝着“高报晓梯”所在的孤零零的小山丘逐渐靠近。此人顶着大雨，沿着牧羊人屋子旁蜿蜒的小路一刻不停地大步前行。

已经快到满月时候了，因此虽然天空中雨云密布，屋子外头却都大体看得见。惨淡的光照出这个孤单的路人灵活的身姿；他的步态显示出他已经过了最敏捷矫健的年龄，但必要时依然还能迅速行动。粗略估计他大约四十岁左右。他个头看上去很高，不过征兵队长或其他善于通过打量估计个头的人就能看出，他之所以显高是因为他非常消瘦，其实他的身高最多五英尺八九英寸[5]。

他步履如常，却透露着谨慎，仿佛每走一步都要经过思索一样；虽然他穿的并不是黑色或深色的外套，但他给人的感觉却像是属于穿黑衣的那一类人[6]。他穿着粗斜纹布衣、平头钉靴子，但他走路的姿态却不太像是个穿惯了平头钉靴和粗斜纹布衫的乡下人。

他来到牧羊人的屋子跟前时，雨正好落下来——或者说一直下着，只是这会儿来势更加凶猛。屋子的外围稍微阻挡了一下急风暴雨，使得他停下站定。牧羊人的住所最打眼的是花园前角处有个空空的猪圈，花园没有栽树篱，因为在这些乡野里，人们还没有要把住处不甚雅观的地方遮挡起来的意识。旅人的目光被猪圈顶棚湿漉漉的石板瓦反射的微光给吸引了。他转身看了看，发现猪圈是空的，于是便在顶棚下躲雨。

这时旁边的房子里蛇形号洪亮的呜呜声伴着小提琴隐隐的奏鸣声传了过来，正好同暴雨落在泥地上的唰唰声，落在花园卷心菜叶上的啪啪声，落在小路旁隐约可见的近十个蜂箱的稻草顶上的哧哧声，以及屋檐水滴落到墙边地上一排桶和锅里的咚咚声相互应和。在像“高报晓梯”这一类的高地住处，住户的一个巨大难题就是缺水；所以但凡下雨，屋里能用得上的锅碗瓢盆全都会摆出来接水。你可能听说过在干旱的夏季，连肥皂水和洗碗水都要被反复利用的一些奇特的节水方法；这在高地人家是绝对必要的。不过目前这个季节需求则没有这么急迫，只要接受上天的赐予，储备起来就足够了。

蛇形号终于停止了吹奏，整个房子安静下来。这中断惊醒了陷入沉思的孤单的旅人。他走出猪圈，沿小路朝屋子正门走去，显然是有了新的打算。到了门前，他的第一个动作是在那一排用来接水的容器旁的一块大石头上跪下，就着其中一个满满饮了一大口。止住渴后，他站起身抬手准备敲门，却又看着门停了下来。木门的面板黑黝黝的什么也看不出来，所以很明显他是在脑中想象着门内的场景，就好像是他想要估算一下这种房子里头会有的各种可能性，以及它们对他进去后可能会造成的各种后果。

举棋不定中，他又转身打量了一下四周，一个人也看不到。脚下的花园小路蜿蜒而下，像是蜗牛爬过的痕迹一样闪着微光；常年干涸的小井上的井架、井口盖板，花园门上的扶手，全都泛着一层暗暗的水光；远处山谷里有隐隐的一线白色，比平时要更明显，表明草场旁的河水水位上涨了。再远处是几点隐隐约约的灯光在急雨中闪烁，灯光指示着小镇的所在，他应该就是打那儿来的。那个方向此时动静全无，这似乎坚定了他的决心，于是他敲了敲门。

屋内，音乐和舞步已被闲聊所取代。篱笆匠正向众人提议唱首歌，但似乎没人愿意响应，所以敲门声来得很是时候，正好转移注意力。

“请进！”牧羊人立刻说。

门闩咔嗒向上抬起，我们的夜行人站在门前的脚垫上。牧羊人站起身，剪去身旁两只蜡烛的烛花，转过身打量来者。

光照之下，陌生人看上去肤色偏黑，五官颇为俊秀。他进门后没有立刻脱帽，帽檐儿低垂，但仍然可以看到他的双眼。他的眼睛大而有神，目光坚定，不是匆匆地一瞥，而是机敏地一扫，掠过整个房间。他似乎对查看的结果很是满意，这才脱下帽来，露出一头乱发，用低沉而有磁性的声音说：“朋友，雨势太大，可否让我进来休息片刻？”

“当然可以了，陌生人，”牧羊人回答，“老实说，你很会挑时间来，因为我们正为一件高兴事儿在聚会作乐呢——当然，一个男人可不希望这种喜事一年多过一次。”

“也不能少于一次，”一个女人插嘴说，“最好是早点儿把该成的家成了，该生的娃生了，早点儿弄完，就可以早点儿累完。”

“敢问这高兴事儿是？”陌生人问道。

“生了个娃，今天受洗命名。”牧羊人回答。

陌生人表达了他对主人的祝贺，希望他往后子嗣不多不少刚刚好，让他能继续高兴下去。主人示意请他喝一口大酒缸里的酒，他也欣然接受了。在进门前他看起来疑虑重重，现在却是一副坦然随性的样子。

“这个时候横穿这山谷有点晚了哟——是不是？”五十岁刚订婚的男子说。

“确实是很晚了，先生，正如你所说。夫人，如果您不反对的话，我想在壁炉边找个位置坐下来，因为我被雨淋到的那一边湿透了。”

牧羊人菲诺的太太同意了，给这位不请自来的陌生人让了让位，他整个人坐进去后，便伸展开四肢，看起来很是自在，完全不把自己当外人了。

“是的，我的鞋面都开裂了，”他发现牧羊人妻子望向他的靴子，便坦率地说，“而且这身衣服也不太合适。我最近日子比较艰难，所以只能有什么就穿什么啦，不过等回到家以后，我就得找一套适合平时穿的衣服了。”

“你就住在附近吗？”她问。

“没那么近——还得再往上走。”

“我估计也是。我也住那边，听你说话的口音我觉得你应该是我娘家那边的人。”

“不过你应该没有听说过我，”他忙回答，“你看，我的年纪可比你要大多了，夫人。”

赞美女主人年轻的话起到了阻止她继续盘问下去的效果。

“我现在再有一样东西就快活无比啦，”陌生人说，“那就是来一点烟叶。真是不好意思，我的烟全都抽完了。”

“把烟斗给我，我帮你装满。”牧羊人说。

“我得请你借我一个烟斗才行。”

“你抽烟，居然随身不带烟斗？”

“我在路上某个地方弄丢了。”

牧羊人拿了一个新的陶土烟斗，装上烟叶递给他，一边说：“反正现在已经在装了，干脆把你的烟盒也递给我，我帮你一起装满。”

男人把所有口袋统统搜了个遍。

“烟盒也掉了啊？”主人问，颇有些讶异。

“恐怕是也掉了，”男子迷惑不解地说，“你就用纸包一点给我好了。”他就着蜡烛点燃烟斗，猛吸一大口，连蜡烛的火焰都被吸进烟嘴里去了。然后他又在壁炉旁坐下来，低头望着他的裤腿上升腾起的淡淡水汽，似乎不打算再多说话了。

这时大部分宾客都不太留意来客了，他们正在全神贯注地同乐队商量下一支舞选哪一首曲子才好。达成一致意见后，他们正准备起身，门口又传来一阵敲门声，把他们的动作给打断了。

听到敲门声，坐在壁炉角的男子拿起拨火棍开始拨弄起壁炉里的那根大木头来，就好像这是他存在的唯一目的似的。牧羊人第二次扬声说：“请进！”很快，又一个人站在门前稻草编的脚垫上。这又是一个陌生人。

这次的来客同第一个可真是迥然不同。他的言行举止看起来更加稀松平常，五官一副快活相，像是个走南闯北见过世面的人。他比头一个人要大几岁，头发已略有花白，眉毛又粗又硬，络腮胡腮帮上的部分被刮掉了。他的脸盘浑圆，肌肉有些松弛，但还是颇有气势。鼻子附近有几个酒糟疙瘩。他把褐色的厚大衣往后一掀，露出了里面穿的一套烟灰色的衣服。他身上唯一的饰物是某种金属制成的又大又沉的徽章，用怀表链吊着，看来似乎需要打磨抛光了。他抖了抖泛着水光的低顶帽，说：“伙伴们，我必须请求你们容我避会儿雨，不然我还没赶到卡斯特桥就已经淋成落汤鸡了。”

“先生，请自便吧，不用客气。”牧羊人说，不过似乎没有第一次那么热忱了。这倒绝对不是因为菲诺生性小气，只是房间不大，空椅子也不多，所以对身着鲜艳长裙的妇人和姑娘们来说，旁边坐个湿漉漉的人确实不太方便。

第二个人脱掉了大衣，把帽子挂在天花板横梁的一根钉子上——虽然并没有人让他挂在那里——然后走到桌前坐下。桌子早已被推到紧挨着壁炉，好多留一些空间给客人们跳舞；一头的边缘都擦到坐在壁炉旁的那个人的手肘了。于是两个陌生人便紧靠在了一起。他们相互点头致意，算是打破互不相识的拘束。第一个陌生人把牧羊人家的大酒缸——一个巨大的褐色陶土容器递给他的邻座。酒缸口的边缘历经数代饥渴唇齿的反复触碰摩擦已经磨损，浑圆的缸身上烧制着几个黄色的字：

我若不来
何以开怀

第二个人毫不嫌弃地把酒缸举到嘴边，喝了一口，两口，三口——直喝到牧羊人的妻子脸色开始微微发青，她看到第一个陌生人如此随意地借花献佛时就已颇感讶异。

“我就知道！”豪饮者心满意足地对牧羊人说，“我还没进门之前，走过你家花园，看见那一排蜂箱，我就对自己说，‘有蜜蜂则必有蜂蜜，有蜂蜜则必有蜜酒’。但是我从没料到老了还能喝上味道这么香醇的蜜酒！”他说完又喝了一大口，从缸子的倾斜程度看，很是不妙。

“你喜欢喝就好！”牧羊人热情地说。

“酒倒是不错，”菲诺太太赞同地说，但语气并不热诚，似乎觉得倾尽酒窖只换得一句赞扬，代价实在是太大了，“酿这酒实在是太麻烦——实话说我们应该不会再酿了。蜂蜜销路很好，而且我们自己要喝的话，只需要用洗蜂巢的水酿淡蜜酒或是蜂蜜药酒就够了。”

“噢，你怎么忍心呢！”穿烟灰色衣服的陌生人用责怪的语气说道。他第三次举起酒缸，一饮而尽。“我热爱蜜酒，尤其是这种陈酿，就像我热爱礼拜天上教堂、平日里天天帮人排忧解难一样。”

“哈哈哈！”坐在壁炉边的那个人大笑起来。虽然他开始一直默默地抽着烟，但同伴的小幽默似乎让他忍俊不禁了。

话说当年的陈年蜜酒，是用最纯的头年蜜或称为少女蜜酿制而成，每一加仑需要四磅蜂蜜——加上蛋清、肉桂、生姜、丁香、肉豆蔻、迷迭香、酵母等辅料，历经酿造、装瓶和窖藏而成。这酒后劲儿其实相当大，但喝起来却并不觉得特别浓。这会儿坐在桌边的穿烟灰色衣服的陌生人酒劲儿慢慢地上来了，他解开了背心的纽扣，向后仰靠在椅背上，伸展双腿，四仰八叉的模样实在引人注目。

“哎呀，哎呀，我刚说到，”他接着说，“我要去卡斯特桥，不去不行啊。本来我这会儿都应该快到了，没想到大雨把我赶进了你们家，不过我可一点也不后悔。”

“你不住在卡斯特桥？”牧羊人问。

“还没有，不过我很快就会搬过去的。”

“是不是打算在那儿找份活干？”

“不，不，”牧羊人的妻子说，“看得出来这位先生是个有钱人，根本不需要工作。”

烟灰色衣服的陌生人顿了一下，似乎在考虑是否要接受这样的定义，随后立刻否定了这种说法，回答说：“夫人，有钱人这个词可不适合我。我有工作，而且非得工作不可。就算我要半夜才能到达卡斯特桥，我明天一早八点也必须开工。是的，不管天晴还是下雨，刮风还是降雪，饥荒还是战乱，明天的活也必须得干。”

“好可怜哪！所以，虽然外表看不出来，其实你比我们还要穷困呀！”牧羊人的妻子感叹说。

“这是我干的这行的性质决定的，各位。与其说是贫困，不如说是我的行当的性质……不过我确实真的得马上走了，不然就算到了镇上也找不到住处了。”他口里这么说着，却并没有挪窝，而是直截了当地又加了句，“现在还有点时间，我走之前可以再喝上一盅友谊的酒，可惜酒缸已经空了，不然我就会马上来一口了。”

“这里有一缸淡蜜酒，”菲诺太太说，“我们说它‘淡’，其实它是洗蜂巢的头一道水呢。”

“不不，”陌生人嫌弃地说，“我可不能让你们头一盅的盛情被这第二盅给糟蹋了。”

“当然不会，”菲诺插进来，“我们又不是天天都生孩子办聚会。我给你把酒满上。”他去到楼梯下放酒桶的暗处，他的妻子尾随而来。

“你为啥要这样做？”两人一独处，她便立刻责备他说，“他已经喝掉了一缸酒了，本来都够十个人喝的！现在他还看不起淡酒，还非要劲头大的！他以为他是谁呀！我们都不认得他！他那副德行，我一点儿都不喜欢。”

“亲爱的，他来都来了，而且今天晚上又下雨，我们还在庆祝洗礼。去他的，多一杯少一杯又有啥关系嘛？下一次熏蜂割蜜的时候再多做一点就是了。”

“好吧，那就这一次，下不为例。”她郁闷地看看酒桶说，“这个人是做啥的，哪儿的人，为啥到这儿来这样打扰我们？”

“我也不晓得。我再问问他吧。”

这一次菲诺太太很警惕地提防穿烟灰色衣服的陌生人又把酒一口饮尽。她把给他喝的酒倒到一个小杯子里，把大缸放得离他远远的，这招果然有效。待到他喝完了杯里的酒，牧羊人重又问起他的行当。

陌生人没有马上回答，坐在壁炉旁的第一个陌生人却突然很坦率地说：“大家都可以知道我的行当——我是修轮子的。”

“在这一带做这个行当挺不错。”牧羊人说。

“大家也都可以知道我的行当——如果你们猜得出来的话。”穿烟灰色衣服的陌生人说。

“一般只要看一个人的手就能看得出他是做啥的了，”篱笆匠发话了，顺便看了看自己的手，“我的指头上都是刺扎过的印子，就跟旧针线包上都是针眼一样。”

壁炉旁的人本能地将双手往暗处藏了藏，又开始抽烟斗，眼睛盯着壁炉里的火。桌前的陌生人接过了篱笆匠的话头，机灵地说：“的确如此。不过我的行当的特殊之处是，它不会在我身上留下痕迹，而是在我的客户身上留下痕迹。”

没人发话来解答这个谜语，于是牧羊人的妻子又问有谁愿意唱歌助兴。但是这次的麻烦跟上次一样——一个人嗓子哑了，另一个不记得第一段的歌词了。坐在桌旁的陌生人酒过两巡，已到了飘飘然的境界，出来帮大家解围，宣布说他要抛砖引玉先来一首。他一只手大拇指扣着马甲的袖圈，另一只手在空中挥舞，眼睛盯着壁炉台上方挂着的牧羊杖柄，开口唱起来：

啊，我的行当实在太稀罕，
我淳朴的牧羊人呀——
我的行当是个大奇观；
客户会被我捆起，再把他们高高吊起，
送他们到遥远的国度去！

他唱完了这一段，屋里所有人都沉默了，只有坐在壁炉旁的陌生人例外。他听到唱歌的人喊：“伴唱！”便用他浑厚悦耳的嗓音应和，“送他们到遥远的国度去！”

奥利弗·盖尔斯、奶牛场主约翰·皮彻、教区执事、五十岁的订婚男子，还有靠墙坐着的一排年轻姑娘似乎都有些走神，但想的似乎并不是什么开心事。牧羊人望着地面若有所思，他的妻子牢牢盯着唱歌的人，狐疑地思索他究竟是在凭着记忆唱一首老歌呢，还是在即兴发挥来应景。在座所有人都迷惑不解，如同伯沙撒王宴会上的宾客一般。[7]只有壁炉旁的第一个陌生人轻声说：“第二段，唱起来！”然后继续抽他的烟斗。

歌者又满满地喝了一杯酒润嗓，应邀继续唱第二段：

我的工具实在太简单，
我淳朴的牧羊人呀——
我的工具一点不稀奇；
给我一小截麻绳，再加根高高的柱子，
这些已够我演一场好戏！

牧羊人菲诺四下瞥了瞥。这下已再无疑问，陌生人正是在用唱歌的方式回答他提出的问题。客人们一个个都吓得向后一缩，发出低低的惊呼声。五十岁男子年轻的未婚妻一副快晕倒的样子，但她发现未婚夫可能身手不够敏捷没法及时接住她，于是便没有再继续倒下去，而是坐了下来，浑身颤抖。

“啊，他就是那个——！”大家悄声低语，提到了一个不祥的公职名称。“他是来干那个的！就是明天，在卡斯特桥监狱！那个偷羊贼——听说是个可怜的钟表匠，原来住在肖茨福特——叫作蒂莫西·萨默斯，后来没有活干了，全家人都快饿死了，于是他就沿着大路出了肖茨福特，光天化日之下偷了别人家的一头羊，公然反抗农场主和他的妻儿，还有在场的每一个人。他——”他们的头朝那个从事死亡职业的陌生人微微点了点，“是从北边过来的，他自己的镇上没多少活干了，所以就到这边来了；我们镇上原来干这活的人死了，他就得了这个职位；以后他就要住到监狱高墙下面的那个屋子里头啦！”

穿烟灰色衣服的陌生人没有理会这一阵窃窃私语，而是又喝了一杯酒润嗓。看到只有壁炉旁的那位朋友对他的欢快有所回应，他便向这位颇有眼光的伙伴举杯致意，对方也举杯回应，两人碰了碰杯。屋里其他人眼睛都盯着歌者的一举一动。他张口正准备唱第三段，突然门外又传来一阵敲门声。这次声音很轻且犹疑不决。

所有人似乎都被吓到了。牧羊人惊慌失措地看看门口，又看看妻子那不赞成的眼色，费了些劲儿才扛住，第三次说出欢迎的话：“请进！”

门轻轻地开了，又一个男人站在脚垫上。跟前两位来客一样，这也是个陌生人。这次的来者个子矮小，肤色白皙，穿着一套体面的深色衣服。

“能否问个路，我想去——”他开口说话了，同时环顾了一下屋内，看看里面都是些什么人，然后他看见了穿着烟灰色衣服的陌生人。后者那会儿正全神贯注开始唱他的第三段，完全没有理会别的事的打岔。他的歌声让所有的私语和询问都停了下来：

明天是我工作的日子，
我淳朴的牧羊人呀——
明天已到干活的佳期；
农夫的羊被宰啦，宰羊的人被逮啦，
愿上帝让他的灵魂安息！

坐在壁炉旁的陌生人举着酒杯快活地伴着歌声挥手，连蜜酒洒出来了都浑然不觉，然后又用他低沉浑厚的嗓音伴唱：“愿上帝让他的灵魂安息！”

在此期间第三个陌生人一直站在门口。大家发现他既没有走进来也没有开口说话，便抬头仔细地打量他，然后惊讶地发现他一副惊恐万状的模样——两腿直打哆嗦，手也抖得很厉害，把拉着的门闩都弄得嗒嗒作响；他张着嘴，嘴唇惨白，眼睛死死盯着屋子中间那位快活的绞刑官。再下一刻他转过身，把门一关，仓皇逃走了。

“这是个什么人哪？”牧羊人说。

屋子里的人一面因最新的发现而恐惧，一面因第三位来客的举止而诧异，个个看上去都有些不知所措，一时间都不说话了。他们不自觉地退后，想尽可能离那位可怕的先生远一点；有的人简直就把他当成了死神本尊。最后他们全都缩在边上围成一个大圆圈，与他之间隔了远远一段距离——

“……一个圆圈，恶魔立于其间。”[8]

屋内一片死寂——虽然里面明明坐着二十多个人——能听到的唯有雨打在窗棂上的声音，以及间或一滴雨落进烟囱滴到火上发出的咝咝声，还有角落里的陌生人抽着烟斗发出的有节奏的吐烟声。

这沉默被出其不意地打断了。远处传来一声枪响，在空气中回荡着——很显然是从三英里外的小镇方向传来的。

“糟糕！”唱歌的陌生人跳起来喊。

“那是什么意思？”几个人问道。

“有人越狱了——就是这个意思。”

众人侧耳倾听，枪声又响了一遍。大家都不说话了，壁炉旁的陌生人低声开口说：“我以前听人说过在这个地方出现这种情况的时候他们就会开枪示警；但今天还是头一回听到。”

“我在想逃走的是不是我的那个人？”穿烟灰色衣服的人自言自语。

“肯定是的！”牧羊人不由自主地说，“我们见到的肯定就是他！现在想想，那个小个子从门口往里头看，一看到是你，又听到你唱的歌，就抖得跟片树叶一样！”

“他吓得牙齿直打架，气都喘不上来了！”奶牛场主也说。

“然后他就像心头落了块大石头！”奥利弗·盖尔斯接着说。

“然后他拔腿就跑，就跟挨了一枪一样。”篱笆匠说。

“确实如此——他牙齿咯咯打战，心头一沉，然后就跟挨了一枪一样拔腿就跑了。”坐在角落的陌生人慢吞吞地总结陈词。

“我都没注意到呢。”绞刑官说。

“我们那——那个时候就在想到底是啥把他吓成这样，一溜烟就跑了。”靠墙坐着的一个妇人结结巴巴地发话，“现在终于晓得了！”

示警的枪声还在间歇地响着，声音沉闷，他们的怀疑变成了确定的事实。穿烟灰色衣服的死神使者振奋起来，语气沉重地问道：“这里有没有治安警察？有的话请上前一步说话。”

五十岁的订婚男子哆哆嗦嗦从墙边走过来，他的未婚妻靠着椅背开始抽泣。

“你是宣过誓的治安警察？”

“是嘞，长官。”

“那就赶快带上人去追犯人，把他带回这儿来。他肯定跑不了多远。”

“好嘞，长官，好嘞——我拿上警棍就去。我马上就回家拿警棍，然后马上回来，然后跟大家一起出发。”

“警棍！——这个时候还管什么警棍，再不去人就跑了！”

“但是没得警棍我不能抓人哪——威廉，约翰，还有查尔斯·杰克，你们都晓得，对不对？因为警棍上头印有国王陛下金黄色的王冠，还有狮子和独角兽，那我把警棍举起来打犯人就是合法的。没得警棍我就不能抓人，不行，真的不行。要是没得法律给我壮胆，哎呀，不是我抓他，倒是他来抓我哟！”

“好吧，我自己就是国王陛下的官差，我可以授权你去干这件事，”令人敬畏的穿烟灰色衣服的绞刑官说，“现在，所有人，各就位。你们有没有灯？”

“是！——你们没有灯？——我需要灯！”警官说。

“你们剩下的那些身强力壮的——”

“身强力壮的男人——对——你们所有人！”警官应和。

“这里有没有结实的棍子和草叉——”

“棍子和草叉——以法律的名义！你们都把武器拿在手头，出发去找人，照我们长官的吩咐去做！”

这样安排完后，男人们便准备出发去追赶犯人。证据虽然只是旁证，但足以令人信服，所以根本不需要再向客人们多解释。他们已经亲眼看到了之前的场景，假如还不马上出去追那第三个倒霉的陌生人的话，那简直就是纵容默许，等同共犯。在这崎岖不平的山路上，那个人最多只能跑出去几百码远。

牧羊人家里最不缺的就是风灯。于是男人们匆匆点上灯，手里抄着搭羊栏用的木棍，涌出大门，朝着与小镇相反的方向往山顶而去，幸好这时候雨势小了一些。

受洗的婴儿被响动给惊醒，也可能是梦到了可怕的受洗，开始在楼上房间里伤心欲绝地大哭起来。哭声透过地板的缝隙传到了楼下女人们的耳中，她们一个接一个地跳起来，赶着上楼去安抚婴儿，似乎很高兴终于有个理由可以离开，因为前半个小时里发生的事实在是让她们心情郁闷。不过两三分钟的时间，一楼便空无一人了。

不过这情况并没持续多久。脚步声刚刚停息，有一个人就从追捕犯人的那个方向回来了。他从屋子的拐角转出来，在门口探头偷偷看了看，发现没人，便大大咧咧地走进来，正是坐在壁炉旁的那个陌生人，他之前跟着大家一起出去了。他回来的目的很快就清楚了：他在刚才坐过的壁炉旁的架子上切下一块油面糕，看来是刚才忘带上了。他又从酒缸里倒了半杯蜜酒，站在那里狼吞虎咽地吃吃喝喝。还没等他吃完，另一个人也悄悄地进来了——正是他那穿着烟灰色衣服的伙伴。

“噢——你也在啊？”后来者微笑着说，“我还以为你跟着他们一起抓人去了呢。”他也暴露了回来的目的，眼睛热切地搜寻那一缸令人沉醉的陈年蜜酒。

“我也以为你跟他们去了呢。”另一个回答，费了点劲儿才又继续吃他的油面糕。

“嗯，我转念一想，人已经够多了，不少我一个，”前者推心置腹地说，“何况还是在这么个夜晚。而且，抓犯人是衙门的事——不该我来干。”

“是的，的确如此。我也是这么想的，人已经够多了，不差我一个。”

“我可不想在这荒山野岭里爬坡下坎，把手脚给摔断咯。”

“我也不想，咱们私底下悄悄说。”

“这些牧羊人倒是习惯了——这些头脑简单的人，你知道的，有点什么动静立马就能爬起来。天亮前他们肯定能帮我把他抓回来，根本不需要我自己动手。”

“他们肯定能抓住他，我们在这件事上也省得劳力费神了。”

“对的，对的。我要去卡斯特桥，我的腿脚也只能走那么远了。我们同不同路？”

“唉，可惜咱们不同路！我得赶回那边的家。”他头朝着右方某个地方点了一点，“我也一样，等我到家上床睡觉的时候，腿估计差不多也快废了。”

另一个人这会儿已经把缸里的蜜酒饮尽了。两人在门边热烈地握握手，互道珍重，然后各自上路了。

与此同时，追捕者们已经来到了这片牧场最高处的猪脊顶。他们并没有一个具体的行动方案，再加上发现从事可怕行当的那位官员不在人群里，于是更加没了主意。他们从各个方向下山搜寻，结果好几个人都掉进了大自然在这片白垩纪地貌区为深夜迷路的人设下的陷阱里。稍微不留神，就会在陡坡的燧石带上滑倒。这些燧石带每隔十几码就有一段，稍不留神踩到，就会失足摔倒，沿着布满碎石的陡坡急速下滑，风灯也脱手而出直滚到山下，侧翻在地，羊角架子都被烧焦了。

待到他们重新聚齐以后，最谙熟这片地区的牧羊人便站了出来，领着大家绕过这片危险的斜坡。风灯灭掉了，因为它对此行的目的毫无裨益，不但刺眼，而且还可能会惊动那个逃亡的人，同时所有人都保持安静。大家在这种更有序的状态下来到了山谷里。谷底杂草密布、荆棘丛生、潮湿狭窄，有心人能在此找到不少藏身之处。大家来回搜索了一遍但没有任何发现，于是又从另一边上了山。他们从这里开始分头行动，隔一阵再碰头汇报进展。等到第二次碰头的时候，他们来到了一棵孤零零的梣树旁，整片山谷只有这么唯一的一棵，很可能是五十年前一只飞鸟经过时落下了种子。就在那儿，靠近树干一侧站着，像树干一样一动不动的，正是他们要找的人。他的轮廓在天空的衬托下格外显眼。大家蹑手蹑脚靠近，然后正面迎上了他。

“要钱还是要命！”警官对着一动不动的人影厉声喝道。

“错了错了，”约翰·皮彻小声说，“我们这边不能这个样子说，这种话是他那种强盗说的，我们是正义的一方。”

“哎呀，哎呀！”警官不耐烦地回答，“我总要说点啥嘛，对不对？要是你心头一直想到要担这么大的责任，你还不是会说错话！嘿，那个坐牢的犯人，我以主的名义——哦不，我以国王的名义命令你，马上投降！”

树下的男人似乎到现在才第一次注意到他们，他慢慢向他们走过来，并没有给他们任何展示勇气的机会。他正是那个个头矮小的第三个陌生人，不过这时他魂飞魄散的神色已经消失了。

“过路人，你们刚才是在对我说话吗？”他问道。

“说对了！你赶快过来，马上束手就擒！”警察说，“我们指控你不在卡斯特桥监狱里头好好待着，等到明天执行绞刑。乡亲们，大家各就位，把犯人抓起来！”

听到上述指控，陌生人似乎终于明白了他们的意图，没有再说什么，而是出乎意料地客气，立刻束手就擒。追捕队员们手持棍棒将他围在中间，押回了牧羊人的小屋。

他们到达小屋时已是晚上十一点。待他们走近时，发现门敞开着，灯光从里透出来，伴随着男人说话的声音，说明他们离开后又有新情况发生了。

他们走进客厅，发现新闯入者原来是卡斯特桥监狱的两个守卫和住在附近庄园、闻名当地的治安官，看来犯人逃走的消息已经传开了。

“先生们，”警察说，“我把你们要找的人带回来了——经过许多波折和危险。当然每个人都要尽忠职守！他现在被这群身强力壮的男人包围着呢，他们帮了我很大的忙，想想他们对官差的工作一无所知，干得算是很不错咯。伙计们，把犯人带上来！”第三个陌生人被押到了亮处。

“这是谁？”一个守卫问。

“逃犯呀。”警察回答。

“肯定不是！”第二个守卫说，头一个也证实说不是。

“咋可能不是？”警察问，“不然他为啥一看到那个唱歌的绞刑官就吓成那个样子？”他于是描述了一遍第三个陌生人在进门听到绞刑官唱歌后的古怪行为。

“不晓得为啥。”守卫冷淡地说，“我只晓得这个人不是那个死刑犯。他们两个完全是两回事。那个死刑犯很瘦，黑头发黑眼睛，长得还蛮标致，声音低沉又悦耳，你只要听到过一次，一辈子都不会认错。”

“天哪，——那不是坐在壁炉旁边的那个人嘛！”

“嘿——在说什么呢？”治安官此前在一旁询问牧羊人事情的经过，现在走上前来，“你们最后还是没抓住那个犯人？”

“是的，长官，”警察说，“这个人就是我们要找的人没错，但是他不是我们该找的人。因为我们要找的人不是我们该找的那个，我这样表达不晓得您能不能明白，我们该找的其实是壁炉旁边的那个人！”

“实在是太混乱了！”治安官说，“你最好马上出发去找另外的那个！”

他们抓回来的陌生人现在终于头一次开口说话了。听到他们提起壁炉旁的那个人，他似乎被深深地触动了。“长官，”他走上前对治安官说，“不必在我身上费心思啦。我想该是我说话的时候了。我没做什么坏事。我的罪过在于，那个死刑犯是我哥哥。今天下午我早早就出门从肖茨福特一路走来准备去卡斯特桥监狱跟他告别。天黑时路过这里，于是我敲门进来想休息一下再问个路。谁知道我一开门，就看见了我哥哥，我本来应该在卡斯特桥监狱的死囚室里才会见到他的。而他就坐在这壁炉旁边，他旁边还紧挨着个人，所以他就算想跑都跑不出去。他挨着的那个人还是专门来取他性命的刽子手，而且还编了一首歌正在唱这件事。刽子手完全不知道坐在旁边的就是他要执刑的犯人，而那个犯人还装模作样地跟他一起唱！我哥哥给我递了个眼色，饱含着悲痛，我知道他在说，‘不要说出来，我的性命就在你手上！’我当时真是给吓得魂飞魄散，站都站不稳了，所以，我自己都不知道做了什么，转过身就赶紧跑掉了。”

说话人的举止和语气情真意切，话的真实性无须怀疑。他讲的故事给众人留下了深刻的印象。

“你知不知道你哥哥现在在哪儿？”治安官问。

“不知道。关上这扇门以后，我就再也没有见过他。”

“我可以做证，后来我们都在场。”警察说。

“他可能会逃到哪些地方？——他是干什么的？”

“他是个钟表匠，长官。”

“他还撒谎说自己是修轮子的——可恶的骗子！”警察说。

“他指的肯定是钟表的齿轮，”牧羊人菲诺说，“我当时就想，修轮子的人手咋会那么白。”

“好吧，我觉得没有必要再拘留这个倒霉的人了，”治安官说，“毫无疑问，你们要抓的是另外那个人。”

小个子男人被当场释放了。但是他看起来依然忧心忡忡，不过治安官和警察对此也无能为力，因为他现在心中最大的担忧并不是自己，而是另一个人。等他重获自由并离开后，夜已经深了，大家决定还是等到第二天一早再去追逃犯。

到了第二天，追捕那位聪明的偷羊人的工作便大面积深入展开了——至少表面上看来如此。但是由于刑罚与罪过实在太不对等，当地的乡民们大多暗暗同情亡命的逃犯。他在牧羊人家的庆祝会上，那样前所未有的场合上表现出的出奇冷静以及同绞刑官的亲密互动、斗智斗勇更是赢得了大家的仰慕。因此，乡民们表面上看起来忙忙碌碌，挨个翻遍了树林、田野和小径，但他们在查看自家的草料棚和外屋时是否也一样仔细就很难讲了。起初有传言说在远离大路的某条荒草覆盖的古道上偶尔看到神秘人影出没，但等到真的去搜查这些可疑地点时，却又一无所获。于是时间一天天、一周周过去了，却始终没有偷羊人的消息。

总之，坐在壁炉旁的那位嗓音浑厚的男子终究没有被抓到。有人说他已离开了英国，有人说他其实只是深藏于某个大城市的人海之中。无论如何，穿烟灰色衣服的绅士没能如期执行卡斯特桥早晨的差事，也没有再在他干活的时候遇到那位曾与他在丘陵牧场牧羊人孤零零的屋子里共度一段休闲时光的好伙伴。

牧羊人菲诺和他节俭的妻子坟头早已绿草萋萋，当年前来庆祝洗礼的宾客们大多已跟随着主人入了土，宾客们为之而来的小婴儿如今已到垂老暮年。但那一晚牧羊人家中的三个陌生来客的故事以及中间的种种细节却流传至今，让“高报晓梯”在当地家喻户晓。

一八八三年三月

[1]森拉克之战是一〇六六年黑斯廷斯战役决定胜负之役；克雷西之战是英法百年战争中的经典战役，发生于一三四六年。两次战争均以弓箭手为决胜关键。

[2]引自《圣经·旧约·传道书》第七章第六节，“愚人的笑声，便如同烧荆棘的爆声，不过是虚空”。意即两者都既喧闹又毁灭自己，毫无意义。

[3]基尼，一六六三年英国发行的一种金币。一基尼等于二十一先令，即一点零五英镑。于一八一三年停止流通，后由英镑取代。

[4]价值五先令。

[5]也就是不超过一点七五米。

[6]指城镇里的技术工人和公职人员等。

[7]出自《圣经·旧约·但以理书》，伯沙撒是古巴比伦王国最后一位国王，在一次宴饮时命人将他父亲从耶路撒冷圣殿中掠夺来的器皿给宾客饮酒。正在纵情欢乐之际，上帝突然显现一只手在宫殿墙上写了几行字，但无人能识。

[8]原文为拉丁文。

高岗故人来

一

沿卡斯特桥镇往北的大路漫长无趣、行人稀少，尤其是在冬季。沿此路前行，可通往长梣树道。长梣树道是一条单调乏味的小径，方圆数英里都看不到村舍与人家，也很少有转弯。不知情的路人，假如过于老迈、年幼或羸弱，走这么远的路会异常吃力。但倘若又非走不可时，他们就只能向往地望望前方，安慰自己，“只要爬上那个小山顶，肯定就能看到长梣树道的尽头了”！然而等他们爬到山顶时，长梣树道却一如既往继续无情地向前伸展。

数年前，曾有一个农场主在一个暮霭沉沉的冬日黄昏骑马走在这条道上。他的朋友，一个奶牛场主，也骑着马与他并肩而行。身后隔几步远处跟着农场主的帮工。三人都骑着浑圆壮实的矮脚马；而在长梣树道上，有好马骑意味着比可怜的徒步行人更容易保持好心情。

不过一路上农场主很少同友人交谈。他的脑子里满是令他来这路上走一遭的那件事，因为那的确是件大事。也许从它对整个社会的价值来衡量并不那么重要，但如果一件事的重要性跟它在做这件事的人心里所占据的空间成正比的话，农场主查尔斯·达顿今晚要做的事几乎可等同于君王的国家大事。

他是个家境殷实的农场主。他的“营业收入”——按专业说法——一年大约有三万英镑。他的农场里驮马奶牛成群，绵羊无数。但这些家业并不是他自己挣来的，而是他的父亲创下的。他父亲同他这个家族血脉的最新代表相比，性格可是完全不同。

老达顿是个一意孤行的人，口袋守得紧紧的，眼睛细细的像条缝，里头满是生意人的精明。而到了儿子这里，这种工于算计的精明却转化成了感性，原来的严苛则完全消失了；若不是他有一群快活的朋友，他也时常小心不跟他们唱反调的话，他简直可以被称为是个忧郁的人。他喜欢沉思，大脑常常成为回忆与希望交汇的静谧场所。因此毫不奇怪，自从他继承家业到现在三十二岁的这些年来，他的家产既未再扩大，也不曾减少。但这故步自封并未让他有丝毫不快，他本就毫无野心也不善计谋，因为他自认为已经拥有了想要的一切。今晚此行的目的同样显示了他对自己不甚在意。

三人的马步缓慢而谨慎，在天色已晚路又难行时这谨慎的确很有必要。在夜色中，农场主达顿的头一上一下颠得很不浪漫。他的好友，杰夫斯·约翰斯，则以更大幅度的抖动与他相应和。而后者的动作又被随从小伙子模仿得毫无美感可言，几近抽搐。随从身上一前一后各搭着一个白色的东西，每走一步就要撞一下，更是破坏了他坐姿的雅观。仔细近看就会发现原来是两个没有盖儿的蒲草篮子——一个装着一只火鸡，另一个装着几瓶酒。

“达顿老兄，你觉得自己真的可以像个男人一样面对命运了哇？”等到他们已经经过了二十五丛树篱后，约翰斯打破了沉默，开口问道。

达顿先生微笑了一下，低声说：“是啊——这就是我的命！娶妻跟上绞刑一样，都是命中注定。”然后两人又不说话了。

夜色迅速变浓，每隔一段时间就能看见它拍动黑翼下降，逐渐笼罩大地。与此同时空气也逐渐凝滞，加速了白昼的结束。随着夜色降临，潮湿的雾气弥漫开来，足以让人不适，但还不至于把人打湿。生为乡下人，可以说他们与四季天气之间只隔着一扇敞开的门——因此他们只把这雾气看作增加了行路的一些障碍，却并不在意它的潮湿。

达顿此次“朝圣”的目的地是一个老式的村庄，因此一路上并没有现代化的车流穿梭增添生气。这个村子是众多欣托克村中的一个（在那片地区有许多村子都叫这个名字，并在前面或后面添个不同的词缀加以区别）——这个村酿的苹果汁和苹果酒是全威塞克斯最好的。村里的堆肥散发出的都是苹果渣的气味，而不像别处尽是牲畜的粪便味。这条小路有些地方非常狭窄，树篱上的刺藤就像是小溪上垂下的钓竿，会挂住他们的帽子或勾住他们的胡须。然而这条人烟稀少的小道在伊丽莎白时代曾是女王的臣民和车马队出行的主要干道。它早已不复当年盛况，作为一条举国闻名的主干道的历史已永远终结。

“我之所以决定娶她，”达顿环视了一下，看到帮工离他们还不算太近，便继续开口（声音悦耳，语气平和，充满自信，充分展示了他的性格气质），“不光是因为我喜欢她，也因为我没有更好的选择了，就算是从很务实的角度来看。有人说我可以找个门第更高的，也许没错，但其实蠢透了。我已经吃过了想高攀的苦头。那以后——你知道是什么时候，我就告诉自己，‘我再也不会去招惹高高在上的女人了。’莎莉长得好，有主见，头脑简单，也不会装腔作势，在她心中我高高在上，就像曾经——你知道是谁——在我心中高高在上一样。”

“对头，”约翰斯回答，“但是我可不觉得莎莉·霍尔头脑简单。第一，莎莉头脑并不简单。第二，就算有的人头脑简单，你的这位也不会。这种说法不应该用来形容一个女人。查尔斯，作为你的伴郎，听到这种话我简直就像遭泼了一盆冷水。感觉就像你花了半个克朗买了一张戏票，结果人家跟你说这出戏里头没有谋杀，没有坏蛋，也没有任何严重伤害一样。”

“哦，你爱怎么想就怎么想吧，反正我的看法跟你完全不同。”接着达顿把对话从哲学思辨转到了世俗现实，说他希望莎莉已经收到了他那天让邮差带给她的东西。

约翰斯问带的是什么。

“是一条长裙，”达顿回答，“不算是结婚礼服，当然如果她愿意也可以当成结婚礼服穿。主要是为了实用而不是为了好看——适合冬天穿。”

“好得很，”约翰斯说，“‘实用’这个词由新郎官说出来简直太明智啦。我要好好表扬你，查尔斯。”

“因为，”达顿辩解说，“结婚就跟死亡一样，都是人一生中最严肃的大事，这种时候为什么要穿得像个走钢丝的杂技演员一样花里胡哨呢？”

“是呀，为啥呢？但是她肯定会穿得花里胡哨，因为她就是要穿得花里胡哨。”奶牛场主约翰斯说。

“哦。”达顿回答。

他们走过的小道一连数英里几乎都是笔直的。现在他们离开了这条道，走上了一条更窄的小路，弯弯曲曲绕了不知道多远后，分成了两条岔路。乡村小路在晚上比白天更容易暴露出丑陋的一面，白天很可能没太留意就过去了。虽然达顿以前走过这条路，但毕竟不常走。他追求莎莉时她住在离他家不远的亲戚家里。他根本不记得在这个地方有两条看起来完全一样的岔路。约翰斯骑马上前几步。

“伙计，不要垂头丧气。”他喊道，“这儿有个路标。伊斯拉——你过来爬上去看一下，告诉我们该走哪条路。”

小伙子翻身下马，跳进了路标所在的一棵树下的灌木丛里。

“把篮子先解下来，不然你会把酒瓶摔碎的！”看见年轻人跟抽筋一样一蹿一蹿地抱着柱子往上爬，身上还背着两个篮子，达顿连忙喊道。

“这个世界已经够没脑子了，你比它还要蠢！”约翰斯说，“算了，蠢蛋伊斯拉，等我来。”他跳下马，吭哧吭哧颇费了些劲儿爬到路标顶端，划了根火柴，借着光察看路牌，小伙子站在下面定定地看着这景象。

“这二十年来我每次被人耍，脾气从来都好得像温开水！”约翰斯说，“但遇到这种事绝对是撞鬼啰！”他把火柴一扔，滑下地来。

“怎么回事？”达顿问。

“牌子上头一个字都没有，既没有圣徒写的字，也没有异端写的字！连去地狱的路咋走都没写——虽然这个话说起来有点罪过！要不就是生霉长苔藓把原来的字吃掉了，要不就是我们到了原始社会，当地人都不会写字喽。我们应该像哥伦布一样带个指南针来才对。”

“我们就走最直的那条路吧，”达顿平静地说，“希望能早点到——骑马还是相当累人的。早知道这样，我就坐马车来了。”

“我也想快点到，先生，”伊斯拉说，“我肩膀上的背带跟犁一样都勒到肉里头去了。要是去您夫人家的路还远的话，达顿老爷，我就要求您让我把这些好东西装一半到我肚子里了——嘻嘻！”

“伊斯拉，不要像个激进党人一样叽叽歪歪，”约翰斯严厉地说，“来，我来拿火鸡。”

等他把火鸡篮子接过来以后，三人踏上了右边的那条小路，小路通往一座小山。左边的那条路则蜿蜒向下通向一片种植林。嗒嗒的马蹄声逐渐上坡远去；那个充满讽刺的路标一如之前，孤零零竖在原地，在阴冷的晚风中伸展着空无一字的手臂，风带来了树林的鼾声，仿佛巨人斯克里米尔正在那里沉睡一般。[1]

二

沿着三人没选的左边那条路向前走三英里，路边有一栋老房子，直棂窗用的是哈姆丘陵岩，烟囱也极其结实。房子位于国王的欣托克村正街旁的一个斜坡顶，离国王的欣托克大宅只有一两英里远，但却同那座府邸及其所辖区域隔绝开来。紧挨着房子正前方有一棵巨大的槭树，树根裸露在地面的部分形成了一个简易的阶梯，沿斜坡下的路直通到大门口。人们根据房子所处的地理位置给它取了个不甚有特色的名字，叫作“高岗”。距房子四十码开外有一条小溪涓涓流过，溪虽小，流水声却十分嘹亮。屋后有一个奶场院子，车辆和牲口可以从侧边的一条“巷子”进出。在这昏暗的傍晚，外头只能看到这户人家的这些情况了。

不过屋内却有足够多的灯光照明——此处的“足够多”是按欣托克村当地的理解而言的。屋内有一个都铎式壁炉，壁炉上方的四圆心尖拱几乎被一个盖着印花蓝布的风箱给挡住了。壁炉旁坐着两个女人——她们是母女——霍尔太太和萨拉，别名莎莉。在这个地区，后一种简称尚未被增进的智识视为鄙俗而废除。叫这个名字的是个年轻姑娘，达顿先生正是打算借助她在翌日告别单身。

母亲孀居多年，如今无论从表情还是穿着都已看不出丧夫的痕迹。她戴回了早年新婚时常戴的头巾软帽，衬以几根玫瑰粉的丝带，使白帽子不至于太过寡淡。莎莉不需要这额外的粉色装点。她面色白里透红，眼神乐观温和，五官轮廓分明，显出理性与决断；说她是个热心、急性子的漂亮姑娘应该不会有错。

说话的主要是莎莉，母亲心不在焉地一边听，一边用火钳把烧得通红的碎木块拣出来，堆到垫底的大木头上。两人的交谈同其中传递的信息比起来可谓惜字如金，常年相伴让她们心有灵犀不点亦通。在她们身后，房间正中央的餐桌上已经摆好了餐具，厨房里间一阵阵带着肉香的蒸气飘进来，表明彼处正在准备晚餐。

“他说要送给你的长裙就跟他本人一样都还在路上。”莎莉的母亲正在说。

“是啊，我估计是还没做好吧，”莎莉说话很有主见，“主啊，就算是永远不送来我也不会觉得奇怪！男人们就是这样，在你面前山盟海誓，一转过身就忘得一干二净。不过他并没打算把它当结婚礼服——只是件外套，什么时候想穿就穿——有些人把这叫作出门装。早来也好，晚来也罢，关系都不大，反正我自己也有裙子可以撑一下。现在几点钟了？”

她走到钟跟前打开玻璃门，因为晚上天黑看不清时间——其实任何时候都没法单靠一瞥就能看清，一定得仔细察看，因为屋子墙多窗少。“快八点了。”她说。

“都八点了，衣服没到人也没到。”霍尔太太说。

“妈，如果您以为这样说就能让我着急，那您可错了！随便他想多晚来就多晚来吧——就算他一辈子都不来——我也无所谓。”莎莉说，但是她说“无所谓”时语气里带着一丝微微的颤抖，暴露了她说这话的勉强。

霍尔太太觉察出来了，淡淡地说她可不认为莎莉真的不在乎。“不过也许你的确不如我那么在乎。”她说，“因为我比你更清楚，这是门能让你发达的好亲事，我们应该感谢达顿先生。而且我相信他会是个好丈夫。所以我们要祈祷上帝让一切顺顺当当，让结果称心如意。”

莎莉这会儿听不进去任何担忧的话。她确信一切肯定都会顺顺当当的。“您别这么忐忑不安啦，妈妈！”她接着说，“不管是什么原因让他来晚了，这会儿他想要快点到这儿的心情比咱们想见到他的心情要迫切得多呢！他的心肯定比他的人跑得快，已经像东边升起的星星一样来到我们家了。快听！”她喊了一声，松了一口气，眼睛闪着喜悦的光芒，“我听到有声音了。是的——是他们来了！”

下一刻她有点耳背的母亲也听到了脚踩着槭树根爬上坡发出的熟悉声响。

“是的，看来他们终于到了，”她说，“唉，总的来说还不算太晚，想想要走那么远的路呢。”

脚步声停了，两人站起身来，等待敲门声响起。她们等了又等，差点要开始怀疑刚听到的脚步声不过是村里某个乡亲，因为喝醉了酒，所以走偏了路。但来人进了走廊，打消了她们的疑虑。房门被轻轻地推开了，可是进来的不是我们已经提到过的那两位旅人，而是一个脸色苍白的男子，穿着极其褴褛——几乎就是一堆破布。

“哦，天哪——是个流浪汉！”莎莉吓得退后一步。

来人脸颊干瘪、眼窝深陷——但很可能更多的是体质虚弱的缘故，而不单是因为饱一顿饥一顿，看得出来他的日子过得并不精心。他定定地望了两个女人一会儿，然后低头望向地面，带着一副羞愧不安、忍辱负重的神情，一言不发地瘫坐到椅子上。

莎莉抢先一步走上前去，她的母亲则站在壁炉边没动弹。莎莉借着烛光仔细辨认来者。

“啊——妈妈，”莎莉转过身，对着霍尔太太，仿佛突然失了力气，“是菲尔，他从澳大利亚回来了！”

霍尔太太大惊，脸色“唰”地一下子变白了。衣着褴褛的男子爆发了一阵咳嗽。“成这个样子回来！”她说，“啊，菲利普——你病了？”

“不，没有，母亲。”他一恢复力气开口，便不耐烦地回答。

“但，我的天哪，你是怎么回来的——而且还在这个时候？”

“唉，我就是回来了，”男子说，“怎么回来的我也不知道。母亲，我之所以回来，是因为迫不得已。在那边什么都不如意，情况越来越糟。”

“那你为什么不告诉我们？——这两三年你从没写过一个字回来。”

儿子哀伤地承认自己没有写过信。他解释说，他一直希望并相信自己也许能挽回局面，就可以给家里报喜。但后来他不得不放弃希望，直到穷途末路只能回来——且待他日东山再起。他看到她们怜悯地打量着他穿的破烂，又重复了一遍：“是的，我的日子很不好过。”

她们把他扶到火边，从他干枯消瘦的手里把帽子接过去。他的手小而光滑，可见他想借以翻盘的办法应该不是干体力活。他的母亲又继续盘问，狐疑地问他是不是有什么特别的原因，所以才特意挑了这一晚回来。

他告诉她没有什么特别原因，只是碰巧而已。说完后菲利普·霍尔环顾四周，这才发现餐桌上的餐具很是奢华，而且不止两个人的数，母女俩的穿着也很隆重喜庆。他赶紧询问是怎么回事。

“莎莉这两天就要成亲了，”母亲回答。她解释说达顿先生，莎莉的未婚夫，今天晚上要同伴郎约翰斯先生一起来做客，以及其他一些详情，“我们听到你的脚步声时还以为是他们来了。”霍尔太太说。

潦倒的流浪汉又一次眼望地面。“明白了——明白了，”他喃喃地说，“是啊，确实，我为什么要今天晚上回来呢？像我这样的人当然不应该出现在这种时候。我根本没有资格出现在这里——搅了别人的好事。”

“菲尔，”他的母亲眼里泛起泪光，但她依然紧抿嘴唇、举止严厉，这应该是源于过去种种而令她不得不这样做，“既然你这样对我说话，那我也对你开诚布公吧。过去三年里你压根儿没管过我们。你离开家的时候不愁钱也不愁力气，你也受过教育，本应好好利用这些条件，过上好日子。可你现在回来，还弄得像个乞丐；而且，不可否认，你回来的时间对我们来说确实非常尴尬。你今晚回来可能会害了我们。不过请记住，只要我还在，这个家就欢迎你。我不会把你拒之门外。事到如今我们也只有尽人事听天命了。你的病严不严重？”

“呃，不严重。只是咳嗽比较烦人。”

她急切地看看他，“我觉得你最好马上去睡一觉。”

“是的——这样我就不会碍事了。”儿子疲惫地说道，“我已经毁了我自己，可别让别人看见我穿着这身破烂，我的天哪，免得毁了你们的幸福。你刚才说莎莉要嫁给谁来着——一个叫达顿的农民？”

“是的——一位绅士农场主——非常富有。地位远高出她的预期。总的来说，这是件大好事。”

“干得漂亮，小莎尔！”她的兄长眼睛一亮，微笑着抬头看她，“我本该写信回来的，但是我怕写了信会更想你。现在让我先躲起来吧，我宁可去跳河也不想在这里被人看到。不过你们有没有什么喝的？我走了很远很远的路，现在渴得嗓子都冒烟了。”

“有的，有的，我们给你送到楼上去。”莎莉说，脸上表情很哀伤。

“好，那非常好。但是，莎莉，母亲——”他欲言又止，她们便等着他说下去。

“母亲，我还没有跟你说完，”他慢慢地开口了，依然低头望着双膝之间的地面，“您看我这副样子已经很落魄，但是还有更糟的在后头。”

他的母亲惊疑不定地盯着他。莎莉走过去靠着柜子，凝神静听，长长叹了口气，然后她突然转过身说：“让该来的都来吧，我不在乎！菲利普，把最坏的事都说出来吧，慢慢说。”

“好吧，”倒霉的菲尔说，“这个烂摊子里，我不是唯一的一个人。上天啊，要是只有我一个就好了！但是——”

“噢，菲尔！”

“我还有个妻子，跟我一样一贫如洗。”

“妻子？”他的母亲问道。

“很不幸！”

“妻子！对啊，养儿子还有这一茬儿！”

“除此之外——”他又说。

“除此之外！噢，菲利普，难道你——”

“我还有两个孩子。”

“妻子和孩子！”霍尔太太低声说，失魂落魄地瘫坐在地上。

“可怜的孩子们！”莎莉不由自主地说。

母亲又转向他说：“我猜你把你可怜的妻儿留在澳大利亚了？”

“不，他们在英格兰。”

“那么，我只能希望你把他们留在了一个还算体面的地方。”

“我没把他们留在任何地方。他们就在这儿——离我们只有几码远。长话短说，他们在马厩里。”

“在……在哪里？”

“在马厩里。我想等我先见到您——母亲——跟您透露一点坏消息之后，再带他们来见您。他们很疲惫了，在里面的稻草堆上歇息。”

霍尔太太的坚毅很明显被击垮了。她也是在体面人家长大的，因此看到儿子斯文扫地，受到的打击比起寻常的奶牛场主遗孀要大得多。“无论如何，都必须得扛着。”她低声地说，双手紧握，“饿得半死的儿子，饿得半死的儿媳妇，饿得半死的孩子！来就来吧。但是你为什么非要在这个节骨眼回来，非要在今天，非要在今晚？为什么要让这样不幸的事情发生在两个无依无靠的女人身上，让我可怜的女儿得到幸福的机会就此被毁掉？菲利普，你为什么要这样害我们？有哪个体面的男人到了这里，看到这一家子的流浪汉，还会愿意跟他们结亲？”

“妈妈，别乱说！”莎莉激烈地说，脸涨得通红，“查理[2]不是那样的人，不会因此抛弃我。但假如他真的因为菲尔回来就不愿意娶我的话，那就让他走，去娶别人吧。我不会为了全英格兰任何一个男人而嫌弃自己的亲人——任他是谁，我都不会！”说完，她扭过头去，眼泪夺眶而出。

“再等二十年，你就不会说这种话了！”她的母亲回答。

儿子站起身来。“母亲，”他苦涩地说，“我怎么来的就怎么走。我只请求您让我和我的家人今晚在您的马厩里歇息一夜。我向您保证，到天亮时我们就会离开，从今往后再不给您添麻烦！”

听到这话，他的母亲霍尔太太变了脸色。“哦不！”她匆忙说，“我可不能让别人说我把自己的亲人拒之门外。菲利普，把他们带进来吧，或者带我过去见他们。”

“我们让他们住到大卧室去吧，”莎莉的脸色高兴了些，“把火生得旺旺的。我们一起过去带他们进来，然后去叫黎贝卡。”（黎贝卡在她们家奶场做帮手并兼做家务，她丈夫则帮着养牛，两人就住在大房旁边的小屋里。）

莎莉到后面厨房拿了一盏灯，但她兄长说：“不需要带灯过去，我已经把挂在马厩那儿的灯点亮了。”

“我们怎么称呼你的妻子？”霍尔太太问。

“海伦娜。”菲利普回答。

母女俩头裹上披巾，向后门走去。

“等一等，”菲利普叫住她们，“我还有件事没说。”

“上天可怜可怜我们吧！”霍尔太太整个人靠向门，双手紧捏在一起，平静而绝望地说。

“我们来的时候经过艾福斯海德，”他接着说，“我顺便去‘猪与橡子’小酒馆看了一眼，看看老迈克还在不在那里干活，正好碰到邮差从谢顿阿巴斯镇过来，他猜我要到这里来——我估计他认出了我——于是让我捎带一个裁缝寄给莎莉的包裹，上面标着‘急件’。我妻子和孩子已经先往前走了。包裹很薄，包装纸磨破了，我看到里面是一件厚实的长裙。我不想让你们看到海伦娜穿得太寒碜，我会觉得很丢人——她生来家境不是这样的。我在路上就把包裹拆了，到下巴恩找她，她在那儿等我。我告诉她我找了件衣服给她穿，让她不要多问。可怜见的，她大概以为是我回到家乡找到了熟人，赊了点账买来的，就很高兴地穿上了。她现在就穿着这件衣服。莎莉应该还有别的衣服吧，我敢说。”

莎莉看了看母亲，一句话也说不出来。

“你肯定还有别的衣服，对不对！”菲尔又重复了一遍，带着病人不耐烦的腔调，“我对自己说，‘就算把莎莉惹哭也好过让海伦娜挨冻。’怎么，这裙子很重要吗？看上去也没有多华丽，至少我看来是这样。”

“不——不，没有多重要。”莎莉凄楚地回答，又柔声加了一句，“你应该不会介意我另外借一件长裙给她，把这条换回来吧？”

菲利普听到这话情绪有点激动，结果又勾起了一阵惊天动地的咳嗽，整个人都快散架了。他实在不适合再坐在椅子里，于是她们立刻扶着他上了楼，匆匆给他倒了一杯药酒，把卧室的火生起来，然后下楼去接那些倒霉的新亲戚了。

三

少女和她的母亲，不久前还喜气洋洋，现在从后门走出来时却有种异样感觉。奶场院子里弥漫着干草的芬芳和奶牛呼出的带着青草味的气息。天上下起了冻雨，她们小跑着穿过院子。马厩门开着，有灯光透出来——正如菲利普所说，他点亮了一直挂在马厩里的那盏灯。她们轻轻地走近门边，霍尔太太呼唤：“海伦娜！”

里面一时没有回应。霍尔太太探头进去，惊愕地发现里面站着两个人。第一个人，不像她想象中的干枯邋遢，而是一个面色苍白，眼睛黝黑，大家闺秀般的女人；不是衣服衬托了她的气质，倒是她的气质衬托得衣服更好看了。她穿着一件簇新的漂亮长裙，正是莎莉的那件，戴着一顶旧帽子。她站在那里，神色激动不安；她的手被在场的另一个人握着——那正是莎莉的未婚夫，农场主查尔斯·达顿。那位面容苍白的陌生女人正凝视着身形健美的达顿，达顿也深深地凝视着她。他另一只手还牵着缰绳，马站在一旁，马鞍尚未卸下，看上去像是刚进来。

两人一看到霍尔太太便马上转过身来望着她，神情有些恍恍惚惚，似乎都想不出任何说辞来解释当下的场景。下一刻莎莉走了进来，达顿先生放开了女人的手，把马牵到一旁，上前问候未婚妻和霍尔太太。

“啊！”他微笑着说，看起来有些故作镇定，“亲爱的霍尔太太，您一定会说我来得太拐弯抹角了吧。其实是因为我们走错了路，所以来晚了。我看到这里有灯光，就牵着马先上来了，我的朋友约翰斯和帮工把马领到前面的小客栈去歇着，省得您这儿挤不下。我一进来就看见这位女士正在这里暂歇——然后才发现我冒昧打扰到她了。”

“这是我儿媳妇，”霍尔太太镇定地说，“我儿子也在家，不过他身体不太舒服已经睡下了。”

莎莉一直站在一旁观望，心里满是疑惑，甚至都没注意到达顿跟她握了握手。直到她看到一堆干草上坐着两个孩子时才如梦初醒。她立刻走上前去跟他们说话，然后把一个抱在怀里，一个牵在手上。

“还有两个孩子？”达顿先生问，由此可见他也是刚到，还没来得及弄明白究竟是什么情况。

“是我的孙子孙女。”霍尔太太回答，依然在故作平静。

尽管刚才菲利普·霍尔的妻子同达顿的邂逅被打断了，但她似乎并未受太大影响，除了达顿，她尚未意识到其他人的存在。然后她突然回过神来，用她忧郁的眼睛探究地打量了一下霍尔太太；结果显然还比较满意，便恭顺地向霍尔太太走去。莎莉同她友好地交谈了几句，便带着孩子们进了屋。霍尔太太和海伦娜紧随其后，后面又跟着达顿先生；他盯着海伦娜的长裙和身形，听着她说话的声音，如在梦中。

等到他们进了屋，莎莉已经带着疲惫的孩子们上楼了。她急速地敲了敲墙，叫黎贝卡过来帮忙一起照料孩子们。黎贝卡家抹灰泥的小木屋就在旁边，紧傍着霍尔太太家高房子的牢固石墙。她过来给孩子们铺了床，又送了些晚餐上来给他们吃。等安排妥当后，莎莉下楼来到会客厅。年轻的霍尔太太也刚进来，在此之前她跟着婆婆进里屋摘掉了帽子，简单拾掇了一下让自己看上去更得体些。所以可以肯定她跟达顿先生在马厩里短暂碰面之后两人再没有说过话。

杰夫斯·约翰斯先生这个时候恰好也到了，引见完毕，他和霍尔太太按社交惯例先就天气问题寒暄了几句，于是大家便没那么拘谨了。众人立刻坐下来开始晚餐，但送的酒和火鸡没有拿出来在今晚享用，因为霍尔太太怕太早将这些礼物呈上会让人怀疑她缺吃少喝、请不起客。

“尽情地喝吧，约翰斯先生，请尽情地喝，”女主人大方地说，“这样的酒我们还有很多哪，不过也许这苹果酒不合你的口味？——这酒其实浓度很高。”

“正好相反，夫人——正好相反，”奶牛场主说，“虽然我继承了我父亲要喝就喝麦芽酒的信条，但我其实是随我母亲，更爱喝苹果酒的。她就是这个地方的人，您知道。我说苹果酒还有一个好处——这个酒更平和，不会像有些烈酒一样喝了就要去把别人放倒。小心点的话，这个酒一年到头喝上十二个月，你都不会打倒一个邻居，或者遭熟人打得鼻青眼肿。”

闲谈就这样开了头并继续轻快地进行下去，但主要是霍尔太太和杰夫斯[3]在聊。说实在的，两人也根本不需要什么帮腔。莎莉既然无须开口，便有大量的闲暇做自己最想做的事——仔细观察她的未婚夫和嫂子，想要弄清她和母亲在马厩里意外撞上两人时那古怪的一幕究竟是怎么回事。如果那一幕有任何含义的话，它至少意味着这两人以前见过面。莎莉看得出来两人没来得及做解释，因为他们两人到现在都还对彼此出现在这里感到迷惑不解，虽然他们都强忍着没问。达顿的眼光依然时不时地瞟向海伦娜穿的长裙，似乎这件事让他的迷惑又多加了一层——虽然对莎莉来说这是整出戏里唯一不是秘密的事。达顿似乎感到在他即将开场的爱的吉格舞中，命运突然恶作剧地给他换了一个舞伴。穿着长裙的本该是莎莉，可转过身却换成了海伦娜的脸。那手伸出袖口，被他握住的竟是一只久违了的手。

莎莉看得出来，无论海伦娜与达顿交情究竟是深是浅，她肯定都不明白为何这长裙会让他如此困惑。这位年轻姑娘有时候几乎都要相信达顿先生之所以总看她嫂子，纯粹是因为这件衣服的关系。但有时候她的爱人眼里流露出更多的探究及情感，又绝非只是衣服和人不对应所能引起的。

莎莉是个独立自强的姑娘，因此极少有妒忌之心。但是这两位来客的关系的确有需要澄清之处。

杰夫斯·约翰斯继续用他那众人熟知的风格天南海北地聊着，间或杂以他对达顿和莎莉的亲事的一些个人感想，说的时候眼神闪闪发亮，看得出来很是自得其乐，但对其他人来说其实是词不达意。最后他终于告辞了，到前面半英里外的路边客栈去歇息。达顿告诉他自己随后就来。

半小时过去了，达顿先生也站起身准备告辞，莎莉和她嫂子两人同时向他道晚安，然后便各自上楼回房间了。霍尔太太把他送到正门口，却发现外面下起了倾盆大雨，便建议他回到壁炉边坐坐，等暴雨停了再走。

达顿接受了她的建议，但坚持说时间已晚，很显然她也累了，所以就不必为了陪他一直熬着，他到时候可以自行离开，在此之前自己一个人在壁炉边抽一斗烟就好了。霍尔太太同意了，达顿便独自一人留在屋里。他摊开双膝烤火，然后像他刚说的那样点燃了烟草，坐在那里眼望着炉火以及壁炉上方挂钩的卡口。

间或有一滴雨沿着烟囱滚落下来，在火上发出咝咝声。他继续抽着烟，心情却并不轻松。尽管他一直在想心事，但白天里上午在地里转悠，下午又骑马走了那么远的路，这劳累奔波终究还是产生了自然而然的结果：他开始打盹了。

他这样半梦半醒睡了多久自己也不清楚。等他突然睁开眼，壁炉里垫底的大圆木已烧裂成了两半，没有明火了，他放在壁炉台上的灯也差不多快熄灭了。尽管如此，房子里还是有亮光——是别处传来的。他转过头，看见菲利普·霍尔的妻子站在会客厅入口处，一只手举着一根床头蜡烛，另一只手提着一个黄铜小茶壶，他送的长裙——看起来应该是那件——还穿在她身上。

“海伦娜！”达顿吃惊地坐起身。

她的表情很惊慌，说出的第一句话是道歉。“我——不知道您也在这里，达顿先生，”她说，脸上泛起一丝红晕，“我以为所有人都已经睡了——我来是想烧点开水；我丈夫的病情好像更严重了。不过也许我可以去厨房把火重新生起来。”

“不用因为我在而去厨房。请照你原来的打算，就把壶放在这儿吧，”达顿说，“让我来帮你。”他走上前去接茶壶，但是她却不肯，自己把壶放到了火上。

两人隔了一段距离，分别站在壁炉的两边等水烧开。蜡烛放在中间的壁炉台上，海伦娜眼睛盯着水壶。达顿率先打破了沉默，问：“我要不要叫莎莉下来？”

“噢不用了，”她赶紧回答，“我们已经添了太多麻烦了。我们本来无权待在这儿，但最后阴差阳错，不得不来这里。”

“无权待在这儿！”达顿惊异地说。

“是的。一时半会儿也解释不清。”海伦娜回答，“这个壶烧水可真慢呀。”

对话又打住了。那句用来形容欲速则不达的谚语“眼望着锅锅不开”在此真是找到了最好的例证。[4]

海伦娜的相貌属于楚楚可怜型，仿佛总在求助，虽然并不自知——跟莎莉正好截然相反：莎莉脸上明明白白写着自力更生。达顿眼睛一会儿看看水壶，一会儿看看海伦娜的脸，再回到水壶，然后在她的脸上停留更长的时间。“所以这个让我分心了一晚上的秘密，我是无权知道真相了？”他问，“一个女人当初拒绝了我的求婚，我想应该是因为我地位低品位差配不上她吧，为什么后来却嫁给了一个看起来比我落魄得多的男人？”

“因为他有优先权。”她回答。

“什么！你在那之前就认识他了？”

“是的，是的！他那时去了澳大利亚，然后写信来要我去跟他会合，于是我就去了。”

“啊——原来是这样！”

“请别再提了，”她恳求道，“不管我犯了什么错，过去的五年里我已经受到了惩罚。”

达顿容易感情泛滥，有时可以说是善良过了头。“我衷心为你感到难过。”他说，不自觉地靠近她。海伦娜后退了一两步，他意识到了自己的举动，连忙又回到了之前的位置。他没有再说话，小水壶开始鸣叫起来。

“所以，如果你愿意，你本可以嫁给我。”他最后又开口了，“当然这些都已成往事无须再提了。不过，如果你遇到任何麻烦或急需钱，我都会很乐意帮你；作为姻亲，我也有权提供帮助。你叔叔知道你的困窘吗？”

“我叔叔已经过世了，他没给我留下一分钱。可现在我和我丈夫还有两个孩子要养活。”

“什么，他一分钱都没留给你？他为什么要对你这么残忍？”

“在他看来，我是名誉扫地丢尽了脸吧。”

“既然如此，”达顿诚恳地说，“让我来照顾孩子们吧，至少在你们安顿下来之前。你属于别人，所以我不能照顾你了。”

“你能照顾她，”一个声音传来，接着一个身影突然出现在他们旁边。来者正是莎莉，“你能照顾她，你看上去也很想照顾她是吧？”她重复了一遍，“她已经不属于别人了……我可怜的哥哥已经死了！”

她的脸涨得通红，眼中泪光闪闪，女人的天性此时表露无遗。“我全听到了！”她激动地对他说，“你现在可以连她带她的孩子一起照顾了！”她转过身看着她不安的嫂子，声音柔和下来，跟刚才的激烈完全不同，“我听到有动静，于是进了他的房间。应该就是在你离开的时候发生的。他那么快就走了，那么虚弱，那么出人意料，所以我都来不及离开去叫你。”

达顿这才从莎莉后面有些语无伦次的话里听明白：在他睡着的时候，尚未谋面的莎莉的兄长病情恶化了；而在海伦娜离开去烧水的当儿，他的大限就这样不期而至了。两个年轻女人匆匆上楼去了，他又一个人留在了会客室。

他在那儿站了一小会儿之后，走到前门往外望了望；然后他轻轻关上门，走到了大槭树下站定。星星冷冷地闪烁着，先头下雨带来的潮气现在挟裹着寒冷袭来。达顿陷入了一种奇怪的境地，他自己也感觉到了。年轻的海伦娜小姐，一位已故海军军官的女儿，由律师叔叔养大，数年前拒绝了达顿的求婚。现在她出其不意地回来了，身无分文。他眼前又出现了莎莉见到他们两人在一起时激动到近乎愤怒的样子，以及突如其来的海伦娜成了寡妇的消息。所有这一切机缘巧合同时袭来，让他一时半会儿不知如何应对。他思忖着是该离开呢还是留下来帮忙。要不是因为莎莉的态度，他会毫不犹豫地选择后者。

他还在树下站着时，前门突然开了，霍尔太太走了出来。她朝旁边的花园门走去，并没有看见他。达顿跟了上去，打算开口说话。她在门前停了一下，似乎在思考什么，然后继续走到了花园里的一处，此处春天阳光最早到达，北风从来吹不到。那儿靠着墙角摆了一排蜂箱。达顿明白了她的意图，于是停下来等待。

在那片地区有个习俗，但凡家里有人去世，就得去拍打蜂箱把蜜蜂唤醒，大家都说假如不这样的话蜜蜂们在来年就会衰竭而死。听到第一个蜂箱里随着她的拍打传出了嗡嗡的回应，霍尔太太又去拍打下一个，一直到整排蜂箱全都拍打完毕。等她一出来，达顿就走上前去。

“霍尔太太，有什么我能帮上忙的吗？”他问。

“哦，不用了，谢谢你，不用了。”她这才看见他，声音里带着一丝哭腔回答道，“我们已经叫了黎贝卡和她的丈夫过来，他们会把一切安排妥当的。”她简短地说了一下她儿子是如何回来的，身体如何已完全垮掉——是的，已到了死亡的边缘，虽然那时她们没有觉察——然后建议说婚礼最好能够推迟，这是她和女儿商量的结果。

“是的，当然应该推迟，”达顿回答，“我想现在就回客栈，告诉约翰斯发生了什么事。”两人握手道别，达顿犹犹豫豫地又转过身来补充说，“既然两个孩子已经没了父亲，能否请您转告他孩子的母亲，我很愿意收养大一点的那个孩子，如果她和您觉得合适的话？”

霍尔太太答应会告知她儿子的遗孀，然后两人便分别了。他沿着树根走下斜坡，消失在通往客栈的方向，去告知约翰斯这突发的情况。与此同时霍尔太太进了房子。莎莉独自一人坐在楼下会客室里，她的母亲告诉她达顿很通情达理地同意了推迟婚礼。

“他当然同意了，”莎莉辛酸地回答，她强调道，“这不是推迟一个星期，或者一个月，或者一年。我永远也不会嫁给他了。她会！”

四

时光飞逝，高岗人家的生活又重归平静，毕竟每天都有日常家事要做，起到了稳定情绪的效果。莎莉·霍尔和达顿保持着断断续续的——非常断断续续的——通信。达顿一直不知道如何理解莎莉在她兄长死去当晚情急之下说出的那些话，便也一直被动地等待着。海伦娜和她的两个孩子还住在高岗，因为她也没有别处可去了，所以达顿觉得自己最好还是回避。

七个月后的一天，达顿同往常一样待在农场里，农场距离国王的欣托克村有二十英里。他收到了海伦娜寄来的一封短信，感谢他之前提出的收养她孩子的好意，她的婆婆当时就已经转告她了，并说她很乐意接受这帮助，让达顿收养她的长子。海伦娜的确需要这么做，因为她的叔叔没给她留下一分钱，而她向住在北部的亲戚们求援也都无果。而且，正如她所说，在欣托克附近也没有什么好学校能送孩子去念书。

在一个明媚的夏日男孩被送来了。莎莉和男孩的母亲把他送到中途的“白马客栈”，这是位于乔克纽顿村的一个很有情调的伊丽莎白时期的古老旅馆[5]；在那里他被交给了达顿的管家，坐上一辆光亮耀眼的轻便弹簧减震马车走了。

他被安排在卡斯特桥镇一所有名的学校走读，学校离达顿的农庄大约三四英里。达顿先教会他骑马，他于是每天骑着他的森林矮种马往返上下学，达顿希望他每天到那知识的源泉探险时都能在里头汲取养分，装满一脑袋带回家。达顿近来常常思绪万千沉默寡言，这孩子的到来让他明显好了不少。

圣诞节学校放寒假了，双方商定安排男孩去母亲那儿度假。出于某种原因，这次旅途跟他来时一样还是分成两个阶段，不过这次没让管家来，而是由达顿亲自带着男孩一起骑马前去。

到了著名的“白马客栈”后，达顿询问霍尔小姐和少霍尔太太是否已如约到达来接小菲利普了。话音刚落，就看到海伦娜独自一人出现在门口。

“要出门时莎莉突然又不肯来了。”她有些支支吾吾地说。

这一次相会差不多明确了这对分离许久的人终于要重修旧好，但是此事并没有立刻开始讨论，而是又拖了一段时间。事实上，莎莉·霍尔通过拒绝与海伦娜同去这一行为已经启动了决定性的第一步。很快，她又推着他们进入了第二步——她给达顿写了这样一封短信：

【亲启】

亲爱的查尔斯，

我同海伦娜同住了这许多时日，朝夕相伴，自然也已知悉了她的过去，尤其是同你相关的部分。我确信在时机恰当时她会很乐意接受你做她的丈夫，而你也应当给予她此机会。你之前信中问我在听到你同她交谈时发脾气（其实并不是）事后是否感到后悔。不，查尔斯，我并不后悔当时说过那些话。

你诚挚的
莎莉·霍尔

既然已经开了头，达顿的心重回到曾留恋过的地方也就只是时间问题了。到了第二年七月，达顿去找他的朋友杰夫斯，告诉他终于可以履行自头一年一月一直推迟至今的婚礼伴郎的职责了。

“绝对没问题，忠贞不渝的好男人！”奶牛场主约翰斯热情地满口答应，“虽然我最近在大热天里头晒干草，皮肤没以前那么白净，显得不够文雅了，但是我一定不会比那些小白脸干得差。感谢上帝，幸好这个世界上还有香水和发油，打扮下看起来就没那么粗糙了。我要好好地恭维她一通。我会跟她说：‘莎莉·霍尔，迟到总比不到好。’”

“不是莎莉，”达顿匆忙说，“是少霍尔太太。”

杰夫斯搞清楚状况之后，脸色马上变了，满是震惊与谴责。“不是莎莉？”他说，“为啥不是莎莉？我简直不敢相信！少霍尔太太！天哪，天哪——你的脑子到哪儿去了？”

达顿简短地解释了一下，但是约翰斯不愿接受。“要是有哪个女人还值得娶的话，那就只有莎莉！”他喊，“你反而还要放手！”

“我觉得我应该可以想娶谁就娶谁吧。”达顿说。

“嗯，”奶牛场主意味深长地扬了扬眉，“这桩婚事太不合适了，查尔斯——真的不合适。要是我这样子干，你肯定会骂我是个该死的北方来的傻瓜，居然被一个花——花——花瓶勾得冲昏了头误入歧途。”

农场主达顿对这言简意赅的评论报以激烈的言辞回应，两个朋友最后不欢而散。约翰斯最终还是没给达顿当伴郎，他断然拒绝了。达顿离开的时候很是遗憾和伤感，而且杰夫斯就快离开此地了，因此两人说的那些反目的话也许永远也没有机会缓和或和解了。

这次会面后不久，达顿就同海伦娜举办了一个简单务实的婚礼，她带着小女儿同儿子团聚了。男孩这时已经把达顿家当成了自己的家。

接下来的几个月，这位农场主度过了一段前所未有的快乐满足的时光。他的生命中曾有所缺憾，如今在人力能及的范围内已得到了完美的弥补。然而很快日子便有些暗流涌动，他的美梦也打上了阴影。海伦娜生性脆弱，不管体力也好道德也好，都缺乏忍耐力。从他最早认识她那会儿——八到十年前——到现在，其间她遭受了重重磨难。简言之，她的爱已燃烧殆尽，现在时不时会自怨自艾一番。她有时候会哀怨地追忆早年过的养尊处优的生活。她不去想现在的生活比起她跟不幸的霍尔在一起时好了多少，却偏要去跟她踏出致命的第一步——与霍尔秘密结婚——之前的生活相比较。她不屑与富有农场主的妻子们通常会打交道的那些人为伍。农家生活的各种琐事在她看来都是令人苦恼的烦琐细节，不愿打理。要不是因为还有两个孩子，达顿的屋子几乎还是跟从前一样黯淡无光。

这些间或的种种不快终于让达顿开始抱怨，觉得他企图重拾旧情以纠正当初爱的偏差的努力最终还是白费了。“也许约翰斯是对的，”他会对自己说，“我应该继续跟莎莉过的。随浪而动见机而行，总好过逆水行舟。”但这些不和谐的想法他只是自己私底下想一想，表面上他依然是个体贴而仁爱的丈夫。

他人生中这一段灰暗的时光过了不到一年半，这些想法便戛然而止了，因为它们所牵涉的那位女子去世了。等她入了土，达顿对她的看法便改观了许多。无论如何，农场有她在还是比没她在强。她不过是一介普通女子，嫁给第一任丈夫后吃了那么多苦，性情变得尖酸一些实属正常。她有时缺乏同理心，时而行为又不可理喻，但底下藏着的是一颗坦诚善良的心，原本她也是个充满了希望与热情的人啊。她人走了，却留下了一个裹在白色襁褓里的红通通的小婴儿。他的全部心思立刻都用在照顾这个可爱的小家伙身上去了。

等到孩子开始蹒跚学步、牙牙学语了，达顿想到了一个可行的计划，很是欢喜。回顾迄今为止他对自己的人生所做的种种试验，他认为自己已经从失败中学会了谨慎、从错误中获得了智慧。

至于他的计划是什么无须深究就能猜到。莎莉·霍尔还同母亲住在欣托克，过着平静的生活，他还有机会纠正错误、改写人生，与她重归于好。海伦娜给一个家庭带来的是哀伤与优雅；而莎莉却会给一个家庭带来欢乐与希望。她不会像海伦娜一般鄙夷农家的质朴生活。而且，她嫁到达顿家还有一个明显的优势，没有谁比她更适合做她兄长的两个孩子以及达顿自己的孩子的继母了——而对莎莉来说，达顿现在也比从前更有可能成为一个好丈夫，因为海伦娜已死，他不会再时不时缅怀一下自己未愈的爱情的伤了。

达顿不是一个想到就做、雷厉风行的人。他的这一补救计划原本很可能会拖上一段时间才执行，但突然一个冬夜到来了，就跟他上一次骑马去欣托克时一模一样，他于是问自己，连周遭的景致都在呼唤他再尝试一次，自己为何还要拖延。

他叫帮工给马备上鞍，穿上讲究的马靴和马刺，打扮得像个小伙子一般，亲了亲最小的两个孩子，然后上路了。他多希望老朋友杰夫斯·约翰斯也在场，这样就可以完美重现上一次的旅程了。唉！可惜约翰斯却不在。他搬到了这个郡的另一头，两人之间的裂痕到现在还没有机会修补。虽然达顿心里已经原谅了他一百次，大概约翰斯也早已原谅了达顿，但现在相隔太远，想要握手言欢的可能性很小了。

虽然没有好友相伴，他还是尽量让自己保持高昂的情绪；他边走边想事情，尽管没有同伴聊天，但也逐渐自得其乐。太阳渐渐西沉，树枝在天幕上逐渐勾勒出其形状，就像是一副蚀刻版画；驼背的老人背着柴火问候“先生，晚上好”，达顿也兴致勃勃地回答“晚上好”。

等他来到那个岔路口的时候，天色就跟当年约翰斯爬上路标那会儿一样暗了。这次达顿没有再走错路。“感谢上天，这次我到了以后也不会再认错人了。”他自言自语地说。一想到这次的求婚跟上一次一样，都是要纠正之前犯下的错误，而不是一时的意乱情迷，他心里就有一种特别的满足感。

这次旅途没有受阻非常顺利，路程似乎还不到上次的一半远。虽然天色很暗，但当大槭树后面霍尔太太家房子的大烟囱出现在他眼帘中时，时间不过傍晚五六点而已。达顿转念一想，又退回来，像上次一样先去了前面路边的客栈歇脚；他对着客栈的镜子仔细修饰了一番，要了点喝的，抚平一下因操劳而开始出现的皱纹，然后快步走向了高岗。

五

那天晚上莎莉正在给挤奶女工们做围裙，她们又添了两位新帮手，霍尔太太和莎莉已经不去挤奶了。不过总的来说她们的家庭生计状况变化不大，房子的外观变化也不大，除了一些小地方，例如那或许已有百年历史的窗上的裂缝，似乎又加宽了一点；而屋子横梁，似乎又变黑了一层；受现代生活品味的影响，她们在原来空空的壁炉角添加了一个格栅；还有黎贝卡，从前头发浓密时总是戴着帽子，现在头发稀疏了却脱掉了帽子，因为她听说现在不时兴戴帽子了。还有莎莉的脸，现在自然多了些阅历、添了些女人味。

霍尔太太正在用火钳夹木炭，就跟原来一模一样。

“五年前的今晚，要是我没记错的话——”她一边说一边放了一块木炭。

“不是今晚——不过应该是这个星期的某一晚。”莎莉的记性从不出错。

“哎，反正差不多啦。五年前达顿先生到这儿来娶你，而我可怜的儿子菲尔到这儿来死在家里。”她叹了口气，“唉，莎莉，”她紧接着说，“如果当初你有点手段的话，达顿先生会娶你的，不管有没有海伦娜。”

“这个没什么好伤感的，妈妈，”莎莉用乞求的语气说，“在这件事上我真的不想耍什么手段。虽然我喜欢他，但我并不是非他不可。加上中间还有这么个结，我绝不能嫁给他，”她态度坚决地补充说，“就算他现在再来找我，我想我也不会答应。”

“我可不敢确定，除非你心里已经有了别人。”

“我不会的，我告诉您是为什么吧。到现在这个年纪，我已经不会为了爱情而结婚了。而且即使我们明天就把奶场给关了，我们也不会缺吃少穿，所以我也不必为了一些更卑微的原因而结婚……我现在已经生活得很开心，这样就够了。”

这话刚说完没多久，外头就传来了轻轻的敲门声，接着黎贝卡进来了，表情就像见了鬼一般。原来这位擅长脱脂及做黄油的能干女工（现在已搬进大屋来住了）开始听到了母女俩的闲聊，接着一开门就看见了达顿先生，这巧合顿时让她觉得毛骨悚然。霍尔太太和莎莉也都一面讶异，一面热情地招呼农场主，但很快他们就无话可说了。

“达顿先生，你可否帮我把壁炉的挂钩往上抬一下？卡口被卡住了。”女主人说。他依言照办，这个自家人一般的小动作一时缓解了他已有四年未曾踏足此地的尴尬和拘束。

霍尔太太很快就看出了他的来意，便起身去为客人准备晚茶，把两位主角留下。眼见莎莉举止温文尔雅，霍尔太太不禁为她刚才断然宣称自己不在乎他而暗暗发笑。等到茶备好了她才出来，觉得达顿看上去似乎没有刚来时那么信心满满；但莎莉看上去倒是很轻松，三人愉快地用过了茶点。

到七点时他起身告辞。霍尔太太一直送他到门前，好让灯照亮他下坡的路。走到门口时，他坦率地告诉她：“我来是向您女儿求婚的；我特意选了这个时辰，做好了各种准备，以为能够得到一个肯定的答复。但是她拒绝了。”

“那她实在太不知好歹了！”霍尔太太重重地说。

达顿停了一下，思考怎么表达，然后问：“我——我想她是不是有别的更中意的人了呢？”

“我说不好到底是有还是没有，”霍尔太太回答，“她有的事会对我保密。不过达顿先生，我肯定支持你。我会跟她谈谈的。”

“谢谢您，谢谢您！”农场主听起来高兴了一些，得到了她的保证后，这次不太圆满的来访便结束了。达顿沿着槭树根走下了斜坡，灯收了回去，门关上了。在斜坡底他差点撞上一个正准备上坡的人。

“在这么黑的晚上，要是个没有知觉的稻草人，恐怕不敢相信自己的眼睛！”一个声音说道。达顿虽然非常意外，但还是马上辨认出了来人。“有可能稻草人不敢，但是我敢相信自己的眼睛！”说话的是杰夫斯·约翰斯。

达顿说虽然这个时间地点不太对，但他还是非常高兴有这个机会让两人摒弃前嫌和好如初，然后问奶牛场主到这儿来做什么。

杰夫斯马上就表现出了他一贯的乐观和自信。“我打算来看看你的——亲戚——我一直都把她们，霍尔太太和莎莉，当成你的亲戚，”他说，“唉，查尔斯，其实是这样的，我发觉打光棍会让一个人越来越像个野蛮人，所以，我打算来这儿接受一点文明的熏陶，因为我觉得你剩下不要的对我来说已经够好喽。”他朝着坡上的大房子方向点了点头。

“你不是要来找莎莉——求婚吧？”达顿问，感觉似乎一盆冰水当头浇来。

“就是，我要用我的个人魅力，加上老天给点运气，争取娶到她。我觉得我应该能成功。我每个星期都要路过这儿——我现在的奶牛场离这儿只有四英里，你晓得吧？我每次都会隔着窗子跟她说几句话。但是今天晚上我是第一次要跟她说正事，是不是有点奇怪？你刚去过她们家？”

“是的，坐了一小会儿。但是她并没有提到你。”

“这是个好迹象，好迹象。现在我下定决心了，我要乘胜追击，按计划今天晚上就要得到她的答复。”

两人又说了几句话，达顿祝愿他的朋友能够成功赢得莎莉芳心，虽然语气听起来略微有些干涩，然后两人便道别了。约翰斯答应会写信来告知详情，接着便沿斜坡而上，消失在大树和房子的阴影中了。一方方形的灯光传来，约翰斯进了屋，一切又重归黑暗。

“幸福的杰夫斯啊！”达顿说，“原来这就是答案！”

他决定当天晚上就回家。一刻钟以后他便出了村，第二天照常劳作，搬运储藏大头菜，就像什么都没发生过一样。

他等了又等，盼着约翰斯写信来告知婚期是否已定下，但是一直没有信来，也没听到任何消息。直到有一天在马匹拍卖会上见到了约翰斯，他喜气洋洋地——至少比他内心的感觉要显得喜气洋洋——问道：“你的大喜日子是哪一天呀？”

出乎意料的是约翰斯并没有回应他的喜气洋洋。“根本没有，”他很小声地说，“事情办砸喽，她不肯嫁给我。”

达顿屏住了呼吸暂停片刻，然后颇为虚伪地安慰说：“你再试试——她可能只是矜持。”

“不是，”约翰斯很肯定地说，“不是这个原因。我们已经直截了当地谈了几十次了。她很直接地跟我说我不适合她。再跟她求婚她就要生气了。唉，查尔斯啊，五年前你放走了她简直就是丢了个宝。”

“确实——确实。”达顿回答。

他从拍卖会回家后，心情又发生了新的变化。他还以为约翰斯是他的对手，原来是完全弄错了。看来他还是有希望可以得到莎莉的。

这一次，因为事务繁忙，达顿只有将此事托付于纸笔传情了。他给她写了一封信，用一个女人能想得到的最具男子气、最直白的方式向她求婚。回信很快就送到了：

亲爱的达顿先生，

我非常明了您是出于何等善意第二次向我提出此事。比我条件更好的女子都会因这份荣幸而引以为傲；我读到过您在卡斯特桥农场主俱乐部上所做的关于甜菜牛饲料及其他类似话题的精彩长篇演讲，真的感到万分荣幸。但是我的回答跟之前一样。我不想费力去解释理由，事实上也很难解释清楚；所以我只能简单地说我必须谢绝同您结婚。

同以往一样祝您一切顺利。

您忠诚的朋友
莎莉·霍尔

信跌落在地上，达顿很是绝望。除了拒绝之外，信里似乎还有一些讽刺的意味在其中——“关于甜菜牛饲料的精彩长篇演讲”读起来很是可疑。不过，讽刺与否，她的回答已经很明确，他必须就此作罢。

于是他便全心投入事务中去以排遣郁闷。近来确实有件事占据了他大部分的心思——最近郡里正在谣传说本地一家银行倒闭，连累他也濒临破产了，他得澄清这个古怪的误会。确实有一个叫达顿的农场主损失惨重，大概是因为两人名字相近，造成了这样的误解。而且很多人都相信了这谣传，所以达顿花了好几天时间四处写信，终于让别人相信他跟原来一样并无负债，这才解决了问题。这件事还在收尾中时，他突然收到了一封莎莉的来信，让他很是高兴。

达顿撕开信封，信很简短：

亲爱的达顿先生，

我们前几天听说您因为XX银行倒闭破产了，非常担忧。现在误会已澄清，我的母亲催促我赶紧给您写信，告诉您我们非常高兴这只是空穴来风。您待我哥哥的两个孩子视若己出，而我无以为报，只能在这种时候写一封信以示关怀。他们两人几天之前都分别给我们来过信。

您诚挚的朋友
莎莉·霍尔

“这个见钱眼开的小女人！”达顿微笑着自言自语，“原来她以为我破产了，所以才拒绝了我啊。”

不过达顿的性格就是这样，几个小时过去后，他再想起这件事就宽宏大量多了，无法再责备莎莉。他问自己希望妻子拥有什么样的品质？爱心与忠诚。除此之外呢？精明世故。那么，不愿意踏上一艘沉船不正是她精明世故的表现吗？而现在她也知道了事情的真相。“管它呢，”他对自己说，“我得再试一次。”

他现在是一颗心全在莎莉身上，而且非莎莉不可，因此决不允许有别的阻挠；他总认为之前不成功是时间不对造成的。

既然上次挑周年纪念去结果不如意，他这次便等到了五月底一个阳光灿烂的日子——这种天气会让所有生命都傻傻地以为自己会永远沐浴在蓝天与阳光之下。他骑马走在长梣树道上时，几乎都认不出来这是他前两个冬日走过的那条道。现在他绝对不会再走错路了，哪怕闭着眼睛也不会。杜鹃的歌声正是最美妙时，不像在四月里还带着踌躇，或是六月时已显出颓势。阳光下爬行动物们就跟壁炉边的猫咪一般温顺迷人。他到达欣托克时已是傍晚，跟上一次到达的时间差不多，但是天色依然大亮，阳光依然明媚，远远地就能看清高岗。他看到莎莉在花园里，心顿时一阵颤抖。他第一想法是先去客栈，但他又对自己说：“不，我就把马拴在花园门前。如果一切顺利，我很快就可以把它牵进去。如果不顺，我就马上骑马离开。”

骑手高高的影子使得屋内变暗了，坐在里面的霍尔太太吃了一惊。他是从一条侧道骑马上斜坡来的，一般很少有人骑马走这条路。几秒钟以后他便进了花园来到莎莉身边。

五分钟——唉，也许只有三分钟——在那排蜂箱后面这桩事情就了结了。虽然春光正明媚，蓝天美得令人心醉，但达顿还是没能如愿。“不，”莎莉非常坚决地说，“达顿先生，我永远，永远都不会嫁给您的。我——曾经很乐意，但是现在我永远都不能了。”

“可是——”达顿乞求地说，他突然变得能说会道，滔滔不绝地描述他愿意为她做的一切。他会每周赶着马车带她回来看望母亲——带她去伦敦——给她一大笔钱——他简直是想尽了各种办法来承诺、哄劝和诱导她。但是全都无济于事。她用一个实实在在的“不”字插进来，结束了他的一番辩解，就像是大路上的铁门轰然关上了一般。达顿停了下来。

“所以，”他简短地问，“你上次拒绝我时并没有听说我要破产的传闻？”

“没有。”她说，“你以为我会因为这样的原因拒绝你，这好像更于事无补。”

“也不是因为几年前我轻慢了你让你记恨？”

“不是。那点记恨早就过去了。”

“啊——那你一定是鄙视我了，莎莉！”

“不，”她缓缓地回答，“我并没有鄙视你。的确，我不再像从前一样视你为英雄，但也只是这样了。真实的原因是，我自己一个人过得就很开心，我压根儿就没打算要跟任何人结婚。现在，我能否请您帮我个忙呢，先生？”她说话时的神态真是难以言喻地令人心动神迷，往后每次达顿一想起来，都禁不住咒骂自己当初愚蠢，如今只得一辈子后悔。

“请尽管吩咐。”

“请你以后再也不要跟我提起这件事了。只要你愿意，我们可以永远是朋友，但是永远也不会是爱人和夫妻。”

“我再也不会了，”达顿说，“就算活到一百岁也不会了。”

他的确再没有提起。他很清楚她的芳心里已经没有自己的位置了。

等到他的养子养女成人，各自成家立业后，达顿同霍尔一家的通信彻底中断了。许多年后，一个偶然的机会，他听人说起莎莉，她因为个人魅力招来好些个求婚者，但她全都拒绝了，一直坚守着她独身的决定。

一八八四年五月

[1]斯克里米尔是北欧神话中的一名巨人。

[2]查尔斯的昵称。

[3]原文此处未用约翰斯而是用他的名——杰夫斯，换称呼的用意是表明闲聊增进了感情，所以称呼从姓变成了名。

[4]英语谚语“A watched pots never boils”，直译为“眼望着锅锅不开”，意即越是心急越办不了事。

[5]哈代原文注释：“该客栈已经被拆除，原址上现在建了一间红砖墙的现代旅馆（一九一二年）——托马斯·哈代。”

乡村旧闻

引子

这是一个礼拜六的下午，正值金秋，天色湛蓝；地点是在一个有名的集市小镇的正街。一辆高大的驿站马车停在“白鹿客栈”前面方方正正的广场上，宽大的顶篷侧面写着几个饱经风雨已有些模糊的字：“博森，往朗普多村”。在这一带有许多这样的客运马车，虽然速度迟缓，但颇为体面，所以广受那些收入不多的正经旅客的青睐。高档一些的大约等同于法国老式的“迪利昂斯”——一种四轮公共马车。

这辆马车定于下午四点准时发车出镇，现在正街最高处塔楼上的时钟显示已到三点半。不一会儿，几个商店的跑腿差役背着大包小包来了，把包裹扔进车里便算完事，然后转身吹着口哨走了。差二十分钟四点，一位年长的妇人来了，把提篮放在车辕上，慢慢爬上车，找了个靠里的座位坐下，双手抄起、双唇紧闭。她已经为本次旅途占好了座位，虽然这会儿既不见拉车的马，也不见车夫本人。到了三刻钟时，又有两个妇人来了，车里头先上来的那位认出一个是上朗普多村租车行的女老板，另一个是书记员的太太。她们也认出了她是同村杂货店年长的女店主。差五分钟四点，那边走过来的是小学校长普罗菲特先生，戴着一顶绒毡帽；还有高级茅屋匠克里斯托弗·屯克；四点的钟声敲响时，又有几位乘客匆匆赶到：教堂执事及太太、种子商和他的书记员老父亲；还有一位不被外界赏识的本地风景画家德先生。他年事已高，一直居住在故乡，作品从未在家乡以外的地方出售过一幅。不过他的同村乡邻都以高尚的行为支持他对艺术的自命不凡，他们对他的天才抱有的信心简直就跟外界对他才华的忽视一样令人惊叹。因此，他的画作在本乡里广为流传（一幅画卖价几个先令，这个不假）[1]，几乎全教区每家每户墙上都挂着三四幅众人仰慕的德先生的大作。

车夫博森这会儿正在车前车后忙碌。马已经套上轭，车夫整理好缰绳，跳上座位，似乎这套活他已经很熟了一样——事实上他的确很熟。

“所有人都到齐了吧？”准备出发前，他对着身后车厢里的乘客扬声问。

那些没到的人自然没有回答，于是他便认定集合完毕。经过一番吱吱呀呀之后连车带人便上路了。马车一路缓慢向前来到了一座桥前，这是市镇的边缘了。车夫突然停住了马车。

“我的老天爷！”他说，“我把副牧师给忘了！”

车厢里所有能从后窗向外望的乘客都抬眼望了望，但是没有看到副牧师的身影。

“不知道他现在人到哪儿了？”车夫又说。

“可怜的人，他都这把年纪了应该得到圣职才对。”[2]

“他应该要守时才对，”车夫说，“我跟他说咯，‘四点整我就要出发。’他自己说，‘我会准时到。’结果他没来。作为一个正儿八经的老教会牧师他应该说话算话才对嘛。福莱克斯顿先生可能晓得他做啥去了，你们两个是同行？”他转头问教堂执事。

“的确，半个小时以前我还跟他谈了好多事，”教会职员回答，大家都认为他同另外那位神职人员应当关系亲密，这也的确不假，“但是他没说他会迟到。”

这时马车的转角突然出现了两束光，打断了大家的讨论，那是副牧师眼镜片的反光。紧随其后出现的是他的脸和几缕白色的腮须，再接着是他随风飘摇的寒碜的长袍后摆。没人责备他，因为大家都看得出来他已经够自责了。他上气不接下气地上了车，找座位坐下。

“现在我们都到齐了吧？”车夫又问。他们第二次起步了，往前走到出了镇差不多三百码的地方，几乎快到第二座桥了。当地人都知道过了桥之后路就拐弯了，打这儿开始大路上的行人车辆就将彻底消失在小镇居民的眼帘中了。

“哎哟，我肯定没看错！”租车行的女老板在车厢里喊出来，她正从方形的小后窗望向市镇的方向。

“咋了？”车夫问。

“有人在向我们招手！”

车又猛地停下来。“还有人？”车夫问。

“是的，真的！”所有人默默等待着，能向外看的则伸着头向外看。

“这次又是哪个哟？”博森接着说，“我就跟你们说，乡亲们，啥人会这样拖拖拉拉耽误时间？我们不是都坐满了吗？这个人到底又是哪个哟？”

“看上去像是个绅士。”小学校长说，他的位置比其他人的更容易看清外面的路况。

招呼马车的陌生人之前一直举着伞吸引他们的注意力，现在看到自己已成功把马车叫停，便颇为从容地走上前来。他的穿着肯定不是本地样式，虽然也说不出来具体哪里不一样。他左手拿着一个小旅行皮包。他一赶上马车便迅速瞟了一眼侧面的字，似乎是要确认一下他招呼的马车没错，然后问车上还有没有空位。

车夫回答说虽然车上人已经很多了，但再多一个应该还装得下，于是陌生人上了车，大家给他腾出了一个位置。驮马们再次抬脚，这次终于不用半路再停下来了，摇摇晃晃拉着共计十四个人上路了。

“先生，你不是这个地方的人吧？”车夫问，“我一看你就晓得咯。”

“不，我就是这个地方的人。”陌生人回答。

“噢？哦。”

接下来的沉默似乎暗示了他颇为怀疑陌生人声明的真实性。“我是说上朗普多，”车夫大着胆子继续说，“我觉得我差不多认得村子里头所有的人。”

“我就在朗普多出生，在朗普多长大，我的父亲和祖父也是。”乘客平静地回答。

“呀，真的呀！”年长的杂货店女老板在后面开口了，“这个不会是约翰·拉克兰的儿子吧——不可能——也不可能是三十五年前带着老婆孩子去了国外的拉克兰本人——但是——我听到的声音——明明就是他父亲的声音呢！”

“就是他，”陌生人回答，“约翰·拉克兰是我的父亲，我就是约翰·拉克兰的儿子。三十五年前，我才十一岁大，我父母带着我和妹妹一起移民到海外去了。走的那天，凯茨家的小子托尼赶车，一大早把我们和行李送到卡斯特桥镇。他是朗普多村里我见到的最后一个人。我们那个星期就坐船漂洋过海去了国外，一直待在那里，我也是从那儿回来的——把另外三人都留在了那边。”

“他们是活着还是死了？”

“死了，”他低声回答，“我现在回到老家，心里头想着——不过还没有决定，只是计划——一两年以后回这儿来，就在这里过完下半生。”

“你成家了吧，拉克兰先生？”

“还没有。”

“你这些年过得还好吧，先生——或者我就叫你约翰吧，你打小我就认识你了。我们都经常听说那几个新国家很有钱，你跟其他人一样在那儿也发财了吧？”

“我并不是很有钱，”拉克兰先生说，“就算是在新的地方，你知道，也总有失败者。比赛不一定总是跑得快的一方赢，打仗也不一定总是兵力强的一方胜。就算有时候是，你也很可能是那个既不快又不强的。不过，先不说我的事了。我回答了你们的问题，现在该轮到你们回答我的问题啦。我现在住在伦敦，来这儿纯粹是想看看朗普多现在变成什么样子了，还有哪些人住在这儿。所以我没有雇一辆马车自己过去，而是更想跟你们一起坐车去。”

“哦，说起朗普多，我们反正都差不多，一样过日子咯。可以说，老一辈的人慢慢就不在了，年轻一辈慢慢又长起来了。你刚才提到，托尼·凯茨在你们走的那天赶着他父亲的马车把你们一家连人带行李送到卡斯特桥镇。我想托尼现在应该还在世，但是不住在朗普多了。他结婚以后就搬走了，住在梅尔斯托克附近的卢门。哎哟，托尼这个人可真是！”

“我认识他那会儿，他的德行还没怎么显露出来。”

“是呀。不过说起德行，他倒也不算坏——除了在女人这一方面。我是不会忘记他的恋爱史哩——永远也忘不掉！”

新回故乡的人静静等待着下文，于是车夫就继续往下说。

花心情圣托尼·凯茨

“我是不会忘记托尼的脸的。那张脸小小的、圆圆的，绷得紧紧的，因为出过天花，所以脸上这儿那儿有一些印迹，但是不至于影响他在姑娘们心中的帅气形象，虽然他小的时候这些痕迹相当严重。他看上去严肃得不得了，从来不会笑，这个小伙子，感觉就像笑一下良心就会痛。他跟你说话的时候，总喜欢盯着你眼睛里头的小光斑看。而且托尼·凯茨的脸上一根胡子都没有，就跟我的手掌一样光溜溜的。他原来还喜欢唱《裁缝的裤子》那首歌，态度还虔诚得很，简直跟唱赞美诗一样——

哎，脱下了你的衬裙来呀，穿上了裁缝的裤子。[3]

还有其他那些乱七八糟的歌。姑娘们都喜欢他，他也来者不拒全部都喜欢。

“但是到了后来托尼慢慢就选定了一个，米莉·理查兹——一个娇小玲珑、温柔漂亮的姑娘。很快就听说他们订婚了。一个礼拜六，他去了趟集市帮他父亲办事，下午赶着马车回家。他来到山脚下——再过十分钟我们就会走到那座山啦——发现山顶上有个人在等他，不是别人，正是尤丽蒂·沙勒，一个漂亮姑娘，他在跟米莉订婚前曾经有一段时间对她很有感觉。

“托尼一走近，尤丽蒂就说：‘亲爱的托尼，能不能搭我回家呀？’

“‘当然了，亲爱的，’托尼说，‘你以为我会忍心拒绝你吗？’

“她微微一笑，跳上了车，然后托尼继续前进。

“‘托尼，’她说，语气里带着温柔的责怪，‘你为啥为了她把我抛弃了？她哪一点比我好嘛？我绝对比她更适合当老婆，而且比她对你更好。一追就到手的女子肯定不是最好的。你想一下，我们都认识好多年了——差不多算是从小就认识了——对不对，托尼？’

“‘是啊，确实是。’托尼回答，似乎被这话里的真相深深打动了。

“‘而且我也没有啥缺点让你觉得不满意吧，有没有，托尼？你给我说老实话。’

“‘没有，我发誓。’托尼说。

“‘而且——难道你觉得我不够好看，托尼？你看看我。’

“他的眼睛在她脸上停了好久。‘绝对没有，’他说，‘说真心话，我觉得你今天比任何时候都要好看！’

“‘比她更好看吗？’

“托尼会咋回答没人晓得，因为他还没来得及开口，就看见前面路上拐弯处的树篱那边有一根他非常熟悉的羽毛——是米莉的帽子上头的羽毛——他之前正打算跟米莉商量要在那个星期去教堂发布结婚告示。

“‘尤丽蒂，’托尼用最温柔的声音说，‘我看到米莉来了。要是让她看到你坐在我旁边，我就要倒霉了。如果你现在下车，她等下拐个弯过来，看到你站在路上，肯定就猜到我们是一起来的。唉，我最亲爱的尤丽蒂，为了避免不必要的麻烦，我想你跟我一样都受不了这种麻烦，所以你能不能躺到马车后头去，让我用油布把你盖起来，等到米莉过去了再出来？只要一分钟就搞定了。求你了！——我会仔细想一下我们刚才说的话，说不定我最后会决定不是向米莉，而是向你提出那个爱的问题。我跟她其实还没最后定下来嘞。’

“哎，于是尤丽蒂·沙勒同意了，躺到了马车后头，托尼把她盖了起来，这样马车看上去就像是空的，只有一些松松的防雨的油布。然后托尼就继续赶车，迎上了米莉。

“‘我亲爱的托尼！’米莉看着他走近，噘起小嘴抬头看他，‘你回家咋花了这么长时间呀！简直就跟上朗普多没有我这个人一样！而我还乖乖地听你的话，到这儿来等你，跟你一起坐车回去，还要讨论我们未来新家的事情——因为你求我，我又答应了你。不然我才不会来呢，托尼先生！’

“‘对哟，亲爱的，确实是我让你——我现在想起来了——我刚才都忘了。你刚才说要跟我一起坐车回去是吧，亲爱的米莉？’

“‘当然了！不然我要咋办？你不可能让我走路回去吧，我都已经走到这儿来了？’

“‘哦不，不，当然不！我只是在想你有可能想去镇上跟你妈妈碰头。我在那儿看到她了——她看上去好像在等你一样。’

“‘没有啊，她已经回家了。她是从田里头走的，所以比你还早到。’

“‘哦！这个我还真不晓得。’托尼说。无奈之下，他只得扶着她上车，让她坐到他身旁。

“他们俩一路愉快地聊天，看花看树看鸟看虫，看田间农民犁地，直到托尼看到了前面路旁的一座屋子，有个姑娘从楼上的窗户往外眺望，正是汉娜·乔里佛，当地的另一个美人儿，也是托尼的初恋情人——早在米莉和尤丽蒂之前，其实他本来差点就要跟她结婚的。她比米莉·理查兹更为时髦和迷人，但是托尼最近差不多已经把她抛在脑后了。汉娜所在的那屋子是她姨妈的。

“‘我亲爱的米莉——我未来的老婆，我应该可以这样叫你，’托尼低声下气地说，声音不大，尽量不让尤丽蒂听到，‘我看到有个年轻女人在窗边打望，我估计她可能会跟我搭话。其实是这样的，米莉，她原来以为我想跟她结婚，结果现在她发觉我要娶别人，而且还比她漂亮，我很怕她要是看到我们两个在一起，可能会大发雷霆。米莉，你能不能帮我个忙——我未来的老婆，我应该可以这样叫你吧？’

“‘当然可以啦，最亲爱的托尼。’她说。

“‘那你能不能爬到车厢前头的油布底下，躲在里面，等我们走过房子以后再出来？她现在还没有看到我们。你想，现在快到圣诞节了，我们应该要过个和平祥和的节日，这样做可以避免惹起怒火大动干戈，我们一直都应该这样过日子。’

“‘为了让你高兴，那我就听你的吧，托尼。’米莉说。虽然她其实并不情愿，但还是钻到了油布底下，伏身蹲在座位的后面，而尤丽蒂则躲在车厢的另一头。马车继续前行，来到了路边的农舍前。汉娜已经看到了他，在窗前等待着，低着头看他。她带着傲慢的微笑鄙夷地甩了甩头。

“‘喂，你是不是应该更有风度一点，问下我要不要搭你的车回家？’她看到他点头微笑了一下之后就打算走，便开口问道。

“‘噢，对哟！我刚才在想啥呢？’托尼不安地说，‘但是你看上去好像还想在你姨妈家多待一阵？’

“‘不，我没有这个打算。’她说，‘你没看到我都已经戴上帽子穿好外套了吗？我只是在回家的路上进来看一看她而已。你咋这么笨呢，托尼？’

“‘这个样子啊——噢——那你肯定应该搭我的车走咯。’托尼说，感觉衣服底下起了一层薄薄的汗。他勒住缰绳，等她下楼来，扶她坐到他旁边，然后继续打马赶路。他的脸已经拉到了一张圆脸所能拉到的最长的长度。

“汉娜转过头，从侧面盯着他的眼睛。‘托尼，这感觉不错吧？我喜欢跟你一起坐车。’

“托尼转头回望着她，过了一阵后回答：‘我也喜欢跟你一起。’总之，看到她之后，他又热血沸腾了。越看她就越喜欢，到后来他自己都想不通有汉娜·乔里佛在，他为什么还会跟米莉或者尤丽蒂提结婚的事。于是两人坐得越来越近，脚一起踩着踏板，肩膀挨挨挤挤，托尼心里翻来覆去想的就是汉娜真是太漂亮了。他说话的声音越来越温柔，到最后就跟耳语一样喊她‘亲爱的汉娜’。

“‘我估计你现在已经跟米莉定下来了吧。’她说。

“‘不——不，还没有完全定下来。’

“‘什么？托尼，你说话好小声呀。’

“‘对——我嗓子有点哑。我说，还没有完全定下来。’

“‘我猜你是打算要定下来了吧？’

“‘嗯，说到这个问题——’他的眼睛盯着她的脸，她也盯着他。他问自己当初咋会这么蠢放弃了汉娜。‘我的汉娜宝贝！’他情不自禁抓住了她的手，完全忘了米莉和尤丽蒂以及所有其他的事情，脱口而出，‘定下来？我并没有打算定下来！’

“‘快听！’汉娜说。

“‘听啥？’托尼放开了她的手，问道。

“‘我刚才听到那个油布底下有尖叫声传出来，哎呀，你车上原来装的是玉米，肯定是车上有老鼠，我敢说！’她赶紧把长裙的裙脚往上拉。

“‘不不，是车的轮轴，’托尼用肯定的语气说，‘天气干燥时它有时候就会这样响。’

“‘可能吧……那，亲爱的托尼，你现在老实给我说，你是喜欢她还是喜欢我？因为——因为，虽然我一直做出一副独立的样子，但我最后还是要承认我确实很喜欢你，托尼。要是你向我提出——你懂的嘛，我应该不会拒绝你的。’

“托尼刚回头看了一眼后面的车厢，汉娜一直都跟后面的两位完全不同（她有时候过于矜持保守，不知道你们还记不记得），现在居然这么主动，立刻便赢得了他的心。他于是柔声低语说：‘我还没有答应她哩，我想我应该可以解决掉她，然后跟你提出你刚才说的那个问题。’

“‘你要把米莉甩了？——为了跟我结婚！我太开心咯！’汉娜又惊又喜，大声喊了出来，还开心地拍手。

“话音未落，又传来一声尖叫——一声愤怒、怨恨的尖叫，然后是长长的呜咽声，像是心碎欲绝的声音，接着车厢里的油布动了一下。

“‘那儿有东西！’汉娜吃了一惊。

“‘没啥东西，真的，’托尼用宽慰的声音说，同时在心里祈祷能找个脱身之计，‘我刚开始没跟你说，因为我怕吓到你。其实，汉娜，我在那底下放了个袋子，里面装了几只鼬鼠，用来逮兔子，它们有时候会打架。我不想让别人晓得，怕别人说我偷猎。哦，别怕，它们跑不出来！——你很安全。那个——那个——汉娜，今天天气很不错啊，对这个季节来说，是不是？你下周六是不是要去集市？你姨妈现在身体还好吧？’托尼不停地东拉西扯，免得她继续谈感情的事，又被米莉听到。

“但是他发现他的努力又白费了，只得又开始寻思怎样才能从这个烂摊子里头脱身，并四下里张望，寻找机会。快到家的时候他看到他父亲在不远处的田里举手示意，好像想要跟他说话。

“‘汉娜，你能不能帮我拉一下马缰？’他大大松了口气，说，‘我要过去看一下我爸想做啥。’

“她答应了，他于是飞快地朝田间跑去，很高兴终于可以喘口气了。他发觉他父亲非常严厉地看着他。

“‘哎，哎，托尼，’一等到儿子站在旁边，老凯茨先生就马上说，‘你晓不晓得，你这个样子可不行！’

“‘啥不行？’托尼说。

“‘啥不行？你打算要娶米莉·理查兹，那你就赶快娶，娶了就算完了，你不能又跟乔里佛家的姑娘赶个车满乡里头逛，惹别人闲话！我可不能让你这样子干。’

“‘我只是邀请她——其实是她要求我——让她搭车回来的。’

“‘她？嗨，听着，如果是米莉，那这样很正常；但是你和汉娜·乔里佛单独走动——’

“‘爸，米莉也在那儿。’

“‘米莉？在哪儿？’

“‘在油布底下！哎呀，爸，是这个样子的，我怕是给自己下了个套喽！尤丽蒂·沙勒也在那儿——是的，就在油布另一头的底下。她们三个都在车上，现在咋办我也不晓得了。我觉得，最好的办法就只有当着她们的面对其中一个明明白白地求婚，然后就算解决了，当然她们几个肯定免不了是要吵翻天的了。爸，要是你是我的话，你会娶哪一个？’

“‘我会娶没主动要求搭你车的那个。’

“‘那就只有米莉了，我不得不承认，是我先邀请她她才上来的。但是米莉——’

“‘那你就继续跟米莉好，她才是最好的……糟了，你快看！’

“他父亲指着马车，‘她拉不住那匹马！你就不应该把马缰交给她的。赶快跑过去把马头拉住，不然那几个女娃儿要出事！’

“尽管汉娜用力拉缰绳，但托尼的马已经开始自己快步走起来了，因为它在外头跑了一整天，很想赶快回马厩去。托尼来不及多说，立刻冲上去追马。

“话说，在所有让他放弃米莉的理由里头，没有哪一条比他父亲推荐米莉更有说服力了。于是他决定绝对不选米莉。既然不能三个都娶，那他就娶汉娜吧。他一边追马车一边心里头盘算好了，没想到这会儿车厢里头发生了意想不到的事。

“刚才在油布下发出尖叫的当然是米莉，她只有通过这样的方式发泄听到托尼说的话所产生的悲愤和耻辱。但是自尊心让她不敢露面，怕被人发现她躲在后面遭耻笑。她越来越焦躁不安，左扭右扭的时候突然发现她头边有一只穿着白色长袜的女人的脚。她吓坏了，因为不晓得尤丽蒂·沙勒也在车里头。但是等恐惧过了以后她决定要把事情搞明白，于是就沿着车厢爬呀爬，躲在油布底下看起来简直跟条蛇一样；然后突然，哎哟，她就跟尤丽蒂面对面喽。

“‘好哇，真是够不要脸的！’米莉愤怒地低声对尤丽蒂说。

“‘确实不要脸，看到你这个样子躲在人家小伙子的车里头，你们两个都不是好东西！’尤丽蒂说。

“‘你给我把嘴巴放干净点！’米莉说，拔高了嗓门，‘我是正儿八经跟他订了婚的，我当然有权利在这儿！我倒是想问，你是凭啥在这儿？他又对你有啥承诺？估计就是一堆花言巧语！但是他跟其他女人说的话不过就是一阵风，我才不会放在心上嘞！’

“‘你不要太自以为是！’尤丽蒂说，‘人家要娶的是汉娜，不是你，也不是我，我都听到喽！’

“结果，汉娜听到油布底下发出来的这些古怪声音，大惊失色，吓得简直要昏过去了。马正好在这个时候开始自己动起来。汉娜拼命扯缰绳，自己都不晓得自己在做啥。等到后面两个越吵越大声，她吓得直接就松手了。马开始自己小跑起来，来到了一个弯道前面，我们就是在那个地方拐弯然后下山去下朗普多村。结果马拐弯拐得太急了，右边的车轮压上了路的边坡，车厢就朝一边歪了，越来越倾斜，然后三个姑娘就都滚下了车掉在路上叠成一堆。

“等托尼给吓得魂飞魄散、气喘吁吁地赶上来的时候，看到三个心爱的姑娘除了被路边树篱上的刺挂了几道之外，都没有受太大的伤，总算放心了。但听到三人吵成一团，他又头大了。

“‘别吵了，各位亲爱的——别吵了！’他边说边脱帽致意。他还差点想挨个亲一下以示公平，但是她们情绪过于激动，不肯让他亲，又吵又闹又哭又叫，直到筋疲力尽才停下来。

“‘现在，我就实话实说吧，因为我也应该说实话，’托尼终于等到她们能听自己说话的机会了，赶紧说，‘事实就是，我已经向汉娜求婚了，她也同意了，所以我们打算把结婚启事在下个——’

“托尼没留意到汉娜的父亲从他背后走过来，也没注意到汉娜的脸被刺划破开始流血了。汉娜看到了父亲，于是朝他跑过去，哭得更厉害了。

“‘我女儿不同意，先生。’乔里佛先生怒火朝天、语气强硬地说，‘汉娜，你同不同意？只要你贞操还在、没啥后患的话，你就给我有点骨气拒绝他！’

“‘我没有碰过她，我敢对天起誓！’托尼勃然大怒，‘说到这个问题，其他两个也一样，虽然你可能以为我是个随便的人！’

“‘我有骨气，我就是要拒绝他！’汉娜说，一来是因为她父亲在场，二来是因为发现事情的真相，而且脸还被划破了，一时间闹脾气，‘我刚才对他好是因为我没想到他居然是这样一个虚伪的大骗子！’

“‘汉娜，你说啥？你不肯嫁给我了？’托尼惊讶得下巴都掉了，跟个死人一样。

“‘我才不嫁给你，我宁愿嫁——嫁给空气！’她喘着气说，心都提到了嗓子眼儿里头，因为其实要是托尼私底下悄悄背着她父亲向她求婚，而且她脸也没被刺划破的话，她是肯定不会拒绝他的。她说完后就挽着她父亲的手臂走了，心里头希望托尼改天再来向她求婚。

“托尼接下来不晓得该说啥了。米莉正在伤心欲绝地哭泣，但是因为托尼的父亲强烈推荐米莉，所以他反而偏不愿意就范。他于是又转向尤丽蒂。

“‘那么亲爱的尤丽蒂，你愿不愿意嫁给我呢？’他问。

“‘捡别人不要的？想得美！’尤丽蒂说，‘我才瞧不上！’说完尤丽蒂·沙勒也大步走了，虽然走了一段路之后她回头望了望，看他有没有追上来。

“于是最后就只剩下米莉和托尼两个人，米莉哭得眼泪都快成河了，而托尼看上去就跟遭雷劈过的树一样。

“‘哎呀，米莉，’他最后终于开口了，朝她走过去，‘看来我们两个是命中注定要在一起，其他人都不行。那我们就听天由命算了。米莉，你觉得呢？’

“‘只要你愿意就行，托尼。你跟她们说的那些话不是当真的吧？’

“‘没一个字是真的！’托尼捏起一只拳头锤在另一只手掌上，斩钉截铁地说。

“然后他就亲了亲她，把马车扶正，两个人又爬上了车。下一个礼拜天他们就在教堂张贴了结婚启事。我当时没去参加他们的婚礼，但听说婚礼后的舞会简直是空前绝后，几乎整个朗普多村的人都到场了，我记得你当时也去了是不是，福莱克斯顿先生？”讲故事的人转头问教堂执事。

“是的，我也去了。”福莱克斯顿先生说，“而且那场舞会还很奇特地扭转了另外几个人的命运；我是指史蒂夫·哈德康姆和他的表弟詹姆斯。”

“啊，是哈德康姆家的，”拉克兰先生说，“这个名字很熟悉！他们怎么了？”

执事清了清嗓子，开始了他的故事。

哈德康姆兄弟交换伴侣

“是的，托尼的婚礼舞会确实是我参加过的最棒的一次。你知道，作为教会职员，我有幸能出席所有的洗礼命名、婚礼以及葬礼后的舞会——这是我们威塞克斯的习俗——所以我参加过许许多多场舞会。

“他们的婚礼舞会是在圣诞周的一个落霜的晚上举办的，应邀参加的人里头就有刚才提到的住在克里默斯顿的哈德康姆家的两个表兄弟——史蒂夫和詹姆斯。两人都是小农场主，刚刚开始自立门户经营农场。跟他们一起来的当然还有他们的未婚妻，住在附近的两位年轻姑娘，两人都漂亮又活泼。应邀来的还有从阿伯茨-塞耐尔、威瑟伯里和梅尔斯托克以及其他不知哪儿来的一些朋友——总之满满一屋子的人。

“为了方便大家跳舞，厨房的家具都被搬走了。年纪大的老人家们在客厅里玩‘普特’和‘全四’纸牌游戏，但后来也不玩儿了，加入了跳舞的行列。跳舞列队的队头排在房间里前头的大窗边，因为人太多，队尾一直出了后门排到了没点灯的外屋。事实上，你根本都看不到头，所以大家都说不清楚到底跳舞的队伍有多长，因为最末尾的一对都被外屋的柴火和树枝堆给挡住了。

“大家跳了几个小时，男人里个子高的因为头顶不时撞到天花板上的横梁，都肿起包了。首席小提琴手把琴弓一扔，说他不想再拉了，因为他也想跳舞。一个小时以后，第二提琴手也放下琴弓说要跳舞。于是只剩下了第三提琴手，他是个退伍士兵，年纪已经很大了，手腕也没什么劲儿。不过，他还是一直坚持拉出很微弱的曲子，但是屋里没有椅子，他的膝盖跟手腕一样没有力气，于是只好挤坐在墙角碗柜上方钉在墙上的一个小角几上，对一个年纪这么大的人来说，这个座位实在不怎么宽敞。

“那些跳得最欢几乎没歇过的人里头就有那两对订了婚的情侣，这对他们来说也很正常。每一对都非常登对，而且跟另一对很不一样。詹姆斯·哈德康姆的未婚妻名叫艾米丽·达诗，她和詹姆斯都是温和、善良、居家的类型，喜欢过宁静的小日子。史蒂夫和他选的爱人奥莉芙·鲍尔则完全不同，他们俩都是急性子，中意寻欢作乐，喜欢新鲜事物。两对人安排好了要在同一天结婚，婚期就在不久之后。参加托尼的婚礼对他们来说就像给他们打了兴奋剂一样，当然这种情况很常见——我在我的职业生涯中已经见过很多次了。

“他们跳舞的意愿真是无比强烈，只有恋爱到了那个阶段的年轻人才会有这样的热情。随着夜色来临，詹姆斯的舞伴碰巧换成了史蒂夫的订婚对象奥莉芙。与此同时史蒂夫正在同詹姆斯的未婚妻艾米丽跳舞。大家发现虽然交换了舞伴，但是两个年轻小伙子享受舞蹈的热忱依然未减。到后来，他们跟交换过的舞伴又开始了下一支舞，虽然一开始他们都严格地同另一位的未婚妻保持着半臂长的距离，生怕离得近了会引起那位女士的正当伴侣的反对，但是随着时间的推移，他们便越靠越近，再过一阵，又越靠越近。

“越往后，表兄弟俩跟属于另一个人的那位年轻姑娘跳得越久，在带着她旋转时便将她搂得越紧。而且，令人惊奇的是两人似乎都并不介意对方这样做。舞会到了快结束的时间，我是最早离开的人之一，因为我第二天一大早还有事要做，所以后面的情形我就没看见了。不过我从其他知情人那里听说了后来的事。

“在跟交换的舞伴，就像我刚提到的，跳过了一场异常热情洋溢的舞之后，两个年轻人相互看了看，过了一会儿一起出了屋，走到了门廊下。

“‘詹姆斯，’史蒂夫说，‘你跟我的奥莉芙跳舞的时候在想些什么？’

“‘嗯，’詹姆斯说，‘大概跟你和我的艾米丽跳舞的时候想的差不多吧。’

“‘我在想，’史蒂夫犹豫了一下，说，‘我不介意我们永远交换下去！’

“‘我当时也是这样觉得的。’詹姆斯说。

“‘我非常愿意，如果你觉得我们俩能搞定的话。’

“‘我也没问题。但是姑娘们会怎么说呢？’

“‘我个人觉得，’史蒂夫说，‘她们应该也不会很反对。刚才你的艾米丽紧紧依偎着我，简直就跟已经是我的人了一样，这亲爱的姑娘。’

“‘你的奥莉芙也是紧紧靠着我，’詹姆斯说，‘我都能感觉到她的心跳，像时钟摆动一般。’

“于是，兄弟俩就同意等到四个人走路回家时把这个问题向两位姑娘提出来。然后他们就真的提了。等到他们当晚分开时，这交换便决定了——大家都还被那一晚热舞的兴奋劲儿笼罩着。在下一个礼拜天的早晨，大家坐在教堂里张着嘴等着听牧师宣读两对新人的结婚启事，期待着听到意料中的名字的时候，发现名字配对弄反了，不禁大为诧异。人们窃窃私语，以为是牧师搞错了，最后发现他并没有念错。既然他们这样决定了，他们也就这样结婚了，都娶了原本属于另一个人的那一位。

“话说，这两对人就这么平平常常地过了一两年小日子，然后对各自配偶的热情便慢慢冷淡下去，这当然是所有婚姻的普遍规律。两个表兄弟开始在心底寻思，当初到底中了什么邪，居然在最后一刻交换了结婚对象，本来他们可以跟上天注定的、自己当初爱上的那个人结婚的。很明显，是托尼的婚礼舞会搞的鬼，他们真希望自己当初没去参加。詹姆斯是个安静、喜欢坐在壁炉边阅读的人，他有时觉得自己跟妻子奥莉芙之间隔着一条鸿沟——奥莉芙非常喜欢骑马、坐车和户外旅行。而总是四处跑来跑去的史蒂夫却有个非常居家的妻子，成天做刺绣啊，织壁炉地毯啊，连大门都不想出，跟他一起赶车出门纯粹是为了让他高兴。

“不过，他们俩很少跟熟人谈论这错误的搭配，虽然有时候史蒂夫会看着詹姆斯的妻子叹息，而詹姆斯也会看着史蒂夫的妻子叹息。事实上，这两个男人到最后彼此都很坦白，不介意私底下提起这事。两人说起来就会苦着脸，黯然微笑，一副不解的神情，再一起摇头，感叹他们居然为了一小时的舞会中的心猿意马便轻易否定了一个深思熟虑的选择。当然，他们都是理智而诚实的年轻人，既然已经如此安排，也就尽力将就下去，而不是成天对已经不能改变和弥补的现状抱怨不止。

“日子就这样过下去，直到一个晴朗的夏日，两家一起每年一度的短途出游，这是他们很久以来一直保持的惯例。这一次他们选了巴德茅斯-里吉斯作为度假地点，于是早上九点他们就穿上最好的衣服出发了。

“到了巴德茅斯-里吉斯后，他们先是在海边两两散步——崭新的靴子踩在潮湿柔软的沙子上发出咯吱咯吱的响声。唉，我现在好像还能看见他们的样子！他们接下来去港口看了看过往船只，然后到瞭望塔上眺望大海，之后又去客栈吃了正餐，最后重新回到海边两两散步，咯吱咯吱地踩着柔软的沙滩。黄昏将近，他们坐在海滨大道旁的公共座椅上听乐队奏乐，然后彼此询问‘我们接下来做什么呢？’

“奥莉芙（即詹姆斯·哈德康姆太太）说：‘我现在什么都不想干，就想到海湾里划船！我们在海上跟这儿一样也能听到音乐，而且还多了划船的乐趣。’

“‘说得对，我也想去。’史蒂夫说，他的喜好向来跟她一样。”

说到这里，执事转过头看着副牧师。

“不过，先生，您比我们其他人都更清楚那个奇特的傍晚发生的奇事的细节，因为他们亲口跟您讲述过，我没有听到。也许您愿意满足这位先生的好奇心？”

“当然可以了，只要他愿意听。”副牧师说。他接着执事的故事讲了下去：

“史蒂夫的妻子很讨厌大海，除非是站在陆地上观赏，坐船的事情她想都不愿意想。詹姆斯跟她一样也不想下水，说他自己更愿意留下来坐在椅子上听乐队演奏，但如果他的妻子很想划船的话，他并不会阻止她去。讨论的结果是詹姆斯和他表哥的妻子艾米丽决定就待在原地听音乐，另外两个人到下面去雇条船，在水上游玩半小时左右，再回来跟坐在海滨大道上的两个人会合，然后一起启程回家。

“这个安排对那两个坐立不安的人来说真是再好不过了。于是艾米丽和詹姆斯看着他们下到海边去找船家租船，挑了一条黄色的小艇，小心翼翼地踏着搭在栈架上的木板来到小艇旁。他们看到史蒂夫扶奥莉芙上了船，坐到她对面的座位。他们坐稳之后，朝岸上望着他们的两人挥了挥手，然后史蒂夫操起两支短桨，和着乐队的曲子节拍划着小艇出发了，奥莉芙则操纵小艇在周围其他来往的小船中间穿梭，因为那天傍晚海面平静如镜，海面上满是荡舟游玩的人。

“‘他们这样划着船看上去真棒啊，是不是？’艾米丽对詹姆斯说（这是他们自己告诉我的）。‘他们俩都非常享受。他们对每件事的喜好都一模一样。’

“‘确实是。’詹姆斯回答。

“‘如果他俩结婚的话，一定会是很般配的一对。’她说。

“‘是的，’他说，‘我们把他们给拆散了，实在太可惜了。’

“‘别提这件事了，詹姆斯，’她说，‘是我们自己做的决定，所以无论好坏都只能接受了。’

“之后他们没有再说话，只是并排坐在那里，乐队依然在奏乐；路人来来往往，史蒂夫和奥莉芙直朝海里驶去，身影越来越小。岸上的两个人还告诉我，他们看到史蒂夫停了一会儿，把外套脱掉了好更方便划船；但詹姆斯的妻子则一直坐在船尾没动，手拉着掌舵索，用来掌握船的方向。他们离岸很远了的时候，她转过头来看了看岸上。

“‘她在对我们挥舞手帕呢。’史蒂夫的妻子说，也掏出了自己的手帕挥舞做回应。

“詹姆斯太太朝着她的丈夫以及史蒂夫太太挥手帕的时候忘了掌舵，于是小船行驶的方向就有些偏了；但是小船继续往前划行，很快他们就看不清两人了，只能依稀看到奥莉芙浅色的披风和史蒂夫白色的衬衫袖子。

“岸上的两个人又聊开了。‘我们在托尼·凯茨的婚礼舞会上决定交换伴侣真是太奇怪了。’艾米丽说，‘据大家说，托尼是个花心大萝卜，我觉得他的德行那天晚上好像传染给了我们。你们俩是谁先提出来不按之前安排好的结婚的？’

“‘嗯——我现在想不起来了，’詹姆斯说，‘我们两人聊起了这事儿，你知道，结果说干就干了。’

“‘就是因为跳舞的原因，’她说，‘跳舞有时候会让人干出疯狂的事情来。’

“‘是的。’他承认。

“‘詹姆斯——你觉得他们俩心里是不是还有对方？’史蒂夫太太问。

“詹姆斯·哈德康姆沉思了一下，承认说也许两人心中时不时还会闪过片刻的柔情吧。‘不过，也没什么大不了的。’他说。

“‘我有时候觉得史蒂夫心里满是奥莉芙，’史蒂夫太太喃喃地说，‘尤其是她骑着驮马飞驰过我们窗前的时候，特别得他的欢心……我永远都做不到，我没法克服对马的恐惧。’

“‘我也不怎么喜欢骑马，虽然为了她我装得很喜欢，’詹姆斯·哈德康姆也低声说，‘不过，他们现在不是应该掉头往回划了吗？其他那些划船的人都回来了。我不明白奥莉芙让船一直朝天边划过去是什么意思？自打出发以后，她就一直让船直直往前走，几乎没有转过弯。’

“‘毫无疑问他们是在聊天，没注意他们正往哪儿去。’史蒂夫的妻子推测。

“‘可能是吧，’詹姆斯说，‘我都不知道史蒂夫居然这么能划船。’

“‘噢，是的，’她说，‘他经常过来这里办事，然后会到海湾里划一划船。’

“‘我现在已经看不到船也看不见他们了，’詹姆斯又说，‘天已经黑下来了。’

“那两个在海上漂着的心不在焉的人，现在在逐渐降临的夜幕中变成了一个小点儿，夜色越来越浓，最后把他们遥远的身影完全吞没了。他们消失时船还在朝着和陆地相反的方向直直地向前行驶，就好像他们打算从大海的边缘跌落到太空中去，再也不回地球了一样。

“岸上的两个人继续坐着，严格地遵守承诺，在原地等着另外两个人回来。海滨大道上的路灯一盏接一盏点亮了，乐队成员收起乐谱架离开了，海湾里的游艇挂起了停泊灯，小船们也一艘接一艘回到了岸边，雇船的乘客又踩着他们之前上船的木板回到沙滩上，但是这些人里头没有史蒂夫和奥莉芙。

“‘他们怎么这么晚！’艾米丽说，‘我身上都冷起来了。我没想到需要晚上在室外坐这么久。’

“听到这话，詹姆斯·哈德康姆说他用不着穿外套，坚持要借给她穿。

“他把外套披在艾米丽的肩上。

“‘谢谢你，詹姆斯，’她说，‘唉，奥莉芙穿着那件薄薄的上衣该有多冷呀！’

“他说他也正在想这事。‘哎，他们现在肯定已经很近了，虽然我们看不见他们。船还没有全都回来。有的人喜欢沿着岸边再划一圈，把剩下的租船时间用完。’

“‘那我们要不要沿着岸边走一走，’她说，‘看看能不能看到他们？’

“他同意了，提醒她说不能走到看不见他们座位的地方，免得迟返的两人回来时跟他们错过，还以为他俩没有遵守约定，又会生气。

“他们就像哨兵巡逻一样在正对着座位的那片沙滩上来来回回地走，但是那两个人还是没回来。最后，詹姆斯·哈德康姆过去找船家，怀疑是不是他的妻子和表哥已经回来了，但是在暮色昏暗中没看见他们，而这两人已经忘了长凳上还有人在等他们。‘所有的船都回来了吗？’詹姆斯问。

“‘还有一条没回来。’租船的船家说，‘我不知道那一对划到哪个方向去了。恐怕在黑暗里可能会撞到什么东西。’

“史蒂夫的妻子和奥莉芙的丈夫于是又继续等，心里越来越焦虑不安。但是黄色的小船还是没有回来。他们会不会是停靠在海滨大道再往前的地方了呢？

“‘有的人为了逃船钱可能会这么干，’船家说，‘但是他们看起来不像是会干这种事的人。’

“詹姆斯·哈德康姆知道他不能把希望建立在这种理由之上。不过，现在想起他和史蒂夫偶尔闲谈时提到各自伴侣时的言语，他第一次想到了另一种可能性，那就是那两位在面对面相处的情景下旧情复燃，强烈程度可能他们自己都始料未及——出海逛逛很显然只是做戏——他知道码头再往前有一处台阶，他们很可能已经在那里上岸了，好有更多时间单独相处。

“但他不愿老想着这个念头，也不想跟他的同伴提及这种想法。他只是对她说：‘我们再继续往前走走吧。’

“他们继续往前走，在船坞和码头之间来回徘徊，直到史蒂夫·哈德康姆的妻子身体不适，不得不挽住詹姆斯伸过来的手臂。夜越来越深，艾米丽已经精疲力竭萎靡不振，詹姆斯觉得有必要先送她回家；而且，那对逃跑的人也不是完全没有可能已经在小镇的另一头，或者别处上了岸，再者以为他们的伴侣不会有耐心等那么久，便出其不意地匆匆赶回了家。

“不过，他还是在镇上找了人帮他留意那两人的下落，当然这是私底下安排的，虽然那两人私奔的可能性不大，但也足以让他保持低调。最后，两个被抛下的人满怀着忧虑搭上了离开巴德茅斯-里吉斯的末班列车，到了卡斯特桥镇后，再赶车回到了上朗普多村。”

“就是我们现在正走着的这条路。”教堂执事补充说。

“是的——就是这条路。”副牧师说，“可是，史蒂夫和奥莉芙并不在家。自从那天早上离开村子后，他们就没回来过。艾米丽和詹姆斯·哈德康姆各自回家，匆匆合眼眯了一会儿，第二天天一亮他们又赶着马车到卡斯特桥，上了去巴德茅斯的第一班火车。

“在他们离开的短短的空当里并没有那两个人的消息。接下来几个小时里，有几个年轻人证实确实见过一对男女划着一艘不太结实的雇船，船头朝向大海那头驶去，两人面对面相互望着，表情如在梦中，似乎完全没意识到他们在做什么、将往何处去。直到那天下午，詹姆斯才收到更多消息。在离陆地很远的地方，人们发现了那条船，底朝天在海上漂着。到了傍晚海水涨潮了，在小镇以东几英里的拉尔温德湾有两具尸体被冲上了岸，消息立刻传遍了小镇。尸体被送到巴德茅斯，经检查确认他们就是失踪的两人。据说发现他们时，两人紧紧搂着对方，他低头亲吻着她的唇，他们的面容依然还笼罩在平静和梦幻般的安乐中，就跟他们在水上划行时旁边人看到的一样。

“詹姆斯和艾米丽都没有追问这对不幸的男女下海的初衷，不过两人的意图不容置疑。无论他们对彼此的感觉将把他们引向何方，但一开始便私相授受肯定不是他们的本性。有人猜测他们很可能在四目相对时，想起这双眼睛曾经只为自己一个人而闪亮，因此陷入了一种深情的恍惚中；他们又不愿承认对彼此的感情，于是便这样恍恍惚惚地继续往前，忘了时间和空间，直到远离陆地，突然被黑暗吞没。不过真相永远也无从知晓了。他们这样死去只能说是命中注定。这两个一半，原本造物主要让他们成为完美的整体，可是生前他们却未能达成夙愿，于是‘死时也不分离’。[4]他们的遗体被带回家，在同一天下葬。我记得在念祷告词的时候我环顾了一下教堂墓地，几乎整个教区的人都来参加了葬礼。”

“是这样的，先生。”执事确认。

“剩下的那两个人，”副牧师继续说（在讲述那对恋人的悲惨命运时他的声音有些沙哑了），“跟第一对相比，虽然没那么浪漫多情，却更深思熟虑、富有远见。他们现在彼此都没了伴侣，因为这事故，反倒能够重新达成造物主给他们设定好的命运，重新实现他们原本早在头脑冷静时就做好的决定。于是一年半以后，詹姆斯·哈德康姆娶了艾米丽做妻子。他们的婚姻无论从哪个角度来说都算得上是幸福美满的。是我给他们主持的婚礼，也是哈德康姆在找我帮他们宣布结婚启事时，告诉了我他是怎么失去第一个妻子的，我刚才跟你们讲的故事几乎就是他的原话，一个字不差。”

“他们现在还住在朗普多吗？”那位新来的人问。

“啊不，先生，”执事插话说，“詹姆斯已经死了有十多年了，他的遗孀六七年前也不在了，他们没有子嗣。威廉·普里威特没去世之前一直在他家干杂活。”

“噢——威廉·普里威特！他也死了吗？——天哪！”拉克兰先生说，“全都去世了！”

“是的，先生。威廉比我年龄大得多，他要是现在还活着，得有八十多岁了吧。”

“威廉的死很是古怪——真的非常古怪！”车厢尾坐着的一个郁郁寡欢的男子说。这是种子商的父亲，他之前一直都没说过话。

“那是怎么回事呢？”拉克兰先生问。

旧仲夏夜惊魂

“你可能也知道，威廉是个怪里怪气、少言寡语的人。他一走近，你就能感觉得出来。要是他在屋子里头或者在你背后，就算你没看到他，你都能感觉到空气中有种阴冷的东西，就像你身边有一扇地窖的门打开了一样。然后，有一个礼拜天——那个时候威廉看起来还健康得很——教堂的钟突然一下子变得特别沉。教堂司事，就是他告诉我的，说他敲钟好多年都没有觉得钟这么沉——他怀疑这预示着教区里可能有人要死了。那是在礼拜天，我刚才说过了。接下来的那个星期，恰好有一天晚上威廉的老婆很晚还没睡，赶着要把衣服熨完，她在哈德康姆家帮男女主人洗衣服。她丈夫已经吃过晚饭，跟往常一样，一两个小时以前就上床睡觉去了。她在熨衣服的时候听到他下楼，在楼梯口停下来穿靴子，他一般都把鞋放在那儿，然后走到她熨衣服的起居室，穿过起居室走到门口——从楼梯走出屋子必须经过这里。他们两个没有说话，威廉本身话就不多，他老婆当时又忙着干活。他走出去关上了门。之前有时候他要是身体不舒服，或者睡不着想抽管烟的时候他就会这样出门，所以他老婆也就没有特别理会，继续熨衣服。过一会儿她弄完之后，看他还没回来，就一边收拾熨斗和其他东西，一边等了他一会儿，又顺便把第二天早上他吃早餐用的桌子先摆好。但他还是没回来，她估计他应该没走远，而且她自己也累了想睡了，就没有闩门，在门背后用粉笔写了几个字：记得锁门（因为他比较健忘），然后就朝楼梯走了过去。

“她走到楼梯口时，非常吃惊，可以说简直是吓到了，因为威廉的靴子就在那儿，跟他去睡觉之前一样。她上楼进了卧室，发现他就在床上睡得跟石头一样沉。在她没有看到也没有听到的情况下他是咋回来的，她实在想不通。有可能是在她乒乒乓乓弄熨斗的时候从她后面轻手轻脚绕过去的；但是这个想法没啥说服力：这么小个房间，他要是进来她怎么也不可能看不到。她实在解不开这个谜团，只是觉得很不对劲。但是她又不好把他叫起来，只好自己睡了。

“第二天一早她还没醒威廉就起床干活去了，她焦虑地等他回来吃早饭好问个清楚，因为天亮以后她仔细想了想，觉得情况越发骇人。等他进屋吃早饭时，还没等她开口问，他就说，‘你用粉笔写在门背后的字是啥意思？’

“她跟他解释了一下，又问他昨天晚上出去做啥了。威廉说他进了卧室以后就再也没出来过，直接脱了衣服躺下睡着了，到了五点钟他就起床干活去了，中间连醒都没有醒过。

“贝蒂·普里威特心里面一万个肯定他绝对出去过，也很肯定他并没有回来。她现在满心不安不想跟他争辩，所以就当是她搞错了，没有再继续这个话题。那天下午她在朗普多街上走着时，遇到了吉姆·维多的女儿南希，便跟她打招呼，‘呀，南希，你今天看起来好像很困哪！’

“‘是呀，普里威特太太，’南希说，‘我悄悄给你说是为啥，不过你不要告诉别人哦。昨天晚上是旧仲夏夜[5]，我们几个人去了教堂门廊，到晚上一点钟才回家。’

“‘是吗？’普里威特太太说，‘昨天是旧仲夏节？说实在的我根本想不起来是仲夏节还是米迦勒节了，我有太多活要干了。’

“‘是呀，而且我们都被看到的事情吓坏了，我跟你说。’

“‘你看到啥了？’

“先生，你很早就去了外国，所以可能不一定记得了，我们这一带都传说在仲夏夜，你可以看到整个教区在这一年里要在死神门前走一遭的人的影子走进教堂。过一阵以后，那些能够病愈的人的影子会再走出来；而那些注定要死的人的影子就再也回不来了。

“‘你看到什么了？’威廉的老婆又问。

“‘呃，’南希有点迟疑地说，‘我们最好不要说出来我们看见了啥，或者看见了谁。’

“‘你看见我丈夫了。’贝蒂·普里威特平静地说。

“‘嗯，既然你自己说起来了，’南希犹豫不决地说，‘我们——觉得好像是看到他了，但是天很黑，而且我们都给吓到了，所以也很可能不是他。’

“‘南希，你不需要有顾虑不敢说出来，虽然我晓得你是出于好意不愿说。他没有再走出教堂，我跟你一样心里头很清楚。’

“南希没有承认也没有否认，两人没有再说下去。三天以后，威廉·普里威特和约翰·柴尔斯一起在哈德康姆先生的牧场上割草，在正午最热的时候他们在树下坐下来吃了顿午饭，喝光了一壶酒，然后两人就坐着睡着了。约翰·柴尔斯先醒过来，他望望对面还在睡的工友，突然看见一只巨大的白色的飞蛾——我们把它叫磨坊幽灵——从他大张着的嘴里爬出来，径直飞走了。约翰觉得这事很诡异，因为威廉小时候曾经在一家磨坊干过好几年的活。他抬头看看太阳的位置，发现他们睡了很久，但是威廉还没醒。约翰就喊他，说该起来干活了。威廉还是没有理睬，约翰上去推他，发现他已经死了。

“然后，就在同一天，老菲利普·胡克洪恩到朗普多泉边去打水，转身时正好看到了威廉，脸色苍白，神情怪异。菲利普·胡克洪恩非常惊讶，因为许多年前，威廉的小儿子——他的独生子——在那个泉边玩耍的时候被淹死了，这个事情一直折磨着威廉，所以大家都晓得他后来再也没靠近过那个泉，宁愿多绕半英里的路也要避开。他问过别人以后，就晓得威廉那时应该在两英里以外的牧场上，出现在泉边的不可能是他本人；后来又发现在泉边看见他的时间正是他死去的时候。”

“这真是个阴郁的故事啊。”归来的侨民沉默了一会儿，评论道。

“确实，确实。唉，人生的起起伏伏，我们都必须要承受啊。”种子商的父亲说。

“拉克兰先生，我估计你可能没听说过安德里·撒切尔和简·瓦伦斯以及司克林普顿的牧师和执事之间的奇事吧？”高级茅屋匠开口了，他眼里闪着一丝光芒，那是被刻意压抑着的活力。他坐在马车车厢前部，两脚搭在车厢外，此前一直在看着道路前方远处的事物，“很少听说牧师和执事有这样的奇遇，刚才那个故事可能让你觉得不舒服，听了这个你可能会高兴一点。”

归来的人回答说他没听说过这故事，很乐意听一听，他现在想起那个叫撒切尔的人来了。

“哦不，这个安德里·撒切尔是你知道的那个撒切尔的儿子；这个撒切尔才刚结婚两三年，我打算给你讲的这个事情是发生在他的婚礼当天，或者要不这儿的其他人给你讲也行。”

“哎呀，哎呀，老兄，还是你来讲最好。”有几个人连忙说。拉克兰先生也加入进来，请他继续说下去，并补充说他离开英国之前跟撒切尔一家相当熟。

“因为你是新来的，所以我就提醒一句，”车夫轻声对拉克兰说，“那个克里斯托弗讲的故事你不要太信以为真。”

侨民点了点头。

“好吧，那我现在就来讲。”高级茅屋匠说，语气听来极为笃定，“其实这个故事跟安德里关系不大，更多是跟牧师和执事有关，所以其实找个教会人员来讲可能比我还更合适一点。”

安德里·撒切尔结婚记

“你可能不清楚，所有这些事情，都是从安德里喜欢喝酒开始的——虽然据大家说他现在已经不喝酒了，这个对他来说当然是好事。他的新娘，简，比安德里要大一些，到底大多少我就不清楚了。她不是我们这个教区的，要看他们的结婚登记才晓得她的年纪。反正，总而言之，她比小伙子年纪要大一些，再加上由于这个小伙子的原因造成她的某种身体状况——

（“哎呀，好可怜哟！”在场的女人们都叹息着。）

“所以她非常着急，要赶在他改变主意前把这件事办成。所以，十一月的一个早上，天才刚亮，她就跟安德里还有他的哥哥嫂嫂往教堂出发了，这样安德里以后就一辈子都是她的了。据说走的时候她看起来兴高采烈。天还没亮安德里就已经出了我们教区，凡是已经起来了的人看到他，都对他挥舞手里头的灯，把帽子抛到空中。

“女方所在的教区教堂离她住的地方不到两英里，因为那个时候正好是一年当中天气最好的时候，他们计划婚礼结束以后就马上动身赶车去布莱迪港度个假，去看一看大海、轮船，还有驻扎的士兵啥的，省得回她住的远亲家去吃饭，然后傻呆呆地在那儿闲坐一个下午。

“嗯，有些人注意到安德里那天早上去教堂时步子有些偏偏倒倒。原来头天晚上他隔壁邻居的娃娃举行命名受洗晚会，还请安德里当教父，他用酒给自己洗礼了一个晚上，还自顾自地说：‘我就算活到了一千岁也不会再有这种福气，头一天当教父，第二天又当丈夫，可能再下一天就当爸爸咯，所以这种千载难逢的机会我要尽情享受啊。’因此他早上出发前根本没合过眼。结果，就像我刚说的，他跟他的新娘走进教堂举行仪式时，牧师（不管在外头咋样，在教堂里头还是个很严格的人）严厉地盯着安德里，然后很尖锐地说：‘小伙子，这是怎么回事？你喝酒了，而且还是一大早就喝。我真替你害臊！’

“‘是的，我确实喝了，先生，’安德里回答，‘但是我要干正事的话，照样可以走得很直，我还可以沿粉笔线走嘞，’他说（这会儿还没什么冒犯的意思），‘就跟其他人一样，而且——（他说着说着语气越来越冲）——我敢保证要是你，比利·土谷牧师，像我一样参加了一整晚命名受洗晚会的话，你可能连站都站不稳咯；你要站得稳才他妈的见鬼了！’

“这个回答让比利牧师——他们是这么称呼他的——很是恼怒，虽然还没到勃然大怒的地步，因为他还算是个性子温和的人，就算惹到他了也不会暴跳如雷。于是他很坚决地说：‘你现在这种情况我不能给你们主持婚礼。我绝不会这样做！你回家去吧，酒醒了再来！’然后他‘啪’一声合上了经书，就像老鼠夹弹起来了一样。

“然后新娘就伤心欲绝地号啕大哭起来，她费尽心思好不容易才让安德里就范，这么一来他说不定就跑了。她于是苦苦哀求牧师继续婚礼仪式。但是没用。

“‘婚姻是庄严的，我不能让你跟一个醉鬼结婚。’土谷先生说，‘这既不合适也不体面。姑娘，我很抱歉，我看得出来你现在状态不妙，但你最好还是回家吧。我真奇怪他这么醉醺醺的你怎么会把他带到这儿来！’

“‘但是如果——如果他不是喝醉了的话他根本都不会来！’她抽抽搭搭边哭边说。

“‘这个我也没办法。’牧师说。她无论怎么哀求都打动不了他。她于是又换了个办法。

“‘先生，要不这样，您先回家去，我们留在这儿，您过一两个小时以后再回来，我敢说那会儿他肯定已经清醒得跟个法官一样了。’她哭道，‘如果您允许的话，我们就留在这里。要是他没有结成婚就走出了这个教堂，以后一百匹马也休想把他拖回来了！’

“‘好吧，’牧师说，‘给你们两个小时的时间，我到时候再回来。’

“‘还有先生，请您把门锁上，这样我们就跑不出去了！’她又说。

“‘可以。’牧师说。

“‘请不要让任何人知道我们在里面。’

“牧师脱下了纯白的罩衫，然后离开了。剩下的人商量怎样才能保密，还好这个地方很偏僻，时辰又很早。至于证婚人——安德里的哥哥嫂嫂，他们本来就不赞成安德里娶简当老婆，来这一趟实属无奈，说他们可不能在这黑洞洞的地方等两个小时，要在吃正餐之前赶回朗普多去。两个人都很固执，执事只好说他们想走就走吧。他们可以就当弟弟的婚礼已经举行过了，并且新婚夫妇已经按计划出发到布莱迪港旅行去了，等牧师回来以后，教堂执事自己再找个过路的人，就可以当证婚人了。

“一切都谈妥之后，安德里的亲戚便乐意之极地走了，执事把教堂门关上，准备把这一对锁在里面。新娘又走过去对他耳语了几句，眼睛里依然泪流成河。

“‘亲爱的执事先生呀，’她说，‘我们要是就坐在这里面等的话，路过的人可能会从窗子里看见我们，然后就知道发生了啥事。到时候肯定会成为丑闻和笑料，我估计一辈子都抬不起头来了，而且，亲爱的安德里说不定会设法跑出去，把我一个人丢在这儿！你能不能把我们锁到塔楼上去呢，亲爱的执事先生？如果你愿意的话，我就把他哄上去。’

“为了让这个可怜的姑娘高兴一点，执事并不反对这样做。他们把安德里哄到了塔楼上，执事毫不犹豫地把两人锁在里头，然后就回家了，打算过两个小时再回来。

“土谷牧师离开教堂回到家不久，突然看到一位身着粉衣、脚蹬长筒靴的绅士骑马经过窗前，脑中陡然一闪，想起来这天正是猎犬在他那个教区边上集合去猎狐的日子。牧师非常热爱打猎，非常希望也能到场。[6]

“一句话，除了礼拜天以及平时有工作在身，其他时间比利牧师可是嗜猎狐如命。虽说他很潦倒，而且骑马的时候整个人在马背上趴成一堆，他的黑马也年老体衰，他的筒靴年龄更老，从上到下都是一种颜色——已经发白的黄褐色，而且到处都开裂了，但他参加过无数次猎狐，已经目睹过三千只狐狸丧生。而且——因为他是个光棍——夏天他每次睡觉都会把被褥展开，从床尾钻进去朝前爬到床头，来提醒自己冬天就快来了，他又可以参加精彩的猎狐运动了，以及又有多少狐狸要逃入洞穴了。每次乡绅家举行受洗命名礼，他事后总是留下来吃晚餐，每次都会喝上满满一大瓶波特酒，绝对够把娃娃再洗一遍了。

“话说，执事平时还给牧师当清洁工、园丁和干杂活，他刚刚才进花园准备干活，就看到了那位身着猎装的绅士路过，接着马上又看见了更多的人，有贵族、乡绅，还有大群的猎犬以及‘猎手’吉姆·崔德海吉、赶猎犬的人等等。执事跟牧师一样是狂热的狩猎迷，以至于他每次只要看到猎犬或听到它们的声音，就会跟听到了天堂仙音一样，完全失控。不管他当时是在睡觉，还是在播种——全都忘得一干二净。他马上扔掉手里的铲子跑进屋去找牧师，后者这会儿跟他一样迫不及待地想出发了。

“‘先生，您的马今天上午很需要，非常非常需要出去遛一遛了！’执事说，声音激动得有点发抖，‘您看要不我带它到小丘上去转一个小时再回来？’

“‘确实，它的确很需要运动一下了。我自己带它去溜达吧。’牧师说。

“‘噢——您要自己去遛吗？那，先生，那儿还有匹矮脚马。哎，它在马厩里关得太久，简直都要关不住了！如果您不介意，我就给它装上马鞍——’

“‘好吧。你当然可以带它出去。’牧师说，他这会儿只要自己能尽快出发，才不在乎执事要干啥。于是，他匆匆忙忙套上长筒靴和马裤朝着集合的地方奔去，打算一个小时以后回来。他刚一走，执事也跳上了矮脚马尾随而至。牧师到了集合地点后遇到了许多熟人，最令人高兴的是猎犬一被放开就发现了猎物，众人都大为兴奋。牧师顿时忘了他本来打算来溜达一趟就马上回去的，反倒跟着猎手队伍跑远了，越过了利匹森林和格林家的灌木林之间的那片休耕地；他打马大步飞奔时环顾了一下四周，发现执事紧跟在他后头。

“‘哈哈，执事——你也来了？’他说。

“‘是的，先生，我也跟来了。’对方回答。

“‘这对马来说真是再好不过的锻炼！’

“‘说得太对了，先生——嘻嘻！’执事说。

“他们就这样往前骑着，进了格林家的灌木林，横穿而过到了高吉尔顿；再跨过我们现在正走着的这条收费公路到了沃特斯顿岭，然后转头往约伯里森林而去。翻过山丘，冲下山谷，跟疾风一样，执事紧跟着牧师，牧师紧追着猎犬。那群猎犬那天的追踪可说是前所未有的精彩；牧师和执事都压根儿没想起来教堂的塔楼上那对没结成婚的人还在等他们回去嘞。

“‘先生，这一趟跑下来，您的马脚力绝对会大有长进！’执事边跑边说，离牧师只一颈之差，‘您今天让它们出来遛遛实在太英明咯！再过两天可能就会下霜而路滑了，这两个可怜的家伙可能就有好几个星期出不来咯。’

“‘的确有可能，的确有可能。夫善士者，待牲畜亦当以仁心行善也。’牧师说。

“‘嘻嘻！’执事望着牧师，目光充满狡黠。

“‘哈哈！’牧师也回望执事，‘嘿！当心！’他突然发现狐狸突破了封锁，于是大声喊。

“‘嘿！’执事也大喊，‘它往那边跑了！哎呀，见他妈的鬼，好像有两只狐狸——’

“‘嘘，执事，闭嘴！别再让我听到你说那几个字！你得记住我们的使命！’

“‘好的，先生，好的。不过确实，打猎容易让人冲昏头脑，让他连更高尚的使命都搞忘了！’下一分钟执事的眼睛又偷偷斜瞄了牧师一下，牧师也瞄了瞄他。‘嘻嘻！’执事又笑起来。

“‘哈哈！’土谷牧师也笑了。

“‘啊，先生，’执事又开口说，‘这比起在冬天早上对着您永恒的经书唱阿门可要好得多了！’

“‘是的，执事，的确如此！凡事皆有定期[7]。’土谷牧师回答，说得真是一字不差，因为他还是一个颇有学识的基督徒，只要他高兴，经书章章句句信口拈来，完全是个正经八百的牧师样子。

“最后狩猎终于在下午结束了，狐狸跑进了一个老妇人家，钻到她的桌子底下，又跳到了钟盒子里。牧师和执事是最早赶到现场目睹狐狸被抓住并杀死的人，他们把脸贴在老妇人家窗子上往里头望啊望。那口钟咣当乱响一气，以前从来没这么响过。接下来问题来了，他们得想办法找到回家的路。

“牧师和执事都不确定能不能回得去，因为他们的马早就累瘫在地了。但他们还是尽量能走就走，虽然他们精疲力竭，只能拖着脚慢慢走，还得走一阵歇一阵。

“‘我们永远、永远都回不去咯！’土谷先生呻吟着说，腰都直不起来了。

“‘永远回不去了！’执事也呻吟着，‘这肯定是神对我们罪孽的惩罚哟！’

“‘我估计是的。’牧师喃喃地说。

“结果，等他们终于踏进牧师家大门的时候天早都黑了，两个人进了教区以后一直偷偷摸摸的，就像偷了把锤子一样，他们不想被教众晓得白天他俩是做啥去了。两个人都累得要死，又怕马也累死，其间根本没想起来那对还没有完成婚礼的人。把马牵回马厩喂过之后，牧师和执事也匆匆吃了点东西便上床睡觉了。

“第二天早上土谷牧师正在吃早饭，脑子里还在回味头一天的辉煌猎事，突然执事慌慌张张上门来找他。

“‘先生，我刚刚突然想起，我们昨天忘记了还要给那对准新人举行婚礼嘞！’

“牧师吃了一半的食物从嘴里掉了出来，整个人就跟挨了一枪一样。‘我的神哪！’他说，‘我们真的给忘了！这实在太糟糕了！’

“‘是啊，先生，太糟糕了。说不定我们已经毁了那个女人！’

“‘啊哟——是呀——我想起来了。她在这之前就应该结婚的。’

“‘要是她就在那个塔楼上面——而且还没有医生或者接生婆在场——’

（“哎呀——好可怜呀！”在场的女士们又异口同声地叹息。）

“‘这个够得上让我们两个上值季法庭了，更不要说我们还让教会也蒙羞！’

“‘天哪，别说了，执事！我要疯掉了！’牧师说，‘真见鬼，我为什么当时没给他们主持婚礼，管他喝醉还是清醒！（在那个时候，牧师就跟其他那些诚实的普通人一样急了也会骂娘。）你有没有去教堂看看他们怎么样了，或者去村里问一问？’

“‘先生，我咋会呢！我刚刚才想起来这件事，而且在教会的事情上我都要先向您请示的嘛。我想起来的时候，吓得腿都软了，先生，您用一根麻雀毛都能把我打倒，我敢发誓！’

“于是，牧师从餐桌旁跳起来，两人匆匆赶去教堂。

“‘他们很可能已经不在那儿了，’土谷先生边走边说，‘说实在的，我希望他们已经走了。他们很可能已经逃出去回家了。’

“然而，等他们打开大门，走进墓地，抬头看塔楼的时候，他们看到窗边有一张惨白的小脸，还有一只小手在挥舞。那是新娘。

“‘我不行了！执事！’土谷先生说，‘我真觉得自己没脸去见他们了！’他跌坐在一块墓碑上，‘我真希望自己当时没那么该死的吹毛求疵！’

“‘确实——当时开都开始了却没有进行下去是有点可惜。’执事说，‘但是，既然您神圣的牧师天性不允许您继续，那这两人也必须要忍受了。’

“‘说得对，执事，说得对！她看上去怎么样，有没有什么早产的迹象？’

“‘我只能看到她肩膀以上的部分，先生。’

“‘那——她的脸色看起来啥样？’

“‘看上去确实白得吓人！’

“‘唉，我们必须做好最坏的打算！天哪，昨天骑马骑得我腰酸背痛！……但是现在还是先把更神圣的事情搞定吧！’

“他们进了教堂，打开了塔楼楼梯的锁，可怜的简和安德里立刻冲了出来，就像饥饿的老鼠冲出碗柜一样。安德里一瘸一拐，神志已经完全清醒。他的新娘则脸色惨白，冷得直哆嗦，但还没有别的状况。

“‘啊，’牧师大大松了口气，‘你们不会一直都待在这里吧？’

“‘是的，先生，我们一直都在！’新娘说，虚弱地坐在一张座椅上，‘我们从那时到现在，一口水没喝过，一口饭也没吃过！没人帮忙我们根本不可能出得去，所以我们就只好一直在这里待着了！’

“‘你们为什么不叫人呢，我的天？’牧师问。

“‘她不让我叫。’安德里说。

“‘因为我们被关在这里头的原因实在太丢人了，’简抽泣着说，‘我们怕要是事情传出去，这一辈子都要成为笑柄！有一两次安德里都想敲钟叫人了，但是他想想又说：“不行，我宁可饿死。我不能让我们两家的姓氏蒙羞，亲爱的。”于是我们等了又等，转了一圈又一圈；但你们直到现在才来！’

“‘我非常抱歉！’牧师说，‘那么，现在我们尽快把这事完成吧。’

“‘我——我想先吃点东西，’安德里说，‘随便一点面包或者一片洋葱都好，可以给我点勇气把仪式完成，我现在饿得前胸都贴到后背了。’

“‘我觉得我们还是先完成仪式吧，’新娘有点不安地说，‘趁我们所有人都在，大家都方便！’

“安德里放弃了对食物的要求，执事从外面叫了个证婚人进来，并确保他不会把这事传出去。很快两人的连理总算打上了个死结，新娘如释重负，笑得格外舒心；而安德里却比往常跛得更厉害了。

“‘现在，’土谷牧师说，‘请你俩务必到我家来，出发之前先好好地吃一顿填饱肚子吧！’

“夫妇俩很高兴地接受了邀请，四人从两条路分头出了教堂，以免引起别人的注意，因为现在时辰还很早。他们走进牧师公馆，假装刚从布莱迪港旅行回来，然后便痛痛快快胡吃海喝了一顿，直到再也装不下为止。

“很长一段时间这件事都还颇为保密，但后来慢慢就传开了，连他们自己现在都会当成笑话来讲；虽然简大费周章得到的并不是啥好货，但至少她保住了自己的名声。”

“这个安德里是不是那个扮成提琴手，圣诞节去乡绅家表演的那个？”种子商问。

“不，不，”小学校长普罗菲特先生说，“那个是他父亲。唉，出那个洋相全都是因为他是个吃货的缘故。”他发现大家都在侧耳倾听，于是便继续讲述起来。

滥竽充数的老安德里

“我那个时候是教堂唱诗班的成员，我们和乐队在圣诞周通常要去乡绅家的府邸，在大厅里给乡绅的家人和客人奏乐唱歌（客人里头有副主教，巴克斯比爵爷及夫人和其他人）；等表演完毕，按照惯例，我们还会在仆役厅里吃上一顿丰盛的晚餐。安德鲁知道这个惯例，等到我们准备出发时跑来找我们，说：‘天哪，我好想跟你们这些幸福的人一起去享受一顿牛排、火鸡、梅子布丁和麦芽酒啊！多一个少一个对乡绅来说根本就没啥区别。可惜我年纪太大装不成唱诗班男娃子，胡子又太多扮不了唱诗班女娃子。好乡亲呀，你们能不能借我一把提琴，我就假装是乐队成员跟你们一起去？’

“唉，我们不想对他太苛刻，于是就借给他一把旧提琴，虽然安德鲁并不比巨人科奈儿更懂音乐。有了这把乐器装样，他便同我们一起在指定时间去了乡绅家，大模大样地走进去，提琴夹在腋下。他尽量装得很自然地翻开乐谱、挪动蜡烛的位置，让光充分照亮那些音符；开始一切都很顺利，我们表演了《牧羊人为证》《星星啊，升起来吧》《听那欢乐之音》等几首歌。乡绅的母亲是一位高个子、坏脾气的老夫人，对教会音乐颇感兴趣。她突然对安德鲁说：‘小伙子，我发现你没有跟其他人一起演奏乐器。怎么回事？’

“眼见安德鲁陷入困境，唱诗班每个人的心都沉到了谷底。我们都看见他开始冒冷汗，不知道他怎样才能脱身。

“‘夫人哪，我的运气不太好，’他像个孩子一样恭顺地鞠了一躬，说，‘我在来的路上摔了一跤，把琴弓摔坏了。’

“‘噢，太遗憾了，’她说，‘确定没法修了吗？’

“‘是的，夫人，’安德鲁说，‘全摔碎了。’

“‘我看看有没有办法帮你。’她说。

“当时看起来好像危险已经过去了，我们又接着表演了D大调升两个半音的《沉睡的人们，欢呼吧》。等我们一唱完，她就对安德鲁说：‘我派人去了阁楼，那里有一些旧乐器，在那里帮你找到了一把琴弓。’然后她把琴弓递给了可怜的安德鲁，他连应该拿哪一头都不知道。‘现在我们终于可以听到完整的伴奏了。’她说。

“安德鲁站在一堆演奏者中间，面前放着乐谱，脸看起来就跟个烂苹果一样；因为全教区要说有谁是人见人怕的，那就数这位鹰钩鼻的老夫人了。不过，他还是装得很像地开始了‘演奏’，比旁边的人稍稍迟一步；他把琴弓在琴上拉来拉去，但没有碰到琴弦，看起来就像是在全神贯注演奏曲子一般。他说不定能这样糊弄过去的，要不是乡绅的一位客人——不是别人，正是那位副主教——注意到他把提琴拿反了，琴马夹在下巴底下，腮托抓在手里；他们开始围拢过来，以为这是一种新的演奏方法。

“于是事情败露了。乡绅的母亲让人把安德鲁这个无耻的骗子赶了出去，整场和谐的表演也被迫中断了许久。乡绅宣布说会通知安德鲁两个星期后搬出农舍滚蛋走人。但当我们完事后到仆役厅时却看见安德鲁安然坐在那里，他从前门刚被乡绅命人赶出去，又从后门被乡绅的太太派人叫回来，大家后来也没听说他要搬出农舍的事。不过自那晚之后安德鲁再也没有扮成乐手当众演奏。现在他已经不在人世了，可怜的人啊，就像我们所有人都将归于尘土！”

“我都差不多快忘了那个老唱诗班了，还有小提琴和低音提琴，”归乡的人若有所思地说，“他们现在还跟以前一样吗？”

“哎呀！”高级茅屋匠克里斯托弗·屯克说，“你还不晓得呀，他们早在二十年前就已经被解散咯。现在由一个滴酒不沾的年轻人在教堂拉手摇风琴，拉得相当不错。当然不如原来的音乐那么好，因为这个风琴要用手转摇柄，那个年轻人说他有时候没法全心投入去表现曲子，因为他手都要摇断了。”

“那他们为什么要换乐队呢？”

“嗯，一方面是因为现在流行手摇风琴，另一方面是因为那些老乐手捅了娄子。真是个大娄子！——是吧，约翰？我反正是永远都忘不了——永远！他们可以说是完全丢尽了教会职员的德行，简直就跟他们从来都没有德行一样。”

“那对他们来说真是太糟糕了。”

“是啊。”高级茅屋匠眼睛盯着前方，全神贯注地回想着过去的时光，仿佛他们就在一英里外一样，然后开始接着讲述。

神游天外的教区唱诗班

“那件事发生在圣诞节后第一主日——也是他们最后一次在朗普多村教堂楼座上表演，虽然当时他们并没料到。先生，你可能晓得，这些乐手组成的乐队相当不错——几乎跟杜伊一家领衔的梅尔斯托克教区唱诗班乐队一样好，[8]这样说大家应该就明白了。乐队成员有领衔的第一提琴手，尼古拉斯·普定康姆；低音提琴手，提摩西·托马斯；高音提琴手，约翰·拜尔斯；蛇形号手，丹尼尔·霍恩海德；罗伯特·道多负责吹单簧管；尼克斯先生则负责双簧管——这些全都是可靠、有感染力的乐手，吹管乐的那几个人也个个中气十足。因为这个原因，他们在圣诞周的时候特别抢手，小型里尔舞及各种舞会都会邀请他们去伴奏：因为他们吹拉弹奏起吉格舞曲和角笛舞曲真是信手拈来，就跟他们演奏赞美诗一样纯熟，甚至更好——我可不是亵渎喔。总之，他们前半个钟头可能还在乡绅府上的大厅里为女士们先生们演奏圣诞颂歌，像圣徒一样谦逊有礼跟人家一起品茶喝咖啡；后半个钟头他们可能就已经在“锅匠的手臂”小酒馆里像脱缰野马一样为九对或更多舞者奏起《英武的白衣中士》，大口牛饮起烈性的朗姆苹果酒了。

“哪，就在那个圣诞节，他们每天晚上都不停赶场子，一个舞会接一个舞会地演奏，差不多就没睡过觉。然后就到了圣诞节后第一主日，他们倒霉的那一天。那一年冬天简直是冷死人，他们在二楼楼座上根本坐不住；虽然楼下正堂里的教众有个炉子可以烤火抵挡一下寒气，楼座上的这些乐手却啥都没有。那天早上，天冷得过一个小时水就多结一英寸冰；做早礼拜时，尼古拉斯就说：‘神哪，我受不了这冻死猪狗的天气咯；就算要花巨款，今天下午我们也要整点东西下肚暖一下身子。’

“他于是买了一加仑兑好的白兰地加啤酒，下午带到了教堂。他们把酒罐子裹得严严实实，放在提摩西·托马斯的低音提琴袋里，让它能保持微温，等他们需要的时候再拿出来喝：在牧师宣读赦罪文时先喝几小口，读完经文之后再喝几小口，剩下的在牧师开始布道时全部喝光。等他们喝下最后一口的时候，觉得浑身暖洋洋的十分舒畅；随着布道的进行——那天下午的布道还特别长，对他们来说真是特别倒霉——他们就睡着了，每一个人都不例外；而且还睡得跟石头一样沉。

“那个下午天色特别暗，布道快结束的时候，教堂里头能看到的就只有站在布道坛上的牧师、他旁边的两根蜡烛，和蜡烛后面他唠唠叨叨的脸。布道终于结束了，牧师宣布晚课赞美诗开始。但是没有听到唱诗班音乐响起，人们便转过头来看是咋回事，接着坐在楼座上的一个男孩，列维·林皮特，推了推提摩西和尼古拉斯，喊：‘开始了！开始了！’

“‘诶？开始啥？’尼古拉斯惊醒了，教堂里面一片昏暗，他的脑子也一片混乱，以为自己还在头一晚通宵演奏的那个舞会上，便拿起提琴和琴弓，开始拉起了我们这个地方当时最流行的吉格舞曲《裁缝中的恶魔》。乐队其他人也都昏头昏脑，毫不迟疑地跟着他们的首席提琴手全力演奏起来。他们演奏得无比卖力，连屋顶上的蜘蛛网都被《裁缝中的恶魔》这曲子的低音震得鬼晃鬼晃的。然后尼古拉斯看到下面没有人动弹，便一边拉琴一边高喊（他平时在舞会上，如果看到别人不晓得这舞步咋跳时就会用这种口吻指挥他们）：‘领舞交叉手牵起来！等我结束时把小提琴拉出咯吱咯吱的声音，男伴就在榭寄生下亲他的女伴！’

“叫列维的那个男娃子吓坏了，闪电一样冲下了楼座，冲出教堂往家跑。牧师听到这邪恶的小调响彻教堂，简直是怒发冲冠。他怀疑乐队是中了什么邪，高举起双手喊：‘停，停，停！快停下来，停下来！你们在干什么！’但是音乐声太大，他们根本就听不见他的声音，他越喊他们吹拉得越大声。

“人们从座席里走出来，彻底懵了，然后议论纷纷：‘他们居然做出这种恶行，是什么意思？我们会不会像索多玛和蛾摩拉一样遭神降罪毁灭啊？’[9]

“接着乡绅也从他铺了绿色羊毛呢的座席里走出来，那天跟他一起来做礼拜的还有许多来他府上做客的贵人和夫人；乡绅走到楼座上，在前头站定，对着乐手们挥舞拳头，说：‘成何体统！在这神圣的地方！成何体统！’

“乐师们终于在演奏间隙听到了他的声音，停了下来。

“‘我从未见过如此丧心病狂、毫无廉耻的行为！从来没有！’乡绅失控地大吼。

“‘从来没有！’牧师走下布道坛，也来到了乡绅旁边。

“‘除非天堂里的天使，’乡绅说，（其实他自己也不是什么好鸟，虽然就这么一次他恰好站在了上帝这一边）‘除非天堂里的天使亲自下凡，’他说，‘否则你们这些厚颜无耻的家伙休想再在这个教堂里面奏响哪怕一个音符！你们对我不敬，对我的家人不敬，对我的客人不敬，对牧师不敬，对上帝不敬，为了你们今天下午做的恶，活该遭此惩罚！’

“倒霉的教堂唱诗班乐队成员终于酒醒了，记起来他们身在何处。当时情景实在是壮观，看到尼古拉斯·普定康姆、提摩西·托马斯和约翰·拜尔斯用胳膊夹着提琴灰溜溜爬下楼梯，还有可怜的丹尼尔·霍恩海德抱着蛇形号，罗伯特·道多抱着单簧管，恨不得缩成一小团的样子；他们就这样离开了教堂。牧师了解了真相以后可能已经原谅了他们，但是乡绅坚决不肯。他在同一个星期就订购了一架手摇风琴，能绝对准确无误地演奏二十二支时新的赞美诗曲子。所以不管弹的人心头有些啥罪恶的念头，拉出来的都只能是赞美诗。而且像我刚才说过的，他还找了一个相当体面的人来专门转手柄，那些老乐手再也没演奏过。”

“我认识的一位老熟人，温特太太，肯定已经不在了吧？就是靠年金过活，平时看上去总是心事重重的那位？”返乡人沉默了很久，然后问道。

马车里似乎没人想起来这个名字。

“噢，是的，她肯定早就已经死了——认识她时我还是个孩子，她那会儿都七十岁了。”他又补充说。

“别人可能都不记得温特太太了，不过我还记得很清楚，”年长的杂货店女店主说，“是的，她死了至少已经有二十五年了。先生，我估计她心事重重，眼神空洞的原因你应该知道吧？”

“我记得有一次听人说，好像是因为她儿子的缘故吧。但是我那时候还太小，所以人家也没跟我详细说。”

杂货店店主叹息着，脑海中又浮现出那久远的过往。“是的，”她喃喃地说，“确实是跟一个儿子有关。”她看看车厢里大家都摆出倾听的姿态，便继续说了下去。

温特与帕姆利两家的爱恨情仇

“故事必须得从头说起——我小的时候，这个教区有两个姑娘都以美貌著称，于是自然成了对手。撇开具体情况不说，总之结果就是两人最后变得势不两立，其中一个还挖了另一个的墙角，抢了对手的恋人并结婚了。被挖走的小伙子姓温特，很快这两人就生了个儿子。

“另一个姑娘单身了很多年；等她差不多三十岁的时候，一个姓帕姆利的沉默寡言的男人向她求婚，她便嫁给了他。你可能不记得朗普多原来有帕姆利这家人了，不过我记得很清楚。她也生了个儿子，当然，比起第一个的儿子要小九到十岁。而且这孩子脑子还不大好使，虽然他母亲把他视如珍宝。

“这孩子八岁的时候帕姆利就死了，留下孤儿寡母，过得很是拮据。她原来的对头现在也成了寡妇，但是丈夫留下的遗产比较丰厚，吃穿不愁。温特太太出于同情，就让帕姆利太太的儿子去她家当帮工，虽然这孩子年纪还小；她自己的儿子杰克已经差不多十七岁了。贫困的帕姆利太太别无他法，只好让儿子去帮工，于是小帕姆利就去了富裕些的寡妇温特太太家里。

“唉，总之，在十二月的一天，这位殷实的温特太太——没人知道她究竟是怎么搞的——打发小男孩送一封信到邻村去，虽然他着实不情愿。天已经快黑了，孩子乞求她不要让他去，因为回来的路上会感到害怕。但是女主人却坚持要他去，与其说是她生性冷酷不如说是考虑不周，反正男孩只好去了。他回来的路上经过雅尔布里森林，有东西突然从树后面跳出来，把他给吓抽风了。这孩子就这样毁了，他从此就变成了个成天说胡话的白痴，没过多久就死了。

“这下另外的那个女人完全没有活着的念想了，她发誓一定要报复这个先是抢走了她的恋人，然后又害死了她的孩子的对头。虽然这丧子之痛肯定不是她那位富有的熟人有意为之，但是不得不说后者对这后果显得无动于衷。可怜帕姆利太太心头有再大的仇恨，也找不到报复的机会。她孤身一人继续过活，时间也许会慢慢冲淡仇恨，让她淡忘她遭受的委屈。孩子死了一年之后，就在那样的情形下，帕姆利太太在埃克森布里城里出生长大的侄女来到了朗普多与她同住。

“这位年轻姑娘——哈丽特·帕姆利小姐——是一个骄傲貌美的姑娘，受过很好的教养，比起我们村子的人要时髦文雅得多，当然想想她从城里来，这也很正常。在她眼里自个儿的地位可比温特太太和她儿子高多了，就像那两位觉得自己比帕姆利太太地位高一样。可惜爱情是个不拘礼节的东西，不该来的偏偏就来了，年轻的杰克·温特对哈丽特·帕姆利一见钟情，可说是难以自拔、不可救药。

“哈丽特比杰克读的书多，对他母亲自认为高她婶婶一等的这种乡下人见识嗤之以鼻，对他的爱慕并没有给予鼓励。但是朗普多实在是个小地方，她既然在那儿常住，两个人难免会时常碰面，因此她虽然心高气傲，但也慢慢开始对他的关注与追求有些沾沾自喜。

“有一天两人在一起采苹果的时候，他向她求婚了。她没料到他这么早就会谈及这么实在的问题，吃惊之下便含含糊糊半答应了；反正至少她没有明确地拒绝，而且还接受了他给她准备的小礼物。

“不过他也看出来了，她只把他当成了一个没见过世面的乡下小子，而不是值得仰慕的恋人，他决定要做些让她刮目相看的事以确保获得她的芳心。于是他有一天就说：‘我得换个地方，设法找个在这里得不到的好活路。’两三周以后他就向她告别，去了蒙克斯布里学习管理农场，打算以后自己做个农场主。他到那儿以后定期给她写信，就好像两个人的婚事是彼此默认了一般。

“话说，哈丽特虽然喜欢小伙子送她的礼物，享受他仰慕的眼神，但是他在信纸上的魅力实在大打折扣。她母亲曾是位学校教师，哈丽特自己对读书写作也很有天赋，在那个时候会写作的人还没现在这么多，写得一手好字这本身就是一种了不起的本事啦。杰克·温特在情书里的表现实在是有损她的城里人气质、不符合她的高雅品位，于是她在回复其中一封信时，用她引以为傲的流畅秀丽的字体，非常严厉、傲慢地命令他，说假如他想取悦她的话，那就好好对着拼音字典练好拼写和书法。他有没有按她说的去做我们不得而知，但是他后来写的信可没什么长进。他还笨拙地在信里冒冒失失地对她说，假如她心里对他感情更深的话，就不会这么介意他的书法和拼写了，当然这说得没错。

“唉，杰克一不在，他在哈丽特心里点燃的一点微弱的小火苗很快就黯淡下去，最后完全熄灭了。他一封接一封地写信，请求乃至乞求她说清楚为什么如此冷淡。她便直截了当地告诉他，她是城里人，他的教养实在是配不上她。

“虽然杰克·温特在读书写字上面受的训练不多，但不代表他就比别人脸皮更厚；事实上他遇事会特别的脆弱敏感。她给的这个抛弃他的理由让他心碎欲绝、羞愧难当、屈辱不堪，这种感觉现在也许很难理解了——在那个时候能够写一手漂亮的字是多么令人羡慕，而不能写出漂亮的字又多么令人悲伤。杰克于是给她回了一封怒气冲冲的短信，而她的报复还击则既巧妙又伤人：她指出他在头一封信里拼错了多少个单词，并宣称光是这一点就已经足够让任何女人打消嫁给他的念头。一定得要个更有学问的人才配做她的丈夫。

“他默默承受了她的拒绝，但心已受到了巨大的伤害——而且越是闷着不说，越是心如刀割。哈丽特再也没有跟他联系。他当初出去闯荡的本意是为了给她一个更好的家，现在既然已失去她，他也就失去了努力的动力，便辞去了农场的工作，回到了母亲的住处。

“他一回到朗普多，就得知哈丽特已经看上了另一个小伙子，是个公路承包商。杰克不得不承认对手确实从举止到学识都比自己强太多。的确，被命运偶然扔到这偏僻山村来的美人再不可能找到比这一位更好的伴侣了，比起前途未卜、能力有限的杰克，他能给她更好的机会。事实太过明显，杰克实在没什么可以责备哈丽特的。

“有一天，杰克偶然看到了一张小纸片上有哈丽特的新恋人的笔迹。字迹行云流水，拼写准确无误，一看就出自惯于同墨水和字典打交道的人的手笔；整个教区都会把这种人称为文化人。杰克脑子里突然想到这个年轻人的书信跟他原来写过的那些可怜巴巴的情书比起来将是多么大的反差，会让他自己的那些字句看起来多么荒谬可笑啊。他懊恼地叹息，希望自己从没给她写过信，心里又猜她是否还保留着他那些一塌糊涂的信。很可能她还留着，他想，因为女人们都有这个习惯，而只要这些信一天还在她手上，他那些质朴笨拙的爱的誓言就有可能会被哈丽特拿出来给她的现任恋人当成笑话讲，或者是被任何碰巧翻到这些信的人嘲笑。

“这个神经脆弱、阴郁的小伙子一想到这些就无法忍受，最后决定让哈丽特把信还给他，既然订婚取消了，他要回那些信也是理所应当的。他花了许多个小时构思、誊抄、再誊抄那封索要信件的便条，写好以后就让人送去她的住处。他派去送信的人捎回了口信，说帕姆利小姐让他带话，她不会放弃本就属于她的东西，并质问他怎么敢这样去打扰她。

“杰克被这回答激怒了，决定自己上门去索要他的信。他挑了一个她肯定在家的时间去，敲了敲门，不顾礼节径直闯了进去；因为虽然哈丽特高高在上，但杰克对她的婶婶帕姆利太太并无敬意可言——她儿子早些时候不过是给他擦鞋的帮工而已。哈丽特在家，这还是她甩了他以后两人第一次见面。他严厉而怨恨地看着她，要求她把信退还给他。

“刚开始，她说他可以把信拿回去，反正她也不稀罕，说着便把信从书桌里拿了出来。然后她瞥了一瞥那一包信最上头的一封，突然改变了主意，没好气地说他的要求实在是太愚蠢了，接着就把那一堆信塞进了书桌上敞开着的她婶婶的工具箱里，上了锁，还带着嘲弄的笑容说她觉得最好还是留着这些信，说不定将来还用得着，可以用来证明她有充分的理由拒绝嫁给他。

“他勃然大怒，‘把信还给我！’他喊，‘这些信是我的！’

“‘不对，’她回答，‘是我的。’

“‘不管是谁的总之我要拿回来！’他说，‘我不想因为自己的字被别人嘲笑。你已经有了新的小伙子，你会给他说你的秘密，讲各种闲话。你会把这些信给他看的！’

“‘有可能哦。’哈丽特大小姐平静又冷淡地回答，就像个没心没肺的女人一样，她也确实是这样的人。

“她的举动简直让他气得发疯，于是他上前一步去抓工具箱，但她抢先一步抓到手里，把它锁到了书桌里，然后转过身一副胜利者的姿态看着他。有一刻他看上去似乎要从她手里把书桌的钥匙夺过来；但他终究忍住了，猛地转身大步走了。

“等他独自一人来到屋外，已经是晚上了，他焦躁不安地走着，想到自己彻头彻尾都被她打败，真是心如针扎。他忍不住想象她把刚才这一幕讲给她的新欢或者熟人听，再跟他们一起嘲笑他急于拿回来的那些写得歪歪扭扭、涂得乱七八糟的信。夜晚一点点过去，他最后执拗地决定，无论付出多少代价也一定要把这些信拿回来。

“等到夜深人静，他从他母亲房子的后门溜出来，钻过花园篱笆，沿着旁边的农田一直来到哈丽特婶婶家后面。据说，那晚月亮特别明亮，月光打在墙上，爬山虎的每一片叶子在月光下都闪闪发光，就像一面面小镜子。熟识多年，杰克对帕姆利太太屋里的陈设了如指掌，就跟熟悉自己家一样。他旁边的后窗是铅条包着小方格玻璃的铰链窗，今天也还用着；而且直到现在，都还是起居室用来采光的两扇窗之一。另一扇在前门，百叶窗紧闭；而后面这一扇却连个窗帘都没有，月光涌进去，房间里家具上的物件从外面都能看得清清楚楚。房间右边是壁炉，你可能还记得；左边放的就是书桌；书桌里是工具箱，他以为是哈丽特的（但其实是她婶婶的），而工具箱里就是他的信。于是，他拿出了小刀，悄无声息地把其中一块玻璃的铅条包边撬下来，取出玻璃，再伸手进去打开窗钻进了房间。房子里所有人——也就是帕姆利太太，哈丽特和一个小女仆——都睡着了。杰克径直走到书桌前，他是这么说的，想看看锁开了没有——通常那个书桌都不会上锁的——但是哈丽特自从那天把信锁进去后就没有打开过。杰克事后说他当时想到她就睡在楼上，对自己无情无义，还嘲笑他和他写的信；而且既然都已经来了就没有回头的余地了。他把刀子的刀片强行插到写字板下面，将那把不牢靠的锁给撬开了；里头正是她白天匆匆塞进去的那个黄檀木的工具箱。现在已经没时间把信从里头拿出来了，他于是把工具箱夹在胳膊底下，关上书桌，设法钻出了房子，把窗子铰链重新闩上，再把玻璃和铅条重新复原。

“温特沿着来时的路回到了他母亲的房子，整个人疲惫不堪，爬上楼就睡了，箱子被他藏了起来，等要把信毁掉的时候再拿出来。第二天一大早他就动手，把箱子拿到他母亲房子后面外建的棚子里。他在灶台边打开了工具箱，开始把他费了那么多心思写成、想起来就无比羞耻的信一封一封烧掉，打算等烧完后把箱子修一修，因为他没有钥匙只好强行开箱以致造成了一点损坏；等修好了还给哈丽特时，里头要再附上一张便条——那将是他写给她的最后一封信——里面将用胜利者的口吻告诉她，她以为自己拒绝把信还给他，他就会屈服于她的反复无常？实在是大错特错了。

“然而当他拿起最后一封信后，着实大吃了一惊。因为在信下头，在箱子底下，还有一堆钱——好几个基尼的金币——‘肯定是哈丽特的零用钱。’他想道。但其实这是帕姆利太太的。他还没来得及从这发现所产生的不安中醒过神来，就听到有脚步声从房子过道向他所在的外棚走来。他急忙把箱子连同里头的东西塞到棚子里堆着的柴火下头去；但他已经被发现了。两个警察进了棚子，在他跪在地上藏箱子和里头东西的时候把他抓了个现行。他们以头一晚闯进帕姆利太太家里盗窃的罪名逮捕了杰克；还没等他明白怎么回事，他们就把他押在中间，沿着连接村头和这条收费公路的巷子，一路带到了卡斯特桥镇监狱。

“杰克的行为被认定为深夜入室盗窃罪——虽然他本意并非如此——而入室盗窃是重罪，在那个时候是要判死刑的。他从帕姆利太太家后窗出来离开时，有目击者看到他的影子映在月光照亮的墙上；工具箱和钱都在他手里找到；而撬开的书桌的锁、动过的玻璃窗等作为旁证也已足够。他辩解说他进去只是想拿回他的信，他认为这些信本该属于他。我不知道他的这些抗辩，如果再加上其他一些证据，能不能对他有利；但是唯一能为他做证的人就只有哈丽特，可她则完全听从了她婶婶的摆布。她的婶婶一心一意要杰克·温特的命。帕姆利太太等候多时的机会终于来了，她终于可以对那个先抢走了她的恋人，又害她心肝宝贝儿子丧了命的女人进行报复了。等到巡回法庭审判周到来时，杰克不得不接受审判，而哈丽特根本没有出庭，于是案件便如常审理，帕姆利太太证实了杰克入室盗窃的种种细节。不知道如果杰克哀求她的话，哈丽特是否会来；也许出于怜悯她会愿意来，但是杰克的自尊心让他不愿意去求一个抛弃了他的女子；他没有去打扰她。审判很快就结束了，他被判了死刑。

“年轻的杰克上绞架的那天是三月里一个寒冷的灰蒙蒙的礼拜六。他的身材还像个男孩一样瘦削纤弱，他们怕他上了绞架后自己的体重不够让颈椎断裂，出于怜悯便不得不给他戴上监狱里最重的脚镣。这脚镣太重，他几乎都没有力气爬上绞刑台的抽板。[10]在那个时候，政府对于死刑犯人的尸体必须葬在监狱附近还没有严格要求，在他可怜的母亲苦苦哀求下，他的尸体被允许领回家。全教区的人那天傍晚都在门前等着她带他回来。我那时候还是个小女孩，我还记得自己站在母亲身边。快八点钟的时候，在寒冷明亮的星光下，我们站在门前石子路上侧耳倾听，听到一辆马车从大路方向隐约传来的吱吱呀呀的声音。马车下到山谷里，声音就消失了。等它缓缓走下一个长长的斜坡时，声音又出现了。然后它就进了朗普多。当天晚上，棺材就放在钟楼里，第二天是礼拜天，我们在早课和晚课的间隙里把他下葬了。当天下午牧师为他进行了葬礼祷告，挑选的经文是，‘这人是他母亲独生的儿子，他母亲又是寡妇。’[11]……是的，那真是个残酷的年代啊！

“至于哈丽特，她和她的恋人在合适的时候就结婚了。不过据说她过得并不开心。由于她跟不幸的杰克之间的纠葛，她和丈夫发现他们已经没法在朗普多好好过日子了，所以就搬去了一个很远的小城，之后再没听说他们的消息。帕姆利太太很快也发现自己最好还是搬去他们那里比较好。这位移居海外的绅士记忆中那个眼睛黝黑，憔悴苍老的温特太太，你们都能猜到，自然就是这个故事里的温特太太。我还清楚地记得她是多么孤单，小孩子们又是如何惧怕她，她如何一直离群索居不同其他人往来，虽然她活了很久很久。”

“朗普多既有欢乐祥和的故事，也有伤心痛苦的经历啊。”拉克兰先生感叹说。

“是的，是的。不过我要感恩地说像那样的经历毕竟不多，虽然我们的生活总是好坏参半。”

“我想起了乔治·歪山——他是那种名声不好的人，我因为工作的原因颇为了解。”登记员评论说，看来他也想要讲个故事。

“我听说过他小时候上学时干过的一些事。”

“是的，歪脖子小树大了也长不直——当然，他倒是没有干什么伤天害理的事，但是有几次差点就被罚去做劳役；还有一次则是当贼反被贼坑啦。”

偷鸡不成蚀把米的乔治·歪山

“有一天，”登记员接着说，“集市刚刚散场，乔治骑着一匹摇摇欲坠的老马慢慢晃出梅尔切斯特，突然看到前面有一个相貌堂堂的年轻农夫骑马出镇，两人同一个方向，他骑的马强壮矫健，要说值钱的话，至少值五十个基尼。在爬上比塞特小丘的时候，乔治特意赶上了年轻的农夫。两人开始闲聊打发时间；乔治先是聊起路况，然后便同那位骑着良驹的陌生人开始了非常友善的交谈。农夫一开始并不想跟乔治多说，但是慢慢地态度也变得友好起来——就跟乔治对他一样热情了。他告诉歪山他之前在梅尔切斯特集市上办了点事，晚上要去肖茨福特广场，第二天好到卡斯特桥集市去。等到了木桉树酒馆他们停下来让马饮食歇息，顺便一起喝两杯。这样两人便越发亲近，接着又继续上路了。他们还没到肖茨福特的时候天突然下起雨了，正巧两人经过特朗翠脊村，天色已晚，乔治于是劝农夫当晚就别再赶路了，淋多了雨肯定会感冒的。至于他自己，听说这个客栈还挺不错，他打算就在这里住下了。年轻的农夫最后也决定就在那里过夜，两人下马进了客栈，美美地一起吃了顿晚餐，聊着各自的闲话，就跟相识多年的老友一般亲热。到了该休息的时候，两人感情已经好得打算同住一间房了。乔治·歪山让老板给了他们一间两床双人间，然后就一起上楼去了。

“两人睡觉前还在房间里继续天南海北地东拉西扯，后来说着说着有意无意地就聊到了乔装易容、交换衣服上头去了。农夫告诉乔治，他经常听到有人这么干；但是歪山说他从没听过有这样的伎俩；很快，年轻的农夫就睡熟了。

“第二天清晨，高个子的年轻农夫还在熟睡中（我是照别人跟我讲这个故事时的原话讲的），诚实的乔治便轻手轻脚地爬下床，穿上了农夫的衣服，口袋里还有农夫的钱。乔治想弄到手的主要是农夫光鲜的衣服和矫健的骏马，因为昨天他在集市上干了桩小小的交易，为了不被别人轻易认出来，很希望能换套行头；但他的欲望还是有界限的，他不打算把他年轻朋友的钱也拿走，最多只拿够付房钱的数额就行了。他于是从里面抽出了相应的钱数，把剩下的钱，连带钱包放在房间的桌上，然后下楼去了。客栈的伙计并没有特别注意顾客的长相，一大早起来的一两个人便把乔治当成了农夫；等他很大方地付了房钱，然后说得马上出发时，没人对他走到农夫的马前给马上鞍表示异议；于是他骑上马，很自然地走掉了。

“大约半个小时后年轻的农夫醒过来了，看到对面床上的朋友乔治穿着不属于自己的衣服离开了，还把又脏又破的衣服好心地留给了他。他坐起身，没有急着起床去叫人，而是琢磨了一会儿。‘钱，钱没了，’他自言自语，‘这太糟了。不过衣服也没了。’

“他接着抬起眼睛，看到了桌上的钱，或者说大部分的钱，都留下来了。

“‘哈！哈！哈！’他欢呼起来，然后在屋里手舞足蹈，‘哈！哈！哈！’他又笑起来，对着刮脸镜子和黄铜烛台里的自己露出灿烂的笑容；然后朝着四面八方挥舞胳膊，好像在进行舞剑操练一样。

“等他穿上乔治的衣服下楼时，看上去似乎并不在意别人把他认成乔治；甚至当他看到他的好马被换成了一匹劣马时，也没打算叫唤。客栈的人告诉他，他的朋友已经付过了房钱，他看起来非常高兴，不等早餐端上来就骑上乔治的马离开了；他没有走大路，而是挑了条最近的小路，不知道乔治之前也是走的这条路。

“他以乔治·歪山的身份骑马走了差不多两英里，那里小路突然转了个大弯，然后他就撞见两个村警扭着一个男子，男子正拼命挣扎。那正是穿走了他的衣服、牵走了他的马的朋友乔治。不过年轻的农夫并没有急着冲上去要回他的财物；要不是他已经被人看到了，他大概会打马往旁边的树林里走。

“‘帮忙，帮忙，快来帮忙啊！以国王的名义！’两个警察大喊。

“农夫没办法，只好骑马走上前去。‘咋回事儿？’他问，尽量装得非常镇定。

“‘逃兵——他是个逃兵！’他们喊，‘他是要给军事法庭审判，肯定要挨枪子儿的。他几天以前从切尔滕纳姆骑兵营跑出来了，一直被搜查队追踪，但是到处都找不到他。我们跟他们说了，如果我们抓到他，就把他扭送到他们那儿去。这个浑蛋从军营跑出来的第二天，就遇到一个受人尊敬的农场主，他在酒馆里把人家灌醉了，哄那农场主说他很有军人的气质，骗人家跟他交换了衣服，说农场主穿上军装肯定帅得很。农场主就真的干了。然后逃兵就说他要去跟老板娘开个玩笑，看下他穿农场主这一身衣服她还认不认得出来，然后就离开了房间。他再也没有回来，农场主乔利斯发现自己穿着士兵的衣服，自己口袋里头的钱没有了，等他去马厩一看，马也不见咯。’

“‘太卑鄙无耻了！’穿着乔治衣服的年轻人说，然后指指乔治，‘那个流氓无赖就是他吗？’

“‘不是！不是！’乔治大喊，在逃兵这件事上面他的确是清白无辜的，‘他才是那个逃兵！就是他穿了农夫乔利斯的衣服，他跟我睡在一个房间里头，然后故意说起换衣服这个话题，然后我才想到在他睡醒以前穿他的衣服的。他穿的是我的衣服！’

“‘唉哟，你们听到没有？’高个子年轻人对着警察抱怨道，‘他还随便栽赃给他碰到的第一个无辜的人！军爷，我给你说——你这样做没用！’

“‘就是，就是！这样做没用！’两个警察应和道，‘还敢厚颜无耻栽赃别人，我们就差没有当场抓到你！哎呀，感谢上帝，我们总算把手铐给他铐上了。’

“‘终于铐上了，感谢上帝，’高个子年轻人说，‘好吧，我要继续赶路啦。祝你们押送犯人好运！’他随即以胯下那匹疲惫羸弱的马能达到的最快速度离开了。

“警察们把被铐住的乔治押在中间，牵着马朝另一个方向大步前进，他们在村里跟派来追逃兵的军营护卫队交谈过，现在要把乔治送到那儿去，乔治一路哼哼：‘我要挨抢子儿咯！我要挨抢子儿咯！’他们走了差不多一英里的时候迎面碰上了护卫队。

“‘嘿！你们好哇！’带头的警察招呼道。

“‘嘿！你们也好！’领队的下士回答。

“‘我们抓到你们要找的人啦。’警察说。

“‘在哪儿？’下士问。

“‘这儿，在我们两个中间的就是，’警察回答，‘你们没认出来，因为他没穿制服。’

“下士仔仔细细打量了一遍乔治，然后摇摇头，说他不是那个逃兵。

“‘但是你们的逃兵跟农夫乔利斯换了衣服，还偷了他的马。你们看，衣服和马都在他这儿！’

“‘这个不是我们要找的人，’士兵们说，‘我们要找的那个是个高个子年轻人，右边脸上有一颗痣，行动起来很有军人风范，这个人明显没有。’

“‘我当时就跟这两位公差大人说是另外那个人！’乔治辩解，‘他们就是不肯相信我！’

“事实很明显了，那个高个子年轻人才是逃跑的骑兵，不是乔治·歪山——农夫乔利斯后来也赶到现场，证实了这一点。由于乔治犯下的罪行是抢了个强盗，所以量刑比较轻。骑兵营的那位逃兵后来一直没有被抓到。连续两次换装给了他最大的掩护让他顺利逃脱；不过他把乔治的马丢在了几英里之外，因为他后来发现骑着这可怜的畜生是成事不足败事有余。”

从国外回来的客人似乎对朗普多的那些问题人物和他们的奇闻逸事兴趣不大，倒是更想了解那些普通人家的日常生活，虽然同车的当地人显然更喜欢前者。他现在第一次打听起了年轻的异性——或者说他离开故乡那会儿还年轻的异性。但是他的同车伙伴们坚持认为奇闻比家常更有讲述的价值，不愿跟他多谈那些来来去去的普通人的简单历史。他们又问他还记不记得奈蒂·萨金特。

“奈蒂·萨金特——是的，我确实记得有这么个人。如果儿时的记忆没错的话，我走的时候她还是个年轻姑娘，跟她叔叔住在一起，是吧？”

“就是她没错。她可是个人物啊，先生。倒不是说她有多坏，你知道，但她绝对啥都做得出来。你应该听听她是如何得到她房子的公簿持有权的。德先生，你说是不是？”

“他应该听一听。”那位怀才不遇的老画家回答。

“那你来讲给他听嘛，德先生。这个故事你讲最合适了，你比我们更了解和法律有关的东西。”

德先生谦虚了一下，然后就开始讲述起来。

奈蒂·萨金特续租记

“奈蒂一直跟她叔叔住在灌木林旁边那座孤零零的房子里，她是个个子高挑、机灵活泼的年轻姑娘。啊，我还清楚地记得她那时候一头黑发，眼睛神采飞扬，想要嘲弄人的时候会把小嘴淘气地噘起来。总之，她刚一成年就已经有许多追求者，慢慢到后来，来了个追求者——你可能没听说过这个人——叫作贾斯帕·克里夫，虽然她应该有很多更好的选择，但她偏偏就喜欢上了这个人，最后就非贾斯帕不可了。那是个自私自利的主，脑子里盘算最多的不是他要做什么，而是他做这事能得到什么。他眼睛看着奈蒂，心里头想的却是她叔叔的房子。当然他也不是一点都不喜欢她——这个我还是承认的。

“这座房子是她祖父的祖父建的，有一个花园和一小块地，是按从前的公簿持有制享有终身持有权的，[12]已经持有好几代了。她叔叔是这块土地的最后一个持有人，一旦死了，假如没有补入新持有人，房子和地就会落入庄园领主的手中。当然要续约并不难——只要交一小笔‘入地费’，他们是这么叫的，大约几个英镑，他便有权根据庄园的习惯做法更新租契；庄园主也不能阻止他这样做。

“那么，他能给自己的侄女也是他唯一的亲人提供的最好供养当然就是让她拥有这个房子的确定继承权了；奈蒂的叔叔当然应该确保按时更新租契，因为假如他不缴纳新的入地费，那么这土地的最后一个持有人去世之后，土地就会被没收；而且庄园领主——乡绅，也非常渴望把房子和地给收回来。每个礼拜天，当老头走进教堂，经过乡绅的座席前时，乡绅都会说：‘他的膝盖更颤巍巍了，他的背又驼了几分——而且他还没有申请重新入地权，哈哈！我终于可以把我宅子附近的那个角落清理个干净啦！’

“现在回头想想，老萨金特居然一直那么拖拖拉拉，真是太不寻常了，不过有的人就是这样。于是一周又一周，他不断拖延着不肯去乡绅经理人的办公室交入地费，还自顾自地说：‘下个集市日我会比现在多点空闲去办。’不过最大的问题其实是因为他很不喜欢贾斯帕·克里夫，贾斯帕·克里夫却不停地催奈蒂，奈蒂又不停地催她的叔叔，所以老头就越发不愿更新地契，能拖多久是多久，故意要恶心恶心那个唯利是图的小子。到后来老萨金特生病了，贾斯帕再也忍不住了：他自己把入地费的钱筹好了，交给奈蒂，然后非常直截了当跟她摊牌。

“‘你跟你叔叔应该要晓得好歹。你最好再催紧一点。钱由我来出，要是你让房子和地从你手里头丢了，我是不会娶你的，打死都不会！这种事都办不好的女人，根本不配找个老公。’

“姑娘忧心忡忡地拿着钱回到家，告诉她叔叔假如没有房子，她就没有丈夫了。老萨金特先生对那笔钱呸呸地痛骂了一阵，本来就没多少钱他又不是出不起；但是他这次确实开始重视这件事了，因为他看出来她是铁了心要嫁给贾斯帕，而他不想让她伤心。乡绅发现萨金特最终还是开始行动了，大为光火，但又不好反对，只好准备好所需要的文书（在这个庄园，公簿持有农们都有书面的文件作为持地凭证，有的庄园是没有的）。由于老萨金特现在身体太虚弱，没法上门去找经理人，所以契约文书就由经理人带到他这里来，将一份乡绅已签过字的交给他作为交过入地费的收据；另一份则让老萨金特签字后带回给乡绅。

“经理人说好了五点钟上门来拜访老萨金特将此事办妥，奈蒂把钱放到桌子抽屉里以方便拿取。她在放钱时突然听到她叔叔发出了微弱的喊声，转过头一看，发现他从坐的椅子里向前栽倒了。她上前扶起他，发现他已经昏迷，而且之后便一直不省人事。无论是用药还是兴奋剂都没法再把他唤醒。之前医生告诉过她，他可能会就这么去了，现在看来是他的大限已到。她还没来得及去找医生，他的脸和四肢就已变得冰冷而灰白，她明白找医生也没用了。他已经彻底断气了。

“奈蒂的思维一片混乱，但她慢慢想起了自己的处境，情况可谓极度严峻。这个房子、花园和土地全都没了——再过几个小时——随之而去的还有她的家和她的恋人。她不愿相信贾斯帕真的会卑劣到兑现他在失去耐心之下说出的话；但是她想起来还是不寒而栗。她叔叔反正都活了这么久了，为什么不再多活几个小时呢？现在已经三点多了；五点钟经理人就会上门来，如果一切顺利的话，五点十分的时候，这个房子和地契就将在她和贾斯帕有生之年都被牢牢地握在手中，因为这次交了入地费后，终身持有公簿的三个名字里会把她和贾斯帕两个人的名字加上。那个该死的乡绅这次终于可以把这块地拿回手里，一定乐坏了吧！他其实并不需要这块地，只是本性使然地讨厌这些小块小块的公簿持有、租赁持有和自由持有地，就像是他那风景旖旎、平静如镜的地产海洋上有一个个独立的小岛一般。

“突然，奈蒂心中想到了一个办法，可以在她叔叔毫不知情的情况下达成她的目的。那是在十二月一个阴沉的下午，她计划的第一步是——别人是这么说的，我自己觉得很有道理，不用怀疑——”

“绝对是真的，”克里斯托弗·屯克证实说，“我那时候正好路过。”

“她计划的第一步是先把大门锁好，确保不会被人打扰。接着她便把她叔叔的那张不大但很沉的橡木书桌移到壁炉前，然后她走到叔叔的尸体前，他还像死时一样坐在椅子上——那是个有填充垫子的扶手椅，下面有轮子，座椅很高，别人是这么说的——她于是把她叔叔连人带椅子推到桌子那儿，让他背对着窗，摆出低头看着前面那个橡木书桌的姿势。我打小就知道那张橡木书桌了，跟我自己家里的家具一样熟悉。她把大开本的家庭圣经打开放在桌上摆在他面前，让他的食指指着那一页；然后她把他的眼皮撑开一些，再戴上他的老花镜，这样从背后看上去，所有人都会以为他在看经书。接下来她把门锁打开，坐了下来；等天色暗下来后，她点亮了一根蜡烛，放在桌上的书旁。

“大家可以想象一下她是怎么熬过那段时间的。等经理人到了，那一声敲门声响起时，她差点吓个半死——反正别人是这么跟我说的。奈蒂立刻起身去开了门。

“‘先生，非常抱歉，’她轻言细语地说，‘我叔叔今天晚上不太舒服，恐怕他不能见您了。’

“‘哼嗯！——好得很哪！’经理人说，‘所以我大老远跑过来办这件芝麻大的事，结果还白跑一趟！’

“‘哦不，先生——我希望您没有白跑一趟，’奈蒂说，‘我想新租约的授予事宜还是可以一样照办的吧？’

“‘照办？当然不行。他必须缴纳续约的钱，然后当着我的面在文书上签字。’

“她看上去忧心忡忡。‘叔叔一直对法律方面的事情特别害怕，’她说，‘所以，您也知道，他就一直把这件事拖了一年又一年。今天他这个样子，我真怕会把他给吓坏了。我跟他说您很快就要来找他签字的时候，他吓得仅剩的三颗牙都在打战。他一直都很恐惧那些经理人呀，上门来收租的呀，诸如此类的。’

“‘可怜的老人家——我对此很遗憾。但是，这件事还是办不成，除非我亲自看着他，见证他签字才行。’

“‘先生，能不能您看着他签字，但是他却看不到您呢？我就安慰他，说您对见证方式的要求没那么严格，不打算进去打扰他。这样只要您在场看着他签字就应该够了吧？他已经是个缩成一团、抖抖索索的老人家了，如果您这样做的话，真是对他莫大的体贴和照顾了。’

“‘当着我的面就可以了，那是当然——我来的目的就是这个。但是他不看到我，我怎么能当目击证人呢？’

“‘哦，先生，是这样的。请跟我到这儿来。’她带他往左边走了几码远，来到了会客室窗对面。百叶窗被特意拉起来了，烛光照到了花园的灌木丛上。经理人看得到屋内靠另一头的地方，老人的后脑勺和头的一侧、肩膀和一只手臂，老人坐在桌前，面前放着书和蜡烛，鼻子上还架着老花镜，就像她之前摆放的那样。

“‘先生，您看，他正在读圣经呢。’她说，声音异常柔顺。

“‘看到了。我一直以为他对于宗教之类的事情不怎么上心。’

“‘他一直都很喜欢看圣经呢，’奈蒂向他保证说，‘虽然我觉得他现在看着看着在打盹儿了。当然了，对一位老人家，尤其是在他身体还不太舒服的时候，这也是很正常的事。先生，您可不可以就站在这里看他签字呢？看他现在这么虚弱。’

“‘好吧，’经理人说，点燃了一根雪茄。‘你应该已经准备好了入地费吧，那点微不足道的钱？’

“‘是的，’奈蒂说，‘我这就拿出来。’她把钱取出来，用纸包好递给经理人。他点过数后，从胸袋里取出了两张珍贵的羊皮纸文书，把其中一张递给她让她拿过去签字。

“‘叔叔的手有一点用不上力了，’她说，‘再加上他现在又有点打盹，迷迷糊糊的，我真不知道他签出来的字会是什么样子呢。’

“‘无所谓，只要他签字就行。’

“‘我能扶着他的手吗？’

“‘行，扶着他的手吧，姑娘——那样就可以了。’

“奈蒂又进了房子，经理人继续在窗外抽烟。接下来就到了奈蒂这场演出最高难度的部分啦。经理人看见她把墨水瓶放到她叔叔面前，轻轻碰了碰他的手肘，像是在唤醒他，又对他说了几句话，再把契约展开放在了他面前；她在纸上指了指，告诉他该在哪里签字，然后把笔蘸好墨水，放进他的手里。在扶着他的手的时候，她巧妙地站到了他的身后，这样经理人便只能看到一小部分老人的头以及她扶着的手；但是他总算是亲眼看到老人的手在文件上面签上了自己的名字。等一切完毕后，她立刻拿着文件走出来交给经理人，经理人借着会客室窗的灯光签上自己的名字作为见证人。然后他便把乡绅签过字的那份契约交给她，离开了。第二天早上，奈蒂告诉大家她叔叔死在床上了。”

“她肯定是给他脱了衣服，再把他放到床上去的。”

“是的，肯定是。哎，我跟你说，这姑娘可真是够有胆量的！总之，长话短说，她就这样重新拿到了房子和土地，从严格意义上来说，本来已经不属于她了。得到了这些之后，她也就顺利得到了一个丈夫。

“常言道，善恶皆有报。奈蒂用她的足智多谋赢得了贾斯帕，结果结婚不过两年他就开始揍她——倒不是很厉害，也就是打了她几巴掌，但已足够让她大为恼怒，于是她就向邻居哭诉自己当初费尽心机得到他，结果现在却如此痛苦，真是悔不当初。等老乡绅死了以后，他的儿子继承了庄园，奈蒂的所作所为开始传了开来。不过奈蒂是个年轻漂亮的女人，庄园主的儿子那时也是个年轻英俊的小伙子，而且比他父亲要开明，并不介意小块土地持有农的存在；所以他一直没有去起诉她。”

谈话声渐渐平息下去，很快马车下了山坡，靠近了山脚下稀稀落落的村子。到了村里，乘客们一个接一个在自家门前下车了。归国的游子来到村里的客栈，要了一张床，简单吃过饭，便出发去看他早年熟悉的地方。虽然月亮刚升起，光芒如潮水般洒落在大地上，但身处实地，周遭的一切却远不如他在两千英里之外时，在心中想象的那般动人。一个彻头彻尾的外国人看到这样一个古老地区的古老村落会觉得特别有吸引力；但他尚留着儿时的记忆，因此反而有了更高的期待，现下便觉得不足了。他一直走啊走，看看这家的烟囱，那处的白墙，最后来到了教堂的墓地，走了进去。

墓碑被月光照得发白，很容易辨认上面的字。在这里，拉克兰第一次感觉到自己是这与之阔别了三十五年的乡村社区的一员。在沙利特家旁边的，是达斯家的墓地，另外一边是保利家，普里威特家，还有萨金特家，以及其他一些他才听过的名字；这些名字他记得甚至比另外那些更牢：吉克斯家，克罗斯家，耐茨家和欧德家。毫无疑问，这些家族或者其中一些，还有后人在世；但是对他来讲，他们都已经是陌生人了。回到这里，他心中并没有油然生起一种落叶归根的感觉；相反，他发现自己反倒好像肩负起了要从零开始，重新让自己在此立足的责任，就跟他从未来过此处，人们也从不认识他一样。时光并未屈尊打算令他欢欣，故土也并未打算接纳他的致敬。

接下来的几天，人们见到拉克兰先生的身影在客栈出现，在村子正街晃荡，在上朗普多的田野和土地里徘徊，然后，就像幽灵一般，又无声无息地消失了。他告诉过一些村民他这次回来的直接目的——看看这个地方，和当地居民聊聊天——已经达成了。然而他的最终目的——回到此地度过余生——也许永远都不会执行了。他上次来访已经是十二到十五年前的事了，从那以后他再也没有出现过。

一八九一年三月

[1]维多利亚时期农村劳动人口的年收入平均约为二十五英镑，月收入约二英镑，折合四十先令。每幅画几个先令对中产阶级来说非常廉价，但对农村劳动者来说价格并不算低。

[2]英国国教中把教区牧师的职位称为“圣职”（Living）。副牧师（Curate）是教区牧师聘用的助手，未获圣职，收入很低。有些副牧师要等待很长时间才能获得圣职，有足够的收入可以娶妻成家。

[3]这是多塞特流传的一首民歌，讲述一个裁缝晚上喝醉了酒，想勾引姑娘，于是穿上了姑娘的裙子跳舞逗乐，没想到反被姑娘趁机穿上他的裤子，偷走了他的手表和钱包的故事。在许多民歌中，裁缝都是被取笑的对象。

[4]引自《圣经·旧约·撒母耳记下》第一章第二十三节，大卫作哀歌祭奠扫罗和他的儿子约拿单：“扫罗和约拿单，活时相悦相爱，死时也不分离。”此处关于两个一半结合成完美的整体的典故出自柏拉图的《会饮篇》。根据古希腊传说，人生来原本有四只胳膊、四条腿、一个脑袋、两张脸。宙斯畏惧人的力量，将人劈成两半，他们终其一生都在寻觅自己的另一半，倘若寻到，便会坠入爱河，永远不分离。

[5]仲夏节（Midsummer）最早是为纪念夏至日而设，后附会为纪念基督教施洗者约翰的生日（六月二十四日）。教皇格里高利十三世为矫正日历的偏差，令人重新编制了更准确的格里高利日历，即现在俗称的公历，于一五八二年颁布。根据新公历，仲夏夜便改到了七月四日庆祝。由于人们不愿接受新的日期，于是仍按照原来的日子庆祝，并在节日前加上了“旧”字。旧仲夏夜（Old Midsummer's Eve）即旧仲夏节前夜，六月二十三日晚上举行庆祝活动。根据英国的传说，人们会在这个晚上有奇异的经历，可能进入魔幻世界。

[6]猎狐运动始于十六世纪的英格兰。由于狐狸对农民的庄稼和畜禽造成危害，因此猎狐被认为是一种驱除害兽的有效办法。到了斯图亚特王朝时期，猎狐开始在王公贵族中大规模流行起来，在十八、十九世纪成为乡绅阶层最喜爱的运动。猎狐活动一般在秋天进行，参加猎狐的“猎手”们一大清早就集合出发，猎犬被带到狐狸的巢穴，以记住狐狸的气味，然后“猎手”们把狐狸从洞穴里驱赶出来，猎犬便开始循着气味追逐这只狐狸。“猎手”们骑着马跟在猎犬后面。狐狸到最后跑得筋疲力尽时，只能在地上刨洞躲起来。这时对这只狐狸的围猎就算结束。猎犬把这只躲起来的狐狸从地洞里赶出来，由专人射杀；如果在地面被猎犬抓住，则会被头犬咬住咽喉窒息而死。二〇〇二年英国政府颁布禁令，禁止在苏格兰猎狐，二〇〇四年又禁止在英格兰和威尔士地区带犬猎狐。

[7]《圣经·旧约·传道书》第一章第三节：“凡事皆有定期，天下万物都有定时。”

[8]哈代于一八七二年匿名发表的第二部长篇小说《绿荫树下》就是以梅尔斯托克教堂唱诗班为背景，讲述了迪克·杜伊与学校新来的女教师范茜·德之间的爱情故事。

[9]索多玛和蛾摩拉（Sodom and Gomorrah），出自《圣经·旧约·创世记》，是摩押平原上的两个城。据第十八、十九章记载，两个城的人因为罪孽深重，被耶和华降天火全部毁灭。

[10]在英国实行的绞刑，犯人脖子上套上吊绳后，把脚下一块可抽动的木板抽开，犯人身体落下时颈椎会断裂，导致窒息和脑部贫血，几分钟内便会死亡。假如颈椎不断，犯人死亡过程将十分缓慢且痛苦。故而给杰克戴上脚镣被说成“出于怜悯”。

[11]引自《圣经·新约·路加福音》第七章第十二节，这一章讲述耶稣令拿因城寡妇之子复活的故事，正好同本故事里的结局相反。

[12]公簿持有是十六、十七世纪英国主要的土地持有形式，租种者向庄园领主租地时，在庄园法庭取得一份文书记录副本，作为其领有份地的契约凭证。公簿持有农根据种类不同，分为可继承持有（租种土地者死后，其后代享有直接继承的权利，租期属于无限期）、终身持有（土地由指定人来继承，被指定的人可以终身保有土地，通常是三人，且是佃户的家属。三人中的最末一个死亡之后，田地就复归庄园主。不过，通常当三人中有一人死亡时，其他两人可以和领主商量补进一个新人，但必须为此付一笔入地费）和定期持有（通常为十二至二十一年，到期后可通过缴纳更新地契费延长租期）。这一制度到十七世纪开始转型为自由持有制和契约租借制，到十九世纪后彻底消失。威塞克斯属于比较落后的英格兰乡村，因此在文中，尽管已经是十九世纪上半叶，但公簿持有制依然还在生效。

西巡路上

一

这位扰乱了下文所描述的两位女子平静生活的男子——顺便说一句，无论从哪个角度看，他都不是什么大人物——第一次认识她们是在十月的一个傍晚，在梅尔切斯特镇。他先是站在围庭里，面前高高的塔楼与锥形尖顶在潮湿又平整的草地上拔地而起；他徒劳地试图在黑暗中一窥这全英格兰最统一的中世纪建筑群落的风貌。[1]他站在那里，更多是靠耳朵而非眼睛分辨出教堂的高墙；虽然看不见它们，但有一阵喧闹声从市镇广场沿街传到围庭，再撞上这栋建筑，并清晰地反弹回他的耳朵里。

他决定推迟到次日再来参观这座现已空无一人的宏伟建筑，把注意力转到了喧闹声上去。噪声里混杂着洪亮的汽笛风琴声、咣当咣当的敲锣声、叮叮咚咚的手摇铃声、啪嗒啪嗒的拨浪鼓声，以及人群含糊不清的呼喊声。喧嚣声所在处有一片火红的光笼罩在空中。他朝着那个方向穿过拱门，沿一条笔直的街道，走进了市镇广场。

寻遍全欧洲，他也不一定能找到比眼前反差更强烈的景象。单就色彩与火焰来看，这简直就是在地狱的第八层；[2]但若论欢乐程度，可说是超越了荷马史诗里描绘的天堂。宽敞的广场被帐篷、货摊和其他临时搭建的摊位塞得满满当当，摊位上挂着无数轻油灯，带着烟尘的黄铜色刺目光芒正从这些灯吐出的火舌上升起来。在这片光芒前有数十个人影，差不多都只能看见轮廓，正前前后后冲、上上下下蹿，或转着圈儿飞，就像是夕阳下飞舞的蚊蚋一般。

他们的动作节奏感极强，简直像是被机器驱动一样。不过很快就看出他们确实是被机器所驱动；这些人影便是乘客，正在荡秋千、坐跷跷板、玩弹跳板，以及乘坐位于最中心的三台蒸汽旋转木马。汽笛风琴的喧闹声正是从那儿发出来的。

年轻人转念一想，辉煌灯火中生气勃勃的人群还是好过黑夜暗影中的建筑。他点燃一根短烟斗，把帽子歪向一侧，一只手插进口袋里，好让自己跟新环境显得更融洽一些，然后走近那台最大、乘客最多的“蒸汽马戏团”，旋转木马的老板是这么称呼它们的。这台“马戏团”做工精美绝伦，现在正在全力旋转。骑手们围绕着汽笛风琴，随着奏出的乐曲旋转着，铜管的喇叭口正对着年轻男子。跟着机器旋转的还有以不同角度安装的长长的玻璃镜子，像万花筒一般把旋转的人和摇动的木马投射到他的眼中。

现在可以看出他跟在场的大部分人都不一样。这是个很绅士的年轻人，是只有在大城市，特别是伦敦，才会见到的一类人。身形秀美，穿着虽不时髦却很得体，看上去应该是专业人士阶层；从相貌上看，他曲线柔和、非常俊美，完全不是那种无聊乏味又务实的人。说实在的，有些人可能会觉得他不算是典型的中产阶级男性；在这个世纪，卑鄙无耻、野心勃勃才是主流的追求，而且已然取代了爱情在过去的宝贵地位。

旋转的人影在他眼前经过，带着出乎意料的祥和与优雅；本来这些人平日的举止根本谈不上祥和与优雅。经过精巧的设计，可说是旋转木马设计史上的巨大成就与完美之作，每一匹木马被赋予的动作——奔腾跃起或降落——的时间都掌握得刚刚好：每一对骏马中一匹在准备起跳时，另一匹则在顶端俯冲。这是我们这个时代最令人欢欣的假日游戏；这种跑马般的起起伏伏让乘客们都深深着迷。这些人中最小的只有六岁，最大的已有六十岁了，中间各个年龄都有。乍一看很难看清某个具体的人，不过慢慢地，这位旁观者的目光逐渐落在了旋转着的几个漂亮姑娘中最漂亮的那个身上。

不是最开始吸引他的穿浅色上衣戴浅色帽子的那个。不，应该是那个穿黑色披肩、灰色裙子、戴浅色手套和——不，也不是她，是她后头的那个；她穿着大红裙子、深色上衣，戴着棕色帽子和手套。没错，最漂亮的姑娘就是她。

最终选定这一个之后，无所事事的旁观者便抓住每一次她划过他视野的短暂时机细细观察她。她除了骑马之外已经浑然忘我：她的面容带着沉浸在狂喜的梦幻中的表情；这一刻她忘记了自己的年龄、过往、相貌，也不记得自己的种种烦忧。而他本人则满怀时下流行的情绪——朦胧的惆怅与抑郁，眼见这年轻鲜活的生命如此快活如同身在天堂，顿觉神清气爽。

他担心藏在这亮闪闪的洛可可式机器背后那个脏兮兮的添煤工会觉得时间已到，这批客人乘坐的时间已值回一个便士的票价，然后毫不留情把整个蒸汽机，连同木马、镜子、小号、锣鼓、铙钹等等都停下来；于是他等待着她的每一次出现，中间那些身影则漫不经心一瞥而过，包括两个相貌逊色得多的姑娘、一个带着孩子的老妇人、两个少年、一对新婚夫妇、叼着陶土烟斗的老头、一个戴着戒指的英俊小伙、坐在战车里的年轻淑女们、两个熟手木匠，等等，直到他心仪的那位乡村美人随后再次出现。他从未见过比这更美的自然造物，每转一圈她就勾起他更深的情绪。接着木马停了下来，乘客们的叹息声清晰可闻。

他绕到她可能会下马的位置去，但她却在座位上没动。空了的马鞍上慢慢又被新来的人填满，看来她是想要再坐一轮。年轻人走到她的坐骑旁，友善地问她玩得是否开心。

“哦，是的！”她眉飞色舞地回答，“我有生以来从没有过这样的感觉呢！”

跟她搭话并不难。她生性毫不拘谨——太过不拘谨了，加上涉世未深，还不懂得怎样巧妙地有所保留；稍加哄劝，她便欣然与他对答起来。她来自大平原上的一个小村庄，[3]现在居住在梅尔切斯特，这是她生平第一次见到蒸汽马戏团，她完全不懂这奇妙的机器是怎么造出来的。她来到城里是应哈汉姆太太的邀请，到她家来接受训练当女仆，假如她能学得会的话。哈汉姆太太是一位年轻女士，出嫁前的闺名是伊迪丝·怀特，住在离她家不远的地方；哈汉姆太太是看着她长大的，因此对她非常和蔼，甚至还不辞劳苦亲自教她读书写字。哈汉姆太太是她在这个世界上唯一的朋友，还没有孩子，所以总是要她做伴而不要其他人，虽然她才刚来不久。放任她几乎是想做什么就做什么，只要她开口要求，就可以随时放假。这位仁慈的年轻夫人的丈夫是镇上一位富有的红酒商，不过哈汉姆太太并不怎么喜欢他。白天里从现在谈话的位置就能看到他们家的房子。比起偏僻的乡下，她更喜欢梅尔切斯特；下个礼拜天她会有一顶新帽子啦，要花十五先令九便士呢。

接着她询问这位新认识的朋友住在何处，他告诉她在伦敦，那座古老而烟雾缭绕的城市。假如要住，就应该住在伦敦；如果不能住在那儿，这辈子简直就白活了。他因为工作原因每年会来威塞克斯两三次；他昨天刚从温顿塞斯特过来，过两天就会去下一个县。有一个原因让他比起城市更喜欢乡下，那就是因为这里有像她这样的姑娘。

说话间那架予人欢乐的机器又开动了，在这个欢快的姑娘眼里，英俊的青年男子、灯火通明人声鼎沸的集市广场、远处的房屋，乃至整个世界都一如之前再次转动起来；在她右手边的镜子里这一切又都在反向旋转，她是固定不动的中心，周围是起起伏伏、绚烂夺目、光怪陆离的宇宙；其间最显眼的便是刚才与她搭话的那个人的身形。每次她转到离他最近的那半边轨道时他们便会微笑着对视，一副会心的表情。那表情在当时并无深意，却常常预示着日后的激情涌动、心痛难耐、分分合合、执迷不悟、儿女成群、做牛做马、心满意足、逆来顺受、心灰意冷。

等木马再次慢下来时他走到她身边，建议她再来一轮。“这次你不用管票钱了，”他说，“我来付吧！”

她笑到眼泪都出来了。

“你笑什么呢，亲爱的？”他问。

“因为——你看起来很体面，一定很有钱，你这样说只是一时兴起！”她回答说。

“哈哈！”年轻人也应声笑起来，同时殷勤地掏出钱，让她再次旋转起来。

当他手持烟斗、身着出门散步时穿戴的粗呢外套和宽边软帽，微笑着站在斑驳的人群中时，谁能想到他就是查尔斯·布拉德福特·雷伊先生呢？他是一名初级律师，在温顿塞斯特念书，又在林肯会馆获得律师资格，[4]现正跟随巡回法庭在西区定期巡回，他的同伴们已去往下一个市镇了，而他因为一桩小仲裁案需在梅尔切斯特做短暂逗留。[5]

二

年轻女孩刚提到的那栋房子在距广场较远的一角，可俯瞰整个广场。这房子看上去颇为气派，占地面积也相当可观，每一层楼都有好些扇窗户。在二楼的一扇窗户后面是一间很大的起居室，窗边坐着一位女士，看起来大约在二十八到三十岁之间。百叶窗尚未拉下，女士手托着腮，漫不经心地看着窗外怪异的景象。屋内没有点灯，但集市广场上耀眼的灯光照进来已足够照亮她的脸。她与其说是美貌，不如说是有吸引力：眼睛黝黑，心思细密，嘴唇娇柔。

一个男人从后面信步走进房间，朝她走来。

“噢，伊迪丝，我没看见你在这里，”他说，“你怎么黑灯瞎火一个人坐在这儿？”

“我在看集市。”女士用慵懒的声音回答。

“噢？每年都有这讨厌的玩意儿！我真希望它能被禁掉。”

“我挺喜欢的。”

“哼嗯。品味这东西是萝卜青菜各有所爱啊。”

出于礼貌他跟着她往窗外打望了片刻，然后又出去了。

几分钟后她打了下铃。

“安娜还没回来吗？”哈汉姆太太问道。

“还没呢，太太。”

“现在这个点儿她该回来了。我本意是只让她出去十分钟的。”

“要不要我出去找她呢，太太？”女仆有些紧张地问。

“不用。没有必要。她是个好孩子，很快就会回来的。”

然而等女仆走开后，哈汉姆太太便站起身进了自己的房间，穿上斗篷、戴上帽子、走下楼去，在楼下遇到了她的丈夫。

“我想去集市上看看，”她说，“再去找找安娜。我已经承诺了要对她负责，所以必须确保她不会出事。她该回来了。你要跟我一起去吗？”

“噢，她不会有事的。我进门的时候看到她坐在那个转来转去的东西上面，跟她的小伙子聊天呢。不过如果你很想让我跟你去的话我就去吧，虽然我恨不得离那儿一百英里远。”

“那你还是离它远点好了。我自己一个人去也没关系的。”

她出了门，走进了广场拥挤的人群中，很快就看到了骑在旋转木马上的安娜。木马一停下来，哈汉姆太太便走上去严厉地说：“安娜，你怎么成了个野姑娘！我只答应让你出来十分钟的！”

安娜一下子懵了，那个起初站在背后的年轻人走上前扶她下了木马。

“请不要责怪她，”他很有礼貌地说，“她之所以逗留这么久全是我的错。她骑马的样子看起来实在太优雅了，所以我就唆使她再多转一会儿。我可以向你保证她非常安全不会有事的。”

“既然这样，那就请你照看好她吧。”哈汉姆太太掉转身欲离开。

但是这会儿想离开却不太容易了。不知道是什么吸引了人群朝着他们后方涌过去；红酒商的妻子被挟裹在其中，跟安娜的新识紧紧贴在了一起动弹不得。他们的脸距离彼此不过几英寸，他的呼吸直吹到她和安娜的脸颊上来。他们只好微笑一下以避免尴尬，但都没开口说话，只是被动地等待着。哈汉姆太太突然感到有男子的手紧握住了她的手指，看看那个年轻人的表情便知道那手是他的，她还知道从安娜所在的位置来看，他一定以为自己握住的是安娜的手。是什么阻止了她，没提醒他弄错了，她也说不清楚。而他还不满足于握住女孩的手，还俏皮地把两根手指悄悄探进了她的手套，放在她掌心里。这个姿势一直保持到人群的压力减弱；但是等到人群逐渐散开，哈汉姆太太能够抽身时，几分钟已经过去了。

“真奇怪，他们是怎么认识的？”她一边往回走一边想，“安娜真的很冒失——而他真是又邪恶又迷人。”

她因这陌生男子的举止和声音，以及他那轻浮而温柔的触摸而有些微微躁动，所以没有立刻回家，而是又转回来，从一个隐蔽的角落观察那一对男女。她还辩解（她跟安娜一样都是感情冲动的人）说无论安娜用了什么办法认识他，这种鼓励都有情可原；他看上去那么绅士，那么迷人，眼睛那么美丽。想到他比自己要年轻好几岁，她不由得长叹一声。

过了许久这一对才离开旋转木马那儿朝哈汉姆太太家门前走去，她能听到年轻人说想送女孩回家。看来，安娜是有了个恋人，而且还是个很痴心的恋人。哈汉姆太太对他颇为好奇。等那对人走近红酒商家门前，这里已经人迹罕至了，两人在一堵墙的阴影里站了一会儿。等他们分开后，安娜继续向门口走去，她的新识则回头穿过广场。

“安娜，”哈汉姆太太走出来，“我一直在看着你呢！我敢肯定那个小伙子在离开前吻了你对吧？”

“呃——”安娜结结巴巴地说，“他说，如果我不介意的话——这对我不会有什么害处，而且，而且，还是对他莫大的恩惠！”

“啊，我就知道！你是今天晚上才认识他的吧？”

“是的，夫人。”

“但是我敢肯定你已经把你的名字和所有底细都告诉他了。”

“他问我的。”

“可他却没有告诉你他的名字和底细。”

“不，夫人，他告诉我了！”安娜骄傲地大声说，“他叫查尔斯·布拉德福特，是伦敦人！”

“很好，假如他是个正经人，我当然不反对你跟他结识，”女主人说道。虽然原则很重要，但她对那个年轻人颇具好感，“不过假如他还想继续跟你来往的话，我就得仔细考虑了。你只不过是个乡下姑娘，这个月才刚来梅尔切斯特，在此之前你从未见过任何一个公职人员，居然有本事俘虏像他这样的城里小伙子！”

“我没有俘虏他。我什么也没做呀。”安娜一脸迷惑地说。

等回了房独自一人时，哈汉姆太太还在想安娜的同伴，他看上去真是个风度翩翩、彬彬有礼的男子。他对她的手的爱抚仿佛有一种魔力；她不禁奇怪他怎么会被那么个姑娘给吸引。

第二天一早，感情丰富的伊迪丝·哈汉姆如常去梅尔切斯特大教堂参加平日礼拜。在晨雾中穿过围庭时，她又一次看见了头天傍晚引起她极大兴趣的男子，他正若有所思地抬头凝望高高耸立的教堂中殿。她刚走进正厅坐下，他也进来了，在她对面的一排座位坐了下来。

他并没有注意到她，但哈汉姆太太不时地对他注目，并愈发不解她那个青涩懵懂的小女仆怎么就入了他的眼。这位女主人几乎跟她的女仆一样，对于“时代末了”的年轻人知之甚少，不然就不会这样大惊小怪了。雷伊把周遭打量了一遍之后就突然起身离开了，并不在意礼拜仪式尚在进行之中；而哈汉姆太太——这位寂寞而善感的人——也对赞美主丧失了兴趣。她多希望自己嫁的是一位懂得怎样谈情说爱的伦敦男子呀，就像这位误打误撞抚摸了她的手的男子，很显然就是个中高手。

三

梅尔切斯特的日程安排很轻松，雷伊只需要出庭几个小时；巡回法庭的下一个开庭市镇在卡斯特桥，那儿没什么工作需要雷伊做，所以他也就没过去。而再下一个市镇要等到下礼拜一才开庭，审判则要等到礼拜二早上。因此正常情况下雷伊应该在礼拜一下午到达后一个小镇；不过事实上直到礼拜三中午他才急匆匆从住处向市镇正街走去，身后随风飞舞摆动的除了他的律师长袍，还有按照最时新的亚述浅浮雕样式做成的层叠鬈曲的银色假发。他虽然进了巡回法庭大厅，但其实却无事可做，便坐在铺着蓝色粗呢台面的桌子后的律师席上，一边削笔，一边想着跟眼前的案子毫无关系的事情。他做了一件始料未及的事——一个星期以前他都不敢相信自己会做出这样的事——想到这儿，他陷入了一种不满与消沉的情绪中。

在集市后第二天，他又设法见到了那位漂亮的乡下少女安娜，并陪她一起出城去参观了旧梅尔切斯特遗址；他对她产生了遏制不住的迷恋，于是整个礼拜天、礼拜一和礼拜二都逗留在梅尔切斯特；在此期间一共哄劝姑娘跟他见面、散步了六七次；在这短短的时间内便得到了她——从身体到心灵。

他猜想大概是因为最近自己在城里独自一人生活太久，才会轻易被激情左右，放纵自己如此对待一个淳朴少女，而她因为涉世未深，一开始就毫无保留地交付自己任由他摆布。他深悔不该因为一时的情欲玩弄她的感情；现在只能希望她不会因为他而一生受苦。

她恳请他再回去看她，苦苦哀求、泣不成声。他答应了她，也打算履行诺言。他不能现在就抛弃她。虽然这种意料之外的交往是有些棘手，但好在两人隔着一百英里——对她这样能力有限的女孩来说就跟隔了一千英里一般——能够有效地避免这段夏日热恋太过影响他的生活；而且当他想勤奋工作的时候，思及她那淳朴的爱，也许能有些反面的好处，让他不必去城里瞎晃找乐子。巡回法庭的工作让他每年有三到四次机会去梅尔切斯特，那个时候他尽可以去看望她。

一开始他并不知道两人这段关系会发展到多深，所以当时情急之下告诉她的是自己的化名，或者说是不完整的名字，倒不是存心要欺骗她。他后来也没有费心跟安娜纠正这个错误，但在离开前他觉得有必要给她留个通讯地址——离他办公室不远的一家文具店，她可以写信寄到那里，收信人就用他名字的缩写“查·布”就可以了。

雷伊按计划返回了伦敦住所，返程途中又经过梅尔切斯特，特意逗留了几个小时，和他迷人的自然之子在一起。回城后他每天过着单调的生活。他和办事处的各个房间大多数时候都被黄褐色的烟雾包围，与外界隔绝开来；等他点亮汽油灯读书写字时，他总觉得自己身处奇境之中，不由得望着灯上的火焰，翻来覆去想的都是梅尔切斯特的那位轻信了他的姑娘。他时常因为疯狂地思念她而倍感郁闷，便从北门走进法院大楼那昏暗肃穆的正厅，挤到其他跟他一样穿着打扮，一样尚未受聘的初级律师中间去；或者挤进这个或那个人头攒动的法庭，里面正在审理一桩轰动一时的案子，就好像他跟这案子有关一样，虽然守在门口的警官和他自己都心知肚明他与这案子毫无瓜葛，就跟站在旁听席门外耐心等候的那些闲人一样；他们早上八点就守在门外等着进来，因为他们跟他一样，都属于一个在等候中打发时光的阶层。但是他无论怎么做都是徒劳，于是不禁思量，这种场合里的这些人同粉粉嫩嫩、活泼可爱的安娜比起来多么迥异啊。

出乎他意料的是这个农家姑娘到现在还没给他来信，虽然他告诉过她想写就尽管写。很显然处于这种状态中的年轻女子不应该会这样按兵不动的。最后他给她写了寥寥数语的短信，直言希望她写信来。回来的邮车没有带来回信，不过一天以后文具店主交给他一封信，上面盖着梅尔切斯特的邮戳，信封上是一个女性娟秀的笔迹。

有信件来这件事本身就已经足够让想象力丰富的他感到满足了。他没有急着拆开，事实上他过了近半小时才展信阅读，预计信里肯定满是些热切的回忆和温婉的恳请。然而等到他走到壁炉边打开信纸，发现信里既没有夸张的情感也没有鄙俗的言辞时，他大为讶异又十分欣喜。这是他收到过的女性来信中最令人心动的一封。是的，信里的语言简单平实，思想也无足轻重；然而它是这般沉着自信，只有为自己身为女子感到矜持自尊的年轻女孩才能写得出来；他从头到尾看了两遍。信写了整整四页纸，还有几行是照着已过时的习惯横过来交叉写的；[6]信纸也非常普通，底色和表面都不时新。不过这又有什么关系呢？他从前也收到过一些完全称得上是大家闺秀的女子的来信，但是统统都没有像这一封这般通晓事理又富有人情味。他挑不出一句话，说它不同寻常机智过人，所以只能说这封信“浑然一体”赢得了他的心；除了请他再给她写信以及早点来看她之外，没有只言片语表明她认为自己对他有权提出要求。

在这种情况下再给她写信并建立起长期通信关系是雷伊事前万万没有想到的；然而他真的又回了一封短信，写了几句鼓励的话语，签上自己的化名，还让她继续来信，并兴冲冲地保证他近期内会设法再去看望她，以及他永远也不会忘记他们相识虽短却情深意浓的爱情。

四

现在我们来回顾一下安娜在梅尔切斯特收到雷伊的第一封信的那一刻。

信是邮差在送早间邮件时亲自交到她手里的。收到信时她从脸一直红到了脖子，把信在手里翻来覆去。“这是给我的吗？”她问。

“嗨，当然了，你没看见上面写着吗？”邮差微笑着说，心里猜想着这封信是什么内容，出自谁手，会让她这样语无伦次。

“哦，是的，当然了！”安娜回答道，看着信封上的字，很勉强地傻傻笑了笑，脸更红了。

她那副困窘的表情并没有在邮差走后消失。她打开信封，亲吻里面的内容，把它放到自己的口袋里，继续沉思着，慢慢地眼里充满了泪水。

几分钟后她端了杯茶送到哈汉姆太太的卧室。安娜的女主人打量了一下她，说：“安娜，你今天早上看起来情绪很低落。怎么了？”

“我没有低落，我很开心。只是我——”她停住了，努力压制住一声啜泣。

“嗯？”

“我收到了一封信——可是这对我来说有什么用呢，我一个字都不认识！”

“哎呀，别难过孩子，如果需要的话，我可以读给你听。”

“但这封信是那个人写的——我不希望任何人看到，只想自己一个人看！”安娜低声说。

“我不会告诉别人的。是那个年轻人写来的吗？”

“我想应该是的。”安娜缓缓把信拿出来，说，“夫人，那么请您念给我听好吗？”

原来这就是安娜难为情又慌乱的原因——她于读书写作一窍不通。她住在中威塞克斯大平原上一个偏僻的小茅屋里，由婶婶抚养长大；就算这时已经有了全民教育制度，但在方圆几英里内也没有学校。[7]她的婶婶是个目不识丁的妇人；也没人来查看安娜的境况，没人在意她是否应接受初等教育；不过跟许多由亲戚养大的孩子一样，至少她吃穿不愁，婶婶待她也不错。自从她来到梅尔切斯特跟哈汉姆太太同住后，后者对她也很慈爱，主动教她怎样得体地说话；安娜在这方面学得很快，这对许多不识字的人来说倒也不难；她很快就能流利自如地像女主人那样遣词造句了。哈汉姆太太还坚持给她一个拼写字帖，让她开始练习拼读书写。安娜在这一方面进展则很迟缓，可是这当口却收到了这封信。

伊迪丝·哈汉姆大大的黑眼睛透出对信件内容的兴趣，不过她担任的只是个念信人的角色，因此她尽量让自己的语气听起来更加单调平淡一些。她读完了那封短信，信的末了貌似漫不经心地要求安娜给个温柔的回音。

“那么——您会帮我写信的，是吗，亲爱的女主人？”安娜急切地问，“而且您会好好地帮我写，就像您平时自己写一样，好吗？我不能让他知道我自己不会写，如果他知道了，我会羞愧到死，恨不得钻到地缝里去的！”

哈汉姆太太从信里的某些措辞看出了端倪，便问了几个问题，安娜的回答证实了她的怀疑。当伊迪丝发现这个女孩已经将自己的幸福委身于这段刚开始的恋情时，顿时大为关切。她责怪自己没有及时干预那次小小的调情，让自己监护下的这个可怜的孩子不得不承受这样严重的后果；虽然当时看到这对男女在一起时她觉得把年轻人的感情扼杀在萌芽状态并非她的分内事。可是木已成舟，她作为安娜唯一的保护人，现在唯有竭尽全力帮忙才是。因此她觉得自己必须答应安娜的迫切恳求，亲自帮她拟定并誊写给这个伦敦小伙子的回信，以尽量保持他对这姑娘的感情；若不是这个情况，她应该会建议安娜找家里的厨子代笔。

一封温柔文雅的回信于是就此拟定了，由伊迪丝·哈汉姆亲自落笔写成。这正是雷伊收到并赞赏不已的那封。它自然是当着安娜的面写的，用的是安娜简陋的信纸，而且也多多少少是照这年轻姑娘的意思写的；但是信中的生气、灵魂和个性，却毫无疑问是伊迪丝·哈汉姆的。

“你至少应该自己签个名吧？”她说，“到现在你总该会写自己的名字了吧？”

“不，不行，”安娜直往后缩，“我写得太难看了。他会以我为耻，再也不想见到我的！”

正如我们已经见到的，信里请求他回信的语气巧妙又恰当，字里行间的魅力足以影响他，令他照办。他宣称收到她的来信真是无比开心，并希望她以后每周都给他写信。于是安娜和她的女主人在接下来的几周便一直如法炮制；每一封去信都由伊迪丝建议并写就，安娜站在一旁观望；回信由伊迪丝朗读和解释，安娜又站在一旁聆听。

在寄出了第六封信后的一个冬日深夜，哈汉姆太太独自一人坐在将熄的炉火旁。她的丈夫已经上床就寝，她自己则思绪万千，仿佛入定了一般，忘记了时辰也不计较天寒。之所以陷入这种情绪是因为她那天做了一件特别的事。自从上次雷伊来过到现在，安娜还是头一回离开，回大平原去找从前村里的朋友玩几天；她不在的时候雷伊的信却不期而至。伊迪丝自作主张回复了这封信，而且完全按照自己的心意，没有等她的女仆回来再合作完成。能够给他写信倾诉只有他才知道的衷肠实在是太过奢侈，她便让自己放纵了一回。

为什么是奢侈呢？

伊迪丝·哈汉姆过着非常孤单的日子。英国的母亲们总认为一桩糟糕的婚姻，哪怕有诸多坏处，也好过一直单身，哪怕当个老姑娘可以自由自在、保有个人喜好、尊严和闲暇。她被母亲洗了脑，于是在二十七岁时——大约是三年前——她终于决定听天由命，便同意嫁给这位年纪很大的红酒商，事后却发现自己犯了一个大错。这只是桩契约般的婚姻，而她作为女性更深的天性却从未得到过一丝满足。

她现在明确意识到在她灵魂深处已深深刻上了一个男子的影子，而对他来说自己不过是一个名字罢了。一开始是他的外貌和声音吸引了她，还有他温柔的触摸；有了这些契机，再加上后来一封接一封地给他写信再阅读那些柔情蜜意的回信，不知不觉让她产生了感情，反过来又激起了他更深的情意；最后两个通信者之间产生了磁铁般的相互吸引，尽管其中一个用的是别人的身份写信。虽然她自己并没有意识到，但对身为女性的她来说，他最大的魅力其实是在于他能够在两天之内便成功勾引到另一名女子。

伊迪丝写到信中并签上别人名字的——为避免收信人起疑全都换成了单音节词和简单句——全都是她自己热烈而又难以抒怀的思想。而安娜却那么开心；假如没有伊迪丝的帮助，浅陋的安娜是决计想不到用这样的妙计来赢得他的心，就算是她自己会写字。伊迪丝已经发现是她自己偷偷藏在字里行间的情感引起了那位年轻律师的回应，而安娜偶尔口授让她加进去的句子显然没给他留下任何印象。

安娜一直没发现在她离开期间伊迪丝写了这封信；但是她第二天早上一回来就说她有急事必须马上见到她的恋人，并请求哈汉姆太太写信让他立刻来。

她举止中那奇特的焦虑不安没有逃过哈汉姆太太的眼睛，最后她终于崩溃了，哭得眼泪成河。她跪倒在伊迪丝膝前，坦承她与恋人的关系很快就会以有形的方式昭告天下了。

伊迪丝·哈汉姆生性宽宏大量，完全没想过要在这个节骨眼上抛下安娜让她放任自流。在她看来，一个真正的女人，哪怕她因此迅速采取行动保护自己珍爱的人，[8]也绝非出于自己的本意。虽然她才刚给雷伊写过一封信，但她还是立刻又写了一封署名为安娜的信，委婉但清楚地说明了事态。

雷伊匆匆写了两句回复，说他听到这个消息很是关切，恨不得插上翅膀立刻过来看她。

但是一周以后，姑娘又拿着一封短信到女主人的房里，读了之后得知他还是无法抽身。安娜悲痛欲绝，但是她听取了哈汉姆太太的忠告，没有像其他处在这种境地的年轻女子一样用滔滔不绝的谴责和怨恨淹死对方。当下最为紧迫的是要让这个男人继续保持对她的爱意。因此，伊迪丝又以安娜的名义请求他无论如何不必为此事烦心，也不必着急赶来。她最大的愿望就是不要成为他事业的负担、高尚工作的绊脚石；她只是想让他知道发生了什么事，他尽可以将之抛于脑后；只要他还能像原来一样温柔地给她来信就好了；他可以等到春季巡回法庭开庭的时候再来，那时候再商量该怎么办也不迟。

可以料到安娜自己的想法跟这些慷慨的言辞必然是大相径庭的；但是女主人的判断力占了上风，于是安娜让步了。“我多希望能像您一样把信写得这样恰如其分呀，我亲爱的、亲爱的女主人！我自己是打死也想不出来该这么写的；虽然等您写出来以后我觉得我正是这样想、这样感觉的呢！”

等信送走了，留下伊迪丝·哈汉姆一人时，她不禁伏在椅背上哭泣。

“我真希望孩子是我的——那该有多好啊！”她喃喃地说，“但是我怎么能说出这么邪恶的话呢！”

五

收到这封信时，雷伊被深深地打动了。得知她的状况对他虽有影响，但远不如她的态度对他的触动大——她在这件事上对他的态度实在是太出乎他意料了。没有一个字的谴责，全是为他的利益考虑，每一行字明明白白都是自我牺牲精神，加在一起构成的是高尚的德行，他做梦也没想到女性身上竟会有这种品质。

“上帝宽恕我吧！”他颤抖着说，“我是个邪恶的浑蛋。我没料到她竟是这样的珍宝！”

他立刻回信安慰她，宣称他当然不会抛下她，他会在某处给她找一个安身之处。与此同时只要女主人愿意留她，她就先待着。

但很不幸的是，在这一点上却出了意外。不知道是不是安娜的情况走漏了风声传到哈汉姆太太的丈夫那里，总之他不顾伊迪丝的苦苦哀求，把安娜给辞退了。于是安娜自己做主，决定先回大平原上的婶婶家去住一阵。这样一来她们就得商量好如何保持通信；由于姑娘没有能力把以她的名义开始的通信自己继续下去，而且以后两人也没法配合行动了，她便请求哈汉姆太太——她在这世上唯一的富裕朋友——帮她收信并自行回复，之后再把那些信转寄到她大平原上的住处，如果她能找到个靠得住的邻居，就可以请人家读给她听。然后安娜便带着行李出发回大平原去了。

这样一来，伊迪丝·哈汉姆发现自己陷入一种奇怪的境地中：她得用妻子才会用的言辞，同一个不是她丈夫的男人通信，谈论的孕事根本不是她自己的，而信末署名的那个女子还不在场；她在扮演这个角色时与这个男子产生了共鸣，内心情愫暗生；这爱恋如此微妙，只存在于想象之中，但又这般热烈、令人如醉如痴。她展开每一封信阅读，就仿佛这信本就是写给她的；而她也完全按自己的心意回复，不再考虑他人。

在安娜离开后的整个通信期间，敏感多情的伊迪丝·哈汉姆一直活在梦幻般的狂喜之中；那想象中的亲密在她心里掀起了前所未有的激情巨浪。一开始为求心安，伊迪丝把他的每一封信连同自己回信的草稿都转寄给安娜；但到后来这些所谓的草稿便被大大删节了，还有好些往来信件则没有再转寄过去。

虽然雷伊耽于情欲，而且至少表面上沾染了这个虚伪社会中自我放纵的恶习，但他德行不坏，底子里依然有诚实与公正存在。他确实对这个乡下姑娘有些情意，而当他发现她竟能用最简单的言语表达出最深沉的感受时，这种情意便愈发真切。他想了又想，举棋不定；最后他决定去问问他姐姐的意见——她比他年长许多，是位富有同情心、心地善良的未婚淑女。在吐露这个秘密的同时，他给她看了几封信。

“她看上去很有教养呀，”雷伊小姐评论道，“而且也很聪慧。她的表达很有品味，应该是天生的吧。”

“是呀。而且她的字写得相当漂亮，是不是？多亏有初级教育学校。”

“可怜的孩子，她真的会让人不由自主想要向着她呢。”

这次商量的最终结果就是，虽然没有得到直接的建议，但雷伊用真名写了一封信——假如没有得到鼓励，他是不会如此自作主张的——告诉安娜他不能没有她，他春天就来帮她摆脱困境，因为他决定要娶她。

雷伊做出这英勇决定的消息是由哈汉姆太太亲自告诉安娜的，她收到信后立刻坐马车赶到了大平原上安娜住的茅屋找她。安娜得知后像个小女孩一般欢快地跳了起来。随后她给伊迪丝·哈汉姆口述了一些贫乏肤浅、词不达意的话请她帮忙妥善回信，伊迪丝回去后又以加倍热烈的浓情写就。

“唉！”她放下笔以后，忍不住长叹一声，“安娜——这可爱又可怜的小傻瓜呀——以她的智力根本欣赏不了他！她怎么能懂他呢？而我——又不是我怀了他的孩子！”

眼下已是二月，通信已经持续了四个月。在又一封信里雷伊偶然提起了他的职业和前景，他说一开始准备要娶她时，他想好了要放弃这个行业，反正这职业到目前为止也并未给他带来多少收益；而且，直白地说，假如娶了她的话，可能也很难继续干下去了。不过她的那些来信却让他意外发现了一座宝藏，在她可爱的天性中原来还潜藏着这样的聪慧与热情，因此他觉得自己大可不必如此悲观。他确信，在他的指导下让她学习一些伦敦的社交礼仪，如果有必要再请一位家庭教师，以她的潜质，一定能成为一位专业人员最理想的妻子，就算他将来升任大法官她也完全可以胜任。她在字里行间流露出的天生贵气，连许多大法官的妻子都比不上呢。

“啊——可怜的人，可怜的人！”伊迪丝·哈汉姆懊悔不已。

她现在迷恋有多深，痛苦就有多深。是她令他陷入这样的境地——缔结一桩毁了他的婚姻；然而出于对女仆的怜悯，她又不能采取任何行动阻止他的计划。安娜这个星期就会来梅尔切斯特，但她不能给这姑娘看他最近的这封回信；里面有太多信息显示出另一个人的存在，而且已经鸠占鹊巢取代了头一个。

安娜到了以后，女主人带她到自己的房间里密谈。安娜有些不安地开口，说她很高兴婚期总算快到了。

“唉，安娜！”哈汉姆太太回答，“我觉得我们必须得把一切都告诉他——让他知道是我一直在帮你写信，好吗？——要是等你嫁给他以后他才知道的话，我怕会造成你们以后争吵和指责——”

“啊，主人，亲爱的主人——请不要现在告诉他啊！”安娜声泪俱下，“如果您这样做了，他可能就不会娶我了；那我该怎么办呢？我都不敢想我会沦落成什么样子！我现在写字已经有进步了。我一直把您好心送我的字帖带在身边，我每天都练习，虽然这真的非常非常困难，但我相信我最终可以做好的，只要我一直坚持下去！”

伊迪丝看了看字帖。范本是她自己写的，而姑娘所谓的进步就是对女主人字体的变了形的临摹。但就算她能完全复制伊迪丝行云流水的字迹，那才情却是模仿不来的。

“您写得那么美妙，”安娜又说，“说出了所有我想说的话，却比我说的好一百倍！我求您不要在这个节骨眼上抛下我不管！”

“好吧，”另一位回答她，“可是我——可是我真觉得我不应该继续下去了！”

“为什么呢？”

伊迪丝有强烈的欲望想倾诉心声，于是说了真话：“因为它会给我造成很大的影响。”

“但是它不可能影响您啊！”

“为什么呢，孩子？”

“因为您已经结婚了呀！”安娜的回答真是清楚明白、一派天真。

“是的，当然不会影响我，”女主人匆匆地说道；虽然心中不安，但她很庆幸还有两三件本想倾吐的事没有说出来，“不过你现在必须照着我写在这儿的范本，专心致志练习，写好你的名字。”

六

很快雷伊就写信来谈到了婚礼的事。原本他以为这不过是一时风流犯下的错误；既然现在决定要将错就错、尽力弥补，他便对这重要的实验投入了许多的热情。为了更好地保密，他希望能在伦敦举行仪式；而伊迪丝·哈汉姆更希望他们在梅尔切斯特举行；安娜则一副被动的样子，等着别人来安排。他的理由占了上风，哈汉姆太太只得一面热心一面悲伤地开始准备安娜的行装。绝望之下，她觉得无论冒多大风险也要亲眼见证自己的梦想破灭，再次见到那个与她心灵感应让她情根深种的男子；她于是主动提出和安娜一起去伦敦，一直陪她到仪式完成——女主人强装笑颜说是要去“看看她的圆满结局”，姑娘满怀感激地接受了这提议；因为她也只有这一位朋友可以作为陪护人和证婚人，在一位绅士新郎面前不会露怯，不至于让他觉得社会地位相差太悬殊，后悔自己犯下了不可弥补的大错。

三月一个灰暗的上午，伦敦西南区一个民事登记处门前。雷伊从一辆四轮出租马车上下来，再小心翼翼地把安娜和她的陪护人哈汉姆太太扶下车。[9]安娜穿着哈汉姆太太帮她挑的入时的衣服，看起来非常可爱，虽然不如当初在梅尔切斯特的集市上那么迷人——那时她还是个天真无邪的小姑娘，穿着乡下姑娘的长裙，骑在木马上。

哈汉姆太太是今早搭乘早班列车过来的。一个年轻人——雷伊的一位朋友——在门口跟他们碰头，四个人一起进了登记处。不算第一次不经意碰面的话，雷伊是在一个小时前才认识这位红酒商的妻子的。不过因为马上要举行仪式了，所以除了开始的寒暄之外他也没机会跟她多说话。在登记处，婚姻的契约很快便结成了；然而在这期间，雷伊却发觉自己和安娜的朋友之间似乎有一种奇特又隐秘的相互引力。

结婚的仪式——或者说是对之前结合的正式认可——完成了，四人一起乘一辆出租马车来到了雷伊最近在一个新市郊租的公寓；他没有租下一整栋房子，因为目前他还付不起租金。安娜切了一个小蛋糕——那是雷伊在头天晚上离开林肯会馆回家路过糕点铺时买的——除此之外她没有再做什么。雷伊的朋友有事得马上离开，他走后剩下的三人里实际在交谈的就只有伊迪丝和雷伊，两人谈得很是热烈。这谈话确确实实只在他们之间进行——安娜就像是家养的宠物一般，只有谦卑聆听的份，却完全不解其意。雷伊意识到这一点时很是吃惊，开始对她的这一缺陷感到不满。

到最后，他实在是大失所望，但又不愿承认，于是说：“哈汉姆太太，我的宝贝可能是因为太紧张了，所以才这么不知所措。我看等这件事结束后，她得需要平静一下才能缓过来，再说出她之前在信里常常让我赞赏的那些温柔又富于哲思的话来。”

他们之前已计划好当天下午就出发去诺尔西，在那里度过新婚的头几天；随着出发时间临近，雷伊让他的妻子去隔壁房间的写字台那儿给他姐姐写张便条——她因身染微恙未能前来参加婚礼——告知她仪式已经结束，感谢她送的小礼物，并希望以后能与她成为闺蜜，因为现在她不仅是查尔斯的姐姐，也是写信者的姐姐了。

“用你最拿手的美妙又诗意的方式来表达这个意思，”查尔斯补充说，“因为我特别希望你能赢得她的欢心，和她成为亲密的朋友。”

安娜看起来很不安，但还是起身去了，雷伊继续留下来跟客人交谈。过了很长一段时间还不见她回来，她的丈夫突然起身，过去找她。

他发现她还趴在书桌上写信，眼里满是泪水；他颇感兴趣地低头看看那张信纸，想看她在这种微妙情形下将如何得体地表达自己的友善之情。他大吃一惊地发现她只写了寥寥几行，字迹和拼写就像出自八岁孩童之手，而思想则更是愚笨不堪。

“安娜，”他紧紧盯着信纸，问，“这是怎么回事？”

“这是说明——说明我只能写成这样了！”她回答，眼泪“哗”地下来了。

“唉？一派胡言！”

“我做不到！”她一边哀哀抽泣，一边鼓足勇气坚持地说，“我——我——那些信不是我写的，查尔斯！我只是告诉她该写些什么！而且也不是每次都是！但是我正在学习，噢，学得非常快，我亲爱的、亲爱的丈夫！你会原谅我的，对不对，原谅我之前没有告诉你？”她徐徐跪地，悲凄地抱住他的腰，把脸贴着他。

他呆立了片刻，把她扶起来，猛地一转身，“啪”地关上门，走回起居室伊迪丝那里。伊迪丝觉察出也许事情已经败露，两人相互凝视了片刻。

“我猜得对吗？”他开口了，面色苍白，语气沉着，“是你一直在代她写信？”

“这在当时很有必要。”伊迪丝说。

“她是一个字一个字口述让你写下来吗？”

“不是每一个字。”

“或者说，其实很少？”

“很少。”

“你每周写的那些信大部分都是你自己的想法，虽然署的是她的名！”

“是的。”

“也许有好些信都是你独处时写的，根本没有和她商量？”

“确实。”

他转身走到书柜前，靠在上面，一只手捂住了脸；伊迪丝看到他这样痛苦，脸顿时“唰”地一下白得像纸。

“你欺骗了我——你毁了我！”他喃喃地说。

“啊，请别这样说！”她悲痛地喊，一下子跳了起来，手搭到他肩上，“你这样说我会受不了的！”

“那些信让我那么欢喜，原来却是假的！你为什么要这样做——为什么！”

“刚开始我完全是为了帮她！为了尽力使这个单纯的姑娘不要遭受不幸，我只能这样做！但是我承认我后来继续写是为了我自己快乐。”

雷伊抬起头，问：“为什么它会让你快乐？”

“这个我不能说。”她回答。

他继续望着她，看到她的嘴唇在他的注视下突然开始颤抖，看到她双眼慢慢浮现出泪水，然后垂下眼帘。她突然惊慌地往旁边走去，说她要去车站赶回家的火车了，能不能请他马上叫一辆出租马车。

但是雷伊走上前去，握住了她的手，她没有抵抗。“唉，想想竟然有这样的事！”他说，“其实，你和我是朋友——恋人——深爱对方的恋人——在通信中！”

“我想，是的。”

“不仅如此。”

“不仅如此？”

“当然不仅如此。你想要对此视而不见也没用。在法律上我跟她结婚了——上帝保佑我和她吧！——但在灵魂和精神上我娶的是你，不是这个世界上任何其他女人！”

“别说了！”

“我一定要说！你何必试图掩盖全部的真相，既然你已经承认了一半。是的，这是你和我之间的结合——不是我和她的！现在我不想再多说什么了。但是，我残忍的爱人啊，我想我有权对你提一个要求！”

她没问是什么，于是他把她搂到胸前，俯看着她。“如果那些信里写的都只是做戏，”他语气坚定地说，“那么就只把你的脸给我。如果都是出自你的真心，就把嘴唇给我。请记住，这是第一次，也是最后一次！”

她把嘴迎了上去，他久久地吻她。“你能原谅我吗？”她哭着问。

“是的。”

“可是你却被毁了！”

“那又怎样呢！”他耸了耸肩说，“是我自己活该！”

她退开，擦干眼泪，进房间去跟安娜告别。安娜没料到她这么快就要走，还在跟那封信做斗争。雷伊跟着伊迪丝下了楼，三分钟后她坐上一辆驶向滑铁卢车站的双轮轻便马车。

他回到妻子身边，“安娜，今天先别管信的事了，”他温和地说，“穿上外套吧。我们也得马上出发了。”

这个头脑简单的姑娘因为自己真的结婚了而备受鼓舞，看到事情败露后他对她依然和颜悦色，感到十分开心。她并不知道此刻在他眼里看到的是一艘奴隶的劳役大船，而他，这个挑剔的城里人，被锁在了船上不得不劳作至死，跟他锁在一起的则是她这个大字不识的村妇。

在回梅尔切斯特的路上，伊迪丝脸上还带着悲伤到麻木的表情，嘴唇还因为他那绝望的热吻而隐隐作痛。她这场激情四射的幻梦终于到了尽头。黄昏时分她到达了梅尔切斯特车站，原定她丈夫会去接她。但一个心不在焉，一个心事重重，两人都没看见对方，她于是一个人走出了车站。

她没有叫出租马车，机械地一路走回了家。进了门后，她无法忍受房子里的死气沉沉，便在黑暗中上楼走进安娜原来的寝室，在那里待了一会儿，默默沉思。然后她转身回到起居室，不知不觉便伏下身趴在了地板上。

“我毁了他！”她反复地说，“我毁了他，因为我不能做出背叛她的事！”

过了半小时，有人打开了房门。

“啊——是谁？”她坐起来惊问，因为房间里一片黑暗。

“你的丈夫——不然还有谁？”那位杰出的商人回答。

“啊——我的丈夫——我都忘了我还有个丈夫！”她低声对自己说。

“我在车站没找到你，”他继续说，“你看到了安娜顺利地嫁出去了吧？希望一切顺利，因为她就快到时候了。”

“是的——安娜已经结婚了。”

在伊迪丝乘车回家的同时，安娜和她的丈夫正坐在向诺尔西飞驰的火车二等车厢相对的两扇车窗旁。他手里拿着一个皮夹子，里面全是有折痕的写得密密麻麻的纸。他把它们一张一张展开，一边默默读着，一边低声叹息。

“亲爱的查尔斯，你在做什么呀？”她在对面窗边怯怯地问，然后慢慢靠近他，宛如朝圣一般。

“在看那些署名为‘安娜’的美妙来信。”他郁郁地回答，带着认命的神情。

一八九一年秋

[1]梅尔切斯特（Melchester）是哈代杜撰的地名，实际对应的是英格兰南部城市索尔兹伯里。索尔兹伯里大教堂是英国著名的天主教教堂，于十三世纪早期建成，主体工程用时三十八年，因此整个教堂建筑风格非常统一，为结构厚重的哥特式。大教堂拥有英国最高的塔楼，教堂的围庭（The Close）是英格兰最大的大教堂围庭，位于教堂南侧，是一个四方形的回廊，由连续的十字拱加六分拱的拱门组成，中间则是大片的草坪。

[2]此处典故来自中世纪意大利诗人但丁的《神曲》。但丁在《神曲》里描绘了地狱的景象，将地狱分为九层，罪行分别从轻到重。第八层地狱里受苦的灵魂生前的罪行是“欺骗”——这与本文的三位主人公有关，因此哈代提及第八层可能是有意为之。

[3]此处大平原对应的是索尔兹伯里平原（Salisbury Plain），位于英格兰南部的西南角，属于白垩高原地形，占地三百平方英里（七百八十平方公里），主要在威尔特郡境内，有一小部分位于伯克郡和汉普郡。

[4]从十三世纪开始，任何要从事出庭律师职业的人，都需要在伦敦众多法律学会的某一家会馆中接受学徒式教育，并获得会馆授予的律师执业许可。因此，律师会馆就是培养法律专业人才的大学。其中最著名的有四所，称为伦敦的四大律师会馆，包括中殿会馆（The Middle Temple）、内殿会馆（The Inner Temple）、林肯会馆（Lincoln's Inn）和格雷会馆（Gray's Inn）。这四大会馆已有超过六百年的历史，是伦敦古老的法律行会的代表。

[5]巡回法庭（Assize）起源于中世纪，是英国司法组织的重要组成部分。全英格兰被分为六个巡回区（Circuit），伦敦法庭的法官定期到各个巡回区的主要市镇主持巡回法庭，每年举行一到两次审判，有陪审团参与判案。西部巡回区（Western Circuit）于一三一〇年形成，包括汉普郡、威尔特郡、萨默塞特郡、多塞特郡（即哈代故乡所在郡）、德文郡和康沃尔郡。巡回法庭受理的案件类型主要是各类法令与普通法规定的重罪，但也受理轻罪，包括大量盗窃案件，同时也受理民事诉讼。

[6]在一八四〇年之前，寄邮件的费用非常昂贵，在伦敦市以内是按页收费，一页纸两到三个便士；伦敦以外的地区则按重量和距离收费，由收信人付费。为节约纸张，人们写信的时候先从左到右写满一页纸，再把纸转九十度再从左到右写；正看的话相当于从底部往上又写了一页穿插在最早一页的字里行间，这种写法叫作交叉信（Crossed Letter）。交叉信非常难读，但如果字写得小，字体也工整的话还是可以读懂的。一八四〇年后国会改革了邮政系统，使邮资大大降低，铁路普及也使邮件收寄速度大大加快，可说是维多利亚早期技术进步和政府干预下的一大成功之举。文中安娜和雷伊通信的时间已是一八四〇年后，邮资已经降低到每封信一便士，不需要再节省纸张，因此交叉信已经比较少见了。

[7]英国政府于一八七〇年颁布了《初等教育法》，目标是填补宗教教育的不足，在没有学校的学区设立公立初等学校，对五至十二岁儿童实施强制性初等教育。此后，英国政府又于一八八〇年颁布了《芒代拉法》，规定对五至十岁儿童实施强制性初等义务教育；一八九一年颁布了《免费初等教育法》，规定初等教育为免费义务教育，并最终于一九一八年完全实现了国民初等义务教育。

[8]维多利亚时期十分强调女子的贞洁，婚前性行为、未婚先孕就等同于道德败坏与堕落。年轻女仆假如未婚先孕，通常会立刻被主人逐出家门，以免带坏家里其他人——亦即文中所谓的“保护自己珍爱的人”。因此，伊迪丝对待未婚先孕的安娜的态度可说是非常开明、十分罕见的。

[9]十八世纪中期至十九世纪初期，在英格兰结婚必须在教堂举行公开仪式才能合法登记；一八三六年取消了这一要求，新人除了去教堂举行婚礼外，也可以选择到民事登记处进行公证结婚（Civil Marriage）。民事登记处登记公民出生、死亡、婚姻数据，并提供公证结婚服务。

一个想象力丰富的女人

在上威塞克斯著名的海滨胜地索伦特希，威廉·马契密尔打听度假屋有眉目后便回客栈去找他的妻子。她跟孩子们一起到海边散步去了。马契密尔照着客栈门厅那位颇有军人气度的行李搬运工所指的方向去找他们。

“天哪，你们怎么走了这么远！我都快喘不过气来了。”马契密尔追上妻子后，颇为不耐烦地说。她正一边走路一边看书，三个孩子跟着保姆早已远远跑到前头去了。

马契密尔太太还沉浸在书中做着白日梦，闻言吓了一跳，回过神来，说：“是呀，你走了这么久。客栈真是无聊透顶，我实在不想待在里面了。不过威尔，很抱歉让你这样找我，有什么事吗？”

“唉，我一直没法拿定主意。每次去看那些号称又通风又舒适的房子，都发现它们其实又不通风又不舒适。你跟我去看看我最后选的那套房合不合适吧？恐怕房间不够多，但实在找不到更好的了。整个镇子都住满了。”

夫妻俩让保姆带着孩子们继续散步，两人先回去了。

这两人年纪相当，相貌般配，家境富足，但性情却迥异：丈夫是个慢性子，温和而略有些迟钝；妻子则神经敏锐、乐观开朗。即便如此，两人也不常争执。主要在于他们的品味和喜好，在那些最细微却又最重要的细节上，两人完全没有共同语言。马契密尔觉得他妻子的爱好实在是犯傻；她则认为他唯利是图、俗不可耐。丈夫是北方一个繁华都市的枪支制造商，总是一心扑在工作上；夫人却喜好风雅，是“缪斯的随从”——用这已过时的套话形容她最贴切不过了。艾拉生性多情善感，每次想到丈夫制造出来的东西都是为了毁灭生命，就会慈悲地打住，不愿再了解再多的细节。为了保持内心安宁，她只有劝说自己那些武器至少有一部分早晚会用来消灭那些害虫与野兽，它们对待更低等物种的残忍程度几乎同人类不相上下。

她之前从未认为他的职业是拒绝他做丈夫的理由。所有称职的母亲都谆谆教诲女儿：女子首要之美德就是不惜任何代价找个一辈子的饭票，所以她一开始根本没有考虑过这个问题；于是她接受了威廉的求婚，又度过了蜜月，这才进入反思阶段。这就像一个人在黑暗中猛然抓住了个东西，她开始思量自己抓住的究竟是什么，在心里一遍遍绕着它打转、揣摩：它究竟是稀世珍宝还是稀松寻常；内里是金银锦绣还是一团草包；是绊脚石还是垫脚石；是知心爱人还是形同路人。

她隐隐约约得出了结论，于是一面同情她的所有者愚钝不堪、缺乏品位；一面自伤自怜，进而白日里写作与做梦，夜深人静时则喟然叹息，将自己温婉细腻的情感宣泄出来，以此证明自己心尚未死。不过就算威廉知道她的这些想法，也不会受太大的困扰。

艾拉身段玲珑、举止优雅、纤细苗条，走起路来步履轻快，甚至带点蹦蹦跳跳。她有一对黝黑的眼眸，双瞳光彩照人、晶莹剔透；像艾拉这类气质的女子一般都有一双这样顾盼生辉的眼睛，往往会令她的异性朋友心痛不已，有时也令自己黯然神伤。她的丈夫身材高大、脸型瘦长，蓄着棕色颏须，脸上带着沉思的神情；而且，还必须补充一点，他对她一直都颇为和善宽容。他说起话来一本正经，对于世间需要仰仗武器的种种乱象感到无比满意。

夫妇俩步行来到了要找的别墅前。这所房屋坐落在面朝大海的一排房子中间，前面有一个小花园，种着用来挡风防水的常青树，还有一直通到门廊的石阶。这一排房子都有门牌号码，大家都称这栋房子为“新大街十三号”，不过它比其他的房子要大许多，而且房东太太别出心裁坚持称之为“科堡别墅”[1]。此地现在正是阳光明媚、游人如织的时候；但到了冬季，就得把沙袋挡在门前，把锁孔堵上防止风雨侵袭；木门上的油漆经风雨侵蚀冲刷，薄得已经能看见底漆和节疤了。

房东太太一直在等马契密尔先生回来，她到走廊上迎接他们，带他们看了几个房间。她说自己是个寡妇，亡夫生前是个公职人员，因为猝然离世导致她生活拮据，又急切地介绍这房子设施的各种便利好处。

马契密尔太太说这房子本身和地理位置都很不错；可惜房子太小住不下，除非能把所有房间都租给她。

房东太太很是失望，想了半天。她说自己迫切希望两位来客能租下她的房子，但很可惜有两个房间被一位单身绅士常年租住着。的确他付的租金不如旺季时的高，但他一年到头都租着，而且他人又特别和气、风趣，从不惹麻烦，她不想为了一个月的短租把他赶走，就算租金再高也不行。“不过，”她补充说，“也许他会自愿暂时离开一段时间。”

马契密尔夫妇不想这样做，于是回了客栈，打算再去中介那里打听打听。结果他们正准备坐下来喝茶，房东太太就找过来了。她说那位先生非常热心，很愿意把他的房间让出来给新来的客人住三四个礼拜。

“这确实是很好心，但是我们不想这样麻烦他。”马契密尔夫妇回答。

“哦，这没什么麻烦的，我向你们保证！”房东太太滔滔不绝地说，“因为，他跟大多数年轻人都不一样——耽于梦想、独来独往、郁郁寡欢——而且他并不喜欢在旺季来这里，反倒更喜欢等到淡季，强劲的西南风猛拍着房门，海水直冲到大街上，整个镇上人影都不见一个的时候来。事实上他很快就要走了——他要去对面岛上的一个小屋暂住一段，算是换个环境吧。”因此她希望他们能去她那儿住。

于是，马契密尔一家第二天就搬进了那栋房子，感觉确实很适合他们。午餐过后，马契密尔先生朝码头方向溜达而去，马契密尔太太打发孩子们去户外沙滩上玩耍，自己好好地安顿下来，在屋子里这儿那儿仔细查看了一番，再测试一下衣柜门上穿衣镜的效果。

她发现后面的小起居室里的家具比起别处更加个人化，这正是那位单身青年的房间。破旧的书籍——都是优秀的版本但并非珍本——随意堆在屋子的角落里，有种奇特的含蓄态度，似乎前任房客并不认为旺季来的客人会有兴趣翻看这些书一般。房东太太在门口守候着，看马契密尔太太有什么不满意之处，好马上调整。

“我就把这间小房间作我的卧室吧，因为这里面有书。对了，那位离开的先生好像有很多书，他应该不会介意我拿几本看吧，胡珀太太？”

“哦，当然不会了，夫人。是的，他有很多很多书。因为，他自己也算是个搞文学的。他是个诗人——是的，就是个诗人——他自己有一小笔固定收入，足够他写诗啦，但是还不够让他飞黄腾达，就算他愿意费那份心思的话。”

“一位诗人！噢，我还不知道呢。”

马契密尔太太翻开一本书，看到了扉页上书的主人的签名。“天哪！”她接着说，“我很熟悉这个名字——罗伯特·崔维——我当然熟悉了，还有他的诗！原来我们占的是他的房间，被我们赶出家门的是他？！”

几分钟后，艾拉·马契密尔独自一人坐下，满怀好奇与惊喜地想着罗伯特·崔维。了解了艾拉最近的经历就明白她为何对他感兴趣了。她自己就是一个不得志的文人的独生女儿，婚后打理琐碎的家事以及为一个平庸男子生儿育女让她逐渐消沉，从前的恬静与灵气也似乎逐渐远去。在过去一两年，她试图为自己不幸搁浅的情感找到一个温和又恰当的宣泄口，于是她开始喜欢上了写诗。这些诗的作者署名均用了男子化名，大多出现在一些不知名的杂志里。但有两首则发表在颇有名气的杂志上，其中第二首是用小一些的字印在页面下方，页面上方用大字印的另一首同一主题的诗就是这位罗伯特·崔维写的。事实上，两人都为日报报道的同一则悲剧事件所触动，不约而同地以此为灵感写就了诗句。编辑在按语中提及这一巧合，并称赞两首诗都很杰出，因此特意将它们并列刊登。

从那以后艾拉，或者说“约翰·爱维”，便十分关注各种刊物上登出的署名为“罗伯特·崔维”的所有新作——崔维作为男子不会因性别受到困扰，自然也从未想到要使用女性化名。当然，马契密尔太太说服自己冒充男子写诗也有其好处，因为没有人会相信这些感情浓烈的诗歌竟是由一位麻木不仁、专心事业的轻型武器制造商的妻子、三个孩子的母亲写就的。

崔维的诗歌与一众新晋小诗人的作品相比风格迵异：他的诗歌也许不算天才之作，但却激情澎湃；也许不算精雕细琢，但却多姿多彩。他既非象征派也非颓废派，应当算是悲观主义者，倘若该特质可用来形容一个人敢于直面人生的最坏与最好。他无意脱离内容单纯追求形式与节奏的完美，因此有时候诗兴大发来不及进行艺术加工时，他便会写下一些伊丽莎白体的不甚押韵的十四行诗，让每一位有正义感的评论家都不禁义愤填膺，口诛笔伐。

艾拉·马契密尔常常一遍一遍地阅读这位对手的作品，他的诗总是那么震撼人心，相比之下，自己的诗句却如此孱弱无力，这让她羡慕嫉妒又伤心绝望。她试图模仿他，但他的境界实在非她力所能及，这有时会让她突然无比沮丧。这样过了数月之后，一天她突然从出版列表中发现崔维把他未发表的诗作整理成册出版了，评论有褒有贬全看运气，但销量已足够支付印刷费用。

他的这一招促使“约翰·爱维”决定把自己的作品也整理一番，除了为数不多的已发表的作品外，还得把许多未付印的诗稿加进去，无论如何也要凑成一本她自己的诗集。出版的费用高得惊人。偶尔有几篇评论提及她这本可怜的小册子，但是既没人谈论也无人购买，于是，不到两周它就夭折了——假如说它曾存活于世的话。

恰好在那时，艾拉发现自己怀上了第三个孩子，因此注意力得到了转移，否则她这次诗意冒险的惨败对她的影响一定会严重得多。她丈夫将医生的账单和出版商的账单一并付清，这事当时就算完结了。不过，虽然艾拉算不上是位了不起的诗人，却也不只是个生儿育女的普通女子。近来，她又开始灵感滋生。就在这时她却阴差阳错地住进了罗伯特·崔维的房间。

她若有所思地从椅子上起身，满怀对同行的兴趣在房间里搜寻。是的，他自己的诗集也在书堆里头。虽然她已经很熟悉书的内容了，但在这儿又不禁重读起来，仿佛它在大声召唤她一般。然后她找了点琐事当借口把胡珀太太叫来，随后又打听起了这位年轻先生。

“啊，夫人，我肯定如果您见到他的话，一定会喜欢他的，可惜他太腼腆，所以估计您是见不到他了。”胡珀太太似乎并不介意谈论前任房客以满足现任房客的好奇心，“是不是住在这儿很久了？是的，差不多两年啦。就算他人不在的时候也保留着房间。这地方空气温和，对他的肺有好处，所以他喜欢随时想来就来。他大多数时间都在读读写写，很少跟别人交往。不过说到这个，他真的是个非常和气善良的小伙子，要是别人了解他的话，一定会乐意跟他做朋友的。现在好人可不常见啦。”

“啊，他心地善良……而且人很和气。”

“是的，只要我开口，他什么事都愿意答应。有时候我会跟他说，‘崔维先生呀，你看上去精神不佳呢。’他就说，‘是呀，胡珀太太，不过我不知道你是怎么看出来的。’我就说，‘不如你换个环境试试？’然后过了一两天他就会说他要去一趟巴黎呀、挪威呀之类的地方。等他回来的时候果真就好多啦。”

“是嘛！毫无疑问，他一定生性敏感吧。”

“是呀。而且他在有些方面有点怪癖。有一次他大半夜写完了一首诗，然后就在屋子里走来走去反复诵读。可是这地板这么薄——这房子盖得偷工减料的，我自己都不得不承认——害得我在楼上都睡不着，真恨不得叫他……不过我们相处得还是很愉快的。”

这次对话只是个开头，随着日子一天天过去，两人常常聊起这位崭露头角的诗人。一次聊天时胡珀太太指给艾拉看一些她之前没注意到的东西：在床头窗帘后的墙纸上有铅笔小字，字迹潦草。

“啊！我来看看，”马契密尔太太掩饰不住心中的好奇，弯下腰把精致的脸庞凑到墙边。

胡珀太太一副知情人的样子说：“这些是他的诗最早的雏形、最初的想法。大部分字他都努力擦过，不过你还是能看得出来。我估计这些都是他半夜醒来，嗯，脑子里想到了几句诗，于是赶紧在墙上记下来，生怕早上起来时给忘了。这里，你看这几句，后来我看到杂志上发表了。有一些更新的，对了，那一首我以前就没见过。一定是几天前刚写上去的。”

“噢，是的！……”不知何故，艾拉·马契密尔突然脸红了，希望她的同伴在告知完她这个信息之后能快点离开。她急切地想要独自一人读那些手迹，但不是出于对文学的热爱，而是一种难以名状的个人兴趣。她于是一直等待那独处的时刻，并预感那时她将获得莫大的情感享受。

也许是因为外海上风浪大，艾拉又容易晕船，所以她的丈夫觉得不带上她，独自一人驾帆船或坐汽船出海更自在。他挺喜欢自己一个人登上廉价的短途汽船，在船上看乘客们在月光下翩翩起舞，然后突然一个趔趄搂成一团。他温和地告诉她，说船上的人鱼龙混杂，不方便带上她。因此，这位事业有成的制造商在此地逗留期间自个儿是换了个环境，好好吹了吹海风，然而艾拉的生活——至少在表面上看来——却单调无比，每天不外乎就是花上好几个小时泡泡水、在海滩上走来走去。但是她的诗兴却不断高涨，激情在心中燃烧，让她对周遭世界浑然不觉。

她反复吟咏崔维的那本诗集，直到把所有的诗都烂熟于心，还劳神费时试图写出能与其中几首媲美的诗，但却徒劳无功，直至失败的沮丧让她眼泪夺眶而出。这位占领了她芳心的主人似乎无所不在却又无法接近：如磁铁般深深吸引她的不是他的智慧或者哲思，而是他的个人魅力——这让她自己也百思不得其解。的确，每天从中午到晚上她都身处他惯常生活的环境中，可说周遭一切都无时无刻不在对她喃喃低诉他的存在。然而他与她素未谋面，打动她的是她自己的本能——她需要将自己无处安放的情思寄托到她碰到的第一个合适的对象身上去——不过艾拉自己并未意识到这一点。

文明社会为使爱情开花结果设置了过于实际的条件，导致所有激情都自然地走向同一结果。艾拉的丈夫对她的爱已所剩无几，甚至可能跟她一样，已消失殆尽，残留的只是间或的友情。作为一个热情洋溢、生机勃勃的女性，她的生命力需要得到爱的滋养，于是这次机缘所得便顺理成章成了养料，更何况它实属上品，可谓千载难逢。

一天孩子们在衣橱里玩捉迷藏，在嬉闹中扯出了几件衣服。胡珀太太说那是崔维先生的，把它们重又挂了回去。艾拉异想天开，等到下午屋里没人的时候，打开衣橱，取出了一件衣服穿上，这是一件雨衣，上面还连着防水雨帽。

“以利亚的外衣！[2]”她说，“唯愿它能赐予我灵感，令我与他比肩，如他这般的慧业才人呵！”

每每念及此端她便会泪水潸然。她转过头在镜子里打量自己：他的心脏曾在这件衣裳底下跳动，他的头脑曾在那顶帽子底下思索，那是她永远无法企及的高度。想到她与他相比那样黯然失色，不免闷闷不乐。她还没来得及脱下雨衣，门突然开了，她丈夫走了进来。

“这是什么鬼——”

她脸红了，脱下衣帽，说：“这是我在这衣橱里面发现的，一时兴起就穿上试试。不然我还能干吗呢？你总是不在！”

“总是不在？呃……”

当天晚上她又同房东太太聊起来，后者很可能自己也对诗人略有些柔情，因此每次都很乐意谈起他，而且总是言辞热切。“夫人，我知道你对崔维先生很感兴趣，”她说，“他刚让人捎了个口信来，说如果我明天下午在的话，他想过来找几本书，问能不能到你房间去拿？”

“啊，当然可以！”

“到时候你就可以跟崔维先生见个面了，如果你愿意在场的话！”

艾拉答应了，心中窃喜。回房睡觉时她心里还在想着他。

第二天早上她丈夫说：“艾尔，我一直在想你昨天说的话，我总是在外面晃，让你一个人待着无聊。可能确实是这样。今天海上风浪不大，我带你一起去坐游艇吧。”

对这样的邀请，艾拉还是有史以来头一次感到不乐意，但她当时还是接受了。出发时间临近，她回房去收拾准备，然后站着想了一会儿。她已明显爱上了诗人，想要见他的愿望如此强烈，盖过了其他所有顾虑。

“我不想去，”她对自己说，“我受不了他来了我却不在！所以我不去了。”

她告诉丈夫她改变主意了，不想出海。他倒也无所谓，自己走了。

这一天接下来的时间里房子里静悄悄的，孩子们去沙滩上玩耍了。阳光下轻柔的海风习习，百叶窗帘轻摆着飞出了窗外。“绿色西里西亚”乐队——为旅游季雇来的一支外国乐队——吹奏出的音符把科堡别墅附近的居民和游客几乎全吸引过去了。这时突然传来敲门声。

马契密尔太太没有听到仆人应门，有些不耐烦起来。书就在她所在的房间里，但是没有人上楼来。她打铃把仆人叫来，说：“有人在叫门呢。”

“哦，不，夫人，他已经走了。我去应了门的。”仆人回答道。这时胡珀太太自己进来了。

“太令人失望了！”她说，“崔维先生来不了了！”

“但是我好像听到他敲门了呀！”

“不不，那是有人在找住处，找错了地方。我忘了告诉你崔维先生在午饭前让人送了个便条过来，让我不用给他准备下午茶，因为他用不着那几本书了，所以就不过来拿了。”

艾拉满心悲苦，很长一段时间都不忍重读他的那首题为“永别的生命”的悼歌，她那颗漂泊无依的心痛苦不堪，她的双眼泪水涟涟。等到孩子们鞋袜尽湿回家，跑上来跟她讲述他们的历险记时，她只觉得自己已经不那么在乎他们了。

“胡珀太太，你有没有——住在这儿的那位先生的照片呢？”不知为何，她近来竟然有些害羞，不敢说出他的名字来。

“啊，当然有了。就在你那间卧室的壁炉台上方的装饰相框里，夫人。”

“不对，那是大公夫妇的照片。[3]”

“是的，没错，不过他就在他们后面。他才是那个相框的正主，我是特意买给他放相片的，但是他在走之前说：‘请一定要记得把我遮起来，别让那些新来的房客看到。我不想被他们盯着看，我相信他们也不想被我盯着看。’所以我就临时把大公和夫人的照片塞进去盖在他上面，正好他们的照片还没有相框，而且比起一个小伙子的私人照片，皇家贵族的照片更适合摆在出租房里做装饰。如果你把他们的照片拿出来你就能看到他了。上帝呀，他如果知道的话一定不会介意的，夫人！他没料到下一任房客会是像你这样迷人的女士，否则他说不定根本就不会想把自己藏起来了呢。”

“他长得帅吗？”她有些羞怯地问。

“我觉得他很帅。也许有的人不觉得。”

“我会吗？”她有些热切地问。

“我觉得你也会认为他帅的，不过有的人说他不是帅而是引人注目。他浓眉大眼，总是若有所思；他四下环顾时眼神敏锐、目光如电，你会觉得，一个不以写诗为生的诗人就应该是这副模样。”

“他多大年纪？”

“他应该比你大个几岁吧，夫人；我想大概三十一二岁的样子。”事实上艾拉已经三十岁零几个月了，不过看上去还很年轻。虽然她心性尚不成熟，但到了这个年龄阶段，她像所有多愁善感的女人一样，开始觉得绝恋也许比初恋更加热烈。唉，很快她还会进入一个更令人抑郁的阶段，虚荣心较强的女人到那时都不愿再接待男性来客了，除非背对着窗或把窗帘半拉下来。她回想着胡珀太太的评论，没有再提年龄的事。

就在此时来了一封电报。是她丈夫发来的，他跟几个朋友乘游艇沿着海峡漂到了巴德茅斯，要第二天才能回来了。

简单用过正餐之后，艾拉带着孩子们在岸边闲逛直到夜幕降临，心里还想着房间里那没有取出的照片，想到即将到来的心醉神迷的时刻，她内心无比平和。这位年轻女子很善于制造细致入微又丰富多彩的想象，因此得知当晚她丈夫不在时，便克制住自己，没有立刻冲动地冲上楼去打开相框，而是决定等到独自一人时再来察看。而且比起午后的炎炎日光，那时已是万籁俱寂、烛光莹莹，窗外是肃穆的大海与璀璨的星光，更能增添一层浪漫色彩。

还不到十点，孩子们就被打发去睡觉，艾拉随后也准备就寝了。为了更好地满足自己强烈的好奇心，她开始做各种准备，先除去所有多余的外衣，换上睡袍，再放一张椅子在桌前，读上几页崔维最柔情蜜意的诗歌。然后她把相框取下拿到灯前，把背板打开，取出照片，举到眼前。

这是一副十分惹眼的面容。诗人蓄了一丛漆黑浓密的髭须和帝髯，帽檐低垂盖住了前额。房东太太描述过的那双又大又黑的眼睛蕴藏了无限的悲凄，在一对俊美的眉毛下方向外张望，似乎正在阅读对面的人脸上那微缩的宇宙，并且看到的景象完全无法令他乐观。

艾拉用她最低沉、最有磁性、最柔美的语调轻声道：“原来这就是你，是你无数次残忍地让我相形见绌呀！”

她久久凝视着照片，陷入了纷乱的思绪，直到热泪盈眶，将唇覆于相纸上。然后她又故作轻松地笑了笑，拭了拭眼睛。

她觉得自己实在是太邪恶了，一个有夫之妇，还有三个孩子，竟然这样不知羞耻，移情别恋于一个陌生人。不，他并不是陌生人！她对他的思想与感受了如指掌，就像熟知自己一般。事实上，他的思想与感受与她如出一辙，而她的丈夫却是个麻木不仁的人。也许对于需要养家糊口的人来说，这其实是种幸运。

“比起威尔，他同真正的我更相似，更心意相通，虽然我们素未谋面。”她说道。

她把他的诗集和照片放在床头柜上。等她斜靠在枕头上后，她又重读了罗伯特·崔维诗作中被她奉为最真挚动人的几首诗。把书放在一旁，她躺下来，把他的照片立起来放在被套上凝视着。接着她就着烛光又浏览了一遍头边墙纸上那些模糊的铅笔小字。它们在这儿——有短语、双韵行、限韵行、诗的句首和句中、草草的想法，就像雪莱随手记在纸片上的诗句一样，不过只言片语，却饱含深情、沁人心脾、令人悸动，就好像是他本人的呼吸，如此温暖而充满爱意，从墙上萦绕而至，轻轻吹过她的脸颊；那面墙曾经无数次围绕在他头颅四周，如今又围绕着她。他一定常常这样举起他的手——手里握着铅笔。是的，这些字迹之所以偏向一侧，一定是因为手这样伸着。

这些题写在墙上的字体来自诗人的世界，那是：

比活人更真实的形态，
一个个永生哺育的婴孩。[4]

毫无疑问，在夜半无人时，他可以毫无顾忌，不惧批评家们的口诛笔伐，于是这些思想与斗争精神便纷至沓来涌入他的脑海。毫无疑问，它们常常是在月光下、烛光中或蓝灰的晨曦里匆匆写就，但也许从不会在日头高悬之时。而此刻，她的长发正散落在他手臂曾靠着的地方，他就将手撑在那里，匆匆记录下自己转瞬即逝的才思。她就睡在诗人的唇边，陷入他精神的怀抱，被他如以太般的灵魂浸润、穿透。

她就这般如坠梦中，时间分分秒秒逝去，突然楼梯上有脚步声传来，很快她听到丈夫沉重的步子踏在门前的楼梯口。

“艾尔，你在哪儿？”

她说不清当时是怎么想的，但她本能地不愿让她丈夫知道她之前都在做什么，立刻把照片塞到了枕头底下。与此同时他推开了门，一副吃饱喝足怡然自得的神气。

“噢，抱歉，”威廉·马契密尔说，“你是不是头又痛了？我是不是打扰到你了？”

“不，我没有头痛，”她说，“你怎么回来了？”

“噢，我们后来发现还来得及赶回来，我也不想多浪费一天，因为明天我还要去别的地方。”

“需要我下楼来吗？”

“噢，不用了。我已经累得像狗了。我美美地吃了一顿，打算马上就睡觉去。我明天早上六点就得起床，希望能起得来……我起来就不叫你了。离你睡醒还早得很呢。”他边说边走进了房间。

艾拉的眼睛跟随着他的一举一动，悄无声息地把照片塞到枕头底下更深处。

“你确定没有不舒服吧？”他又问，弯下腰来看她。

“没有，只是有点心烦。”

“那就没啥关系。”他俯下身吻她，“今晚我要跟你在一起。”

次日一早六点就有人来叫马契密尔；她听到他惊醒，打哈欠，然后自言自语，“在我头底下嘎吱嘎吱响的到底是什么鬼东西？”他以为她还在睡觉，四处搜了一下，扯出来个东西。艾拉眼睛悄悄睁开条缝，发现那是崔维的照片。

“哎哟喂，真是见鬼！”她丈夫喊道。

“怎么了，亲爱的？”她问。

“噢，你醒了？哈哈！”

“你笑什么呀？”

“某个家伙的照片——我猜是我们这位房东太太的朋友吧。奇怪，怎么会跑到这儿来，可能是他们在铺床的时候不小心从壁炉台上带下来的吧。”

“我昨天在看这个照片，应该是那个时候掉下来的。”

“噢，他是你的朋友？上帝保佑他那颗诗情画意的小心脏吧！”

艾拉对她倾慕的偶像十分忠诚，无法忍受听到他被嘲弄。“他是个聪明人！”她温柔地说道，但声音却在发抖，她自己都觉得不应该，“他是位新兴诗人——我们来之前这两间房就是他在住，不过我从来没见过他。”

“要是你从来没见过他，你怎么会知道他的呢？”

“胡珀太太给我看的照片，然后告诉我的。”

“噢，好吧，我得起床走了。我今天会早点回来。抱歉今天不能带上你，亲爱的。小心看着孩子们，下水时别让他们淹着了。”

当天马契密尔太太问房东太太崔维先生最近有没有可能会再来。

“有的，”胡珀太太答道，“他下周的今天就会到附近一个朋友家来住，直到你们离开。他肯定会来打个招呼的。”

马契密尔确实下午很早就回来了。他看过了几封他不在时收到的信件后，突然宣布说他们一家得比预计的要提前一周离开了——也就是三天后。

“我们还可以再多待一周吗？”她乞求说，“我喜欢这儿。”

“我不喜欢。日子过得实在太慢了。”

“那你可以留下我和孩子们自己先走呀！”

“艾尔，你怎么这么任性！多留几天有什么用？我还得回来接你们！不行，我们得一起回去。我们之后可以在北威尔士或者布莱顿再多住几天。再说，接下来你还可以再待三天呢。”

这个男人，才华让她自愧不如、无比倾慕，个人则令她彻底沦陷、深深着迷，可是却命中注定她无法与他相见了。但是她还是决定孤注一掷。她从房东太太那里打听到崔维就住在对岸岛上一个僻静地点，离热闹的镇上不远，于是第二天下午就从邻近码头乘邮船到了对岸。

这趟旅途是多么徒劳无果啊！艾拉对房子的方位只有个模糊概念，当她以为她找到了，并鼓起勇气问路人崔维是否住在那里，得到的回答却是不知道。就算他真的住在哪里，她又怎么好去拜访他呢？有的女子也许够自信敢去求见，但是她不行。他一定会认为她疯了。她也许应该邀请他来拜访她，但她也没有勇气这样做。她满怀哀伤地在风景如画的海滨小岛上徘徊，最后不得不回镇上搭乘返航的汽船，好赶回客栈吃晚饭，免得离开太久引起注意。

出乎意料的是，在最后一刻，她丈夫又说既然她这么想留下，那么他不反对让她和孩子们继续待到这个周末，只要她能自己带着孩子们回家就行。这延期让她心中狂喜，但她尽量不表露出来。第二天一早马契密尔就自己离开了。

可是一周过去了，崔维却没有来。

周六上午，马契密尔一家留下来的成员也离开了这个给过艾拉那么多狂热幻梦之地。火车除了乏味还是乏味；阳光照进来，光柱里飘满尘埃，坐垫晒得发烫；铁道上尘土飞扬；电线一行一行，间距相同——一路上只有这些伴着她。窗外深蓝的海平面慢慢从视野中消失，与之一起消失的还有她的诗人的家。她心情沉重，想要看看书，却一时泪如泉涌。

马契密尔的生意可谓蒸蒸日上，他们一家人住在一栋崭新的大房子里，坐落在他做生意的中部城市几英里外，占地面积颇为可观。艾拉在这儿的生活非常孤单，住在郊区就是这样，尤其是在某些季节；因此她有大把的时间创作她热爱的抒情诗和挽歌。她刚一回来就在她最喜爱的杂志的最新一期上读到了罗伯特·崔维的新作，应该就是在她到索伦特希之前写的，因为里面有两行双韵体诗她在床头的墙纸上看到过，胡珀太太也说了那是新写的。艾拉控制不住自己，冲动地提笔给他写了一封信，自称约翰·爱维，并以诗人同行的名义祝贺他能如此娴熟地运用音步与节奏将震撼灵魂的思想完美地表现出来，反观自己在同一行当里的表现却是惨不忍睹。

几天以后，有一封信寄到了她的住址，虽然她一开始根本不敢想——回信客气而简短，信中青年诗人说虽然自己不太熟悉爱维先生的诗作，但还记得曾经读到过他署名的几首很有潜力的作品。他很高兴能与爱维先生成为笔友，也非常期待未来能见到他的更多新作。

大概是因为她假扮成男子写的去信中有种稚气胆怯的口吻，于是崔维便自然地在回信中带着老大哥的语气，显得高高在上。不过这有什么关系呢？重要的是他回信了，而且是在她熟悉的房间里、自己亲手写成，因为他已经回到了该住处。

两人的通信便这样开始了，并持续了两个多月。艾拉·马契密尔时不时会寄一些自认为写得最好的诗歌给他，他也非常客气地收下了，但他并未说已经认真拜读过了，也没有给她寄任何作品作为答谢。艾拉知道崔维完全被蒙蔽，把她当成了男子，所以没有那么介意，不然她肯定会感到很受伤的。

然而这种境况毕竟还是不太令人满意，她内心里常有一个小小的、奉承的声音在告诉她：假如他能见到她，只需一面，情况就会大不相同。一开始，她本打算直接向他坦白承认自己的女子身份的，不过这时她有了个惊喜的发现，便觉得这样做没有必要了。她丈夫有个朋友是本市最重要的一家报社的编辑，某天他们一起用餐时，谈话间提及了这位诗人，编辑说他的兄长是一位风景画家，与崔维先生是朋友，两人这会儿正一块儿在威尔士旅行。

艾拉跟编辑的兄长略有相识。次日上午她就坐下来给他写了封信，邀请他回来时到她家来做客，如果可能的话，也请带上他的同伴崔维先生，她很希望能够与之结识。几天后她收到了回信，说他同他的朋友崔维先生非常乐意接受她的邀请，南下时会顺路过来做客，大约是在下一周的某天。

艾拉顿时满怀希望，无比快活。她的计划终于成功了，她那虽未谋面却挚爱的人儿就要来了。“看啊，他就站在我们墙壁后，从窗户往里观看，从窗棂往里窥探。”她欣喜若狂地想着，“看，冬天已往，雨水止住过去了，地上百花开放，百鸟鸣叫的时候已经来到，斑鸠的声音在我们境内也听见了。”[5]

不过还得考虑他食宿的各种细节。她无微不至地安排妥当后，便等待着那意味深长的日子与时辰的到来。

那天下午大约五点时她听到门铃响起，门厅里传来编辑兄长的声音。虽然她是位女诗人——至少自视如此——但也未能免俗，那天依然花费无数心思精心打扮了一番，穿了一件富丽堂皇的料子做成的时髦长裙，有些类似古希腊的希顿长袍，这款式在有艺术品位、好浪漫情调的女士们中间非常流行，是艾拉上次去伦敦时在邦德街的裁缝那里定制的。客人进了起居室。她望向他身后；没有人再跟进门来。那么，爱神哪！罗伯特·崔维到底在哪儿？

“哦，很抱歉，”寒暄过后，画家说，“马契密尔太太，你知道，崔维真是个古怪的家伙。他本来说要来的，结果他又说来不了了。他就是这么含含糊糊的。我们都带着行装走了好几英里了，结果他说他要继续往家去。”

“他——他不来了？”

“他不来了，他让我代他说声抱歉。”

“你是什么时候跟他分——分——分开的？”她问道，下唇开始不停颤抖，说话间好像装了个颤音塞一般。她无比渴望能从这个无聊得要死的家伙身边逃开去痛哭一场。

“就在刚才，在那边那条公路上。”

“什么！他刚刚就从我的门前经过？”

“是呀。我们来到门前——这大门可真气派，是我见过的做工最好的现代熟铁工艺品啦—我们来到门口，停下聊了一会儿，然后他就跟我道别自己走了。其实是因为，他刚才心情有点郁闷，不想见人。他人非常好，也很热心，但是有时候有点喜怒无常、郁郁寡欢，他想得太多了。你知道，他的诗歌在有的人看来太色情太奔放了。昨天刚出版的《××评论》上就有一篇文章猛烈抨击了他，他在火车站时碰巧看到了。可能你已经读过了？”

“没有。”

“没有更好。唉，这种文章根本不值得往心里去：就是那种按吩咐写的文章，不过是为了迎合心胸狭隘的订户，以保证发行量。但他却因为这篇文章很是愤懑。他说，对他作品的扭曲误读让他很受伤，他可以经得起公正的批评，却受不了那些他无力反驳也无法阻止其扩散的谎言。这就是崔维的弱点。他总是一个人离群索居，所以这些恶意中伤才能够这样影响他。要是他多出来搞点社交，感受下繁华的商业生活，就不会这么在乎这个了。总之，他就不肯来了，理由是这房子看上去太新，太铜臭——请原谅——”

“但是——他一定知道——这里有人理解他呀！他难道没提到他收到过从这个地址寄出的信件吗？”

“是的，他是提到过，有一位约翰·爱维——他估计是你的亲戚，正在这里做客暂住？”

“他——喜欢爱维吗，他有没有说？”

“嗯，我想他对爱维并没有太大兴趣吧。”

“那对爱维的诗也没什么兴趣？”

“对爱维的诗也没什么兴趣——就我所知，应该是的。”

罗伯特·崔维不喜欢她的房子，她的诗，也不喜欢诗的作者。她一能脱身后便来到育儿室，毫无理由地把孩子们狂亲了一通以发泄自己的情绪，直到她突然想到孩子们跟他们的父亲一样，相貌平庸，不禁心头一阵厌恶。

在对话间，那位愚钝又直率的风景画家压根儿没发觉她想接待的不是他，而是崔维。他尽情地享受了一番做客的乐趣，看起来很喜欢同艾拉的丈夫交往，艾拉的丈夫也很喜欢他，带着他把附近逛了个遍，两人都压根没注意到艾拉的情绪。

画家走了不过一两天后，艾拉早上独自在楼上坐着，浏览刚到的伦敦报纸，读到了以下一则新闻：

诗人自尽

近年来在我国诗坛崭露头角的抒情诗人罗伯特·崔维先生上周六晚在索伦特希的寓所持左轮手枪击穿右太阳穴自尽。读者们都知道崔维先生最近出版了一本新诗集《致无名女子》，书中多为激情澎湃的情诗。这本诗集道尽了世间万般情感，面世后备受好评，却遭到《XX评论》严厉——近乎猛烈——的批判。虽不能确定，但在诗人的写字台上发现了该刊物，因而推测这一惨剧可能有部分原因应归咎于该刊的这篇批判文章；并且有人透露说自从这篇批判文章问世后，诗人便一直情绪低落。

接下来是死因聆讯报告，内附一封信，是崔维写给远方友人的：

亲爱的××：

在你收到这封信之前，我应当已获得解脱，再也不必看到、听见和知悉这俗世的种种事情。我不想多说自己为何走到这一步，以免使你困扰，但请相信我的理由全都合理且合乎逻辑。假如上天能赐我一位慈母、一位姐妹或一位对我温柔体贴的红颜知己，我或许还愿意继续苟活于世。正如你所知，我早就梦想着有这样一位知己，却始终无法得到。正是这位难以寻得、捉摸不透的女子给予我灵感，让我写出了我的新诗集。虽然在某些地方已说过，但诗集的书名中所指的女郎只是我想象中的女子，并不是任何真人。自始至终，这位女子都没有出现，我从未遇见过她，也从不曾赢得过她的芳心。我想这一点必须提及，以免伤及无辜，导致任何女子横遭误解和指责，说她的冷眼和无情导致我轻生。请代我向房东太太致歉，我很抱歉给她带来许多不便与不快，不过相信我在那里居住过的事情很快便会被世人遗忘。我在银行尚有许多资金，应该足以支付所有费用。

罗·崔维

艾拉呆坐了片刻，震惊不已。然后突然冲进了旁边的卧室，扑到床上埋住脸。

她悲痛不已、心乱如麻、肝肠寸断；她就这样一时痛苦一时狂乱地在床上躺了一个多小时，颤抖的唇时不时吐出些许支离破碎的呓语：“啊！要是他认识了我——认识了我——我！……啊，要是我能见过他一面——只要一面。把我的手放在他滚烫的额前——亲吻他——让他知道我有多爱他——就算身败名裂千夫所指我也不怕，我愿意为了他生，为了他死！或许这样就能挽救他那宝贵的生命了！……可是我没有——因为上帝不许我那样做！上帝也嫉妒我们，他不愿让我们得到这样的幸福！”

再没有任何“如果”了，两人已永无可能相会。即便如此，在幻梦中她似乎还能看到那些“如果”发生的场景，虽然永远无法实现了——

那曾经可能却再无可能的时刻，
那曾在他与她心中孕育滋生的时刻，
自此以后只剩一生苍茫。[6]

她用第三人称给索伦特希的房东太太写了封信，尽量用较为克制的语气，告知胡珀太太，说马契密尔太太在报纸上读到诗人死亡的不幸消息。她在科堡别墅逗留期间对诗人颇有好感，想必胡珀太太也有所察觉，因此希望胡珀太太能在崔维先生入棺之前剪下一缕他的头发，连同相框中那张照片一并寄给马契密尔太太以作纪念，她将不胜感激。随信还附上了一金镑的邮政汇票。

下一班回程邮递送来了一封信，装着她索要的东西。艾拉对着照片哀哀痛哭了一番，然后把它锁到了自己抽屉里。那一绺头发她则用白丝带系好放在胸前，在没人注意的角落里不时拿出来亲吻一下。

“怎么了？”有一次，她丈夫看报纸时抬起头来看到了，便问道，“你在对着什么东西哭？一绺头发？谁的？”

“他已经死了！”她低声说。

“谁啊？”

“威尔，我现在不想告诉你，除非你一定要我说！”她答道，声音中夹着一声重重的抽泣。

“噢，好吧。”

“你不介意我拒绝告诉你吧？我以后会告诉你的。”

“当然不啦，一点都不介意。”

他吹着不成调的口哨走开了。等他到了市区工厂里时，这件事又浮现在他脑海中。

他也已知悉他们在索伦特希住过的度假别墅中发生了一起自杀事件。想到他妻子近来手里常翻着的诗集，在别墅居住期间听到过房东太太关于崔维的谈话，他猛醒过来，自言自语道：“噢，那肯定是他！见鬼！她是怎么认识他的？女人真是些狡猾的动物！”

然后他便平静地继续忙他的日常事务，将此事抛于脑后了。而艾拉此时在家已经下定了决心。胡珀太太在寄来头发和照片的同时，还告知了她葬礼举行的日期。随着这天上午、中午慢慢过去，这位悲天悯人的女子已无法克制越来越强烈的愿望，想知道他们到底将他葬在何处。现在她已不在乎丈夫或者旁人怎么去看待她的古怪行为了。她给马契密尔留了个便条，称她有事要离开，下午和晚上都不在，但次日一早便会回来。她把便条留在他桌上，把同样的话吩咐给仆人，然后便步行出了门。

马契密尔下午很早就回来了，仆人们一个个都神色不安。保姆把他请到一旁，隐晦地暗示女主人近来看起来无比悲伤，很担心她会自寻短见投水而死。马契密尔回想了一下，说他觉得总体来说她应该不至于这样。不过他也立刻出门了，没告诉仆人们他的去向，只说他们晚上不必等他回来。他驾着马车赶到火车站，买了一张去索伦特希的车票。

虽然他乘的是快车，但到达时天已黑了。他知道他妻子如果比他早出发的话，只有慢车可坐，所以不会比他早太多到达。索伦特希旅游旺季已经过去，大道上现在昏暗凄清，出租马车稀少又便宜。问过了公墓该怎么走后他很快就到了。大门已经落锁，看门人说里面已经没有人了，但还是让他进去了。虽然还不算太晚，但时值秋季，夜色已渐浓。守门人指给他看过日间新下葬的一两处墓地的方向，但他发现蜿蜒曲折的小径已经很难看清。他时而踩到草地上，时而被钉在地上的木桩绊个踉跄，时而弯下腰仔细辨认有没有人影映在天幕上。他什么也没看见。突然他来到某处，地上泥土似乎被反复踩踏过，然后看见新立的墓碑旁有什么东西蹲伏在地上。她听到了他的脚步声，一下子跳了起来。

“艾尔！你怎么做出这样的蠢事！”他怒声说，“离家出走——我从来没有听说过这种事！当然，我并不嫉妒这个倒霉的男人。但是你身为有夫之妇和三个孩子的母亲，而且马上就要生第四个了，却为一个死去的情人冲昏了头做出这样的事，实在太不像话了！……你知不知道你被锁在这里面了？你很可能一个晚上都出不去了！”

她没有回答。

“为了你好，我希望你跟他没有做出太出格的事。”

“不要侮辱我，威尔。”

“记住，以后我不允许你再干出这种事。听清楚了吗？”

“清楚了。”她回答。他拉过她的手臂挽住，带着她走出了公墓。当天晚上是回不去了，但顶着这副狼狈相他也不想让别人认出来，于是带她去了火车站附近一家破落的小咖啡馆，次日凌晨便离开了，旅途中两人几乎没有再开口交谈。两人都意识到婚姻中最糟糕的情况已经出现，语言也于事无补。他们在中午回到了家。

几个月过去了，两人都绝口不提这个插曲。艾拉总是一副黯然神伤、无精打采的模样，简直可说是日渐憔悴。眼见着她第四次临盆的日子渐渐逼近，但这样的压力也无法让她打起精神来。

“我觉得我这次可能熬不过去了。”有一天，她这样说道。

“呸！说什么胡话呢，幼稚！以前都熬过去了，这次为什么就不行？”

她摇摇头说：“我几乎敢肯定我会死掉的。我倒也乐意，要不是我放不下奈莉，还有弗兰克，还有泰尼。”

“还有我！”

“你很快就会找到别人来接替我的位置，”她喃喃地说，带着忧伤的笑容，“你完全有权这么做，我向你保证我很乐意。”

“艾尔，你不会还在想着你的——那个诗人朋友吧？”

她既没有承认也没有否认。“我这次是熬不过去了，”她再次强调说，“我有预感我好不了了。”

一般来说，有这种想法通常就是开了个坏头，于是六周以后，在一个五月天，她躺在房间里，脉搏微弱，脸色苍白，奄奄一息，只有出的气没有进的气了。她为之付出了自己生命的婴儿，那本不必出生的生命，倒是肥胖健壮。临死之前，她柔声对马契密尔说：“威尔，我要向你告白那件事全部的来龙去脉——你知道是指的哪一件——那次我们去索伦特希度假。我不知道是中了什么邪——我怎么能这样把你抛在脑后呢，我的丈夫！但是我当时陷入一种病态。我觉得你对我不够好，觉得你对我不闻不问，还觉得你才情不如我，而他却远胜于我。也许，我并不是想要一个情人，而是一个能够完全欣赏我的人——”

她已经精疲力竭，无法再继续说下去。几个小时以后，她突然陷入昏迷，随后便撒手人寰了，还没来得及跟她的丈夫继续说明她跟诗人的关系问题。威廉·马契密尔，说实话，跟大部分做了多年丈夫的男人一样，并不会因这种过往的情爱而吃醋、扰乱心神，也没有急着催促她说出和死去的情人的全部真相，反正那个男人已无法再给他增添麻烦。

然而等她已入土一两年后，一天马契密尔正翻查一些以前的资料，打算在第二任妻子进入之前先行毁掉。突然，他在一个信封里发现了一束头发以及已故诗人的照片，背后还有死去的妻子手写的日期，正是他们在索伦特希度假的时候。

马契密尔若有所思地看着头发和照片，看了很久很久，心里突然想到了什么。他那夺走了母亲生命的小儿子现在已经是个吵吵闹闹的蹒跚幼童了。他把男孩抱坐在膝盖上，把那一缕头发放在孩子头边，再把照片放在后面的桌上，好仔细比对两张脸的五官。这肯定是造化弄人，但其原因却不得而知：这孩子的脸同艾拉从未谋面的那位男子的脸竟然十分相似；诗人那梦幻般特别的神情，犹如思想转移一般，出现在孩子的脸上，连头发的颜色都一模一样。

“真他妈该死，我早该想到了！”马契密尔嘟哝道，“所以她真的背着我跟那个浑蛋在度假屋里给我戴了绿帽子！等我算一算：她写的日期是——八月的第二周……五月的第三周……是的……果然……滚开，你这个该死的小杂种！你根本和我毫无关系！”

一八九三年

[1]科堡（Coburg）位于德国巴伐利亚州北部的弗朗克地区，是维多利亚女王的丈夫阿尔伯特亲王的故乡。该城的艾恩斯特家族数百年间与欧洲各国王室均有联姻关系。房东太太坚持将房子命名为“科堡别墅”，一来是致敬维多利亚女王与阿尔伯特亲王；二来可能因为该门牌号“十三号”在西方属于不吉利的数字，因此怕如此直呼会导致房客有顾虑而难以出租。

[2]以利亚是公元前九世纪以色列的先知。在《圣经·旧约·列王纪上》第十九章中，以利亚将外衣搭在以利沙身上，表示收他为徒；而在《列王纪下》第二章里，以利亚用外衣击打约旦河水，水便分开让以利亚和以利沙通过；后来耶和华遣火车火马接以利亚上天，以利沙便拾起以利亚的外衣，继承了他的衣钵，成为以色列新的先知。因此，“以利亚的外衣”此处是权力和能力的象征，也寓意继承某人的权力与事业。

[3]即约克公爵（后继位为乔治五世）与符腾堡州台克公爵的女儿玛丽公主，此照片可能为两人于一八九三年七月六日婚礼大典的照片。两人即爱德华八世与乔治六世之父母、现任英国女王伊丽莎白二世之祖父母。大公（Royal Duke）是在公爵（Duke）前加上王室（Royal）一词，是专为同英国君主有合法血缘关系的公爵特设的头衔，在爵位中位列最高。此头衔可以继承，但最多到第三代，即君主的孙辈。之后则要将Royal一词去掉，只能称为公爵。

[4]出自英国十九世纪上半叶著名的浪漫主义诗人珀西·比希·雪莱的诗剧《被解放了的普罗米修斯》第一幕，原诗中即用这两句形容诗人通过想象创造出生命的力量。哈代对雪莱极为推崇，多次在自己的作品中提及、引用雪莱以向诗人致敬。本故事中的罗伯特·崔维便有雪莱的影子。

[5]出自《圣经·旧约·雅歌》第二章第九至十二节。《雅歌》主要记载男女间爱情的欢悦与相思的忧苦，第二章以新婚夫妇对唱形式写成。

[6]引自哈代同时代的十九世纪英国拉斐尔前派重要画家兼诗人但丁·加百列·罗塞蒂的十四行诗集《生命殿堂》第五十三首《胎死腹中的爱》。

浪子回头

一

这个人就住在“小镇之巅”（大家都这么称呼那个地点）下方一栋大大的老房子里，除了本故事的主人公们，就只有他碰巧熟知他们大部分的历史了。这房子和周围房子的区别在于二楼有一个飘窗，可将整个高街从西到东尽收眼底，西边包括萝拉的住处、旁边的市镇大道尽头（接下来会讲到在这里发生的恶作剧）、向西隆起的波特-布雷迪路，以及通往骑兵营的拐角，上尉就住在兵营里头。从这个绝佳的观景瞭望处向东眺望可俯瞰全镇，只见房子挨着房子随地势逐渐下沉、缩小，直到跟横穿过荒原的公路融为一体。公路像条白丝带，过了四分之一英里开外的格雷桥后，便消失在无数蜿蜒迂回的乡间道路中、幽僻的密林深处，以及人烟稀少的丘陵山谷里；延绵一百二十英里，然后在海德公园角重露出康庄大道的面目，与一个熙熙攘攘繁华热闹的世界相连。

方才提到的骑兵营里最近迎来了第X骠骑兵团的进驻，该团初到此地。镇上居民还不太认识兵团的人，就已听到传言说这是一群“顶呱呱”的小伙子，随行的军乐队更是出类拔萃。不知什么原因，小镇已经多年未作骑兵总部之用了，之前在这里驻扎的各部队只是些普通的分遣队而已；因此当镇上所有人得知此次来的兵团乃是“顶呱呱”的骠骑兵时，都觉得脸上有光——包括把桌椅板凳租给已成家的分遣队士兵的那些旧家具商。

在当时，骠骑兵们的左肩上还披着帅气的镶毛边皮披风，松松地垂在背后，就像是鸟儿受伤的羽翼一般，大家把这饰物叫作“霹雳斯”，但士兵们自己叫它“斯林斗篷”。在女人的眼中——其实在男人眼中也一样——这披风给骑兵们平添了许多非凡的魅力。

住在有飘窗的房子里的那位市民平日白天里大部分时间都坐在窗前，因为他是个病人，无事可做，只有对外界保持持续关注才不会觉得度日如年。骠骑兵们到来才一个礼拜，他就听到楼下街上一个小学生在对另一个喊：

“哎，你听说了骑兵团的事没有？听说他们遭鬼缠了！真的——有个鬼一直在骚扰他们；已经一路满世界地跟了他们好几年咯！”

一个闹鬼的骑兵团。不管是病人还是健康人，听着可都是件新鲜事。飘窗后的听者得出结论：第X骠骑兵团里一定有些上蹿下跳的活跃分子。

一天他坐着轮椅去参加了一个下午茶会——这是他为数不多的出行，因为身体状况不允许——得以非正式地结识了蒙布里上尉。蒙布里是个二十八到三十岁左右的英俊男子，行为举止间无不透露出迷人的浪子气质，笃定会使他成为良家女子们的梦中情人。他脸色苍白，大大的黑眼睛熠熠生辉，充分展露出这种邪气；不过他眼中的光芒真是变化多端，这一秒可以忧郁悲伤，下一秒又可以严肃认真，可谓随心所欲尽在他掌握中。

当时在场的一位又老又聋的太太贸然问蒙布里上尉：“我们听说的那是怎么回事？他们说你的兵团闹鬼呢。”

上尉的脸上露出沉重甚至哀伤的神情。“是的，”他回答说，“再真实不过了。”有的年轻女士满不在乎地笑了，然而当她们发现他看上去不像在说笑时，顿时也面色一凛。

“真的吗？”老太太又问。

“真的。当然我们都不愿意多谈这种事。”

“是的是的，当然不想。但是——是怎么个闹法啊？”

“嗯，这个——东西，我姑且这么叫它吧，一直跟着我们。不管是乡下还是城里，国外还是国内，它都一样跟着。”

“那是为什么呢？”

蒙布里压低了声音说：“嗯，我们估计是因为我们团里有人曾经犯下了罪过。”

“天哪……太可怕了，太古怪了！”

“不过，我也说了，我们很少谈这事。”

“是的……是的。”

等这位骠骑兵走了，一位年轻小姐再也无法抑制强烈的好奇，问有没有人见过这个鬼。

律师的儿子一向对镇上的最新消息了如指掌，他回答说虽然除了骑兵们很少有人见过，但有不止一个市民，有男有女，已经偶然瞟到了，差点没被吓死。这鬼魂大多是在深夜出现，在距离兵营最近的市镇大道的浓密树丛底下徘徊。它高达十英尺，牙齿咔嗒作响，声音又干又涩，就像骷髅发出来的一般，连臀骨骨臼相互摩擦的声音也清晰可闻。

后来在冬夜最阴暗的几周里，有好几位胆小的居民就被符合这生动描述的东西吓得魂飞魄散，连警察都被惊动来调查此事。打那以后鬼魂出现的频率就少了，兵团的一些小伙子还感激涕零地宣称数年来他们一直被鬼魂纠缠不休，自从来了卡斯特桥镇以后，终于好多了。

这些年轻小伙子住在小镇顶端的兵营里，那是座长满青苔的红砖建筑，拱顶石上还刻着“战时总部”的缩写“W. D.”和一个宽宽的箭头。对他们来说，这种闹鬼的把戏不过是他们的娱乐节目里头最无伤大雅的玩笑罢了。还有那些更出格的行为——谈情说爱、酗酒打牌、吆五喝六等，也都成了镇上居民的谈资，当然肯定会有些夸大其词。但是骠骑兵们，包括蒙布里上尉在内，让镇上和附近村子里多位年轻姑娘伤心流泪，这绝对不假；当然这也是因为这个小镇古老偏僻，所以这群快活的小伙子才会如此引人注目，要是换成是个繁华都市，就不会激起这么大水花了。

二

骑兵们照例每周一次着行军装外出操练。

一次行军归来回到镇上时，每个骑士肩上那浪漫的“霹雳斯”都迎着柔和的西南风飘舞，蒙布里上尉抬头望向飘窗，同坐在窗后看书的人相互点头致意。看书人和屋内另一个在场的朋友目送着部队沿路上坡，来到了萝拉住的房子对面，然后看到那位年轻姑娘出现在阳台上。

“我听说他们已经订婚了。”朋友说。

“谁——蒙布里和萝拉？不会吧——这么快？”

“是呀。”

“他不会结婚的。已经有好几个姑娘跟他不清不楚了。我真为萝拉感到难过。”

“噢，你完全不必担心。这两人是绝配。”

“她不过是下一个而已。”

“她是下一个，但不仅于此。她已经套牢了他。她是个天生的爱情玩家，懂得怎么在他擅长的游戏里打败他。要说全镇有哪个姑娘能够立于不败之地成为他的终结者，那就只有萝拉啦。”

结果真是如此。也许是天性使然，萝拉从一开始便醉心于军营爱情；这从她青睐的角色以及她同他们上演的故事情节便可以看出来。自她刚成年到现在，只要她周围能见到一个士兵，无论此人多么平庸，她也绝对不会对平民感兴趣，无论这个平民多么优秀。也许是因为她叔叔的房子（她就住在叔叔家）正好位于西街离军营最近的一角，每天从窗户就可以看到两百米开外部队进进出出，号角不时地吹响，加上她对于军营内的真实生活一无所知，于是将之理想化了，因此强化了她最初的偏见，认为军人才是唯一值得她倾心的对象。

蒙布里上尉则是她的最高战利品：他是周围所有少女的梦中情人，姑娘们为他心乱如麻、绞尽脑汁、伤心哭泣，但他却被她的才智与手段征服，拜倒在她的石榴裙下。嫁给自己中意的男子固然让她心满意足，但更让她得意的是周围所有适婚少女的母亲们都对她恨之入骨。

飘窗后的那个男人去参加了他们的婚礼仪式。不是应邀前往，因为这时他跟夫妇俩还只是点头之交而已。主要是因为教堂就在他家旁边，还有一部分原因是因为大家潜意识里都觉得，这对夫妇虽然日后可能会幸福，但也有充分的理由不会幸福，这样旁观者就可以一边悲天悯人地揣测，一边沾沾自喜，所以许多人都是冲着这个原因去观礼的。他那个时候偶尔还能写些很不错的格律诗，于是在等待中，他用铅笔在祈祷书的空白页上写了几句诗来打发时间。这首诗那时并未被发表，不过这里可以公开了。

闪婚观礼有感
（八行两韵诗）[1]

若二人有福，愿此刻永驻。
贪一时之欢，惹一生牵绊。
结一世姻缘，变万般束缚。
若二人有福，愿此刻永驻。
愿东升太阳，永不会日暮。
愿熊熊烈火，永不会黯淡。
若二人有福，愿此刻永驻。
贪一时之欢，惹一生牵绊。

虽然这场恋爱——至少在蒙布里这一方——一开始并没有抱着正经的目的，但是这对夫妻似乎找到了让婚姻永葆恋爱时的激情的秘诀，就仿佛是为了向众人证明所有预言都是错的。接下来的那个冬天，他们是卡斯特桥镇及附近地区——不，应该说是整个南威塞克斯——最受欢迎的一对。凡是从镇上驾车能到的范围内，那些年轻快活的乡绅府上要举办时髦晚宴的话，必定得有他俩到场才算完美；在全郡舞会上蒙布里太太是舞姿最轻盈快活的那个。接下来便是驻军小镇生活里不可避免的事件：业余戏剧表演，两人还是一样受欢迎。他们宣称这演出是为了不起的××慈善机构筹款——不过没人关心具体名称，只要有戏可看就行——蒙布里上尉和他的妻子都参与了演出，事实上两人就是这次演出的始作俑者。总之一切都开心顺利，两人生活中充满了欢声笑语、无忧无虑，活动精彩纷呈。尽管夫妻俩在付账时有些不大爽快，不过公平来讲，他们无论早晚最后还是付清了所有欠款。

三

一个星期天，在专为部队设的小教堂里，布道坛上出现了一张陌生的面孔。这是新来的副牧师。他放在布道坛桌上的不是大家熟悉的传道书，只有一本《圣经》而已。飘窗后的那位朋友当时并不在场，但他很快听说这位年轻的副牧师给了会众们一个大大的惊喜。来听布道的会众构成复杂，虽然骑兵们占据了会场正厅，但犄角旮旯里头则挤满了平民。不过哪怕是最厚道的人都说，这些人去那儿做礼拜是醉翁之意不在酒。

但现在他们又多了一个理由要挤进这个本就人满为患的教堂：听惯了高谈阔论、空洞无物的布道，圣威先生言辞典雅令人折服的布道真是一股清流，一时间镇上其他的教堂听众流失严重。

在十九世纪的这个时期，听布道是大部分信教群众去教堂的唯一原因。读福音祷告不过是预备式，就像巡回法庭开庭时宣读王室公告一样，都是正餐开始之前的开胃菜罢了。等到做完礼拜回家后，别人只会问：今天是谁在布道，讲得好不好？就算是大主教本人来主持，也没人会在意祷告了些什么，唱了些什么。而现在，原来只参加早课的教众也开始来参加晚课了，甚至有时连午课的特别演讲也来听。

一天，蒙布里上尉走进妻子的起居室时——屋里全是租用的家具——她还以为是别人进来了，因为他没有像往常一样哼着时下最流行的曲子，露出漫不经心的样子。

“杰克，出什么事了吗？”她没有抬头，一边问一边继续写信。

“嗯——没什么大事，就我所知。”

“哦，但肯定有什么事。”她一边写一边嘟囔。

“是啊——这个该死的新来的，穷得只能裹张床单，瘦得像条麻秆——我是说新来的牧师！他要我们把礼拜天下午的乐队表演停了。”

萝拉抬起头来，一脸惊骇。

“天哪！我们这些为数不多的有脑子的人就靠这个才熬过了礼拜一到礼拜六啊！”

“他说就是因为全镇的人都跑来听音乐所以不去做礼拜了，而且演奏的这些曲子要么堕落亵渎，要么无聊低俗，要么空洞无物——总之不该在礼拜天演奏。当然最后是由洛特曼来搞定这些事了。”

洛特曼是乐队的指挥。在礼拜天下午，军营绿地事实上已经成了大多数市民欣然前往的散步场所，甚至包括许多参加过圣威先生早课礼拜的教众。那些本应下午聆听副牧师讲道的小男孩，许多都在草地上滚来滚去，在更体面的听众背后扮鬼脸。

有两三个星期萝拉都没有再听到这件事。一天她突然想了起来，便问她丈夫还有没有再收到抗议。

“噢——是圣威先生。我忘了跟你说了，我已经跟他认识了。他人不坏。”

萝拉问蒙布里，他或者某位长官有没有把这位不知天高地厚、胆敢干涉他们的副牧师好好训斥一顿。

“呃——我们忘了这茬了。他们告诉我，他的布道真是令人拍案叫绝。”

两人的交情显然在不断加深，因为没过多久上尉又跟她说：“圣威反对礼拜天下午乐队奏乐其实是蛮有道理的。毕竟这离他的教堂太近了。不过他并没有太过分地给我们施压。”

“我很吃惊你居然会为他辩护！”

“我只是突然想到了。我们当然不想冒犯镇上的居民，如果他们不喜欢乐队奏乐的话。”

“可是他们都喜欢啊。”

飘窗后的那位病人一直不大清楚这世俗与教会观念交锋进展的具体细节；但其结果是礼拜天下午卡斯特桥军营广场上的乐队演奏从此中止了，这让乐队成员们大失所望，外头散步的情人们大感悲愤，镇上和附近村子里的孩子们大为遗憾。

到这时，蒙布里夫妇已经常常去听那位虽然有些狭隘但和善文雅的副牧师布道了。因为他们固然生性轻浮、漫不经心、放荡不羁，但为了体面也得去教堂做个样子，不过他们可不会像那些十足的俗人一样遵守教义。然而有一天飘窗后的朋友居然看到蒙布里上尉同圣威先生一边热切地交谈着一边沿高街往下走。他跟一位来访友人提起此事，对方告诉他这两人总是形影不离，大家都开始议论纷纷。

不过即便没人告诉他，这位观察者也会很快亲眼见到。那两人开始几乎每天都一起路过他楼下。在此之前，时常同蒙布里上尉结伴而行的是身着时髦外出服的蒙布里太太，但现在却不常见了。这两个男人亲密又奇特的友谊持续了近一年后，圣威先生被委任去中部郡一个人口稠密的小城领圣职了。他只得同教众们依依惜别，临走前的讲道刊发在本地报纸上，真是感人至深。失去他大家都很惋惜；后来卡斯特桥教众听说他刚上任不久，就因为一次恶劣天气导致肺部发炎不治身亡，大家都陷入了真切的悲痛中。

现在我们要谈到正题了。在所有认识已故副牧师的人里头，最伤心欲绝的莫过于那个他刚来时蔑称他为“穷得只能裹张床单，瘦得像条麻秆”的男人了。蒙布里太太对这位众人瞩目的牧师一直没多少好感。事实上，她听说他升迁去别处时心里颇为窃喜，因为他让这位热爱游戏人间、呼朋唤友、尽情享乐的女人少了许多乐趣。虽然她对丈夫失去了一位朋友表示遗憾，但这朋友反正也不是她的。可是，接下来发生的事却让她始料未及。

“亲爱的，最近有件事我一直想跟你说，”一天早饭时，他犹犹豫豫地说，“你猜过是什么吗？”

她从没猜过。

“我想退伍。”

“什么！”

“自从圣威死后，我就一直在想他，还有他从前对我说过的那些真挚的话。我内心里听到了神的召唤，让我放弃这打打杀杀的职业并投身教会，我要听从这召唤，我相信这决定是正确的。”

“什么——你要当牧师？”

“是的。”

“那我该做什么？”

“当牧师的太太。”

“我才不要！”她断然拒绝。

“但是你没得选呀！”

“我宁愿离家出走！”她言辞激烈地说。

“不，你绝对不可以。”蒙布里回答道，他通常在下定决心时才会用这种语气说话，“你会慢慢习惯的，因为天意驱使着我必须实现这个想法，就算它同我的世俗利益背道而驰。上帝的手在推动我去追随圣威的脚步。”

“杰克，”她脸色苍白、双眼圆睁，语气平静地问，“你是真的已经打算好了不当战士而去做牧师了吗？”

“我想说牧师也是战士——是教会这支军队的一员。当然我不想在这里说教，惹你不快。我明确地回答，是的。”

过了一段时间，一天深夜，他发现她坐在房间里微弱的炉火旁独自垂泪，没有注意到他进来了。

“我可怜的宝贝，你为什么要哭呢？”他问。

她吓了一跳，然后说：“因为你跟我说过的那些话！”

上尉很是心烦意乱，但并未因此改变主意。

不久后，镇上的人听说蒙布里上尉从第X骠骑兵团退伍，去了芳托神学院进修，要改行做牧师了，都不禁惊诧万分。

四

“唉，太可惜了！这么英俊潇洒的一个军人——这么受人追捧——简直就是全镇的骄傲——社交生活的灵魂人物啊！结果现在！……虽然不该说死人的坏话，但是都怪那个可恶的圣威先生——他这是造孽啊！”

当蒙布里上尉，现在已经是约翰·蒙布里牧师，得天时地利，如愿回到了原来建功立业的地方，成为一个传福音的牧师时，大家各种说长道短，总结起来不外如是。镇上有一片低洼地区，当时密密麻麻地挤满了贫民窟居民，正急需一位副牧师，蒙布里便慷慨地主动请缨，虽然明知自己的努力很可能徒劳无功，也不会有感谢、赞扬或酬劳。

如果诚实地评价他作为一名传教士的成就，那完全跟出色沾不上边。大家都能看出他勤勉努力、专心致志、虔诚真挚，但是他的演讲太过刻意，他的布道太过枯燥，而且，唉，太过冗长。就连那些此刻正坐在白鹿客栈的酒吧厅里——客栈就坐落在刚提到的贫民窟和之前蒙布里混得风生水起的富人区的分界线上，因此从地理位置上来说也是严格的不偏不倚的——公正的看客判官也大体上赞同西城区那些年轻姑娘的观点，虽然他们表达得更加简洁尖刻：“唉，上帝他老人家真是毁了个优秀的军人，造出来个糟糕的牧师，把蒙布里上尉弄得跟个木乃伊一样干巴巴的！”

蒙布里知道别人怎么评论他，但他依然每天出入那些肮脏破败的小屋，内心平静，毫不受影响。

飘窗后的病人就是在这个时候同蒙布里太太有了更深的交情。她同丈夫一起回到了镇上，就住在他的辖区正中央的一所小房子里，通过某种渠道她成了这位病人的访客。她与一位两人共同的朋友正坐在他屋里聊天，外面发生的事又触及了她心底的痛处。她的脸比原来苍白消瘦了许多，失落使她的脸庞多了些柔和与若有所思，让她那以前有些轻佻的脸现在显得更迷人了。这两位女士来访是希望借飘窗一用，好目送骠骑兵团拔营离开，他们要迁到离伦敦更近的军营去了。

士兵们转过军营路拐角，踏上高街顶端，走在最前面的是领头的乐队，正在演奏《我留下的姑娘》（从前但凡这种时刻就会奏这曲子，不过现在已经弃用了）。他们渐渐走近，经过飘窗，有一两位军官抬头看到了蒙布里太太，向她行礼致意。她听着乐声逐渐远去，不禁热泪盈眶。这三人还没从刚才那壮观场面带来的浪漫气氛中回过神来，就看见蒙布里先生沿着人行道走来。他大概已经在街头跟从前的战友们道过别了，因为他正从那个方向过来。蒙布里先生穿着寒碜的教士长袍，胳膊上还挎着个篮子，里面装的似乎是他为贫苦的教众买的一些东西。跟那些骑兵完全不同，他对自己的外表或者周围环境淡然置之。

对萝拉来说这种反差实在是太强烈了。她嘴唇开始颤抖，问那位病人他怎么看待她的际遇变化。

这个问题对方很难回答，但她一时情绪激动，又任性地重复了一遍这个问题。

“你认为，”她又补充说，“作为有家室的人，一个丈夫有权这样做吗，就算是他觉得自己受到了神召？”

她的倾听者对她和她丈夫都抱着巨大的同情，因此没法给出一个满意的回答。萝拉满怀向往地望着窗外，骑兵们现在正朝着梅尔斯托克岭的方向逐渐远去，变成了尘土飞扬的一条细线。“我，”她说，“本来应该坐在马车里跟着他们一起去伦敦的，结果却注定要在邓诺威巷的窟窿里头腐烂化脓！”

从她那天离开到病人再见到她，这中间发生了许多事，有许多关于她的传言。

五

卡斯特桥曾历经战乱与和平时期，有欢乐的岁月，也有忧伤的日子，而现在则突降天灾。霍乱在这片苦难的土地上肆虐，这个古老市镇洼地上的区域则惨遭最严重的蹂躏。蒙布里的教区在邓诺威区的米克森巷，是重灾区。但是这恶疾选在蒙布里在任时爆发，已经算是对人们的一种怜悯了。

疾病传播得太快，许多人不得不离开镇上到附近乡下或农场暂住。蒙布里先生的房子距离受灾最重的街区很近，而他每天早中晚都在努力扑灭病魔，缓解被感染的病人的痛苦。因此为了慎重起见，他决定让妻子暂时离开，同自己隔离。

她想到了海边的一个村庄，离巴德茅斯—里吉斯很近。她的住处被安排在了克雷斯顿，离卡斯特桥镇不过六英里，然而有一道高高的山岭将之与卡斯特桥所在的山谷隔绝开来，因此那里现在的气氛完全不同。

她便去了该处，在这安全地带过着乡下生活。与此同时，她的丈夫正在贫民窟里日夜操劳。这时她认识了一位第Y步兵团的中尉，范尼科克先生，他所在的团正驻扎在巴德茅斯步兵营里。萝拉常常坐在海滩边的乘凉架下，望着一层层细浪缓缓爬上沙滩，漫不经心地倾听浪花退去时冲蚀鹅卵石的声音。而他则常常在那边散步。

两人很快从相识到相知。她的境遇、过往、美貌与年纪——比他年长一两岁——都在这个年轻人心中刻下了深深的烙印，于是很快在那片孤独的海滩上，两人开始了毫无顾忌的调情嬉闹。

事后，有些恶意诋毁她的人说她当初选这个地方住就是为了接近这位先生，但是我们有理由相信她在去之前与他从未谋面。而此时卡斯特桥正疲于应付自己的悲惨遭遇——每天都有人下葬，有被污染的衣物和寝具需要销毁——因此就算有关于两人的流言传来，也无暇传播。悲剧的阴云笼罩了一切，没人有功夫理睬萝拉的事。

与此同时，在山另一侧的巴德茅斯，人们的情绪则大不相同。这边受灾情况很轻而且很早就过去了，现在已经恢复了正常的工作和娱乐。蒙布里先生设法每周去看萝拉两次，都是在露天里，以保证她不会被他感染，而且他丝毫没有听说那些隐约的传闻。一个风大天干的下午，他如常与她在隔开两地的山顶见面，附近就是连接各市镇的公路，与古老的山脊路呈直角交叉。

他看到她走近，微笑着挥挥手，大声对她喊：“亲爱的，我们就隔着这个墙说话吧。”（在此地，田地之间都用矮土墙做篱笆。）“我一定不能让你有危险。托上帝的福，应该不会太久了！”

“那我就照你的吩咐做吧，杰克。但是你自己却在冒着巨大的风险，是不是？我没有听人说起你，但我猜你肯定是身处危险中。”

“我的风险并不比别人的更大。”

两人就这样一本正经地聊了一会儿，吹来一阵风拍打着中间那磨坊矮堰般的土墙。

“你好像有什么事情要问我是吗？”他又补充了一句。

“有的。你知道，我们正想办法在巴德茅斯筹款帮助你的受灾民众。我们想到的方式是戏剧表演。他们想让我参加演出。”

他的脸色黯淡下来，“这事我再了解不过了，还有背后的各种花招！我希望你们能想点别的方法筹款。”

她轻描淡写地说恐怕事情已经定下来了。“所以你反对我参加演出是吗？当然——”

他告诉她，他并不是说全然反对，但希望他们可以选择清唱剧、演讲，或者其他方式，好与救济的目的更相称一些。

“但是，”她有些不耐烦地说，“大家根本就不会去看清唱剧或者听演讲呀！他们只会挤着去看喜剧或者闹剧。”

“是啊，我无法命令巴德茅斯人应该怎样去赚那些要用在我们身上的钱。是谁来筹办这次表演？”

“第Y步兵团的小伙子们。”

“噢，是了，那是我们的老把戏！”蒙布里先生回答，“卡斯特桥的苦难正是他们寻欢作乐的理由！坦率地说，亲爱的萝拉，我希望你不要参加演出。不过我不会禁止你这样做，由你自己来做判断吧。”

这次会面结束了，两人便各奔南北。事后众人才知晓，蒙布里太太在喜剧中扮演的是女主角，而她剧中的恋人一角则由范尼科克先生出演。

六

这对相互吸引的人早就在酝酿着要做一件事，而这次演出则促成了此事。

细节无须赘述，第Y步兵团要离开巴德茅斯去布里斯托尔了，这加速了他们的行动。犹豫了一个礼拜之后，她同意离开克雷斯顿的住处，在附近的山岭上同范尼科克碰头，跟他一起去巴斯，他会在那里帮她找好住处，这样她离他所在的营地就只有十多英里远。

于是在选定要离开的那天傍晚，她在梳妆台上给丈夫写了一封信，上面写着：

亲爱的杰克，

我无法再继续忍受这样的生活，所以决定要与它作别。我告诉过你，如果你坚持要去当牧师我就会离家出走，现在我履行了诺言。我天性如此，无法改变。我已决定往后要同范尼科克先生休戚与共。我希望——但并不指望——你能原谅我。

萝

然后她连行李都没带就出发了，傍晚时在暮色中登上了山岭。几乎就在上次同她丈夫相会的同一个地点，她看到了范尼科克的身影，他从布里斯托尔一路过来接她。

“我不要在这儿跟你见面——太晦气了！”她朝他喊道，“我的天哪，我们另外选个地方吧。你退回到路碑那里去，我过来见你。”

他往回走到了山岭北面斜坡上的路碑旁，那是老路与新路交会处，她在那里跟他碰了头。

他问她为何不肯在山顶上跟他会面，她沉默不语，面色戚戚。过了一会儿，她询问他们要坐什么交通工具旅行。

他解释说，他打算步行去到卡斯特桥镇另一端的梅尔斯托克山，那里会有一辆轻便的双轮出租马车等着他们，再带他们走捷径到艾威尔公路，一直送他们到艾威尔镇。去布里斯托尔的铁路就经过艾威尔。

他们依计行事，在一片朦胧昏暗中轻快地走着，慢慢靠近了卡斯特桥镇。为避人耳目他们到了罗马圆剧场后便转而向右，绕到了邓诺威十字路口。那儿有一条人烟稀少的路穿过荒原通往梅尔斯托克山，去往艾威尔的马车就在那里等着他们。

“我刚才一直注意到，”她说，“镇上邓诺威区那一头上空闪耀着刺目的光。好像是从米克森巷某个地方传来的。”

“可能是灯光吧。”他猜想说。

“那条巷子里没有一盏比灯芯草蜡烛还大的灯。那是霍乱最严重的地方。”

在过了十字路口稍远一些的斯坦德法斯特拐角，他们突然看到了小巷尽头的景象。在路中间，许多巨大的火堆在熊熊燃烧，以做净化空气之用；人们把铺盖和衣物从巷子里那些沿街的破落房屋里搬出来。有的被扔进了火里，剩下的放到手推车上推到荒原上去，正好在这两个私奔者的必经之路上。

他们沿路继续往前走，看到了露天安放着一口巨大的铜锅。铺盖衣物等就在这里用滚水煮沸消毒。借着灯光，萝拉发现她的丈夫就站在铜锅旁，正是他把手推车上的东西卸下来浸入水中。夜晚如此宁静闷热，铜锅边的对话清晰地传到她耳中。

“今晚还有很多车需要消毒的衣物吗？”

“先生，还有些今天下午死掉的人的衣服。要不我们还是等到明天吧，你肯定已经累得不行了。”

“我们还是马上消毒吧，我不能让别人来做这件事。你把这一车倒在草地上，回去把剩下的拿过来吧。”

男子依言照办，推着手推车走了。蒙布里暂停片刻，擦了擦脸，在这一派肮脏污秽、水汽蒸腾的环境中继续干他那平凡的苦差，用一根看起来像旧擀面杖的东西把铜锅里的衣物下压、搅拌。锅中升腾起的蒸汽，满载着死亡的讯息，低低地飘过草地。

萝拉突然开口说：“我今天晚上还是不去了。他太累了，我一定得帮帮他。我没想到情况会这么糟糕！”

范尼科克的胳膊从她腰上垂了下来，之前走路时他的手一直搂着她的腰。“你会离开吗？”她问。

“如果你坚持要我走的话我就走，不过我更想一起帮忙。”他的语气听起来并没有反对或抗议。

萝拉此刻已经走上前去，“杰克，我来帮你的忙了！”

疲惫不堪的牧师转过身，举起灯笼察看。“啊——怎么会是你，萝拉？”他吃惊地说，“你为什么来这儿掺和？你最好回去——太危险了。”

“但是我想帮你的忙，杰克。请让我一起帮忙吧！我不是一个人，是范尼科克先生陪我来的。如果他还没有走的话，应该也能帮上忙。范尼科克先生！”

年轻的中尉有些不情愿地走上前来。蒙布里先生很正式地跟他交谈了几句，就继续劳作去了，顺便说了一句：“我以为第Y步兵团已经去了布里斯托尔了呢。”

“是的，不过我因为有事处理所以又回来了一趟。”

两位新来的人开始干活，范尼科克把背着的小包放到地上，里面装的是萝拉的盥洗用品。很快推车的男人又推了一车衣物过来了，几人一起干了近半小时，一个马车夫从北面的阴影里冒了出来。

“对不起，先生，”他小声对范尼科克说，“我在梅尔斯托克山那儿等得太久了，最后就赶车下山到了大路上；我看到这儿有光，就过来看看发生了什么事。”

范尼科克中尉告诉他再等几分钟，最后一车衣物已经处理完了。蒙布里先生伸了个懒腰，喘着粗气说：“好啦！我们只能干到这儿了。”

一旦神经松懈下来，他似乎就被剧烈的疼痛侵袭了。他双手按着两肋向前弯下腰。

“啊！我估计病魔最终还是找上我啦，”他吃力地说，“我得想办法回家去，萝拉，让范尼科克先生送你回去吧。”

他在他们的搀扶下走了几步，然后不得不颓然坐在草地上。

“恐——怕——你们得去弄个架子，或者板子之类的来了，”他虚弱地说，“或者想办法把我弄到手推车上去。”

但是范尼科克已经去喊马车夫了。等到车夫把马车从附近的大路上赶过来，蒙布里先生被扶了进去。萝拉也跟着上了马车，来到了他在十字路口附近的简陋住所，把他送上了楼。

范尼科克在屋外空马车旁等候了一阵，但是萝拉没有再出来。他于是上了马车，让车夫带他回艾威尔镇去了。

七

蒙布里先生在救助受苦受难的穷苦民众时操劳过度，最终成了夺走无数生命的病魔的牺牲品——也是最后一批之一。两天以后他就躺在了棺中。

萝拉就在楼下的房间里。仆人送来了一些信件，她大致浏览了一下。其中一封就是她自己写给蒙布里的，告诉他她无法忍受跟他一起生活，打算跟范尼科克私奔。读完后她把信带上楼，塞进了死者的木棺中。第二天她便将他下葬了。

她现在自由了。

她封了他在邓诺威十字路口的房子，回到了克雷斯顿的住处。很快她收到了范尼科克的来信。她丈夫去世六周之后，她的情人过来看她了。

“我忘了把这个还给你——那天晚上。”他随即说到，把她私奔时装着她全部行李的小包递给她。

萝拉接过来，漫不经心地把包抖开。掉落在地板上的是她的牙刷、梳子、拖鞋、睡衣和其他旅行用品。它们现在看上去丑恶不堪、令人讨厌，她试图把它们盖起来。

“现在我可以，”他说，“合法地向你求婚了——再等上一段时间——不用像我们当初打算的那样私奔了。”

他说这话时显得无精打采，似乎在暗示说者有些言不由衷。萝拉把地上的东西捡起来，回答说他自然可以向她求婚——反正她已经自由了。但是她的表情同样完全看不出一丝热忱。然后她的眼睛眨得越来越快，只得用手帕掩住了脸。一时间她泣不成声。

他没有动，也没有试图安慰她。是什么介入了两人之间呢？没有任何活人。他们曾是恋人，现在也没有任何实质性障碍阻止他们结合了。然而那个故去的人的影子却挥之不去：他消瘦的身形，在阴暗的邓诺威荒原上，在那可怕的熔炉前来来回回走动着。

不过范尼科克如果到附近来的话，还是会去看看萝拉，虽然次数不多；但两年后，似乎是故意要促成这桩人人都认定了的婚事，第Y步兵团又回到了巴德茅斯-里吉斯驻扎。

这样一来两人就不得不经常碰面了。但是或许是因为障碍才是爱情之源，又或许是因为心怀负罪感，也可能是因为做了寡妇的蒙布里太太美貌大不如前，他们对彼此的热情已然消退，从以前的如火如荼变成现在的不温不火。后来范尼科克是否成家，飘窗后的朋友不得而知。但蒙布里太太终其一生都是寡妇，不曾再婚。

一九〇〇年

[1]Triolet是西方文学中的一种诗歌体裁形式，一般为八行，有两个韵脚，因此汉语中译为“八行双韵体”。十九世纪英国诗歌在使用八行双韵体时，一般习惯采用ABaAabAB格律，即一、三、四、五、七行均押a韵（本文中为-est韵），但一、四、七行重复同一个单词（本文中为blest）；二、六、八行押b韵（本文中为-ire韵），但二、八行重复（本文中为desire）。同时，每一行诗句均为四步抑扬格，即含有四个音步，每个音步有两个元音，前一个弱读后一个重读，称为抑扬格。如“If hours/be years/the twain/are blest”，就是典型的四步抑扬格诗句。译文韵脚也对应使用了英文的格律模式（a韵为-u，b韵为-an）。

第二章　汤姆的幼年时代

我们现在跳过若干年，来谈谈以后的事情吧。

当时伦敦已有一千五百年的历史，以那时候的规模而论，要算是一个大城市了。全城有十万居民——有人认为比这还要多一倍。街道都很狭窄、弯曲而肮脏，尤其是汤姆·康第所住的那一带离伦敦桥不远的地方。那儿的房屋都是木头建筑的，第二层楼突出于第一层之外，第三层又把它的胳臂肘伸出第二层的范围。房子盖得越高，上面的面积也就越大。房屋的骨架是用结实的木料钉成交叉的形式，中间加上一些牢靠的材料，外面再涂上一层灰泥。房屋的主人按照各自的脾性把屋梁漆成红色、蓝色或黑色，这就使得那些房屋显出一副很雅致的气派。窗户都很小，嵌着菱形的小玻璃；窗扇都像屋门那样，是向外开的，装的枢纽也像门上的一样。

汤姆的父亲所住的房子，在布丁巷外面一个名叫垃圾大院的肮脏小死巷里面。那所房子又小又破，东歪西倒，里面却挤满了一些穷得要命的人家。康第那一窝在三层楼上占着一个房间。母亲和父亲在一个角落里有一张也算是床的床铺；可是汤姆和他的祖母，还有他的两个姐姐——白特和南恩，却不受拘束——全部的地板都归他们享用，他们爱在哪儿睡就在哪儿睡。屋里有一两条破得不像样的毯子，还有几捆又旧又脏的稻草，可是要把这些东西叫作床铺，似乎不大妥当，因为它们是乱七八糟的；每天早晨，这些东西老是整个儿被踢成一大堆，到了晚上，大家再把它们从这一堆里挑出来使用。

白特和南恩都是十五岁——一对双胞胎。她们是心肠很好的姑娘，满身肮脏，穿得非常破烂，愚昧透顶。她们的母亲也和她们相似。可是父亲和祖母简直是一对恶魔。他们只要有酒喝，就喝得烂醉；然后他们就互相打架，或是碰上谁就和谁相打；无论醉与不醉，他们老是咒骂不休。约翰·康第是个小偷，他母亲是个乞丐。他们把孩子们都教成了叫花子，可是还没有能够把他们变成小偷。在这所房子里住着的乌七八糟的穷人当中，有一位善良的老神父，可是他并不属于他们那一伙。国王给了他一点点极微薄的养老金，把他从家里一下子撵了出来；他常爱把孩子们叫到一边，暗自教他们一些正当的行为。安德鲁神父教给汤姆一点拉丁文，并且还教他读书写字；他本想把这些东西也教给那两个姑娘，可是她们害怕朋友们的嘲笑，因为如果她们俩要有那些稀奇的学问，朋友们是绝不会容忍的。

整个垃圾大院里乱哄哄的一窝正和康第家里一模一样。酗酒、胡闹和吵嘴在那儿是家常便饭，每天晚上都是如此，而且几乎是通宵达旦。在那一带，打破脑袋和饥饿是同样寻常的事情，可是小汤姆并不觉得不愉快。他的日子过得很苦，可是他自己并不知道。他那种生活和垃圾大院所有的孩子过的是一样的，因此他也就以为那是合适的、舒服的生活。他晚上空手回家的时候，知道他父亲首先就要骂他一顿，再揍他一顿，等他父亲打骂够了之后，祖母又要再来一遍，而且更加厉害；他还知道，到了深夜，他那饿着肚子的母亲就要偷偷地溜到他身边来，把她宁肯自己挨饿也要给他省下来的一点儿半点儿可怜的面包皮或残屑拿给他吃，虽然她常因这种大逆不道的行为被发觉而要挨她的丈夫一顿毒打。

反正汤姆的生活是过得很顺当的，尤其是在夏天。他只去讨到够他自己活命的东西，因为禁止行乞的法律很严厉，刑罚也很重；所以他把许多时间用来听安德鲁神父讲那些关于巨人和仙女，矮子和妖怪，以及妖魔盘踞城堡，气派的国王和王子的迷人的古老故事和传说。他脑子里渐渐装满了这些稀奇的事情，于是有许多个晚上，当他在黑暗中躺在他那薄薄的、发臭的稻草上，又倦又饿，挨过鞭打之后还在疼痛的时候，他就展开他的想象力，津津有味地给他自己描绘着一座王宫里的一位娇养的王子那种惬意的生活，因此不久就把他的痛楚都忘记了。后来就有一种愿望日夜在他心中萦绕，那就是要亲眼看见一个真正的王子。有一次，他向那些垃圾大院的玩伴谈这桩心事；可是他们非常刻薄地嘲笑他，挖苦他，以致他从此以后情愿把他的梦想留在自己心里。

他常常读神父的古书，并且还请他讲解，再把那里面所说的加以渲染。后来由于梦想和读书的结果，他心理上起了一些变化。他的梦中人物都非常漂亮，以致他渐渐地为他自己的破烂衣服和满身的肮脏而感到痛心，并且还希望自己能干净一些，穿得好一些。他还是照常到泥潭里去玩，并且也玩得很痛快；他也到泰晤士河里去拍水玩，却不像过去那样只是为了游戏，而是因为河水可以把他身上和脸上洗干净，使他开始发现了它的另一种价值。

汤姆经常可以看到契普赛街的五月柱[2]周围和市集上有些活动；间或逢着某一位不幸的要人由陆路或水路被押解到伦敦塔[3]去的时候，他和伦敦其余的人还有机会看到军队的行列在街上通过。某年夏季有一天，他还在史密斯菲尔德区看见不幸的爱恩·艾斯裘和三个男人被绑在火刑柱上烧死，并且还听见一位前任主教给他们讲道，可是他对这位主教所讲的话并不感兴趣。是呀，汤姆的生活大体上是花样够多，也很愉快的。

后来汤姆所读的关于王子生活的书和他在这方面的梦想竟对他产生了那么强烈的影响，以至于他不知不觉地扮演起王子来了。他的谈话和举动变得特别斯文而有宫廷派头，使他那些亲密的朋友非常羡慕，也觉得非常好玩儿。于是这时候，汤姆在这些年轻小伙子当中的威信一天天增长了；后来他在他们心目中终于成了一个超凡出众的人物，大家对他都怀着一种敬畏的心理。他似乎知道得真多呀！他居然能做出和说出那许多了不起的事情！而且，他还那么足智多谋！他说的话和他的举动，都由这些孩子报告给他们的父兄；这些人也就马上开始谈论汤姆·康第，而且把他看成一个最有才华的非凡角色。成年人把他们的疑难拿来向汤姆请教，他的解答所表现的才智每每使他们大为惊异。事实上，除了他自己家里的人以外，在他所有相识的人的心目中，他都成了一位英雄——只有他家里的人一点儿也看不出他有什么了不起的地方。

过了不久，汤姆居然暗中组织了一个小朝廷！他自己当王子，他的亲近玩伴有的当警卫，有的当宫内大臣，有的当武官，还有当侍从和宫女的，有当王室成员的。这位假扮的王子天天都按照他从书本上那些传奇故事里学来的一些繁缛的礼节接受大家的拜见，这个虚构的王国的国家大事天天都在御前会议上被提出来讨论，这位假扮的殿下天天都给他想象中的陆军、海军和总督们颁发法令。

这以后，他就穿着那身破烂衣服到街上去，讨几个小铜板，吃他那少得可怜的面包壳，再照例挨打挨骂，然后在他那一小把肮脏的稻草上躺下来，又在梦想中恢复他那虚构的荣华富贵的生活了。

然而他还是想见到一位真正的、活着的王子，亲自看他一眼。这个愿望一天又一天、一个礼拜又一个礼拜地在他心中越发强烈，直到后来，它把其他一切愿望都吞没了，终于成了他生活中的唯一热望。

一月的一天，他照例出去行乞，无精打采地在明兴巷和小东契普街一带来回地缓步走着，光着脚，冷得难受，眼睛直往食品店的橱窗里瞟，渴望吃那里面摆着的猪肉饼和其他叫人馋得要命的新花样——在他看来，这些东西都是专供天使享用的美味；这就是说，从它们的香气中判断，应该是如此——因为他从来没有走过那种好运，不曾享有和吃过这类东西。天上下着寒冷的毛毛雨，天空是阴沉的，那是个凄凉的日子。晚上汤姆回到家里，浑身湿透，又乏又饿，以致连他的父亲和祖母看了他这种倒霉的光景，也不能不表示同情——他们自有他们表示同情的方式。于是他们马上使劲赏了他一顿拳头，叫他去睡觉。有好一阵工夫，他的疼痛和饥饿，还有那所房子里正在进行着的咒骂和殴打，老使他睡不成觉；可是后来他的思绪终于飘到了老远的、神秘的地方，于是他就睡着了。他在梦中和一些戴着宝石饰品、满身金光闪闪的小王子在一起，这些王子都住在偌大的宫殿中，面前有许多仆人行着额手礼，飞快地跑去执行他们的命令。然后就像往日一样，他又梦见他自己是一个小王子了。

整夜里，他那帝王身份的荣光始终照耀着他；他在灯烛辉煌中，在大臣和贵妇当中走动，呼吸着香气，陶醉于美妙的音乐中；闪闪发光的人群一面给他让出路来，一面毕恭毕敬地向他鞠躬致敬，他就派头十足地冲这儿笑一笑，冲那儿点点头，表示答礼。

清早醒来时，他一看周围那种倒霉的情景，他那一场好梦就对他起了惯常的作用——使他那环境的肮脏鄙陋增强了一千倍。于是随之而来的就是苦痛、伤心和眼泪。

第三章　汤姆和王子的会见

汤姆饿着肚子起来，又饿着肚子出去游荡，可是他心里还是忙着回想头天晚上他做的梦里那些模糊的辉煌景象。他在城里到处游荡，甚至不大注意自己在往哪儿走，也没有发觉身边发生了一些什么事情。人们拼命挤他，还有些人骂他，可是这一切对这个沉思的孩子都完全不起作用。后来他走到了邓普尔门，这是他由家里往这个方向走得最远的一次。他站住想了一会儿，然后又沉入他的幻想中，随即继续往前走，出了伦敦的城墙。河滨马路当时已经不是一条乡间的大路了，而说它是一条街道，却也很牵强；因为它虽然有一边排列着大致紧密相连的一排房屋，另一边却只有几所分散的大房子，这些大房子都是当时富有的贵族之家的大厦，前面宽大而美丽的庭园一直延伸到河边——这些庭园中现在都密密地盖满了占地若干英亩的、威严的砖石建筑物了。

汤姆随即就发现了翠林庄。他在早前一位死了亲人的国王在那儿建的一座美丽的十字碑前休息了一会儿，然后又顺着一条幽静的、可爱的路闲逛过去，经过红衣大主教的庄严宫殿，朝着一座更雄伟、更堂皇的建筑——威斯敏斯特宫——走过去。汤姆瞪着眼睛望着那老大的一堆建筑物，望着那伸出很远的边厢，那威严的棱堡和角楼，那巨大的石造大门，上面有金漆的门栅，门前排列着许多庄严的、庞大的花岗石狮子，还有其他英国皇家的标志和表征，他简直看得满心欢喜，非常惊奇。难道他心中的愿望终于可以得到满足了吗？这儿可的确是一座国王的宫殿呀。假如老天爷愿意开恩的话，他现在岂不是有希望见到一位王子——一位有血有肉的王子了吗？

那金漆大门两边都站着一个活的雕像，那就是说，一个站得笔挺的、威严的、一动也不动的士兵，从头顶到脚跟穿着全副闪亮的钢盔甲。有许多乡下人和城里来的人，为了表示尊敬，站在一段距离之外，大家等待着机会，希望偶然有王室成员出现的时候能够饱一饱眼福。豪华的马车里坐着尊贵的人物，外面还有华丽的仆从，一辆辆地从穿过皇家围墙的另外几座雄伟的大门里驶进驶出。

可怜的小汤姆穿着他那身破烂衣服走过去，他心头剧跳，希望高涨。当他畏怯而迟缓地走过那两个卫兵的时候，忽然从那金漆门栅里一眼瞟见里面有一个出色的人物，这使他几乎欢喜得大声喊叫起来。门内有一个漂亮的男孩子，他因为常进行露天游戏和运动，皮肤晒得又红又黑；他穿的衣服全是漂亮的绸缎，满身宝石闪着光彩；他腰上带着一把剑和一把匕首，都镶着宝石；脚上穿着雅致的红后跟短筒靴；头上戴着一顶华丽的深红色帽子，从帽子上垂下的羽毛由一颗巨大的、闪光的宝石扣紧。有几个打扮得很讲究的男人在他近旁站着——不消说，那都是他的仆人。啊！他准是位王子——准是位王子，活生生的王子，真正的王子——毫无疑问，那贫儿心中所祈求的事情终于如愿以偿了。

汤姆兴奋得呼吸都加快和短促起来，他的眼睛也因为惊奇和高兴而睁得很大了。他心里立刻就忘记了一切事情，完全让一个愿望占据了：走近王子身边，把他仔细盯住，好好地瞧一瞧。他对自己的举动还在无知无觉的时候，就把脸贴近那栅门了。那两个兵士之中马上就有一个很粗暴地揪着他，一把推开，推得他像个陀螺似的滚出老远，滚到那些张着嘴看热闹的一群乡下人和伦敦的闲人当中去了。那个士兵说：

“规矩点儿吧，你这小叫花子！”

那一群人都嘲笑起来，还哈哈大笑；可是那年轻的王子飞跑到大门那儿，满脸涨得通红，眼睛里闪着愤怒的光。他大声喝道：

“你怎么胆敢这样虐待一个可怜的孩子！你怎么胆敢这样虐待我父王最低微的老百姓！快打开大门，让他进来！”

这下子那一群反复无常的闲人连忙摘下帽子来，那真是叫你看了好笑。你只消听他们大声欢呼“太子万岁”，也会觉得怪有趣的。

那两个兵士举起戟来敬礼，随即打开大门，并且在那“穷人国的王子”穿着那身随风飘动的破烂衣裳走进来和那富甲天下的王子握手的时候，他们又敬了一次礼。

爱德华·都铎说：

“你好像疲倦了，肚子也饿了吧，你受了委屈哩。跟我来吧。”

五六个仆从猛地向前面扑过去，想要——我不知道是干什么；不消说，是想阻挡吧。可是王子气派十足地摆了摆手，叫他们退到旁边。于是他们就在那儿呆呆地站着不动，活像几尊雕像一般。爱德华把汤姆带进王宫里一个豪华的房间，他说这是他的私室。仆人遵照他的命令，送来了一份讲究的饭菜，这种食品汤姆除了在书里看见过以外，从来没有碰到过。王子毕竟有王子的斯文派头和礼貌，他吩咐仆人们都出去，好让他这位卑微的客人不致因为他们在场品头论足而感到局促不安；然后他坐到近旁，一面让汤姆吃饭，一面问他一些问题：

“你叫什么名字，小伙子？”

“禀告王子，贱名汤姆·康第。”

“这名字有些古怪哩。你住在什么地方？”

“禀告王子，我住在旧城里。住在垃圾大院，在布丁巷外面。”

“垃圾大院！真是，这又是个古怪名称。父母在世吗？”

“父母我都有，王子，还有个奶奶，她对我可以算是个可有可无的亲人，这话说出来也许有罪，但愿上帝饶恕我；另外还有一对孪生的姐姐，南恩和白特。”

“那么我猜你奶奶对你准是不太疼爱吧。”

“禀告殿下，她无论对什么人都不大好。她心肠很坏，一辈子专干坏事。”

“她虐待你吗？”

“她也有住手的时候，那就是她睡着了，或是醉得不能动弹的时候。可是她的脑筋一清醒过来，她就要拼命地打我，打够了才算数。”

小王子眼睛里露出非常生气的神情，他大声喊道：

“怎么！她打你吗？”

“啊，王子，禀告殿下，她确实是打我。”

“打你呀——你的身体这么弱，个子这么小！听着，不等到晚上，就叫她上塔里去[4]。我的父王……”

“殿下，您忘记了她是下等人哩。塔里是专关大人物的。”

“这话有理。我没有想到这个。我要考虑怎么处罚她。你父亲对你好不好？”

“也不比康第奶奶强哩，殿下。”

“当父亲的大概都一样吧。我的父亲脾气也不好。他打起人来使老大的劲儿，可是他不打我；不过说老实话，他嘴上可不一定饶我。你母亲对你怎么样？”

“她很好，殿下，她一点儿也不叫我发愁，也不叫我吃苦。南恩和白特也是这样，正像我母亲的脾气。”

“她们俩多大年纪？”

“禀告殿下，十五岁。”

“我姐姐伊丽莎白公主是十四岁，堂姐洁恩·格雷公主和我同岁，都长得很好，也很和气；我姐姐玛丽公主的态度却阴沉沉的，她——咦，我问你：你姐姐也不许她们的仆人笑，怕的是这种不端庄的行为会摧毁她们的灵魂吗？”

“她们吗？啊，殿下，您以为连她们也有仆人吗？”

小王子认真地把这小叫花子打量了一会儿，然后说：

“请问你，为什么没有？晚上谁帮她们脱衣裳？早上起来，谁帮她们打扮？”

“没有人帮忙，殿下。难道她们还能把衣裳脱掉，光着身子睡觉——像野兽那样吗？”

“脱掉衣裳就光着身子！难道她们只有一件衣服？”

“啊，殿下圣明，她们还要更多的衣服有什么用？真是，她们每人并没有两个身体呀。”

“这个想法真是古怪，真是稀奇！对不起，我并不是故意发笑。可是我要叫你的好姐姐南恩和白特有好衣服，还要有够她们使唤的用人，而且很快就会有：我叫我的财政大臣去办。不，用不着向我道谢，这不算什么。你说话说得很好，很文雅。念过书吗？”

“我不知道我算不算念过书的，殿下。有一个名叫安德鲁的神父好心地教过我，我念的是他的书。”

“你懂得拉丁文吗？”

“我想我懂的很有限哩，殿下。”

“好好学吧，小伙子，只有开始的时候难。希腊文还要难一些；可是无论是这两种，或是任何别的文字，伊丽莎白公主和我的堂姐学起来都不难。你要瞧见这两位姑娘念起那些洋文来才有趣哪！可是你还是给我谈谈你们那个垃圾大院吧。你在那儿过的日子很痛快吗？”

“说实在话，那是很痛快的，殿下，只有肚子饿了的时候才不好受。那儿有潘趣傀儡戏，还有猴儿——啊，这些小畜生真有趣！穿得也真漂亮！——还有些戏里的角色都拼命地嚷，拼命地打斗，一直斗到戏里的人都被杀光才算完，那可真好看，看一回只要一个小铜板——不过殿下您可不知道，我那一个小铜板赚来可是真费劲呀。”

“你再给我说一些吧。”

“我们垃圾大院的孩子们有时候拿着棍子彼此打斗，就像那些戏里的角色那样打法。”

王子眼睛里闪出喜悦的光彩。他说：

“哟！这我倒觉得很不错。再给我说一些吧。”

“殿下，我们还赛跑哩，为的是要看谁跑得最快。”

“这个我也很喜欢。再往下说吧。”

“殿下，每到夏天，我们就在运河和大河里蹚水和浮水，各人都把身边的人按在水里，拍水溅他，并且还往水里钻，或是大声嚷，在水里摔跤，还……”

“只要能像这样玩一回，拿我父亲的江山作为代价也值得！请你再往下说吧。”

“我们还在契普赛街围着五月柱跳舞唱歌；我们在沙土里玩，各人把身边的人拿沙子盖起来；我们还常拿泥做糕饼——啊，多好玩儿的泥呀，真是全世界没有像那么有趣的东西！殿下您别怪我胡说，我们简直就在泥里打滚。”

“啊，请你别再说了，真是妙不可言！要是我能穿上你那样的衣裳，脱光了脚，到泥里去痛痛快快玩一次，只要玩一次，没有人骂我或是禁止我，那我想我连王冠都可以不要了！”

“殿下，要是我能把您那样的衣服穿一次——只要能穿一次……”

“哦嗬，你爱穿吗？那么就这么办吧。把你的破衣服脱下来，穿上这些讲究东西吧，小伙子！这可以暂时换点快乐，可是那也还是一样过瘾。我们趁这机会痛快一下吧，不等别人来干涉，就可以再换过来。”

几分钟之后，小太子就披上了汤姆那身随风飘的破烂东西，同时那贫民窟的“小王子”却穿上了豪华的皇家服装，打扮得很神气了。他们俩走到一面大镜子前面，并肩站着，哈，真是一个奇迹：就好像根本没有换过衣服似的。他们睁开眼睛互相望着，然后又望着镜子，再互相望着。后来，那一脸疑惑的小王子终于说：

“你看这是怎么回事？”

“呀，殿下您可别叫我回答这个问题。我这样下贱的人说出那种话来，未免不大妥当。”

“那么就让我来说吧。你和我的头发是一样，眼睛是一样，声音和态度是一样，外貌和身材也是一样，面孔和气色还是一样。我们俩要是光着身子走出去，谁也分不清哪个是你，哪个是太子。现在我既然穿上了你的衣裳，似乎更能够体会你的委屈，我想起刚才那个野蛮的卫兵——嘿，你手上不是有个伤痕吗？”

“是的，不过这不要紧，殿下您知道那个可怜的卫兵……”

“且住！这事情太可耻，也太残忍！”小王子跺着他的光脚嚷道，“要是国王——你站住别动，等我回来！这是我的命令！”

片刻之后，他拿起一张桌子上放着的一件国宝，把它收好，马上就跑出去，穿着那身像旗子似的破衣服，飞跑着穿过宫中的庭园，脸上直发烧，眼睛里直冒火。他一走到大门那儿，就抓住栅门，把它使劲摇晃，一面大声嚷道：

“开门！把栅门打开！”

起先对汤姆很凶的那个兵士立刻就照办了。王子怒气冲天地冲出门口的时候，那兵士狠狠地打了他一个很响的耳光，把他打得一转一转地滚到大路上，一面骂道：

“赏你这个吧，你这叫花崽子！你让太子殿下跟我过不去，我这是还你的礼！”

外面那一群人哄笑起来。王子从泥潭里挣扎着爬起来，凶暴地向卫兵跑过去，一面嚷道：

“我是皇太子，我的御体是神圣不可侵犯的。你竟敢动手打我，我要处你绞刑！”

那卫兵举起手来敬礼，嘲笑地说：

“我给殿下您敬礼。”然后含怒地说，“快滚开，你这发了疯的小杂种！”

于是那看戏的一群人向着可怜的小王子围拢来，连挤带推拥着他顺着大路走了很远。大家嘲骂他，大声嚷着：“给太子殿下让路！给皇太子让路呀！”

第四章　王子开始遭难

经过好几小时持续的追逐和折磨之后，那一群闲人终于把王子抛开，不再纠缠他了。当他还能对那群暴徒大发脾气，摆出皇家的架子吓唬他们，并且发出皇家的命令，供他们取笑的时候，大家都觉得他怪好玩儿的；可是后来疲劳终于迫使他保持缄默，那些作弄他的人就对他不感兴趣，另找别处寻开心去了。这时候他向四周张望，可是并不认识那是什么地方。他是在伦敦城里——他所知道的就只有这一点。他漫无目的地往前走，过了一会儿，房屋渐渐稀少，过路的人也不多了。他把他那双流血的脚在小河里洗了洗，这条河流过的地方就是现在法林顿街的所在。他休息了几分钟，然后再往前走，不久就来到一块大空地，那儿只有几所疏散的房屋，还有一座巨大的教堂。这个教堂他是认识的。到处都搭着许多棚架，还有成群的工人，因为教堂正在进行维修。王子马上就精神焕发了——他觉得他的苦难现在已经结束了。他心里想道：“这是古老的圣芳济教堂，父王把它从修道士手中接收过来，改成了一所贫儿和弃儿的收养所，并且改名为基督教堂了。这里的人一定会乐于照顾这位对他们有过这么大恩惠的施主的儿子——尤其是因为那个儿子自己也像这里所收容的或是以后将要收容的儿童那样穷苦无依，他们更不能不予以照顾了。”

他不久就走到了一群男孩子当中，他们正在乱跑乱跳，打球和做跳背游戏，或是玩耍别的花样，玩得非常热闹。这些孩子都穿着同样的衣服，那种服装的样式是在当时的仆人和学徒当中很流行的——这就是说，每人头顶上戴着一顶黑色小扁帽，大小和茶碟差不多。这种帽子尺寸很小，对于遮盖头部并没有什么用处，同时也说不上有什么装饰的作用；头发并不分开，就从帽檐底下垂到额部中间，周围剪得整整齐齐；颈部围着一条像牧师系的那种宽领带；身上穿着一件紧身的蓝色长袍，一直垂到膝部，或是更低；又长又宽的袖子；红色的宽腰带；鲜黄色的长袜子，袜带系在膝部以上；短筒鞋，鞋上有大颗的金属鞋扣。这种服装真是够丑陋的。

孩子们停止了玩耍，围拢在王子身边，王子以天生的高贵神气说：

“好孩子们，去告诉你们的所长，就说皇太子爱德华要和他谈话。”

孩子们一听这话，大嚷了一阵，有一个粗鲁的小家伙说：

“哎呀哈，你是殿下的差人吗，叫花子？”

王子气得脸色通红，他马上就伸手到腰下去摸，可是腰下什么也没有。孩子们又大声哄笑了一阵，有一个孩子说：

“瞧见了吗？他还当是有一把剑哩——说不定他本人就是王子哪。”

这一句俏皮话又引起了一阵大笑。可怜的爱德华高傲地挺直身子说道：

“我就是王子。你们受了我父王的恩惠，反而这样对待我，未免太不懂礼。”

孩子们听了这话又觉得非常有趣，这可以由他们的一阵大笑看得出来。首先说话的那个小伙子对他的同伴们嚷道：

“嗬，你们这些畜生、奴才，靠太子殿下的父王施恩养活的家伙，怎么这么无礼？你们这些贱骨头快跪下，一齐跪下，瞻仰太子殿下的威仪和他这套皇家的破烂衣裳吧！”

大家在一阵狂笑中一齐跪下，以开玩笑的态度向他们作弄的对象致敬。王子一脚猛踢最靠近的那个孩子，暴怒地说：

“先赏你这一脚，且等明天我再给你搭起一个绞架来！”

哎呀，这可不是闹着玩的——简直超出开玩笑的范围了。笑声立刻停止，转成愤怒了。十几个孩子嚷道：

“把他拉走！拉到洗马池[5]那儿去！狗在哪儿？嗬，来吧，狮子！嗬，獠牙！”

随后就发生了英国从来没有见过的一桩事情——皇太子的御体被老百姓的手粗暴地殴打，并且他们还唆使恶狗去袭击和撕咬他。

那天夜幕渐渐降下的时候，王子来到了城内房屋稠密的地区。他已遍体鳞伤，手上在流血，一身破衣服沾满了污泥。他继续往前游荡，走了又走，心里越来越慌张；他疲倦无力到了极点，以至于两条腿简直有些拖不动了。他再也不向人探询，因为他问话问不出消息，反而引起人家对他的侮辱。他老是自言自语地低声说：“垃圾大院——就是这个地名，我要是不精疲力竭，倒在地上，就能找到这个地方，那我就得救了——因为他家里的人会把我带到王宫里去，证明我不是他们这家的人，而是真正的王子，那么我就可以恢复我的身份了。”他心里时时回想起基督教养院里那些粗野的孩子对待他的情形，于是他就说：“等我当了国王的时候，他们就不仅会得到面包和住处，还要读书受教育。因为只吃饱肚子，脑子里却闹饥荒，心灵也得不到营养，那是没有什么价值的。我要把这个随时牢记在心里，不忘掉今天所受的教训，以免我的百姓因此而吃苦；因为学问可以使人变得温和，培养文雅和仁爱的品质。”

各处的灯光渐渐地闪烁起来，天上也下起雨来了，随即又刮起了风，于是狂风暴雨之夜就开始了。那落魄的王子，无家可归的将要继承英国王位的太子仍旧在往前走，越来越深入那些迷宫似的肮脏小巷，那是一些又穷又苦的人家像密集的蜂窝似的聚居在一起的地方。

忽然有一个高大的醉汉一把揪住他说：

“又是一出去就到这会儿还不回家，我看准还是一个铜子儿也没带回来！要真是这样的话，我要不把你这一身瘦骨头全给打断，那我就情愿改个姓，不算是约翰·康第了。”

王子把身子一扭，摆脱了那个人，还不知不觉地把他那被玷污了的肩膀拍拍干净，然后迫切地问道：

“啊，原来你就是他的父亲，真的吗？多谢老天，但愿如此——那么你去把他带走，让我恢复身份吧！”

“他的父亲！我不懂你这是什么意思，我只知道我是你的父亲，你回头就会……”

“啊，莫开玩笑，莫说废话，莫耽搁工夫！——我累了，我受了伤，我再也熬不下去了，你把我带回我父王那里去，他会让你大阔特阔，你做天大的梦也想不到的。相信我吧，喂，相信我吧！——我不说谎，我说的都是实话！——你伸出手来救我一把吧！我的确是太子！”

那个人愣住了，他低下头瞪着眼睛望了望这孩子，然后摇摇头，嘟哝着说：“你发疯了，简直和疯人院里的疯子一样！”然后又把王子揪住，一面发出粗俗的笑声和咒骂，说道，“可是不管你疯不疯，我和你奶奶回头就会弄清楚你这身贱骨头哪儿最软，要不然我就不算好汉！”

他说完这话，就把那气得发疯的、拼命挣扎的王子拽着走，拽进房屋前面的一条窄巷，背后跟着一群很感兴趣的、乱哄哄的闲人。

第五章　汤姆当了王子

汤姆·康第独自留在王子的私室里，充分利用这个机会，欣赏了一番。他站在大镜子前面，把身子左右转动，欣赏他那一身华贵的衣裳；然后又走开，一面模仿王子那种出身高贵的风度，一面在镜子里观察着效果。然后他就抽出那把漂亮的剑来，鞠一个躬，吻一吻剑，再把它横放在胸前，这些姿势是他五六个星期前，从所看见的一位高贵的爵士那儿学来的。那时候这位爵士押解着诺阜克和索利那两个大勋爵，把他们移交给伦敦塔的副官看管时，就是这样给他敬礼的。汤姆还抚弄着大腿旁边挂着的那把镶着宝石的短刀，又仔细察看屋子里那些贵重和精致的装饰品；他试坐每一把豪华的椅子，心里想着，假如垃圾大院那一群野孩子也能往里面偷看一下，瞧见他这副威风十足的样子，他该会多么得意。他怀疑他回家之后给他们叙述这段经过，他们会不会相信他这个神奇的故事，是不是会摇摇头，说他那想入非非的脑子幻想过度，终于使他丧失理智了。

过了半小时，他忽然想起王子已经出去很大工夫了，于是他立刻就觉得寂寞起来；不久他就开始静听和盼望，再也不玩弄他身边那些漂亮东西了；他渐渐感到不安，然后又感到焦急，再往后就感到苦恼。万一有人进来，发现他穿着王子的衣服，而王子又不在这儿，那岂不糟糕！难道他们不先把他处以绞刑，然后再来调查这桩事情的真相吗？他曾经听说过大人物处理小事是说做就做的。他的恐惧越来越高涨，于是他战战兢兢地悄悄打开通往外面那个房间的门，决定跑出去寻找王子，希望从他那里获得保护和解脱。六个穿着华丽的御仆和两个穿得像蝴蝶似的高级小侍突然一齐站起，在他面前深深地鞠躬致敬。他连忙后退，把门关上。他说：

“啊，他们和我开玩笑！他们会去报告。啊！我为什么要上这儿来送死呢？”

他在屋里走来走去，心中充满了无名的恐惧，一面静听着，每逢有点儿小声音他就大吃一惊。随后那扇门忽然打开，一个穿绸衣服的小侍说：

“洁恩·格雷公主驾到。”

门又关上了，于是有一个穿得很阔气的可爱的年轻姑娘向他蹦蹦跳跳地走过来。可是她忽然站住，用焦急的声调说：“啊，您怎么了，不舒服吗，殿下？”

汤姆吓得几乎要断气了，可是他勉强撑持着吞吞吐吐地说：“哎呀，请您开恩！老实说我并不是什么殿下，不过是城里垃圾大院可怜的汤姆·康第罢了。请您让我见到王子，他就会开恩把我的破衣服还给我，并且还放我走，不叫我吃亏。啊，请您大发慈悲，救救我吧！”

这时候汤姆已经双膝跪下，同时用眼睛和举起的双手帮助着唇舌恳求。那年轻的姑娘似乎是被吓得魂不附体了。她大声喊道：

“啊，殿下，您怎么下跪？——怎么向我下跪呀！”

于是她惊惶地逃跑了；汤姆因绝望而痛苦不堪，他瘫倒在地上，喃喃地说：

“无可挽救了，无可挽救了。这下子他们准会来把我抓去呀。”

他在那儿躺着因恐惧而失去知觉的时候，可怕的消息在宫中飞快地传播开了。这个消息由大家用耳语传播着——因为宫廷里照例是用耳语传播消息的——这个奴仆告诉那个奴仆，官臣告诉贵妇，顺着所有的长廊一直传播过去，这层楼传到那层楼，这个花厅传到那个花厅，“王子发疯了，王子发疯了！”不久，每个花厅、每个大理石的大厅，都聚集了成群的光彩夺目的官臣和贵妇，还有成群的服饰耀眼的其他次要人物，大家都在一起关切地低声谈论着，各人脸上都露出惊慌的神色。随后，一位衣着华丽的官员迈着大步走过这些人身边，发布庄严的公告：

以国王的名义：不准轻信此项无稽谣言，亦不得议论此事，或向外传布；违者处死。以国王的名义！

耳语的交谈突然终止了，好像谈论的人都一下子变成了哑巴似的。

过了一会儿，各处走廊上到处又有一片叽叽喳喳的声音，大家都说：“王子！瞧，王子过来了！”

可怜的汤姆慢慢地走过来，经过那一群一群的深深鞠躬的人身边，想要鞠躬答礼而又不敢，同时他那双慌张的、可怜的眼睛畏畏缩缩地注视着周围那种稀奇的情景。大臣们在他两边走着，让他靠在他们身上，借此使他的脚步走得稳一些。他背后还跟着御医和几个仆人。

随后，汤姆发觉他自己到了宫里的一个豪华房间里，听见他背后有人把门关上了。他周围站着那些陪他一同来的人。

在他前面距离稍远的地方，有一个身材高大、长得很胖的人斜倚在床头，面孔宽大而多肉，脸色很庄严。他那头发是灰白的；他只在面孔周围留着络腮胡子，像一个镜框似的，胡子的颜色也是灰白的。他的衣服是用讲究的材料做的，可是有些地方已经旧了，而且稍有磨破的痕迹。他那一双发肿的腿有一条底下垫着一只枕头，上面捆着绷带。这时候没有人说话，除了这个人以外，所有的人都恭恭敬敬地低着头。这个表情严厉的病夫就是那威严的亨利八世。他说：

“我的爱德华王子，你好吗？你是不是故意调皮，和我开玩笑，叫我上当呢？我是你的父王，对你很疼爱、很体贴呀，你怎么这样淘气呢？”他开始说话的时候，脸上就显出温和的神色了。

汤姆有些迷乱，这些话的前半部分，他还极力镇定地倾听着，可是“你的父王”这几个字钻进他耳朵里的时候，他的脸色就发白了；他立刻就跪下来，好像腿上中了一枪似的。他举起双手，大声喊道：

“您就是国王陛下？那我的确是完蛋了！”

这话似乎使国王大吃一惊。他那双眼睛不由自主地望望这个的脸，又望望那个的脸，然后他就张皇失措地盯住他面前那个孩子。于是他以深感失望的声调说道：

“哎呀，我本来还以为谣言与事实不符，可是恐怕并非如此。”他深深地叹了一口气，又用温和的语调说，“孩子，到你父亲面前来吧，你有点儿毛病哩。”

汤姆被人扶着站起来，心虚而发抖地走到大英国王陛下跟前。国王用双手捧着那惊骇的面孔，关切而慈爱地注视了一会儿，好像希望在那上面发现一些理智恢复过来的迹象，然后他把汤姆那满头卷发的脑袋按在自己胸前，温柔地拍着。随即他又说：

“孩子，你认识你的父亲吗？不要叫我伤透老年的心呀，你说你认识我吧。你的确认识我，是不是？”

“认识，您是万民敬畏的国王陛下，上帝保佑您！”

“对呀，对呀——这很好——定定心，不用这么哆嗦，这里没有人来伤害你，这里没有一个人不爱你哩。你现在好些了，你的噩梦过去了——是不是？现在你也知道你自己是谁了吧——是不是？他们说你刚才把自己的名字弄错了，现在不会再弄错吧？”

“禀告国王陛下，我刚才说的是真话，请您开恩相信我。我是您的百姓当中最下贱的，生来是个穷叫花子，我是偶然遭了个意外的不幸才到这儿来的，不过这事情并不能归咎于我。我现在就死，未免太年轻了，您只要说一句话就能救我的命。啊，请您说吧，陛下！”

“死？不要说这种话吧，可爱的王子——你心里受了刺激，快安静安静吧——不会叫你死的！”

汤姆马上跪倒下来欢呼道：

“国王啊，您这样慈悲，上帝会给您好报的，祝您万寿无疆，恩泽四方！”然后他一下跳起来，满脸喜色地转向那两个侍从喊道，“你们听见了吧！不叫我死，这是国王说的！”除了大家都毕恭毕敬地鞠了一躬而外，没有人动弹，谁也没有说话。他有点儿心慌，迟疑了一会儿之后，胆怯地转向国王说：“现在我可以走了吧？”

“走？要是你想走，当然可以。可是你为什么不再待一会儿呢？你打算到什么地方去？”

汤姆把眼睛往下看，谦恭地回答说：

“恐怕是我弄错了，可是我的确以为我恢复自由了，所以就想回到那狗窝似的家里去；我是在那儿生来就受罪的，不过毕竟有我的母亲和两个姐姐住在那儿，所以那总算是我的家。这里的豪华富贵我可是不大习惯——啊，陛下，我求您让我走吧！”

国王沉思了一会儿，没有作声，他脸上露出越来越多的愁容和不安。随即他又说：

“或许他只在这一方面神经错乱，谈到别的问题，他的理智大概就没有什么毛病了吧。但愿上帝保佑，是这样才好！我们来试一试吧。”国王的声调里含着几分希望。

然后他用拉丁文问了汤姆一个问题，汤姆也说着蹩脚的拉丁文回答了他。国王很高兴，而且露出了这种神色。大臣和御医们也表示了满意。国王说：

“这与他所受的教育和才能还是配不上，可是足见他的心不过是有点儿病态，并不是受了什么致命伤。你觉得怎样，大夫？”

国王所问的御医深深地鞠了一躬，回答道：

“陛下的看法与小臣的愚见不谋而合，陛下，您推测得完全正确。”

国王得到这番鼓励，显得很欢喜，因为说这句话的人是个了不起的名医。于是他又兴高采烈地继续说道：

“大家注意，我们再来试他一下。”

他又用法文问了汤姆一个问题。汤姆因为那么多眼睛盯着他，觉得很窘，所以他站在那儿停了一会儿没有作声，然后才胆怯地说道：

“禀告陛下，我没有学过这种文字。”

国王在床上往后一倒。仆役们连忙去扶他，可是他挥手叫他们走开，说道：

“不用麻烦——我这不过是一阵坏血病引起的发晕。把我撑起来！对，这就行了。过来吧，孩子，好，把你那可怜的、混乱的脑袋靠在你父亲的胸前，安下心去吧。你不久就会好的，这不过是一阵暂时的神经错乱罢了。你不要害怕，你不久就会好的。”然后他转过脸去向着在场的人，他那温和的态度改变了，眼睛里射出很凶的闪电似的光来。他说：

“你们都听着！我这儿子是疯了，可是并不是永久发疯。这是念书太用功，还有点儿管制得太严的缘故。丢开他的书，不要他的老师！你们赶快遵办。让他痛痛快快地玩儿，想些好办法给他解闷，好叫他恢复健康。”他再把身子支起了一些，抖擞精神继续说道，“他疯了，可他毕竟是我的儿子，毕竟是英国的太子；无论疯与不疯，反正是要叫他登位！你们还要听清楚，并且要宣布：谁要是把王子有毛病的消息说出去，那就是危害全国的治安和秩序，准叫他上绞架！——拿点儿水给我喝——我心里发烧，这桩伤心事使我心力交瘁——喂，把杯子拿走——扶着我吧。哈，就这样好了。他疯了，是不是？即令他再疯一千倍，他也还是太子，我当国王的一定承认他。就在明天，我要让他按正式的古礼就太子位。赫德福伯爵，立刻传令下去吧。”

贵族当中有一位在御榻前面跪下来说：

“陛下知道英国世袭大典礼官现在已被褫夺了公权，关在塔里。您似乎不应该叫一个被褫夺了公权的人……”

“住口！不许拿他那可恨的名字脏了我的耳朵。这个人难道能永远活下去吗？我的旨意难道要受到阻碍吗？难道太子还要因为英国缺少一个犯叛国罪的典礼大臣给他上尊号，而耽误他就位的大事吗？不，这是万万不行的！通知我的国会，叫他们在明天日出之前把诺阜克处死，否则他们就要受到严厉的惩罚！”

赫德福伯爵说：

“国王的意志就是法律。”他说罢就站起来，回到他的原位。

老国王脸上的怒气渐渐消失了，他说：

“亲亲我吧，我的王子。喂……你有什么可害怕的？难道我不是你的慈爱的父亲吗？”

“伟大仁慈的国王啊，您对我太好了，我实在不配，这个我很懂得。可是——可是——我想起那将死的人就难受，我……”

“哈，你就是这样，你就是这样！我知道你的神经虽然受了刺激，你的心肠始终还是一样，因为你的天性向来是很宽厚的。可是这位公爵对你的荣誉是有妨碍的。我要另外找个不会玷污他的伟大职位的人来代替他。你尽管安心吧，我的王子。你千万不要把这桩事情放在心上，使你的脑筋受到搅扰吧。”

“可是国王陛下，这岂不是我催他快死？要不是为了我，他不是还可以活得很长久吗？”

“不要为他操心吧，我的王子。他是不值得你这么关心的。再亲亲我，就去开玩笑、寻开心吧；我的病使我很痛苦哩。我疲倦了，需要休息休息。你跟赫德福舅舅和你的侍从们去吧，等我身体好一点儿，你再来吧。”

汤姆被人从国王面前引着走开了，他心里感到沉重，因为他本来存着恢复自由的希望，现在国王最后的圣旨对他的这种希望却成了一个致命的打击。他又一次听见一阵阵低微的声音像苍蝇叫似的喊道：“王子，王子来了！”

他在两旁排列着的那些服饰耀眼的躬着腰的侍臣当中走过的时候，心情越来越沉重了；因为他现在看出了自己的确成了一个俘虏，也许永远会被囚禁在这个金漆的笼子里，做一个孤零零的、举目无亲的王子，除非上帝对他开恩，给他恢复自由。

无论他走到什么地方，似乎总看见那诺阜克大公爵被砍掉的头和他那副令人难忘的面孔在空中飘动，那双眼睛含着责难的神情盯着他。

从前他的梦想原是非常愉快的，而眼前的现实却是多么可怕啊！

第六章　汤姆习礼

大臣们把汤姆引到那陈列豪华的最大房间里，请他坐下——这是他不情愿做的事情，因为他身边有些年长的人和职位很高的人。他请求他们也坐下，可是他们只鞠躬致谢，或是小声地表示谢意，大家仍旧站着。他本想再请他们坐，可是他的“舅父”赫德福伯爵对着他的耳朵悄悄地说：

“殿下，请您不要催他们坐，他们在您面前坐下是不合适的。”

这时候有人通报圣约翰勋爵求见。他向汤姆鞠躬致敬，然后说道：

“臣奉国王之命来此，有要事禀告，需要保守机密。可否请殿下吩咐侍从人等暂行回避，仅留赫德福伯爵一人？”

赫德福看出汤姆似乎不知道应该怎么办，就悄悄地告诉他做个手势，如果不想说话，尽可以不必开口。侍从和臣子们退出之后，圣约翰勋爵说：

“国王陛下命令，因为关系到国家安危，王子殿下应尽其所能，多方注意隐瞒自己有病的消息，直到健康恢复，一切如常。殿下万不可向任何人否认自己是真正的王子，应继承大英王位；同时必须保持王子的尊严，接受符合历来习惯的敬礼和仪式，不得用语言或手势表示拒绝；王子由于幻想过度，以致损害健康，影响了理智的健全，因此信口乱说出身寒微、生活卑贱，今后务须注意，万勿失言；王子对于一向熟识的面孔，务须极力回忆——万一记不起来，也要保持缄默，切勿表示惊讶，或做其他表示遗忘的举动；凡关国家大事，如有疑难，不知应采取何等措施，或出言不知如何措辞，切勿显露慌张神色，使好奇的旁观者看出破绽。凡遇此种情况，王子应采纳赫德福伯爵或小臣的意见；我等奉国王之命，为殿下随时效劳，直至圣命取消时为止。国王命令如此，钦命向王子殿下致意，并祝上帝赐福，使殿下早日健康，永获天佑。”

圣约翰勋爵鞠躬致敬，退到一边站着。汤姆无可奈何地回答道：

“国王说了这样的话，当然无人敢于玩忽，纵有困难，也不能随意搪塞，只求省事。圣命必须遵守。”

赫德福伯爵说：

“国王有命，王子殿下暂勿读书，或做其他劳心之事。殿下不如多多娱乐，消遣时间，以免赴宴时感觉疲劳，乃至有伤尊体。”

汤姆脸上显出怀疑的惊讶神色；他发现圣约翰勋爵忧愁地转过眼睛来注视着他的时候，就不由得脸红起来。勋爵说：

“殿下的记忆力还是不济事，所以又表示了惊讶——不过您不用为这点小事烦心，因为这种毛病是不会长久的，自然会随着尊恙的痊愈而消失。赫德福伯爵所说的是两个月以前国王答应让殿下幸临的京城大宴会，现在您想起来了吗？”

“我很遗憾，不能不承认实在是记不起来了。”汤姆用迟疑的声调说着，又涨红了脸。

这时候有人通报伊丽莎白公主和洁恩·格雷公主来了。两位爵士互相使了个意味深长的眼色，赫德福赶快向门口走过去。那两个年轻的姑娘走过他身边时，他就低声嘱咐她们说：

“公主们，请你们对他的怪脾气故意装作没有发现，他的记忆力不济的时候，你们也不要表示惊讶——每一桩小小的事情他都要想半天，真叫人看了难受哩。”

同时圣约翰勋爵凑近汤姆耳边说道：

“殿下，请您牢记国王陛下的愿望。您要尽量回忆一些事情——其他一切也要装出记得的样子。千万不要让她们看出您比过去有多大变化，因为您知道这两个老玩伴心里对您多么亲切，要是知道您不好，她们该会多么难受。殿下，您愿意我留在身边吗？——还有您的舅父？”

汤姆做了个手势，还低声说了个“好”字，表示同意，因为他现在已经在学着应付了，他那天真的心里已经打定了主意，要极力按照国王的命令行事。

虽然多方小心谨慎，这几个年轻人之间的谈话，有时候还是不免有些窘。事实上，有好几次汤姆都几乎撑持不住了，就要承认他自己扮演这么一个重要角色是不胜任的；还好伊丽莎白公主的机智总是能给他解围，要不就是那两位细心照应的爵士之中有一位故意装作随意说出的神情，插进一句能够产生同样效果的圆场的话。有一次洁恩小公主转过脸去向着汤姆，问了这么一个使他慌张的问题：

“殿下，您今天给王后殿下请过安吗？”

汤姆迟疑着没有回答，露出苦恼的神色，他正想信口胡诌地支吾一下，这时候圣约翰勋爵就连忙插嘴，替他回答，他说得非常自然流利，正符合一个惯于应付微妙的难关、善于临机应变的大臣的从容和优雅的风度：

“公主，他去请过安了，谈到国王陛下的病况时，她还大大地给他说了一番宽心的话，是不是这样，殿下？”

汤姆含糊地说了一句什么话，听上去像是表示同意，可是他觉得这实在是有些冒险。又过了一会儿，两位大臣提起汤姆暂时要停止读书，于是小公主就惊喊道：

“这真是可惜，真是太可惜了！您本是进步很快的。不过您尽管耐心等待一些时候，绝不至于耽误太久的。我的殿下定会博学多才，就像您父亲一样，并且还会像他那样，精通许多种语言。”

“我的父亲！”汤姆一时猛不提防，又说漏了嘴，“我想他连本国话也说不清楚，只有在猪圈里打滚的猪才懂得他的意思。至于说到什么学问的话……”

他抬头望了一下，看到圣约翰勋爵眼睛里有一种庄严的警告的神情。

他停住了，又是一阵脸红，然后郁郁不乐地低声继续说道：“哎呀，我的病又来作弄我，我又精神恍惚起来了。我并不是有意对国王陛下不敬哩。”

“我们知道，殿下，”伊丽莎白公主以尊敬而又亲切的态度，双手把她“弟弟”的手按在掌心当中，温柔地说道，“关于这点，您不用着急。过错不在您，只怪您的尊恙。”

“亲爱的公主，你真是性情温和、善于安慰人哩，”汤姆感激地说，“我心里很受感动，愿意向你道谢，希望你莫嫌我冒昧。”

有一次，那轻浮的洁恩小公主脱口而出向汤姆说了一句简单的希腊话，伊丽莎白公主那双敏锐的眼睛马上就看出对方脸上那副茫然的神情，知道洁恩公主这一招做错了；于是她就帮汤姆的忙，从从容容地用响亮的希腊话叽里咕噜地回答了她，然后马上又把谈话转到别的问题上去了。

时光愉快地度过，而且大体上过得相当顺利。暗礁和沙洲越来越少见了，汤姆越来越感到自然，因为他看到大家都对他很亲切，一心一意来帮助他，并不理会他的错误。后来，他听说那两位小公主将要在那天晚上陪他去赴市长的宴会时，他心里马上感到轻松愉快，欢喜得跳起来，因为他觉得现在不怕在那无数的陌生人当中没有朋友了；要是在一小时之前，一听到她们要陪他一同去，那就不免会使他感到无法忍受的恐怖了。

在这次谈话中，给汤姆担任守护神的两位爵士不像另外那两位在场的角色那么安心。他们觉得那简直就像在一条危险的河流里驾驶一艘大船一般：他们老是提心吊胆，谨防意外，感觉到他们的任务实在不是儿戏。因此后来当那两位公主的拜见将告结束的时候，有人通报吉尔福·杜德来勋爵求见，这两位大臣不但觉得他们所照料的这个活宝贝已经受够了洋罪，而且他们自己也不大有精神来把他们那艘船驾回原处，再来提心吊胆地航行一次了。所以他们就很恭敬地劝汤姆借故不接见杜德来勋爵，汤姆也正乐于这么办；不过洁恩公主听说那个华贵的年轻小公子被挡驾，她脸上也许是稍微露出了一点失望的神色。

这时候大家沉默了一阵，这是一种有所期待的静默，汤姆却不了解它的意义。他向赫德福伯爵瞟了一眼，圣约翰勋爵就给他做了一个手势——可是他连这个也还是不懂。脑筋灵活的伊丽莎白又以她那惯有的从容优雅给他解了围。她行了个鞠躬礼，说道：

“王弟可以开恩让我等告辞吗？”

汤姆说：

“当然，两位公主凡有所求，我无不乐于同意；但眼看两位离去，不免顿失光彩，只可惜我别无上策，不能继续挽留你们。祝你们两位晚安，愿上帝保佑你们！”随后他暗自在心中笑道，“幸亏我在书本里和王子们相处过，还学会了他们那种文雅和优美的言谈，懂得了一点他们说话的习惯！”

那两位光彩非凡的少女走了之后，汤姆疲倦地转过脸去向着他那两位监护人说：

“请问两位大臣，可否容许我去找个安静地方休息休息？”

赫德福伯爵说：

“禀告殿下，您凡事尽管随意吩咐，臣等无不遵命。殿下应当休息，实属急需之事，因为您稍待须发驾进城。”

他敲了一下铃，马上就有一个小侍进来了，伯爵吩咐他去把威廉·赫伯特爵士请来。爵士立刻就来到了，他把汤姆引进一个里面的房间。汤姆到了那里面，第一个动作就是伸手去取一杯水；可是有一个穿着绸子和天鹅绒衣服的仆役接过杯子来，跪下一膝，把它用金托盘端着侍奉给他。

随后这个疲倦的俘虏坐下来，正想脱下他的短筒靴，一面怪害臊地瞟过眼睛去征求同意，可是另外一个穿绸子和天鹅绒衣服的讨厌鬼又跪下来替他做了这桩事情。他再试了两三次想自己动手，可是每次都让别人抢先干了，所以他最终放弃了他的企图，无可奈何地叹了一口气，嘟哝着说：“该死！我不知道他们为什么不干脆连呼吸也给我代办了呀！”他被人服侍着穿好了睡鞋，披上了一件华丽的长袍，终于躺下来休息，可是无法睡着，因为他脑子里充满了各种念头，屋子里的人也太多了。他无法排遣他的心事，所以那些念头就在他脑子里停留着；同时他又不知道怎样打发那些人，所以他们也就在屋子里站着不走，这使他很懊恼——他们也茫然不知所措。

汤姆走了之后，就剩下了他那两位高贵的监护人在一起了。他们沉思了一会儿，一面不住地摇头，还在屋子里踱来踱去，然后圣约翰勋爵说道：

“老实说，您觉得怎样？”

“老实说，是这样：国王眼看就快去世了，我的外甥又发了疯，疯子要登王位，疯子要留在王位上。既然英国需要这样，那就但愿上帝保佑我们这个国家吧！”

“的确会是这样。可是……难道您不怀疑吗？关于……关于……”

圣约翰勋爵迟疑了，他终于住了口，没说下去。他显然是觉得有些为难。赫德福伯爵在他面前站住，用明朗和坦率的眼光望着他的脸，然后说道：

“往下说吧——除了我就没有别人听见。为什么事情要怀疑？”

“我很不愿意把心里的话说出来，伯爵，您和他血缘关系这么近，我不便说。可是我要是有所冒犯只好请您原谅；您说是否有点儿奇怪，疯癫居然能使他的举动和态度改变得这么厉害！他的举动和谈吐固然还是有王子的风度，可是有些无关紧要的小事，他的表现又和他从前的习惯确实有些不同。疯癫竟使他连他父亲的相貌也记不起来了；他身边的人对他照例要遵行的仪式和礼节，他也忘记得干干净净；还有拉丁文他还记得，希腊文和法文他却都忘了，您说这岂不奇怪？伯爵，您不要生气，还是请您给我说明一下，让我好放心吧，那我就很感激您了。他说他不是王子，这事情老在我脑子里转来转去，所以……”

“住口，阁下，您说的话是犯叛国罪的！忘了国王的命令了吗？我要是听您说这些话，您犯的罪也就有我的份了。”

圣约翰脸色发白，连忙说道：

“我老实承认我犯了错误。请您不要告发我，请您帮帮忙，给我这个恩惠吧，以后我再也不想这桩事情，再也不谈它了。您千万别跟我过不去，否则我就完蛋了。”

“我同意，阁下。只要您承诺不再犯，无论是在这里，或是跟别人谈话的时候，您都当作根本没有说过这些话吧。不过您不用担心。他是我姐姐的儿子，他的声音、他的面貌、他的身材，难道不是我从他睡在摇篮里的时候就熟悉的吗？您看见他做的那些古怪的矛盾的事情，都是可以由疯癫产生的，有时候还更厉害。您不记得吗，马雷老男爵发疯的时候，他连自己那熟识了六十年的面貌都忘记了，硬说是别人的；还不止这样，他甚至说他是马利亚·抹大拉[6]的儿子，还说他的头是西班牙的玻璃做成的；真是，他还不许任何人接触它，唯恐不凑巧，会有粗心的人把它打碎。好心的勋爵，您不必怀疑吧。这正是王子，我认得很清楚——不久他就会当您的国王了；您把这个记在心里比较有好处，多想想这个，比您刚才那些念头强些。”

他们又谈了一会儿，圣约翰勋爵再三声明，他现在的信心是有充分根据的，决不会再被任何怀疑干扰了，借此掩饰他刚才所犯的错误。随后，赫德福伯爵就叫他这位同来侍奉王子的大臣先去休息，他自己坐下来担任看守之责。不久他也就转入深思了。显然他想得越久，心里就越加烦躁。后来他就开始在屋里走来走去，自言自语地低声说：

“得了吧，他非是王子不可！难道还会有人说，英国竟有两个血统不同、出身不同的角色和双生子似的相像得这么出奇吗？而且即令有这种事，居然会有意外的机缘，让其中的一个来代替了另外那一个，那就更加是不可理解的奇迹了。不会的，那简直是荒唐的想法，太荒唐、太荒唐了！”

随后他又说：

“假设他是个骗子，自称为王子，那么也还自然，也还近情近理。可是世界上何曾有过这样的骗子，国王把他叫作王子，朝廷上也把他叫作王子，人人都把他叫作王子，他本人却偏要否认这个尊贵身份，极力恳求不要把他升为王子？不对！无论如何，绝不会有这种事！这的确是真正的王子发了疯！”

第七章　汤姆的初次御餐

下午一点钟稍过了一会儿，汤姆听天由命地受了一场活罪，任凭人家给他打扮起来，准备进御餐。他发现自己还是穿得像以前那样讲究，可是一切都不同了，从绉领一直到袜子，一切都变换了。他随即就被引导着派头十足地走进一个宽大而华丽的房间里，那儿已经摆好了一桌给一个人吃的筵席。屋里的陈设都是大块大块的黄金做的，上面还有许多图案，几乎使这些家具成为无价之宝，因为那都是本汶努图的作品。那些穿戴华丽的仆役占了半个房间。有一个牧师致了餐前祷词；汤姆因为一向就和饥饿分不开家，非常嘴馋，他正想开始取食，却被柏克莱伯爵阻止了，给他颈上系了一条餐巾；因为专给皇太子管手巾的要职是由这位贵族家里世袭的。汤姆的司酒也在场，每逢他想要自己斟酒喝，司酒就抢先给他斟了。太子的试食官也在场，随时准备冒着被毒死的危险，遵命尝食任何可疑的菜肴。这一次他只是一个装点场面的人物，汤姆很少吩咐他执行他的职务。可是不知多少年以前，曾经有过一些时候，试食官的职务是有危险的，因此并不是一个人人羡慕的职位。为什么不用狗或是流浪儿来试验，似乎有些奇怪，可是王室的一切作风都是奇怪的。宫中第一侍从官达赛勋爵也在场，天知道他是干什么事的；可是他反正是在那儿——那就随他吧。总膳司也在场，他站在汤姆背后，受站在近处的皇家事务大臣和御厨总管大臣指挥，监督王子进餐的隆重仪式。除此而外，汤姆还有三百八十四个仆人；可是他们当然并不都在这间屋子里，连四分之一都不到；而且汤姆根本还不知道他有那么多用人。

所有到场的人都在不到一个钟头以前受过严格训练，要记住王子暂时有些神经错乱，当心不要在他有什么荒唐举动的时候表示惊讶。这类“荒唐举动”不久就在他们面前表演起来了，可是这只引起大家的惋惜和忧虑，而没有使他们发笑。他们看见亲爱的王子有了这种毛病，真是感到深重的痛苦。

可怜的汤姆主要是用手指抓饭吃，可是谁也没有笑他，甚至还故意装作没有看见的样子。他好奇地细看他的餐巾，很感兴趣，因为那是用很讲究、很漂亮的材料做的。后来他天真地说道：

“请把这个拿开，免得我不当心的时候把它弄脏了。”

世袭的手巾大臣恭恭敬敬地把它拿开，他一声不响，也没有任何反对的表示。

汤姆很感兴趣地把萝卜和莴笋仔细看了一阵，然后问问那是什么东西，是不是可以吃的；因为这两种菜从前都是作为奢侈品从荷兰输入的，最近才有人在英国种植。他的问题有人非常恭敬地给他回答了，谁也没有表示惊讶。他吃完饭后的点心之后，就在口袋里装满了栗子；大家都装作根本没有发觉他这个举动，谁也没有因此而吃惊。可是他自己反而马上就为这桩事情烦恼了，而且表现出局促不安的神气；因为他吃这顿饭的时候，只有这桩事情是人家让他亲手干的，所以他就知道自己毫无疑问地做了一桩极不礼貌、极不合王子身份的事情。这时候他鼻子上的肌肉开始搐动起来，鼻尖也往上翘，并且皱起来了。这种情形继续下去，汤姆渐渐表现出越来越大的痛苦。他以恳求的态度望望身边这个大官，又望望那个大官，眼睛里不由得流起泪来了。这些大官的脸上露出慌张的神色，连忙走到王子跟前，请问他有什么不舒服。汤姆十分苦恼地说：

“请你们不要见怪，我的鼻子简直痒得要命。遇到这种紧急情况，依照惯例应该怎么办？请快说，因为我实在不能再熬多大工夫了。”

谁也没有笑，可是大家都觉得不知所措，彼此互相张望，为了急于要给王子出个主意而苦恼不堪。哎呀，这可真叫大家碰壁了！英国历史上从来没有任何记载，可以帮助他们渡过这一关。掌礼官又不在场，没有人敢于大胆地冒险在这没有航行标志的大海上通行，擅作主张来解决这么重大的一个问题。真糟糕！可惜没有一位世袭的抓痒官。就在这段时间里，汤姆的眼泪已经流出眼眶外面来，开始顺着脸往下流了。他那搐动的鼻子比之前更加迫切地恳求脱离痛苦。最后还是本能突破了礼仪的藩篱，汤姆自己动手在鼻子上抓痒，他暗自在心中祈祷，如果他做得不对，希望上帝饶恕他。这么一来，也就使他那些臣子们沉重的内心获得了解脱。

这一顿饭吃完之后，就有一位大臣进来，在汤姆面前端着一只大而浅的金盘子，里面盛着很香的玫瑰水，给他漱口和洗手指；专管手巾的世袭大臣站在一边，手里拿着一条餐巾供他使用。汤姆不知所措地瞪着眼睛对那只盘子望了一会儿，然后把它端到嘴边，郑重其事地喝了一口。然后他把盘子交还给那伺候着的大臣，说道：

“不，阁下，我不喜欢喝这个；这种酒味道倒是很香，可是太没有劲头。”

王子的病态心理又有这种古怪的表现，这使得他身边的人都心痛了，可是这种不幸的情景没有引起任何人发笑。

汤姆接下来的一个不自觉的错误，就是正当牧师在他椅子后面刚刚站定，举起双手，闭上眼睛，抬起头来正要开始祝福的时候，他却站起来离开了餐桌。可是，大家还是装作没有看出王子干了什么反常的事情。

随后由于汤姆自己的要求，他被引到他的私室里去了，陪送他的人把他独自留在那儿，让他自由自在。那橡木壁板上的钩子上有一副亮晃晃的钢制盔甲，一件件分开挂着，上面都是镶金的精致的美丽图案。这套武士的甲胄是属于那个真王子的——这是王后巴尔夫人新近送他的礼物。汤姆穿上胫甲、臂铠，戴上插着羽毛的头盔，还有他不要别人帮助就能穿上的其他部件，随后他就想要叫人来帮忙，把其余的东西都穿上。可是他又想起了吃饭的时候带回来的栗子，觉得现在可以自由自在地拿出来吃，没有那一大堆人看着，也没有那些世袭的大官来帮他的忙，惹他厌恶，那该是多么好玩儿；所以他就把那几件漂亮东西归还原处，接着就砸起栗子来了。这是他以为他有罪、被上帝罚他当了王子以来，几乎第一次感觉到的自自然然的快乐。栗子通通吃完之后，他就东翻西找地在一个壁橱里找到了几本有趣的书，其中有一本是关于英国宫廷礼节的，这是个宝贝。他就在一张豪华的长睡椅上躺下，全神贯注地开始研究礼节了。现在我们就让他在那儿待着，暂时不再谈他吧。

第八章　玉玺的问题

大约在五点钟，亨利八世从一场不大舒服的午睡中醒过来，自言自语地嘟哝着：“噩梦呀，噩梦呀！我的末日快到了，从这些预兆可以看得出；还有我的脉搏很弱，也足以证明。”随后他眼睛里射出邪恶的光来，嘟哝着说，“可是我要叫‘他’先完蛋，然后我自己再死才行。”

他的仆人看见他已经醒了，就有一个人告诉他说，大法官在外面等候朝见，问他意思怎样。

“让他进来，让他进来！”国王急切地大声喊道。

大法官进来，跪在国王床前说道：

“我已经把命令传达下去，现在上院的贵族遵照国王的指令，都穿着礼服，站在上院的特别法庭里；他们在那里判定了诺阜克公爵的死刑之后，正在恭候陛下对此事做下一步的指示。”

国王听了很高兴，他脸上露出一阵狂喜。他说：

“把我扶起来！我要亲自到国会去，亲手在执行令上盖上玉玺，了结我这……”

他的声音接不下去了，一片灰白的惨色扫除了他脸上的红晕；仆人们扶着他仍旧靠在枕头上，连忙拿些强心剂来挽救他。随后他就悲伤地说：

“哎呀，我多么渴望着这个时刻来到！哎，可惜来得太晚了，我坐失了这个向往已久的机会。可是你们要赶快，你们要赶快！我既不能干这桩痛快事情，就让别人去干吧。我要把玉玺委托给几位大臣，你们快把负责的人选出来，替我去办这桩事。喂，赶快呀！不用再过一昼夜，现在就要把他的头拿来给我看。”

“谨遵圣旨，定当照办。可否请陛下吩咐将玉玺交给我，以便我赶快去办这桩事情？”

“玉玺！难道不是你，还有别人保存着玉玺吗？”

“禀告陛下，两天以前您就从我手里拿去了！您说非等您亲手把它盖在诺阜克公爵的死刑执行令上，不许再拿它做别的用途。”

“噢，我的确是这么说过，我记得很清楚……我是把它怎么安置的……我非常衰弱了……这些天来，我的记忆力老是不济事，专跟我捣蛋……真奇怪，真奇怪——”

国王口齿不清地自言自语起来，时时软弱无力地摇着他那灰白的头，摸索似的想要回忆起他把玉玺放在了什么地方。最后赫德福伯爵大胆地跪下来，报告玉玺的下落：

“陛下，恕我冒昧，这里有几个人都记得您把玉玺交给了太子殿下保存，准备……”

“不错，一点儿也不错！”国王打断他的话说，“快去拿来！快去！时间过得太快了！”

赫德福伯爵飞跑到汤姆那儿，可是他不久就空着手焦急地回到国王这里来。他说了下面这么一段话：

“国王陛下，我给您带来这么沉重和讨厌的消息，真是抱歉；可是王子的病还没有好，天意如此，无可奈何；他竟想不起曾经接受过玉玺这回事。所以我赶快回来禀报，因为如果在王子殿下所在的那一长排房间和花厅里进行搜寻，我觉得那不免浪费宝贵的时间，而且还毫无……”

伯爵说到这里，国王呻吟了一声，把他的话打断了。过了一会儿之后，国王陛下才以含着忧愁的声调说道：

“不要再去打搅他吧，可怜的孩子。上帝在严厉地责罚他，我心里对他不胜爱怜，只可惜我这饱经忧患的衰老的肩头不能替他承担罪孽的担子，使他获得平安。”

他闭上眼睛，低声自言自语了一阵，忽然又沉默了。过了一会儿工夫，他又睁开眼睛，茫然地向四周张望；后来他一眼瞟见了跪着的大法官，立刻就怒气冲天地涨红着脸说道：

“怎么，你还在这里！我对天发誓，你如果不去把那个叛徒的事情办好，你自己的脑袋明天就要搬家，你的帽子也就要休假了！”

吓得发抖的大法官回答道：

“陛下圣明，小臣恳求您开恩！我是在此等候玉玺的。”

“呸，你疯了吗？我从前时常随身携带着的那颗小玉玺在我宝库里放着哩。大玉玺既然不见了，就用这个不行吗？你疯了吗？快滚！你听着——不把他的头带来，就不许你再进宫。”

可怜的大法官赶紧离开了这个危险的地方；被推选负责处理这件案子的大臣们也连忙奉圣命去批准国会里那帮奴颜婢膝的人的决议，下令第二天就执行英国头等贵族、不幸的诺阜克公爵的死刑。

第九章　河上的盛况

晚上九点钟，王宫前面整个河滨大马路上都是一片灯火辉煌的景象。河里向城内那一面，凡目力所及的地方，水面上都挤满了船夫们的船和游玩的彩船，船边上都挂着彩色灯笼，被波浪轻柔地摇荡着，看去就好像是一片无边无际的百花怒放的花园，被夏天的微风吹得微微动荡一般。那一直通到河边的雄伟的石阶，宽大得足以容纳一个日耳曼公国的军队在上面排队；这时候那上面站着一排一排的穿着亮晃晃的盔甲的皇家戟兵，还有一队一队打扮得非常漂亮的仆人上下跑动，来来往往，忙着准备这桩大事。这真是一个热闹场面。

随后有一道命令传达下来，马上一切的生物都从石阶上走开，无影无踪了。于是空气中就充满了焦急和期盼的静默气氛。要是有人一眼望去，就可以看见那些船上成千上万的人都站起来了，大家把手搭到眼睛上面遮住灯笼和火炬的强烈光线，向王宫那边注视着。

四五十只华丽的御船排成一行，向石阶靠拢。这些豪华的大游船都漆着富丽的金色，它们那高起的船头和船尾都雕刻着精致的花纹。有几只船上还装饰着飘扬的旗幡；另有几只挂着金丝锦和绣着纹章的花帷；还有些船上飘着绸子的旗帜，旗上系着无数小银铃，每逢微风一吹，这些银铃就发出一阵一阵的悦耳声音；另外还有一些排场更大的船，因为是属于那些侍奉在王子身边的贵族的，所以两旁都用盾牌卫护着，盾牌上还雕刻着华丽的纹章。每只御船都用一只差船拖着，这些差船上除了划船的水手而外，每一只上面都载着一些头戴亮晃晃的钢盔、身披胸甲的兵士，还有一队乐师。

期待中的游行队伍的前卫这时候在大门口出现了，那是一队戟兵。他们下半身穿着黑色和茶色相间的条纹紧身裤，头戴两边镶着银色玫瑰花的天鹅绒帽子，上身穿着暗红和蓝色料子的紧身衣，前后都绣着三根用金线编织的羽毛，代表王子的纹章。戟柄都裹着深红色的天鹅绒，用镀金的钉子钉住，还有金色的穗子装饰着。他们向左右两边分成两队前进，排成了两个很长的单行，一直从宫殿的大门口排到河边。然后有王子的仆人，身穿金红两色相间的号衣，把一幅带条纹的厚毡子或是地毯摊开，铺在这两排戟兵之间。这一着完毕之后宫殿里面就奏起了一阵响亮的号声，河上的乐师们又奏了一首生气勃勃的前奏曲。于是有两个拿着白色指挥棒的前导官从门口迈着缓慢而庄严的步子前进。他们后面跟着一个手执权杖的官员，他背后又来了一个捧着城市之剑的官员；再后面是城市护卫队中的几位军士，他们都是全副武装，袖子上都佩戴着徽章；随后是身穿制服的嘉德纹章局长；再后面是几个巴斯级的骑士，每人袖子上都缠着一条白丝带；然后是他们的扈从；然后是身穿红袍、头戴白帽的法官；然后是英国大法官，他穿着深红色礼服，前面敞开，镶着白毛皮的边；然后是穿红袍的京都市参议会代表团；然后是穿着礼服的各市民团体的领袖。跟在他们后面的是十二个法国贵族的侍从，他们穿的华贵礼服包括白色锦缎上用金线配着线条的夹衣、镶着蓝紫色线缎里子的艳红色天鹅绒短斗篷和淡红色的灯笼裤；他们顺着石阶往下走。这十二个人是法国大使的随从，他们后面跟着十二个穿着毫无装饰的黑天鹅绒礼服的西班牙大使的随从骑士。跟在这些人后面的是几位英国大贵族，还带着他们的随从人员。

宫里又传出一阵号声，王子的舅父、未来的桑莫赛大公爵从大门里出来了。他穿着一件黑底子金丝缎的紧身衣，一件深红色缎子的长袍，上面绣着金花，还用银色的网纹镶着边。他转过身去，脱下那插着羽毛的帽子，非常恭敬地弯下身去，开始往后退，每走一步就行一个鞠躬礼。随后有一阵很长的号声和一声呼喝：“赶快回避，太子爱德华殿下驾到！”宫殿的墙头高处有一长排通红的火舌向前跳动，伴随着雷鸣般的一声炮响，河面上聚集的人群轰轰地发出一阵欢迎的吼声；这一宏大场面的主人公汤姆·康第出场了，他只微微地把他那高贵的头点了一下。

他穿着一件华丽的白缎子紧身衣，胸前配着一块紫色的金丝缎，那上面嵌着许多宝石，镶着貂皮的边。他在这上面披着一件白底金丝缎的斗篷，斗篷顶上是一个三根翎毛的顶饰，里子用的是蓝色缎子，斗篷上嵌着珍珠和宝石，前面用一个钻石别针扣着。他颈上挂着嘉德勋章和几个外国的王子勋章，凡是有光线射到他身上的地方，都有宝石反射出耀眼的光芒。啊，汤姆·康第，他不过是个小破房子里出世的穷孩子，在伦敦的贫民窟里长大的，一向与破烂、肮脏和苦难结下了不解之缘，现在这番景象却是多么煊赫啊！

第十章　落难的王子

我们上次说到约翰·康第拖着真正的王子往垃圾大院里去，后面跟着一群嘈杂而高兴的闲人。只有一个人替被抓的孩子求情，但是没有人理睬他：吵闹声太大了，他的声音连听也没有人听见。王子继续挣扎，企图脱身，并且对他所遭的侮辱大发脾气。直到后来，约翰·康第简直忍耐不住了，他忽然暴怒起来，把他那根橡木棍举到王子头上。唯一替那孩子求情的人一下子跑过去挡住康第的胳臂，于是打下来的一棍就落在这个人的手腕上了。康第大声吼道：

“你来管我的事吗，是不是？那就叫你尝尝滋味吧。”

他的棍子在那管闲事的人头上狠狠地敲下去，于是随着一声惨叫，就有一个模糊的人影倒在人群的脚下，随即他就在黑暗中独自躺在地上了。闲杂的人群又拥挤着前进，他们的兴致丝毫也没有因这一幕插曲而受到打搅。

随后王子就发现他自己已经到了约翰·康第家里；约翰关上了门，把那一群人关在外面。王子在一支插在瓶子里的蜡烛的微弱光线之下看出了这个令人作呕的狗窝的大致轮廓，也看出了屋里那些人的模样。两个邋遢的女孩子和一个中年妇人在一个角落里靠着墙哆嗦，她们那样子就像几个受惯了虐待的畜生，现在也正在战战兢兢地等待着虐待。在另一个角落里，有一个衰老的母夜叉披着灰白的头发，瞪着一双凶恶的眼睛，悄悄地走过来。约翰·康第对她说：

“等一等！这儿有一出怪有趣的滑稽戏。您别打搅，先开开心再说，完了之后您爱怎么使劲就怎么使劲打。站过来吧，小伙子。现在你再把那一套傻话说一遍吧，要是你没有忘记的话。先说你的名字吧，你叫什么？”

因受辱而激起的血液又涨到王子脸上来了，他抬起头来，愤怒地定睛注视着那个人的脸说道：

“像你这种家伙居然吩咐我说话，真是太无礼了。刚才我就告诉过你，现在再给你说一遍吧：我就是太子爱德华，不是别人。”

这个令人震惊的回答使得那母夜叉牢牢地在原地站住，好像脚底下钉了钉子一般，她几乎连气都透不过来了。她瞪着眼睛盯住王子，显出一种傻头傻脑的惊讶神情，这使她那坏蛋儿子大感兴趣，因此他发出了一阵响亮的笑声。汤姆·康第的母亲和两个姐姐的反应却不同，她们害怕汤姆挨打的恐惧心理马上就变为另一种痛苦了。她们脸上露出悲痛和惊惶的神色，连忙跑向前去惊喊道：

“啊，可怜的汤姆，可怜的孩子！”

母亲在王子面前跪下，伸手按在他肩上，眼眶里含着泪，爱怜地注视着他的脸。然后她就说：

“啊，可怜的孩子！你傻头傻脑地念那些书念入了迷，终归遭了殃，弄得发疯了。哎，我早就警告过你，叫你不要念，你为什么偏要念呢？你简直把你妈妈的心伤透了。”

王子注视着她的脸，温和地说：

“好心的太太，你的儿子并没有毛病，并没有发疯。你放心吧，他在王宫里，你让我回宫里去，我的父王马上就会把他交回给你。”

“你说国王是你的父亲呀！啊，我的孩子！千万别这么胡说吧，你说这种话是要治死罪的，你的亲人也会遭殃。你醒一醒吧，别再做这种可怕的梦了。把你那颗可怜的野马似的心叫回来，想想从前的事情呀。望着我吧，难道我不是生你和爱你的母亲吗？”

王子摇摇头，怪不情愿地说：

“上帝知道我不愿意伤你的心，可是我实在是从来没有见过你的面哩。”

那女人晕了，往后一倒，坐到地板上。她用双手蒙着脸，不由得伤心痛哭起来。

“让这出戏再演下去吧！”康第嚷道，“怎么啦，南恩！怎么啦，白特！好不懂礼的死丫头！你们怎么胆敢在王子面前站着？快跪下，你们这些穷骨头，快给王子磕头！”

他说完这话又粗声大笑了一阵，两个女孩开始胆怯地替她们的弟弟告饶。南恩说：

“爸爸，您要是让他去睡觉，他只要休息休息，睡上一觉，疯病就会好的；求求您，让他睡吧。”

“让他睡吧，爸爸，”白特也说，“他今天比平常更疲倦哩。明天他的脑子就醒过来了，他一定拼命去讨钱，不会再空着手回来的。”

这句话使她的父亲头脑清醒过来，不再穷开心了，他认真想起了正经事情。于是他转过脸来向着王子，很生气地对他说：

“明天咱们一定要给这个破房子的房东两个便士，两个便士，记住呀——这些钱是给他付半年房租的，要不然咱们就得滚蛋。你这懒骨头，讨了一天到底讨到多少钱，都给我拿出来吧。”

王子说：

“你别说这些肮脏的事情，叫我生气了。我再告诉你一遍，我是国王的儿子。”

康第伸出宽大的手掌在王子肩膀上“啪”的一声打了一掌，把他打得东歪西倒，他倒在康第大婶怀里，她就把他抱在胸前，用自己的身体挡在两人中间，顶住康第像急雨般的拳头和巴掌。

那两个女孩吓得退回她们的角落里去了，可是她们的祖母急切地走上前来，帮助她的儿子。王子从康第大婶怀里挣扎出去，大声喊道：

“你不用替我吃苦头，太太。让这两个畜生尽量在我一人身上打个够吧。”

这句话更惹得那两个畜生大怒，于是他们就加紧干起来。他们两人互相帮忙，把那孩子痛打了一顿，然后又打那两个女孩和他们的母亲，为的是她们不该对那受难的孩子表示同情。

“好吧，”康第说，“你们都去睡觉，这番款待，简直把我累坏了。”

随后就熄了灯，全家都睡觉了。当那一家之主和他母亲的鼾声表示他们已经睡着了的时候，那两个女孩马上就爬到王子躺着的地方，温柔地把干草和破絮盖在他身上，不叫他受凉；她们的母亲也爬过去，抚摸他的头发，对他哭起来，同时还对着他的耳朵悄悄地说了些安慰和爱怜的话。她还给他留下了一口吃的东西，可是这孩子因为痛得太厉害，一点儿食欲都没有——至少对这点无味的黑面包皮是没有胃口的。他为了她那样勇敢而不惜牺牲地保护他，为了她对他的怜恤大受感动；于是他用很高贵的、王子派头的口吻向她道谢，请她去睡觉，把她的苦恼忘掉。此外他还说，他的父王不会辜负她这番忠心的好意和热忱，一定会酬谢她。他这样再发“疯癫的毛病”又使她大为伤心，于是她再三把他使劲在怀里拥抱了一阵，才满脸流着眼泪回到她的“床上”去了。

在她躺着想心事和悲伤的时候，她心里渐渐起了一个念头，她觉得这个孩子无论是否发了疯，反正是有一种汤姆·康第所没有的、难以说明的特点。她无法形容这个特点，也说不出究竟是怎么回事，可是她那母性的本能似乎是察觉得到这点区别的。万一这孩子果真不是她自己的儿子，那可怎么办？啊，真是胡思乱想！她虽然又发愁，又着急，可是她想到这里还是几乎发笑了。不过尽管如此，她还是觉得这个念头不肯“甘休”，偏要在她脑子里打转。它纠缠着她，折磨着她，老萦绕在她的心头，不让她忘却，或是置之不理。后来她终于看透了，非等她想出一个测验的方法来，清清楚楚地、毫无疑问地证明这个孩子究竟是不是她的儿子，借此消除那些恼人的疑团，否则她心里就永远也不会太平。哈，对啦，这才分明是解决困难的正当办法，因此她就立即开动脑筋，要想出一个测验的方法来。可是一桩事情总是想着容易做起来难。她心里翻来覆去地想，考虑了一个又一个可能灵验的测验方法，可是最终不得不把它们通通放弃——这些方法没有一个是绝对有把握和绝对妥当的，而一个不大妥当的方法又不能使她满意。她显然是极费心机——她似乎是很明显地不得不放弃这个打算。当她心里转着这种丧气念头的时候，耳朵里忽然听见那孩子均匀的呼吸声，于是她知道他已经睡着了。她再一听，就听出那平稳的呼吸声被一种轻微的惊喊声所打断，这种喊声是做噩梦的人所常发出来的。这件偶尔发生的事情立刻就给她提供了一个很好的办法，那比她煞费苦心所想的那些测验方法合到一块还强。她马上就狂热却不声不响地动手把蜡烛再点着，一面低声自言自语：“刚才他说梦话的时候，我要是瞧见他，那我就准明白了！自从他小时候火药在他面前炸开的那一天起，他每逢忽然从梦中惊醒，或是正在想事的时候惊醒过来，总是伸手挡在眼睛前面，就像他那一天那样。可是他伸出手去的姿势和别人不同，不是把手掌向里，而是把手掌转向外面——我瞧见过无数次了，从来没有两样，也没有不做这个举动的。不错，现在我马上就可以明白了！”

这时候她已经用手遮住蜡烛的光，悄悄地摸到那酣睡的孩子身边。她小心谨慎地在他身边弯下腰去，抑制着兴奋的情绪，几乎停止了呼吸；然后她突然把蜡烛的光照到孩子脸上，同时在他耳边用指节敲着地板。孩子马上就把眼睛睁得很大，惊骇地瞪着眼睛向四周张望了一阵，可是他并没有用手做出什么特别的动作。

这可怜的女人突然遭到惊讶和懊恼的袭击，几乎不知如何是好；可是她极力把她的情绪隐藏起来，还是哄着那孩子再睡觉，然后她悄悄地走到一边，很懊丧地暗自思量着她这次测验的不幸结果。她极力想要相信那是汤姆的神经错乱放弃了他这种习惯的动作，可是办不到。“不对，”她说，“他的手并没有疯，绝不会在这么短的时间内忘掉这么长久的一种老习惯。啊，这真是个叫我难受的日子！”

但是现在她还是顽强地保持着希望，正像她原来抱着怀疑那样。她简直不能使她自己相信那次测验的判断，她必须再试一次——第一次的失败想必只是偶然的事情，所以她稍隔一会儿又把那孩子从睡梦中一次又一次地搅醒——结果还是和第一次的测验一样——然后她拖着疲乏的身子回到床上，伤心地睡着了。她临睡时还说：“可是我还是不能放弃他——啊，不行，我不能，我不能——他非是我的孩子不可！”

后来王子因为不再被这可怜的母亲打搅，他的痛楚也渐渐失去了搅扰睡眠的力量，于是极度的疲劳终于封住了他的眼睛，使他安静地酣睡了。时间一小时又一小时地溜过去，他仍旧睡得像死人一样。四五个钟头的工夫就这样过去了。然后他的睡意开始减轻，不久，他就在半睡半醒的状态中含糊地喊道：

“威廉爵士！”

过了一会儿又喊道：

“嗬，威廉·赫伯特爵士！你快来，听听这个荒唐的梦，我从来没有……威廉爵士！你听见了吗？嗨，我还以为我真变成了一个叫花子哩，还有……嗬，听着！卫队！威廉爵士！怎么的！难道没有宫中侍从官在这里吗？哎呀，真该收拾一下这些……”

“你怎么了，不舒服？”他身边有人悄悄地问道，“你在叫谁？”

“叫威廉·赫伯特爵士。你是谁？”

“我？我不是你的姐姐南恩，还会是谁？啊，汤姆，我忘了！你还在发疯哪——可怜的孩子，你还在发疯哪，我还不如根本没有醒，免得听到你这些疯话！可是千万请你别再胡说，要不然咱们都得挨打，一直到被打死才算完事！”

大吃一惊的王子稍稍翻身坐起来，可是他那些发僵的伤处忽然感到一阵剧痛，使他清醒过来。于是他就在那一团肮脏的干草当中往回卧倒，一面呻吟着，不由自主地喊叫道：

“糟糕，那么原来还不是个梦呀！”

片刻之间，睡眠已经替他消除了的深沉的悲伤和苦痛又全部涌上心头，他发觉他已经不是宫中的一个娇生惯养的、为全国的人爱慕的眼光所注视的王子了，而是一个穿得破破烂烂的叫花子、流浪儿，一个被关在只配给畜生住的窝里的俘虏，跟乞丐和小偷混在一起了。

在这一阵悲伤之中，他开始听到外面有些欢腾嘈杂的喊声，好像只相隔一两排房子的距离。又过了一会儿，门口就有几声很响的敲门声。约翰·康第停止了打鼾，问道：

“谁敲门呀？你来干什么？”

有一个声音回答：“你知道昨晚上你的棍子打着的是谁？”

“我不知道，也不关心。”

“恐怕你回头就得改变个说法吧。你要是打算留下你这条命，那除了逃跑就没有别的办法。那人现在已经断气了，他就是安德鲁神父呀！”

“我的天哪！”康第惊喊了一声。他把全家人叫醒，粗声粗气地命令道：“你们都快起来，赶紧逃跑——要不然就待在这儿等死！”

还不到五分钟，康第这一家人就到了街上，慌忙逃命。约翰·康第揪住王子的手腕子，拉着他在黑暗的路上往前急跑，同时低声给了他这么一个警告：

“你这疯头疯脑的傻子，千万不许乱说，也别说出咱们的姓名。我马上就要改个新名字，叫当差的那些狗东西找不着抓我的线索。可不许乱说呀，我告诉你！”

他又凶狠地对家里其余的人说：

“万一咱们走散了，大伙儿就上伦敦桥那儿去，谁要是走到了桥上最后的那家麻布店那儿，就站住等着别人来到，然后咱们就一同逃到南市去。”

这时候这伙人忽然从黑暗中冲到光亮的地方了，而且不但是到了光亮的地方，还到了聚集在河边上唱歌、跳舞和呐喊的成千上万的人当中。尽目力所及地望过去，只见泰晤士河的下游沿岸到处都是火，伦敦桥也被灯光照得很亮，南市桥也是一样；整个的河上都被闪烁而辉煌的彩色灯光照得通红，花炮不断的爆炸使天空充满了四处放射、缤纷交织的光辉和密雨似的耀眼的火花，几乎使黑夜变成了白昼，到处都是狂欢的人群；伦敦全城似乎都在任意胡闹一般。

约翰·康第暴怒地咒骂了一声，命令大家撤退，可是已经来不及了。他和他那一家人被那万头攒动的人群所吞没，马上就无可奈何地被冲散了。我们并没有把王子当成他家里的一分子，可康第仍旧揪住他没有放手。王子的心这时候被脱逃的希望激动得剧跳起来。康第拼命地挤，企图从人群中钻出去，于是他粗鲁地把一个健壮的水手猛推了一把。这个水手或许是喝醉了酒，兴致很高，他伸出一只大手按在康第肩膀上说：

“嘿，伙计，你跑得这么快，要上哪儿去？所有的老实人都在痛痛快快地庆祝，难道你脑子里还在为一些肮脏的事情转念头吗？”

“我自己的事情自己管，用不着你瞎操心，”康第粗鲁地回答道，“你快撒手，让我过去吧。”

“你的脾气这么坏，我偏不让你过去，非叫你先喝一杯酒给太子祝贺不行，我告诉你。”那水手坚决地挡住去路，说道。

“那么，把杯子给我吧，快点，快点！”

这时候，别的喝贺酒的人也对他们感兴趣了。大家喊道：

“拿爱杯[7]来，拿爱杯来！叫这个怪脾气的坏蛋喝爱杯，要不咱们就把他推到河里去喂鱼。”

于是有人拿过一只很大的爱杯来，那水手用一只手抓住杯子的一个把柄，另一只手捏着一条想象中的餐巾，按照正式的古礼把爱杯递给康第；康第也就不得不按照历代相传的仪式，用一只手握住爱杯另一边的把手，另一只手揭开杯盖。这么一来，当然就使王子暂时没有被人揪住。他不失时机，马上就往身边那些树林似的人腿当中一钻，逃得无影无踪了。转瞬之间，他就沉没在那动荡的人海里，要想寻找他，就像从大西洋里寻找一枚六便士的银币那么困难。

他不久就明白了这种情况，马上就忙着干他自己的事情，再也不往约翰·康第身上想了。另外他还很快地明白了一桩事情，那就是：有一个假太子冒充着自己，正在受全城人民的宴饮祝贺。他很容易推断出那就是贫儿汤姆·康第有意利用他那千载一时的机会，成了一个僭位的角色。

因此王子只有一条路可走——找到市会厅[8]去，宣布自己的身份，揭露那个小骗子。他还打定了主意，让汤姆有一段相当的时间忏悔祈祷，然后按照当时惩治叛国罪的法律和惯例，处以绞刑，挖出肠肚，肢解尸体。

第十一章　市会厅的盛会

御船由那一队豪华的舰队陪伴着，庄严地从一片无边无际的灯火辉煌的船当中穿过，顺着泰晤士河往下走。空中飘荡着音乐，河边到处升起庆祝的火焰；远处有无数视线以外的篝火把天空照得通红，城内就笼罩在它们那柔和的火光之中；城市的上空高耸着许多细长的尖塔，上面都镶饰着闪烁的灯笼，因此远远地看去，它们就好像投向高空的镶着宝石的标枪一般；舰队飞快地划过去的时候，两岸就有不断的大声欢呼、不停的礼炮的火光和轰隆轰隆的响声向船上表示欢迎致敬。

汤姆·康第靠在他那些绸缎的腰枕当中，身子几乎埋掉了一半。在他看来，这些声音和这番盛况实在是一种无法形容的庄严和惊人的奇迹。但是在他身边的两位小朋友伊丽莎白公主和洁恩·格雷公主的眼中，这一切都算不了什么稀奇。

舰队到了杜乌门之后，就被拖进清澈的华尔河（这条河的河道现在早已覆盖在一大片房屋底下，有两世纪之久了），一直开到巴克勒斯伯里，沿途经过的一些房屋和桥梁下都拥挤着狂欢的人，而且都点着光辉灿烂的灯火，最后船队终于在伦敦旧城中心的一个小湾里停住了，这就是现在的御船场所在的地方。汤姆下了船，他和他那些威武的侍从穿过契普赛街，再经过老犹太街和碑信浩街走了一段短路，就到了市会厅。

汤姆和那两位小公主都由戴着金链子、穿着大红礼服的伦敦市长和市参议员们按照正式礼仪出来迎接；再由传令官做前导，一路报告王子殿下驾到；还有侍卫拿着权杖和宝剑在前面走，引着他们到大会厅上首的一个富丽堂皇的华盖下面。伺候王子和他那两个小朋友的贵族和贵妇人都到他们的座位后面站着。

在下面一点儿的一桌席上，朝中大臣和其他显要贵宾同城中的富豪坐在一起；下议院议员们都在大会厅当中那许多席位上坐下了。那自古以来的伦敦城守护神——巨人戈格和麦戈格，居高临下地玩味着他们下面这一番盛况，他们那两对眼睛已经在不知多少年间看惯了这套把戏了。随后一声号响，跟着就有人传令，一个胖胖的膳司在左边墙里一个高处出现，后面跟着他的下属们，一本正经地抬着一盆冒着热气、准备切下来吃的御餐牛腰肉走来。

祈祷谢饭之后，汤姆就站起来（这是随侍的大臣教给他的）——全厅的人也跟着站起来——他和伊丽莎白公主从一只金质大爱杯里各自喝了一口酒，随后酒杯就递给了洁恩公主，再从她那里递给全体在座的人都喝了一遍。御宴就这样开始了。

半夜里，宴饮的狂欢到了高潮。这时候，出现了当时大受赞美的生动场面之一。亲眼看到这场热闹的一位史官曾经留下了一段古雅的记载，至今还可以查考得到：

“大厅里腾出了一片空地，随即进来了一位男爵和一位伯爵，他们都仿照土耳其的服装，穿着洒金的锦缎长袍；头戴艳红色天鹅绒帽子，上面配着金丝缎的大卷边；身边挂着两把短弯刀，都用金色的粗丝带系着。随后又来了一位男爵和一位伯爵，他们仿照俄国的式样，身穿黄缎长袍，上面镶着白缎子的横条，每条白色缎带子当中还配着一条大红缎带；头戴灰色皮帽；他们两人各自手里都拿着一把斧头；靴子前头都有向上翘起的一英尺长的尖头。他们后面又来了一位骑士，再后面是海军大臣，还有五个贵族和他同行。他们穿的是深红色天鹅绒的紧身衣，颈项前后都露在外面，胸前贴着银色丝带；紧身衣上面披着大红缎的短袍；头上戴的是舞蹈式的帽子，上面插着野鸡毛。这些人是仿照普鲁士人打扮的。人数有一百左右的火炬手紧跟而来，穿着大红和绿色缎子的衣服，像摩尔人那样，脸上也涂黑了。他们后面进来了一个演哑剧的人。然后化装的歌手们跳起舞来，贵族和贵妇人也跟着狂舞，那真是叫人看了很痛快的场面。”

汤姆高高地坐在上位，注视着这场“狂欢的”舞蹈，一心望着下面那些衣着华丽的人像旋风似的舞动着，呈现出那种耀眼的千变万化的色彩混成一团的奇景。正在这时候，那穿着破衣服的真正的太子却在市会厅门口宣布他的权利和不幸的遭遇，他揭露了那冒充的太子，大吵大闹地要进来！外面的人群对这场风波极感兴趣，大家拼命挤上前去，伸长脖子来看这个小捣乱鬼。随后他们开始辱骂和嘲笑他，故意逗得他更加愤怒，更加使他们开心。耻辱激起的眼泪涌出眼眶，可是他坚持着站住不动，以十足的皇家气派对抗着那群暴徒。跟着又是一阵辱骂，新的嘲笑刺痛着他，于是他大声喝道：

“我再给你们说一遍吧，你们这群无礼的恶狗，我是太子！我现在虽然举目无亲，没有人给我说句公道话，或是在我遭难的时候救救我，可是我决不能让你们赶走，还是要坚持站在这里！”

“无论你是不是王子，反正都一样，你真是个有骨气的孩子，而且也不是没有朋友！我就站在你身边，可以证明这句话不假。我告诉你吧，我迈尔斯·亨顿给你做个朋友虽然算不了什么，可是用不着你到处去寻找。你且不用再开口吧，孩子，我会说这些下贱的小畜生所说的话，就像是一个本地人说的一样。”

说话的人的服装、气派和态度都表明他是个落魄的王族后代。他身材高大，体形端正，壮健有力。他的紧身衣和短裤都是用讲究的材料做的，可是已经褪了色，穿得露出了底线，那上面镶的金丝带也变得颜色晦暗了；他的绉领已经皱得不成样子，而且破了；他那垂边帽上插的翎毛已经断了，显出一副狼狈不堪的寒碜相；他腰间带着一把轻巧细长的剑，插在一只锈了的铁鞘里；他那架子很大的派头却又表明他是个惯于吹牛的风尘人物。这个狂妄角色所说的话遭到一阵讥讽和耻笑。有人喊道：“这又是一个乔装的王子！”“当心点儿，别乱说吧，朋友，也许他这人是很凶的！”“可不是吗，看他那神情的确像是那样——瞧他那双眼睛！”“把那孩子从他那儿抢过来吧——抓着这小畜生丢到洗马池里去！”

立刻就有人受了这个妙计的鼓动，伸手去抓王子；那位陌生人也来得快，他马上就抽出了他那把长剑，用剑面噼啪地猛敲了一下，就把那多事的人打倒在地了。随后就有许多人齐声嚷道：“揍死这个狗东西！揍死他！揍死他！”一大群暴徒向这位武士围拢，他就把背靠着墙站着，像个疯子似的向周围挥动他的长剑。挨了剑的人一个个东倒西跌，可是暴徒们像潮水似的从那些扑倒的身体上继续涌上前来，愤怒不息地向这位勇士猛冲。他似乎是再也支持不下去了，势必性命难保。偏巧这时候忽然响起了号声，有人嚷道：“快让路呀，国王的传令官来了！”随即就有一队骑兵向那群暴徒急冲过来，大家只好亡命地飞跑，逃脱危险。那勇敢的陌生人把王子抱在怀里，不久就远离人群，逃出险境了。

我们现在再回到市会厅里面来吧。忽然有一阵响亮的号声压倒了那庆祝的狂欢中欢声雷动的声音，大家立刻就静默下来，鸦雀无声了；然后有一个人高声说话——那是王宫里派来的传令官——他开始扯着尖嗓子宣布一个公告，所有的人都肃立静听着。最后的一句话念得特别严肃，那就是：

“国王驾崩！”

在场的人全体一致把头垂到胸前，大家把这种姿势保持了几分钟，一片沉寂；然后全体同时跪下，向汤姆伸出手去，发出一阵洪亮的呼声：

“国王万岁！”这声音似乎把屋宇都震动了。

可怜的汤姆望着这个惊心动魄的场面，不由得用他那双迷茫的眼睛东张西望，最后他恍恍惚隐地向跪在他身边的两位公主望了一会儿，然后又望着赫德福伯爵。他忽然动了一个念头，脸上也露出了欢喜的神色。他靠近赫德福勋爵的耳边，低声说道：

“请你凭良心说话，老老实实地回答我！我想要颁布一道命令，那是除了国王以外谁也没有权力颁布的；要是我把它颁布出来，大家会不会服从？该不会有人反对吧？”

“不会，陛下，全国都不会有。陛下是英国的一国之主，您是国王——您说的话就是法律。”

汤姆用坚定而诚挚的声音，兴高采烈地回答道：

“那么从今以后，国王的法律就是仁慈的法律，再也不是血腥的法律了！快起来，到塔里去，宣布国王有令，诺阜克公爵免死！”

这几句话立刻就被别人听见了，于是大家口口相传，很快就在大会厅里传遍了。赫德福急忙从御前走开的时候，又有一阵异常洪亮的欢呼爆发了：

“血腥的统治完结了！大英国王爱德华万岁！”

第十二章　王子和他的救星

迈尔斯·亨顿和小王子摆脱了那一群暴徒之后，马上就穿过一些背街小巷，匆匆向河边奔逃。他们在路上没有受到阻挡，一直跑近了伦敦桥，然后他们又在万人攒动的人群中挤着往前走，亨顿紧紧地握着王子的手——不，国王的——手腕子。那惊天动地的消息已经四处传开，这孩子同时从无数的人声中听到了——“国王驾崩了！”这个不幸的消息使这漂泊无依的孩子心头打了个寒战，浑身发抖。他体会到他所遭的损失有多么大，心中充满了深切的悲恸；因为那位威严的暴君虽然对别人横暴无比，对他却向来是很慈爱的。热泪涌到他眼眶里来，使他视线朦胧，一切都看不清楚了。在那一刹那间，他感到自己是上帝的生灵中最孤苦伶仃、举目无亲、没人理睬的了——这时候又有另一阵呼声像响雷似的震动了夜空：“爱德华六世国王万岁！”这使他高兴得眼睛里发亮，一股得意的情绪立刻渗透全身，连手指尖上都感觉到了。“啊，”他心里想，“这显得多么庄严而又神奇呀——我当了国王！”

我们这两位朋友在桥上从人群中穿过，慢慢地往前走。这座存在了六百年的桥在那些年代里一向都是一条熙熙攘攘的通道，它是座稀奇的建筑物，两旁紧密地排列着许多商店，楼上尽是些住家的房屋，从河的一边一直延伸到对岸。这座桥本身就可以算是一个市镇：那上面有小客栈，有啤酒铺，有面包房，有服饰杂货店，有食品市场，有手工业工场，甚至还有教堂。在它的心目中，它所连接起来的两个邻区——伦敦和南市——如果作为郊区，还算不坏，但此外就没有什么特别了不起了。这个地方可以说是一个生息相关的小天地，它是一个狭窄的市镇，只有一条五分之一英里长的街道，它的人口只够一个村镇的人数，那里面的居民个个都和他们所有同镇的人熟识，并且还认识他们的父母和祖先——连他们的家庭琐事也都一清二楚。这个地方当然也有它的贵族阶级——那些上流的屠宰世家、面包世家等，应有尽有，他们在那些古老的房屋里已经住了五六百年，对这座桥的悠久历史从头到尾都知道得清清楚楚，还知道它的一切稀奇的传说。他们说的老是桥上的事情，想的老是桥上的念头，说起瞎话来总是很冗长，语调平匀，直截了当，内容丰富，自有一种桥上的派头。这种地方的居民必然是狭隘、无知而又自负的。孩子们都是在桥上出生，在桥上长大，在桥上活到老年，然后在桥上死去；他们除了这座伦敦桥以外，一生一世从来不曾踏足到其他任何地方。日日夜夜，络绎不绝的行人车马的巨流从这条街上穿过，经常有乱嚷乱叫的人声，还有马嘶、牛吼、羊叫，再加上那些兽蹄嘚嘚的响声，真是热闹极了；那些住在桥上的人自然认为这番景象是人间唯一的奇观，把他们自己多少当成这种奇观的专利者。而事实上也的确如此——至少他们可以从窗户里展示这种奇观，每逢有一位回朝的国王或是英雄人物临时给这种奇观添上一层光彩的时候，他们就果然享受到他们的特权，因为要想从头到尾、清清楚楚、一直不断地看到那些威武的行列，再没有像桥上这么好的地方了。

在桥上出生和成长的人们无论到什么别的地方，都觉得生活空虚无聊，简直无法忍受。历史上曾经记载过这么一个人，他在七十一岁的时候离开了伦敦桥，退休到乡间去了。可是他只能在床上辗转反侧，心烦意乱，他简直睡不成觉，因为他觉得那万籁无声的寂静太讨厌、太可怕、太沉闷了。后来他终于厌弃了那种环境，还是逃回了他的老家；这时候他已经熬成了一个消瘦而憔悴的幽灵，一回到老家，就在那激荡的流水拍岸的声响和伦敦桥上的人声、车声、蹄声的催眠合奏中，怪舒适地获得了安息，恢复了甜蜜的美梦。

在我们所写的那个年代，这座桥给当时的儿女们提供了英国历史的“实物教学”材料——那就是，桥头的拱门顶上钉着一些尖头长铁钉，那上面挂着一些有名人物的惨白的腐烂的头颅。可是我们现在且不谈这个吧。

亨顿的住处就在这座桥上的小客栈里。他带着他那位小朋友走近门口的时候，有一个粗暴的声音说：

“好，你总算又来了！我老实告诉你，这回可别想再逃跑了；要是把你这一身贱骨头捣成肉酱就能叫你得点教训的话，下回也许你就不会让我们这么老等了。”——约翰·康第一面说着，一面就伸出手去，要抓住这个孩子。

迈尔斯·亨顿把他挡住，说：

“先别忙动手吧，朋友。我看你大可不必这样粗鲁，这孩子是你什么人？”

“你要是专门爱找麻烦，爱管别人的闲事的话，你得知道他是我的儿子呀。”

“胡说！”小国王愤怒地喊道。

“说得好，有胆量，不管你那小脑袋是正常的，还是不清醒，我都相信你。可是这个浑蛋流氓究竟是不是你的父亲，那反正没有关系；只要你情愿跟我在一起，我就不许他把你抓去打骂，他吓唬你的话算是白说。”

“我愿意跟你在一起，我愿意——我不认识他，我讨厌他，我宁死也不跟他去。”

“那就这么决定了吧，别的话再没什么可说的了。”

“你说得好呀，我倒要看看你能怎么样！”约翰·康第大声说道，一面迈着大步走过亨顿身边，要去抓那孩子，“我要强迫他……”

“你这人面畜生，你要是胆敢碰他一下，我就把你一剑戳穿，就像戳一只鹅那样！”亨顿挡住他，一面把手按在剑柄上，一面说。康第把手缩回去了。“你听着吧，”亨顿继续说，“刚才有一群像你这样的暴徒想要虐待这个孩子，也许还想要他的命，我保护了他；难道你以为现在我会不管他，让他遭到更坏的命运吗？——无论你是不是他的父亲——说老实话，我想你是撒谎——像他这么个孩子，即便堂堂正正地让人家很快就弄死，也比落到你这种畜生手里受活罪强得多。好吧，滚开，还得滚快一点儿，因为我这个人生来没有多大耐性，不爱跟人家多费口舌。”

约翰·康第一面嘟哝着说些威胁和咒骂的话，一面走开，随后就消失在人群中，不见踪影了。亨顿叫了一顿饭，让茶房给他送上楼去，然后带着他所保护的孩子，爬上三层楼梯，到了他的房间。那是个简陋的屋子，里面有一张破床和几件零七碎八的旧家具，点着两支暗淡的蜡烛，光线相当微弱。小国王拖着脚步走到床边，卧倒在那上面，他因饥饿和困乏，几乎是筋疲力尽了。现在已经是清早两三点钟，他将近有一天一夜的工夫，一直都在站着走着，并且还没有吃过一点儿东西。他困倦地低声说道：“开饭的时候请你叫我一声。”马上就酣睡起来了。

亨顿眼睛里闪过一些微笑，他自言自语道：

“真是，这个小叫花子上人家屋里来，占据了人家的床铺，他可是若无其事，心安理得，好像什么都是归他所有似的——根本就不说一声对不起或是请不要见怪这类话。他发起神经病来，胡说八道的时候，居然自称为太子，并且还把这个角色扮演得很妙哩。可怜的、无依无靠的野孩子，不消说，他一定是因为受的折磨太多，弄得神经错乱了。好吧，我要做他的朋友；我救了他，这就使我对他产生了深厚的感情；我已经很喜欢这个敢说大话的小坏蛋了。他反抗那些肮脏的暴徒，用他那种高傲的藐视态度向他们还击，真是十足的军人气概！睡眠的魔力把他脸上的愁容和悲伤都消除了，他这张面孔显得多么清秀、多么可爱、多么温柔啊！一定要教他，我一定要治好他的创伤；是呀，我还要做他的哥哥，还要照顾他、保卫他；谁要是打算欺负他或是伤害他，那就得叫那个家伙赶快给他自己准备寿衣，因为我哪怕是为这事情遭火刑，也非要那个人的命不可！”

他弯下腰去望着这孩子，以慈祥和爱怜的眼光打量着他，同时用他那棕色的大手温柔地轻拍着那孩子的脸蛋儿，把他那乱蓬蓬的卷发往后面抚平。一阵轻微的颤动掠过这孩子的全身。亨顿喃喃地说：

“你瞧，我这人怎么这样大意，居然让他躺在这儿，不给他盖点东西，这岂不要使他染上致命的感冒吗？那么我怎么办呢？要是把他抱起来，放到床铺里面去，就会把他弄醒，可是他又非常需要睡眠。”

他向四周张望，想找到一点多余的被盖，可是没有找到，于是他就把自己身上的紧身上衣脱下来，给这孩子裹上，一面说：“我已经受惯了刺骨的寒风，穿惯了单薄的衣裳，我是不大怕着凉的。”随后他就在屋子里来回走动，使血液流通，一面仍旧在自言自语：

“他那受了创伤的心灵使他相信自己是太子；要说现在我们居然还有一个太子的话，那未免是件怪事，因为原来是太子的，现在已经不是太子，而是国王了。这颗可怜的心只怀着那么一个幻想，不肯把道理想清楚，看不出现在应该抛弃王子的称号，自称国王……我在国外坐了七年地牢，一直没有得到过家里的音信，如果我父亲还在世的话，他一定会看在我的面上，欢迎这可怜的孩子，给他慷慨的接待；我那好心肠的哥哥亚赛也会欢迎他；我的兄弟休吾……可是他要干涉我的话，我就要敲破他的脑袋，这个狡猾的、坏心肠的畜生！对，我们就往那儿去吧——马上就走。”

一个茶房端了一份冒热气的饭菜进来，把它放在一张小松木桌子上，再摆好椅子，就出去了；像这样的穷房客得自己伺候自己了。他出去的时候，还把门使劲一带，“砰”的一声把那孩子惊醒了；他一翻身就坐起来，挺愉快地向四周扫了一眼；随后他脸上又布满了愁容，他长叹了一声，喃喃地自言自语：“哎呀，原来是一场梦。我真伤心啊！”后来他又看见了迈尔斯·亨顿的紧身上衣，他把视线从这件衣服移到亨顿身上，明白了这位好心人为他而牺牲了自己的温暖，于是他就温柔地说：

“你对我很好，真的，你对我太好了。拿去穿上吧——现在我不需要它了。”

然后他就站起来，走到角落里的脸盆架跟前，站在那儿等着。亨顿用愉快的声调说：

“现在我们可以痛痛快快地饱餐一顿了，饭菜样样都是又香又热的，还在冒气哪。你睡了个小觉，再好好地吃一顿，又会成个挺有精神的小伙子，你放心吧！”

那孩子没有回答，他只是定睛望着那带剑的魁梧武士，那种神情既有巨大的惊讶，又含着几分不耐烦的意味。亨顿感到莫名其妙，于是他说：

“怎么啦？”

“喂，我要洗洗脸。”.

“啊，原来是这么回事呀！你爱干什么都行，用不着向我迈尔斯·亨顿请示。我的东西你尽管随便使用，你千万不要客气，我很欢迎你。”

那孩子仍旧站着不动，不但如此，他还把一只脚挺不耐烦地在地板上跺了一两下。亨顿简直不知是怎么回事，他说：

“哎呀，这是怎么回事？”

“请你把水倒上，不要多话！”

亨顿忍住了一阵大笑，心里想着，“天哪，这可真是扮得像！”于是他就敏捷地走上前去，做了那傲慢无礼的小家伙所吩咐的事情；然后他就站在旁边，不禁有些因诧异而发呆，直到后来，又是一声命令，“过来——给我毛巾！”这才把他猛然惊醒过来。他从那孩子的鼻子底下拿起毛巾，递了给他，可并没有表示什么意见。这时候他才动手把自己的脸也洗一洗，让它痛快痛快；他在洗脸的时候，他这个收养的孩子就在桌子跟前坐下了，准备着用餐。亨顿迅速地洗完脸，然后把另外那把椅子往后一拉，正待坐下来吃饭，可是这孩子愤怒地说：

“慢着！你竟敢在国王面前坐下吗？”

这个晴天霹雳使亨顿大吃一惊，甚至脚跟都受到了震动。他悄悄地自言自语说：“瞧，这个可怜虫的神经病真是跟上了时代呀！国家有了变故，他的神经病也跟着变过来了，现在他在幻想中居然成了国王！哎呀，我可得顺着他这个狂想才行——没有别的办法——真的，要不然他就要叫我上塔里去坐牢了！”

他打定了这个开玩笑的主意，心里很高兴，于是他把那把椅子从桌子前面搬开，在国王背后站着，尽他所能地按照宫廷礼节开始伺候他。

国王吃饭的时候，他那王室的尊严稍微减少了一点威风，他越吃越高兴，因此就乐于谈话了。他说：

“我记得你好像是说你叫迈尔斯·亨顿，我该没有听错吧？”

“是的，陛下，”迈尔斯回答说，然后他心里又这么想，“我要是非顺着这个可怜孩子的神经病不可，那我就必须称他为国王，必须称他为陛下，决不能弄得不三不四；既然扮演了这个角色，我就不能有任何顾虑，否则我就会扮演得不好，把这桩好心好意的事情也弄糟了。”

国王喝了第二杯酒，心里就更加有了兴致，于是他说：“我想要了解你这个人——你把你的来历告诉我吧。你的举动很有英勇的气概，而且有高贵的精神——你是贵族出身吗？”

“禀告国王陛下，我家忝列贵族之末。家父是个从男爵——较小的勋爵之一，称爵士衔[9]——他是理查·亨顿爵士，住在肯特郡僧人洲附近的亨顿府。”

“这个名字我现在记不起来了。再往下说吧——把你的来历都告诉我。”

“陛下，我的来历没有多少可说的，不过既然没有更开心的事情可说，我讲讲我的来历或许可以供您半小时的消遣。家父理查爵士是很富有的，而且生性非常豪爽。我还是个小孩子的时候，家母就去世了。我有两个弟兄：我的哥哥叫作亚赛，他的心肠正像家父一样；我的弟弟休吾是个卑鄙龌龊的家伙，他贪得无厌，诡计多端，心地狠毒，专爱暗算别人，是个卑鄙阴险的小人。他生下来就是那样，十年前我最后看到他的时候，他还是那样——他才十九岁就成了个十足的坏蛋，那时候我才二十岁，亚赛二十二岁。家里另外没有别人，只有我的表妹爱迪思小姐——那时候她才十六岁——相貌很美，性情温柔，心肠很好，是个伯爵的女儿，她家就只剩下她一个人，一笔很大的财产和那断嗣的头衔都归她继承了。家父是她的监护人。我很爱她，她也爱我；可是她从生下来就和亚赛订了婚，理查爵士不许毁除婚约。亚赛爱上了另外一个姑娘，他叫我们不要灰心，坚持我们的愿望，将来总有一天，日子拖久了，再赶上个好运气，总会让我们各自的好事如愿以偿。休吾爱上了爱迪思小姐的财产，虽然他口头上说他爱的是她本人——不过他向来是这样，老是嘴里说的是一套，心里想的又是另一套。可是他的诡计在这位姑娘身上施展不开，他能骗得过我的父亲，可骗不了别人。我父亲在我们弟兄三个当中最喜欢他，也最信任他，最听他的话；因为他是最小的孩子，别人都恨他——这些特点自古以来总是足以博得父母的欢心；他还有一张很甜的嘴，最会哄人，撒谎的本领又特别高明——这些特长又正好能够大大地助长那盲目的疼爱。我是有些狂放——说老实话，我还可以进一步承认我的确是非常狂放，不过我那种狂放是天真烂漫的，因为除了我自己，它对谁也没有害处，也不丢谁的脸，也不叫谁受什么损失，又没有任何罪恶和卑劣的意味；对我那高贵的身份也没有什么不适合的。

“可是我那兄弟休吾偏要利用我这种毛病来施展诡计——他知道我们的哥哥亚赛身体不太好，一心希望他短命，他估计着只要把我扫除出去，他就可以为所欲为了——就是这样——可是，国王陛下，这件事情说来话长，并且还不值得细说。那么，简单说一下，我这位兄弟把我的毛病巧妙地加以夸大，说成是一些罪过；他进行这种卑鄙的毒计，到最后就捏造事实，硬说他在我的房间里发现了一架丝绳的梯子——其实是他自己设法弄到我屋里去的——他就凭着这个证据，还收买了几个仆人和另外一些撒谎的坏蛋帮着做伪证，使家父深信我打算违反他的旨意，把我的爱迪思带走，和她结婚。

“于是家父就说，把我从家里驱逐出去，叫我离开英国，在外面流放三年，或许可以使我成为一个军人和有出息的角色，并且还可以使我学到一些聪明智慧。于是我就参加了大陆上的战争，我在那长期的考验中打出一条出路来；我尝尽了艰难困苦，遭过一些严重的打击，经历过一些冒险的场合；可是在最后一场战斗中，我终于被俘了。从此以后，春夏秋冬，一年又一年地过去，我在一个外国的地牢里一直被关了七年。最后我凭着自己的机智和勇气，获得了自由，才一直逃回家乡来；我是刚到的，穷得既没有钱，又没有衣服；至于这沉闷的七年里，亨顿府和那里的人以及其他一切究竟发生了一些什么变化，我就更是一无所知了。禀告陛下，我这个乏味的故事已经说完了。”

“你受了无耻的陷害！”小国王说，眼睛里闪出了愤怒的光，“可是我要给你申这个冤——凭主的十字架起誓，我一定要这么做！这是国王的承诺。”

然后由于迈尔斯遭到冤屈的故事使他受到了触动，他也就滔滔不绝地说开了他最近的不幸遭遇，使这位倾听者不禁目瞪口呆。他说完了的时候，迈尔斯心里想道：

“瞧，他的想象力多么丰富！单凭这个离奇故事里所说的那些凭空捏造的情节，就足以说明这不是平凡的脑子，否则无论它是疯了还是正常的，绝不能编出这么一个有条有理、有声有色的奇谈。可怜的、遭了摧残的小心灵啊，只要我还活在人间，我就决不让它没有朋友，决不让它没有归宿。我永远不让他离开我的身边，我要把他当作心爱的人，当作我的小伴侣。我一定要治好他的毛病！——是呀，要使他头脑清楚，恢复正常——然后他就可以成名——将来我就可以自豪地说，‘是呀，他是我的人——我把他这无家可归的小流浪儿收养了，可是我看出了他的长处，我说过日后他会声名远扬——你看，我说对了没有？’”

国王又说话了——他用的是深思的、平稳的语调：

“你救了我，使我没有受到伤害和羞辱，也许还救了我的性命，因此也就挽救了我的王位，这种功劳是应该受大赏的。你把你的愿望说出来吧，只要不超出我的王权范围，你就可以如愿以偿。”

这个异想天开的提议使亨顿从他的幻想中惊醒过来。他正想向国王谢恩，声明他所做的是分内之事，并不希望得到什么奖赏，借此把这件事情应付过去，可是他脑子里忽然起了一个比较聪明的念头；于是他请求国王让他安静几分钟，考虑考虑国王赏他的这番恩典——国王对他这个主意郑重地表示同意，他说对待这种意义重大的事情，最好还是不要匆忙决定。

迈尔斯沉思了几分钟，然后就想道：“对，这么办正好——要是用别的办法，绝不能达到目的——真是，有了这一个钟头的经验，我就知道老像这么下去，那是非常累人、非常不方便的。对，我就提出这个要求吧。我没有随便放弃这个机会，总算是万幸。”于是他单膝跪下说：

“那微不足道的效劳原是做臣子的分内之事，因此无功可言；但陛下既然开恩，认为应予嘉赏，我就不揣冒昧，敬恳恩准一事。陛下知道，将近四百年前，英王约翰与法王有仇，当时曾由国王宣布圣旨，命令武士二人在比武场中交战，以所谓上帝的裁判解决争端。两位国王和西班牙王都亲自到场来看这场战斗，裁判胜负。这时候法国的武士出场了；但是英国武士们一看他勇不可当，都不肯出来和他交手。这件事情是很重大的，看情形对英王颇为不利，大有弃权认输的趋势。当时英国最强的武士柯绥勋爵被囚禁在伦敦塔里，被剥夺了爵位和财产，并且还因长期囚禁，身体也日渐消瘦。这时候有人请他出来应战，他同意了，于是武装起来，准备出场；但是那个法国人一眼看见了他那魁伟的身材，又听说了他的大名，便临阵脱逃，结果法王就输了。约翰王恢复了柯绥的爵位和财产，并且还说，‘你有何愿望尽管说出来，我一定照准，即令要与我平分国土，我也在所不惜。’当时柯绥就像我现在这样跪着，回答说，‘国王，我只请求这一件事情：我希望我和我的后代能在大英国王面前有不脱帽子的特权，从今以后，王位一日存在，这种特权就永不取消。’约翰恩准了他的请求，这陛下是知道的。四百年来，这个家系从来没有断嗣的时候；因此直到如今，这个历史悠久的世家的家长还是在国王陛下面前戴着帽子或是头盔，不受阻挡，别人是一概不许这样做的。[10]现在我援引这个前例来帮助我考虑我的愿望，恳求国王恩准，赐给我一种特权——这就足够奖赏我还有余——此外别无所求；我的愿望是：我和我的后嗣永远可以在大英国王陛下面前坐下！”

“迈尔斯·亨顿爵士，起来吧，我封你为爵士，”国王庄严地说——他用亨顿的剑举行了爵位的授予典礼——“起来坐下吧，你的请愿已经照准了。英国一日存在，王位一日继续，这种特权就一日不取消。”

国王陛下沉思着走开了，亨顿倒在桌子跟前一把椅子上坐下，暗自想道：“这是个绝妙的主意，总算给我解除了一大困难；我这两条腿简直酸得要命了。假如我没有想到这个，我一定得站上几个礼拜，直到我这可怜的孩子的神经病治好了的时候才行。”过了一会儿，他又继续想道，“这么一来，我就在梦想和幻影的王国里成为一名爵士了！对于我这么一个实事求是的人来说，这实在是一个非常稀奇古怪的爵位。我决不笑——千万不能笑，因为这件事情在我心目中虽然是空虚的，他可是觉得真有其事。并且对我说来，也有一方面不能算是假的，因为这件事情实在是反映了他有一种慷慨而美好的情怀。”停了一会儿，他又想，“啊，万一他当着大家叫出我那漂亮的头衔来，那可怎么好！我的荣誉和我的衣服这么不相称，岂不要叫人家笑话！可是那也不要紧，他爱怎么称呼我就怎么称呼吧，我反正是心满意足的。”

第十五章　汤姆当了国王

第二天，各国大使带着派头十足的随从来了，汤姆非常庄严地坐在宝座上接见他们。那个辉煌的场面起初使他看着很感兴趣，并且还使他心花怒放，但是接见的时间太长，又很枯燥，大使们的致辞也多半雷同，因此这件事情开始虽然使他高兴，后来却渐渐地显得令人厌倦，并且还使他想起家来了。汤姆不时把赫德福教给他的话说一遍，极力要做得令人满意，但是他对这种事情太生疏了，而且很不自在，所以只能做到勉强过得去的地步。他看上去十足地像个国王，心里却不大能有个国王的感觉。后来这个仪式结束的时候，他才觉得满心高兴。

他把一天的大部分时间“浪费”了，干的都是他作为国王分内的苦事——这是他内心的想法。就连专门供国王消遣和娱乐的两个钟头，对于他也成了一种负担而没有丝毫趣味，因为那些游戏都有许多限制和礼节上的规矩，使他受到束缚。但是他和他的代鞭童单独待了一个钟头，这可是他认为绝对有利的事情，因为他一方面得到了娱乐，同时又获得了急需的信息，真是一举两得。

汤姆·康第当国王的第三天的经过和头两天大体相同，但是他总算有一方面轻松了一些——他不像起初那样不自在了；他渐渐习惯于他的遭遇和环境；他身上的锁链仍旧磨得他发痛，但并不总是那样；一个钟头又一个钟头在他头上飞过去，他也觉得那些大人物在他面前对他那么恭敬，越来越不使他感到痛苦和狼狈了。

假如不是有一件事情使他提心吊胆，他看到第四天快到的时候，就不会十分着急了——那件事情就是当众用餐，这是要从那一天开始的。日程里还有些更重大的事情——那天他还要临朝主持一次会议，大臣们将要在会上听取他的意见和命令，决定他对全世界远近各国打算采取的政策；赫德福还要在那一天正式被选为摄政大臣；另外，还规定了要在那一天解决一些别的重要事情，但是在汤姆看来，这些事情都比叫他当众用餐还要轻松一点；他觉得自己一个人吃饭，却有无数双好奇的眼睛盯住他，无数张嘴悄悄地评论他的举动——假如他运气不好，犯了错误，也要受人议论，这实在是顶受罪的事情了。

然而那第四天是无法阻拦的，它终于来到了。

那一天，汤姆无精打采，心神恍惚；这种情绪持续着，他简直摆脱不了。上午的一般公事在他手头迟缓地挨过去，使他感到厌倦。于是，他又觉得那种坐牢似的心情沉重地侵袭着他。

下午较晚的时候，他在一个宽大的朝见室里和赫德福伯爵谈话，正式等待着许多重要官员和大臣在预定的时间前来拜见。

后来汤姆随便走到一个窗户跟前，对王宫大门外面的大马路上熙熙攘攘的情景很感兴趣——他并非无聊而感到有意思，而是满心渴望着亲自去参与那种热闹和自由的生活——过了一会儿，他看见一大群乱嚷乱叫的、乌七八糟的、最穷和最下等的男男女女和孩子前面领头的一些人，从大路上走过来。

“我真想知道这是怎么回事啊！”他带着一个孩子对那种情景的好奇心，大声说道。

“您是国王！”伯爵毕恭毕敬，庄重地说，“陛下是否可以让我执行命令？”

“啊，好极了，照办吧！啊，我很高兴，照办吧！”汤姆兴奋地大声说道，随即又心满意足，自言自语地说，“真是，当个国王并不完全是枯燥无味的——这种生活也有它的回报和好处。”

伯爵叫了一个小侍来，派他到警卫队长那儿去传达命令：

“挡住那一群人，问清楚他们为什么那么热闹。这是国王的命令！”

过了几秒钟，就有一长排皇家卫队穿着亮晃晃的钢制盔甲，从大门里出去，在那一大群人前面拦住了马路。一个报信的差使回来了，他报告说那一群人是跟着去看一个男人、一个女人和一个年轻的姑娘被处死刑，他们犯的罪是扰乱治安和破坏王国的尊严。

给这些可怜的无辜百姓处以死刑——而且还是惨死呀！这个念头使汤姆大动恻隐之心。同情心支配着他，使他对其他一切都顾不到了；他根本没有想到这几个犯人所触犯的法律，也没有想到他们给予受害者的苦痛或损失，他除了绞刑架和悬在被判死刑的犯人头上的悲惨命运以外，什么也想不到。他的关切甚至使他暂时忘记了自己不过是一个国王的替身，而不是真正的国王；他还没有想到这一点，就冲口而出地发了一个命令：

“把他们带到这里来！”

随后他满脸涨得通红，一句类似道歉的话几乎到了嘴边；但是他一看他的命令都没有引起伯爵和侍童什么惊讶，他就把正待说出的话咽了下去。侍童以理应遵命的态度，深深地鞠了一躬，就向后退出这个房间，传达命令去了。汤姆感觉到一阵强烈的自豪感，重新体会到做国王的苦痛换来的好处。他心里想：“从前我看老神父那些故事书的时候，我就想象着自己是个君王，对所有的人发号施令，说‘你去干这个，你去干那个’，谁也不敢违抗我的旨意。现在，我果然有那种感觉了。”

这时候有几扇门打开了，有人通报了一个又一个响亮的头衔，跟着就是具有这些头衔的人物进来了，于是这地方很快就被高贵人物和华丽衣裳挤满了一半。但是，汤姆对于这些人的到场像是没有感觉到似的，因为他的心思完全在其他更有趣的事情上。他心不在焉地坐在宝座上，转过眼睛去望着门口，表现出迫不及待的神情。大臣们一看这种情形，就极力不打搅他，大家杂七杂八地交谈起来，既谈国家大事，又谈宫廷闲话。

稍过了一会儿，就听见一些军人整齐的步伐声越来越近，犯人们在一个副执法官的看管之下，由一小队国王的卫队监管着，来到国王面前。那位文官向汤姆跪拜了一下，然后站在旁边；那三个死囚也跪下来，一直跪着不动；卫队在汤姆的椅子背后站定了。汤姆好奇地把那几个犯人仔细打量了一番。那个男人的衣服和外表似乎并不陌生，这在他心中唤起了一种模糊的回忆。“我好像觉得从前看见过这个人……可是想不起来是什么时候和什么地方了。”——汤姆这样想着。正在这时候，那个人迅速地抬头望了一眼，又迅速地低下头去，因为他没有胆量正视国王那种威仪，但是已经足够汤姆看清楚他的整张脸了。他心里想：“现在事情已经很分明了；这就是在刮着大风、冷得要命的新年第一天把查尔斯·威特从泰晤士河里打捞出来，救了他一命的那个陌生人——那是个勇敢和好心的行为——可惜他又干了坏事，把自己卷进这起不幸的案子中……我还没有忘记那个日子，连时间都还记得；这是因为过了一个钟头以后，正打十一点的时候，我让奶奶狠狠地揍了一顿，这一顿打得特别厉害，所以在那以前或是在那以后发生的事情和这顿毒打比较起来，就好像慈母的抚爱和拥抱似的。”

于是汤姆就下令把那个妇人和姑娘暂时从他面前带出去一会儿，然后他就对那副执法官说：

“请问你，这个人犯了什么罪？”

那位小官跪下来回答说：

“禀告陛下，他用毒药毒死了一个人。”

汤姆对这个犯人本来是深表同情的，对他救出那个快淹死的孩子的英勇行为也非常敬佩，现在他这种心情却受到了极沉重的打击。

“这件事情已经证实是他干的了吗？”他问道。

“非常清楚，陛下。”

汤姆叹了一口气，说：

“把他带走——他是罪有应得的。真可惜，他是个勇敢的好汉哩——不——不，我是说他看起来很勇敢。”

犯人突然使劲把双手交叉起来，绝望地拧着，同时用一些断断续续的、满含恐惧的话向“国王”哀求：

“啊，国王陛下，您要是能可怜可怜遭难的人，那就请您可怜可怜我吧！我是没有罪的——他们给我加的罪名也是证据不足的——可是我要说的不是那个；给我判处死刑已经定了，那也许不能更改；可是我在绝路上还要请求一个恩典，因为我的死法实在是叫我受不了。开恩吧，开恩吧，国王陛下！请陛下大发慈悲，恩准我的请求吧——请您发个圣旨，给我处绞刑吧！”

汤姆吃了一惊，他想要的结果不是这样。

“哎呀，我的天哪，这真是个稀奇的请求！他们给你判的死刑不是这样吗？”

“啊，善心的陛下，不是这样！他们判决把我活活地煮死！”

这话简直把人吓得要命，几乎使汤姆从椅子上跳起来了。他刚一清醒过来，马上就大声喊道：

“你可以如愿，可怜的人！即令你毒死了一百个人，也不应该让你死得那么惨。”

犯人磕下头去，把脸都碰到地上了，他热情地说了一大堆感激的话——末尾是这么一句：

“万一您将来遭到不幸——那当然是天不许的事情！但愿人家记得您今天对我的恩典，报答您的好心！”

汤姆转过脸去，向赫德福伯爵说：

“伯爵，给这个人判这么残酷的刑罚，难道能叫人相信那是有法律根据的吗？”

“陛下，照法律规定，惩治放毒犯是用这种刑罚。德国惩治造假钱的犯人，是把他们下油锅炸死——还不是一下就丢进去，而是把他们用绳子拴着，慢慢地往下放，先炸脚，再炸腿，再——”

“啊，伯爵，请你不要再说下去，我受不了！”汤姆喊道，双手把眼睛蒙起来，不去想那场景。“我请你赶快下个命令，修改这条法律——啊，千万不要再让可怜的老百姓受这种活罪吧。”

伯爵脸上显出极度的喜悦，因为他也是个心地慈悲和宽大的人——在那残暴的时代，他那个阶级里的人有这种好心肠，真是少见。他说：

“陛下这句高贵的话从此把这种刑罚禁止了。这件事将要名垂青史，永远是您皇家的光荣。”

副执法官正想把他的犯人带走，汤姆做了个手势，叫他等一等，然后说：

“我还要把这件事情问问清楚。这个人刚才说过他的罪行证据不足。你把你所知道的告诉我吧。”

“敬禀国王，审案的时候，问明了这个人走进了艾林顿小村里一户人家，那里躺着一个病人——有三个见证人说那是在上午正十点钟，有两个说还要迟几分钟——当时只有病人在家，并且还睡着了——这个人刚进去又出来，跟着就走掉了。他走了之后，病人连抽筋带呕吐，简直痛得要命，还不到一个钟头就死了。”

“有谁看见他下毒吗？发现了毒药没有？”

“啊，没有，陛下。”

“那么怎么会知道有人下了毒呢？”

“敬禀陛下，医生证明除非中了毒，否则病人临死的时候绝不会有那种症状。”

这就是有力的证据——在那个简单的时代。汤姆看出了这个证据的重要性，就说：

“医生是内行的——也许他们对了。这事情对这个可怜的人似乎是不利的。”

“但是还不止这个，陛下，另外还有更厉害的证据哩。有许多人证明有个巫婆曾经预言过这个病人会被人毒死，现在那巫婆早已离开那个村子，谁也不知道她上什么地方去了；她是私下对着他们的耳朵小声说的——她还说下毒的是个陌生人——一个棕色头发的、穿着一身破烂的普通衣服的陌生人；当然这个犯人和捉人的通告上说的是完全相符的。陛下，这个事情既然是有巫婆预言过的，当然就非常可靠，请您承认这是个有力的证据吧。”

在那迷信的时代，这是个非常有力的理由。汤姆觉得这桩事情是确定了；如果重视证据的话，这个可怜人的罪状就算是证实了。但是他还是给了犯人一个机会，他说：

“如果你有什么能替自己辩护的话，你就快说吧。”

“我说不出什么有用的话，陛下。我是没有罪的，可是我无法证明。我没有朋友，否则我可以证明那天我根本就不在艾林顿；并且我还可以证明他们所说的那个时候，我离那儿有三英里远，因为我在华宾老码头那儿；噢，还有呢，国王，我还可以证明，他们说我要人家的命的时候，我可正在给人救命呀。有一个孩子在河里快淹死了——”

“不要说了！执法官，你快说那是哪一天的事情！”

“那是新年第一天，上午十点钟，或是稍迟几分钟，那时候……”

“把犯人释放了吧——这是国王的旨意！”

他这句不合国王身份的感情用事的话又使他脸红了，于是他极力掩饰他这个失礼的举动，补充了一句：

“只凭这种靠不住的、粗枝大叶的证据，就把一个人处以绞刑，真是使我生气！”

一阵表示敬佩的低沉的议论声在现场的人群中迅速地传开了。那并不是敬佩汤姆所宣布的命令，因为他赦免了一个定了罪的放毒犯，在场的人没有几个会觉得应该承认那是恰当的，也不会有人敬佩他这种举动——不，大家所敬佩的是汤姆表现出的智慧和精神。有些低声的议论是这样的：

“这并不是个疯子国王——他的脑袋是清醒的。”

“他那些问题问得多么聪明——他这样突然采取果断的手段处置了这件事情，跟他本来的天性多么像呀！”

“谢天谢地，他的神经病已经好了！这不是个小糊涂蛋，而是个真正的国王，他简直像他的父亲一样有气魄。”

空气中充满了赞扬的声音，汤姆耳朵里当然就听到了一些。这对他所起的作用是使他大大地安心了，同时也使他周身充满了欢悦的感觉。

但是他那年轻的好奇心不久就压过了这些愉快的念头和情绪，他急切地想要知道那个妇人和那个姑娘究竟是遭了什么致命的大祸。于是他发出命令，把那两个吓得要命的、哭哭啼啼的可怜虫带到他面前来。

“她们两个犯了什么罪？”他问执法官。

“敬禀陛下，有人告发她们犯了邪恶的大罪，并且清清楚楚地证实了，因此法官就按照法律判处她们绞刑。她们把灵魂出卖给魔鬼了——这就是她们的罪状。”

汤姆打了个冷战。人家曾经教过他，要憎恨犯这种罪的人。但是虽然如此，他还是不打算放弃这个机会，偏要获得那满足好奇心的愉快，于是他问道：

“她们是在什么地方干的这件事情？什么时候干的？”

“十二月有一天半夜里——在一所破教堂里干的，陛下。”

汤姆又打了个冷战。

“有谁在场？”

“只有她们两个，陛下，另外还有‘那一个’。”

“她们承认了吗？”

“没有，她们没有承认，陛下，她们是否认的。”

“那么，请问是怎么知道的？”

“有几个见证人看见她们上那儿去，陛下，这就引起了怀疑，后来又有些确凿的事实证明了这种怀疑是不错的。特别重要的是，她们利用这么得来的魔力，引起了一场暴风雨，结果把邻近一带完全毁坏了。有四十多个见证人证明了有这场风暴；其实要找一千个见证人也没有问题，因为大家都吃了这场暴风雨的亏，当然都不会不记得。”

“这实在是一桩严重的事情。”汤姆把这个邪恶的罪行在心里反复地想了一会儿，然后问道：

“这个女人也遭了这场暴风雨的灾吗？”

在场的人当中有几位老人点了点头，表示他们承认这个问题问得很聪明。但是执法官没有看出这一问有什么重大的意义，他直截了当地回答道：

“她当然受了灾，陛下，这是她应得的报应，大家都这么说。她住的房子被大风刮跑了，她自己和她的孩子都无家可归。”

“她运用魔力给自己带来了这么大的灾难，我看她这种魔力可真是花了不小的代价换来的。即令她只花了一个铜板，那也是受骗了；可是她居然把她的灵魂和她的孩子的灵魂当作代价，这就足见她是疯了。她既然是疯了，也就不知道自己所干的事情，所以也就不算犯罪了。”

那些年长的人又一次点头，称赞汤姆的聪明。有一个人低声地说：“如果像谣言所说的，国王自己是个疯子，那么我所知道的某些人要是能凭上帝的神意，染上他这种疯病，倒反而可以使他们的脑袋更清楚一点儿哩。”

“这孩子多大年纪？”汤姆问道。

“九岁，敬禀陛下。”

“请问你，法官，按照英国法律，儿童也可以跟人家订约，出卖自己吗？”汤姆转过脸去，问一位有学问的法官。

“陛下，法律不许儿童决定或是参与重大事情，因为他们的头脑太幼稚，还不能应付大人的智力和阴谋。魔鬼如果情愿的话，他可以买一个孩子，孩子也可以同意，但是英国人可不行——只要是英国人，他们的契约就视作无效。”

“英国法律剥夺英国人的特权，反倒让魔鬼有这种自由，这似乎是一件很粗鲁的、不合基督教精神的事情，制定这条法律是欠考虑的！”汤姆认真而激动地大声说道。

他对这件事情的新奇见解引起了许多人的微笑，并且有许多人把它记在脑子里，预备在宫廷里到处转述，证明汤姆不但在心理健康方面有进步，而且还有创见。

那个年长的犯人已经停止哭泣了，她怀着兴奋的心情和逐渐增加的希望，聚精会神地倾听着汤姆的话。汤姆看出了这种情形，这使他的同情心强烈地倾向于这个在危难和无亲无友的处境中的女人。随后他说：

“她们是怎么掀起暴风雨的？”

“陛下，她们用脱下袜子的办法。”

这使汤姆吃了一惊，同时也把他的好奇心燃烧到了狂热的程度。他急切地说：

“这真是奇怪！她们这种做法，随时都有这么可怕的效果吗？”

“随时都有的，陛下——至少是只要这个女人有这种愿望，并且还念些必要的咒语，无论是在心里或是在嘴里念都行。”

汤姆向那女人转过脸去，迫不及待地说：

“施展你的魔法吧——我愿意看见一场暴风雨！”

在场的那些迷信的人忽然都脸色惨白起来，大家都想走出这个地方，只是没有流露出来——汤姆对这一切都不在意，因为除了他所要求的那一场灾变以外，无论什么事情都不能引起他的注意。他看见那女人脸上显出一种为难和诧异的神情，就很兴奋地补充了两句：

“不用害怕——决不会怪你。不但如此——我还要释放你——谁也不许动你一下。施展你的魔法吧。”

“啊，陛下，我并没有什么魔法——我是被人冤枉了。”

“你的恐惧心理使你不敢做。尽管大胆做吧，决不会叫你吃亏。你造成一场暴风雨吧——哪怕是顶小的一场也不要紧——我并不需要大暴风雨，也不需要有害的，我的愿望恰好相反——你只要这么做，我就饶了你的命——一定放你出去，还让你带着孩子，这是国王的特赦，你在全国都不会受任何人的伤害和欺负。”

那妇人扑倒在地，流着泪发誓说，她实在没有创造这个奇迹的魔力，否则既然服从国王这个命令，就可以得到这么大的恩典，她单只为了救她的孩子的命也心甘情愿，自己还愿意牺牲哩。

汤姆又催促了一阵——那妇人仍旧坚持她的申辩。最后他就说：

“我想这个女人说的是真话。假如我的母亲处在她的位置，也有魔鬼的本领，那她一定片刻都不迟疑，马上唤起暴风雨，把全国都毁得一塌糊涂——只要她施展魔法，就可以挽救我被判死刑的命，她一定会那么干！足见所有的母亲天生是一样的心肠。现在你免罪了，太太——你和你的孩子都没有事了——因为我觉得你们是无罪的。现在你既然被赦免，再没有什么可怕的了——你把袜子脱掉吧！——你要是能给我掀起一场暴风雨，我就让你发财！”

那得救的可怜人有说不尽的感激，于是她开始遵命行事；汤姆以迫切而期待的眼光望着，多少还有几分提心吊胆；同时大臣们都表现出明显的焦虑和不安。那妇人把自己的袜子脱掉了，还脱掉了她的小女孩的袜子，她显然尽了全力要引起一次地震来报答国王的恩典，但是结果完全失败，使人大失所望。汤姆叹了一口气说：

“算了吧，好人，你不必再费劲了，你的魔力已经跑掉了。你放心走吧；随便什么时候，你如果恢复了你的魔力，那可不要忘记我，千万要来给我掀起一场暴风雨呀。”

第十六章　御餐

御餐的时刻渐近了——但是奇怪得很，这个念头并没有引起汤姆多大的不安，恐惧的心理更是几乎没有。那天上午的经验已经大大地建立了他的信心；这个可怜的小家伙经过四天的习惯之后，已经对他这个新奇的安身之所很熟悉了。比一个成年人过了整整一个月还要熟悉哩。小孩子适应环境的本领，没有比这个表现得更出色的了。

现在让我们这些享有特权的人赶快到大宴会厅去，看看那儿的人替汤姆安排一切，让他进行这次排场十足的御餐的情况吧。那是个宽大的房间，大柱和墙柱都是涂着金漆的，墙上和天花板上都绘着图画。门口站着高大的卫士，站得笔挺，像雕像一般；他们都穿着富丽而鲜艳的服装，拿着长柄的戟。宴会厅的周围有一道高高的回廊，那上面有一个乐队，还拥挤着许多男男女女，他们都穿着光彩夺目的衣裳。在那个房间当中的一个高台子上，摆着汤姆的餐桌。现在让古代的史官来叙述吧：

“一位侍臣拿着权杖走进屋里来，和他同来的另外一位拿着台布；他们两人非常恭敬地跪拜了三次之后，拿台布的侍臣就把它铺在餐桌上，然后他们又跪拜了一次，才一同退出；随后又进来了两个侍臣，一个还是拿着权杖，另外那一个拿着一只盐瓶子、一只碟子，还有面包，他们像先来的那两个人一样跪拜之后，再把带来的东西放在桌子上，又行过先来的人所行的礼才出去；最后来了两位衣冠华丽的贵族，其中一个拿着一把试味刀，这两个人以极度感恩的态度跪拜一番之后，走到桌子跟前，用面包和盐把桌子擦了一遍，他们都显出万分敬畏的神情，仿佛国王在场一般。”[13]

庄严的准备工作就此结束了。这时候，我们听见那发着回声的长廊里远远地传来一阵吹号的声音，还有一阵模糊的喊声：“给国王让路！快给最圣明的国王陛下让路！”这些声音时时刻刻都被重复着，而且越来越近了，后来军号的声音几乎就在我们面前响起来，同时还有响亮的喊声：“给国王让路！”这时候光彩夺目的队伍出现了，大家排着队，用整齐的步伐从门口走进去。现在再让史官来叙述吧：

“前面走着的是些侍从、男爵、伯爵、嘉德勋章爵士，都是穿得很讲究、没戴帽子的；其次是大法官，他左右有两个侍从，一个拿着国王的节杖，另一个拿着一把装在红鞘里的御剑，鞘上镶着金色的百合花纹，剑梢向上；后面来的是国王本人——他一出现，就有十二支号和许多鼓一齐响起来致敬，表示热烈的欢迎，同时长廊里的人们都在原位起立欢呼，‘上帝保佑国王！’他后面跟着随侍的贵族，左右有他的御前警卫，就是他那五十名侍从卫士，都拿着金色的战斧。”

这一切都是辉煌耀眼、喜气洋洋的。汤姆的脉搏急促起来，眼睛里闪着快乐的光芒。他的举止表现得相当优雅，尤其是因为他并没有想着自己在怎样装模作样，所以就更加自然，因为他这时候看见周围那些赏心悦目的情景，听见那些悦耳的声音，就感到心旷神怡，别的事全不觉得了——并且无论是谁，穿着那种非常合身的美丽衣裳，既然已经有些习惯了，自然就不会显得怎样难看——尤其是当他暂时没有把这个放在心上的时候。汤姆记得他所受过的教导，把他那顶着翎毛的头微微点了一下，表示答谢敬礼，并且还亲切地说了一声：“谢谢你们，善良的臣民。”

他在餐桌前面坐下，并没有脱去帽子；他这么做的时候，丝毫也不慌张，因为戴着帽子吃饭是王室和康第家里的人唯一一致具有的习惯，以他们对这种习惯的熟习程度而论，这两家原是不相上下的。随侍御驾的人分开了，他们很美观地排列成几组，仍然没戴帽子地站着。

这时候随着悦耳的音乐声，御前侍卫们进来了——“他们是全英国身材最高和最有力气的勇士，本来就是根据这个标准选拔出来的。”——但是我们还是让史官叙述吧：

“御前侍卫们进来了，他们都没戴帽子，穿着大红制服，背上绣着金色的玫瑰花；这些人来回地走着，每一次都端进一份用盘子盛着的菜肴。这些菜肴由一位侍从接过来，他还是照那些人递菜的仪式把一份一份的菜接到手上，放在餐桌上，同时试食官把他所端来的每一道菜分一口给每个卫士尝试，以防有毒。”

汤姆痛痛快快地吃了一顿，不过他老是感觉有成百上千的眼睛望着他把每一口食物送到嘴里，盯着他吃下肚去；即令他吃的东西是一种致命的炸药，足以把他炸得血肉横飞，那也不能引起他们更深切的兴趣吧。他特别注意到要不慌不忙，也同样注意到什么事都不亲自动手，等着那专职的官员跪下来替他做。他一直把这顿饭吃完，总算没有犯什么错误——这是一次完美无瑕的、了不起的成功。

最后御餐完毕，他由那欢快的侍从队列陪伴着走出去的时候，耳朵里充满了响亮的号声、隆隆的鼓声和震耳的欢呼声。于是他觉得他虽然可以说是渡过了当众用饭的难关，但是如果让他受这种考验，就可以使他摆脱国王分内的其他某些更为难的苦事，那就即令叫他每天吃几次这样的苦头，他也是心甘情愿的。

第十七章　疯子一世

迈尔斯·亨顿连忙往伦敦桥靠南市那一头走，一面睁着大眼睛搜寻他所寻找的那几个人，盼望着很快就能赶上他们。但是结果让他大失所望。他东问西问，总算有人指点他在南市跟踪了一段路程，后来就完全找不着踪影了，他简直不知如何是好。但是他在那一天还是拼命地找，一直找到天黑。到了黄昏的时候，他的腿都跑酸了，肚子也饿得要命，而他的愿望仍旧是一场空；于是他在特巴客栈吃了晚饭，就去睡觉，决定第二天清早就动身，再到全城各处去彻底搜寻一番。他躺在床上一面寻思一面盘算的时候，随即就开始这么推想：只要有机会，那孩子一定会从他那真假不明的父亲手里逃掉；他会不会回到伦敦去，找他原来住过的地方呢？不，他不会那么办，他要避免再被人抓住。那么，他究竟会怎么办呢？他从来就没有一个朋友，也没有人保护他，直到后来遇到迈尔斯·亨顿，才算是有了救星，所以他只要是无须冒着危险，再到伦敦去，他当然就会要设法再把这个朋友找到；他会往亨顿府去，那才是他所要采取的办法，因为他知道亨顿正在回家去，他到那儿去也许能把他找到。对，亨顿觉得这件事情有把握了——他决不应该再在南市耽搁工夫，必须立刻穿过肯特郡，向僧人洲前进，一路在森林中搜寻，还要找人探询。现在我们再回来谈谈那失踪的小国王吧。

客栈里的茶房在伦敦桥上看见那个流氓“快要”跟那个年轻人和国王走到一起，但是事实上他并没有当真跟他们走到一起；他只是紧跟在他们后面走。他什么话也没有说，他的左胳臂用挂带吊着，左眼上戴着一块绿色的大眼罩；他稍微有点儿瘸，拄着一根橡木的拐杖。那个年轻人领着国王穿过南市，走了一段曲折的路，不久就走到郊外的大路上了。这时候国王生气了，他说他要在这儿停住——亨顿应该到这儿来见他，不应该让他去找。这样傲慢无礼，他实在受不了，所以他就要在他所在的地方停住。那年轻人说：

“你打算在这儿待着，难道就让你受了伤的朋友躺在那边的树林里不管吗？那也好，随你的便吧。”

国王的态度立刻就改变了。他大声问道：

“受伤了？是谁胆敢把他打伤？不过现在先不管这个吧；再领着我往前走吧，往前走吧！快点儿，小子！你脚上拴着铅锤吗？他受伤了，是不是？哼，即使是一个公爵的儿子干的，我也决不饶他！”

那儿离树林还有一段相当的距离，但是很快就走完了。那年轻人向四周张望了一下，发现地上插着的一根树枝，那上面还拴着一小块碎布片，随后他就引着路走进树林里去，还随时寻找类似的树枝，过一会儿就会发现一根；这些树枝显然是些带路的标志，把他引到他所要去的地方。后来他们终于走到了一片空旷的地方，那儿有一座烧焦了的农庄的遗址，附近还有一个日渐倒塌和衰败的谷仓。四下里毫无生人的踪影，绝对的寂静笼罩着一切。那年轻人走进谷仓里去，国王急切地在后面紧跟着。那儿什么人也没有！国王用惊讶和怀疑的眼光向那年轻人瞥了一下，问道：

“他在什么地方？”

那年轻人的回答只是表示嘲弄的一声大笑。国王马上就大发脾气，他拿起一块木头，正要往那年轻人身上打过去，忽然又听见另外一声嘲弄的大笑。这是那个流氓发出来的，他一直都在远远地跟着。国王转过身去，很生气地说：

“你是谁？你到这里来干什么？”

“别装糊涂了吧，”那个人说，“安静点儿，我的装化得并不算好，你总不能假装认不出你的父亲了吧。”

“你不是我的父亲，我不认识你。我是国王。你如果把我的仆人藏起来了，就给我去把他找来，否则你干了坏事，我一定要叫你吃苦头的。”

约翰·康第用严厉而稳重的声调回答说：

“你分明是疯了，我也不愿意处罚你；可是你要是惹我生气，我就非收拾你不可。你在这儿胡说八道还不要紧，反正没有人听你这些傻话，可是你这张嘴还是要当心才行，不许乱说，免得我们搬了地方之后，惹出是非来。我犯了杀人案，在家里待不下去了——你也不能再待在家里，因为我得要你帮忙才行。我已经改了姓，这是个聪明的办法，改成了霍布斯——约翰·霍布斯，你叫作贾克——千万要记住。好，你快说吧。你母亲在哪儿？你姐姐她们在哪儿？她们都没有上约定的地方来——你知道她们上哪儿去了吗？”

国王绷着脸回答说：

“你不要说这些莫名其妙的话让我伤脑筋吧。我的母亲已经死了，我姐姐她们都在王宫里。”

站在附近的那个年轻人爆发出一阵嘲弄的大笑，国王想要向他扑过去，可是康第——照他自称的姓，就是霍布斯——把他挡住，一面说：

“别笑了，雨果，你别惹他吧。他的神经错乱了，你对他这种态度叫他心烦。你坐下吧，贾克，安静点儿，我还要给你点儿东西吃哩。”

霍布斯和雨果低声交谈起来，国王尽可能远离这两个讨厌的家伙。他躲到谷仓另外一头的阴暗处，发现那儿的土地上铺了一英尺厚的稻草。他就在那上面躺下，扯了一些草盖在身上，代替毯子，随即就专心致志地沉思起来了。他有许多伤心事，但是那些较小的痛苦几乎被忘记了，淹没于最主要的一件伤心事——那就是，他失去了父亲。在世界上其他人的心目中，亨利八世的名字是使人战栗的，它使人联想到一个吃人的恶魔，鼻孔里喷出杀人的毒气，手里干的事无非是给人以灾难和死亡；但是对于这个孩子，他的名字带来的只有愉快的感觉，它所唤起的形象满脸都是温柔和慈爱的神色。他心里回想起他的父亲和他自己之间一连串相亲相爱的往事，很亲切地仔细回味着，他那畅流的眼泪证明他心头萦绕着的悲伤是多么深厚和真切。那天下午渐渐过去的时候，这孩子终于因悲哀而困倦，渐渐地转入宁静而舒适的酣睡了。

过了一段相当长的时间之后——他也说不清是多久了——他的意识勉强挣扎着达到一种半醒状态，于是他闭着眼睛躺着，恍恍惚惚地寻思着他究竟是在什么地方，刚才发生过一些什么事情。这时候他听到了一阵低沉的响声，那就是雨点打在屋顶上的凄凉的声音。他感到一种舒适的滋味浸透全身，但是这种感觉马上又被一阵尖声的嬉笑和粗声的哄笑混合起来的声音打断了。这阵笑声很讨厌地把他惊醒了，于是他把头上盖的稻草揭开了，看看这种扰人的声音是从哪儿来的。一幅可怕和难看的情景映入他的眼帘。谷仓的另一头有一堆熊熊的火正在地面中间燃烧着；火的周围有一群乱七八糟、男女混杂的、衣衫褴褛的流浪汉和歹徒，东歪西倒的和趴在地上的都有；通红的火光把他们照得怪可怕的；这些角色，他在书里和梦中都从来没有见过。他们当中有身材高大、体格壮健的男人，皮肤因风吹日晒而黑黄，披着长头发，穿着稀奇古怪的破烂衣服；也有中等身材、相貌野蛮的青年，穿着相似的衣裳；还有瞎眼的乞丐，眼睛上戴着眼罩，或是扎着绷带；还有瘸腿的，装着木腿或是拄着丁字杖；还有一个相貌凶恶的小贩，带着他贩卖的一包东西；此外还有一个磨刀匠，一个补锅匠，一个剃头匠兼外科医生，各人带着本行的行头；女人当中有一些是还没有完全长大的姑娘，有一些正在青春时期，还有一些是年老的、满脸皱纹的母夜叉，她们个个都是嗓门很大、脸皮很厚、满嘴说下流话的家伙，个个都满身油泥、邋遢不堪；另外还有三个脸上生疮的小娃娃；还有两条饿得很瘦的贱狗，脖子上套着绳子，它们是给瞎子引路的。

黑夜来到了，那一伙人刚刚饱餐完毕，开始狂欢作乐，大家把酒罐子递来递去，喝个不停。大家一齐呼喊：

“唱个歌！蝙蝠和木腿阿三唱个歌吧！”

几个瞎子当中有一个站起来，揭掉他那双好极了的眼睛上蒙着的眼罩，丢开那张写着他的苦难的纸牌子，准备唱歌。木腿阿三把他那条累赘的木腿取下来，用他那条健全的真腿在他那位坏蛋同伴身边站着。然后他们就扯开嗓子唱了一首嘻嘻哈哈的小调，每唱到一节末了的时候，就由全体伙伴齐声欢呼地和唱着。后来唱到了最后一节，大家那种半醉的热情就达到了顶点，于是人人都跟着一起唱，一直从头唱到末尾，那邪恶的高唱声把屋梁都震动了。那一段动人的歌词是这样的：

“再见吧，我们的窝，

不要忘记，遥远的路在我们面前；

再见吧，土地，等待我们的

是树上的领结和不醒的长眠。

我们将在夜里打秋千，

在空中摇摇晃晃；

留下我们那些破旧东西，

冤家将要拿去分赃。”[14]

随后大家就开始谈话，他们并不是用歌词那样的贼帮黑话来谈，他们只有在担心让外人听见的时候，才用黑话交谈。他们在谈话中透出了消息，原来“约翰·霍布斯”根本就不是一个刚入伙的生手，而是曾经一度在这一帮里受过训练的角色。大家叫他讲一讲近来的经历，当他说到“偶然”打死了一个人的时候，大家都表示颇为满意；随后他又说明那个人是个神父，于是他就受到全体的喝彩，并且还不得不陪每个人喝一杯酒。老伙计们兴高采烈地欢迎他，新交的朋友们也以能和他握手为荣。人家问他为什么一去那么几个月不回来，他回答说：

“伦敦比乡下好，并且近来这几年还比乡下安全些，因为法律太严厉，而且执行起来又很认真。要不是因为出了那桩事情，我还会在那儿待下去。我本来已经打定了主意要住在伦敦，一辈子也不打算再到乡下来了——可是后来出了这个案子，一切都完了。”

他问现在帮里有多少人。名叫“帮头”的贼帮首领回答说：

“二十五位结结实实的溜门子的、二仙传道的、溜兜儿的、追孙儿的、讨百家饭的，连那些追孙儿的丫头和婆娘还有别的娘儿们都算在内。[15]一多半都在这儿，其余的往东边走，打冬天的起发[16]去了。咱们等天亮就跟上去。”

“我在这儿看见众位老实的弟兄姐妹，可是没有肉疙瘩。他到哪儿去了？”

“可怜的小伙子，他现在啃硫黄去了，对于口味清淡的人来说，实在是太辣了。他今年夏天不知在什么地方跟人家吵架，让人家打死了。”

“这真叫我听了伤心，肉疙瘩是个能干的人，也挺有胆量哩。”

“他就是这样，真的。他的姑娘黑贝西还跟我们在一起，可是她现在不在这儿，跟他们往东去了；她是个好姑娘，态度挺不错，举止也挺温和，从来没有谁看见她常常喝醉，一个礼拜里顶多也不过有四天吧。”

“她向来是挺守规矩的——我还记得很清楚——真是个标致姑娘，很值得夸奖。她母亲比她随便些，没什么特别的，就是个爱吵架的、脾气臭的刁婆娘，可是天生有些鬼聪明，比一般女人强。”

“就因为这个，她把命都送掉了。她因为会相掌，还有些别的算命的本事，后来就出了名，人家都管她叫作巫婆。官家把她抓去，在慢火上把她活活地烤死了。我看见她临死的时候那股勇敢劲儿，实在是感动得很，心里真有些难受——火焰直往上升，烧到她脸上，把她那挺稀的头发都烧着了，围着她那灰白的头烧得噼噼啪啪地响，可是她老是咒她周围张嘴瞪眼看热闹的那些人，冲他们破口大骂——我是说咒骂他们吗？——对，咒骂他们！嘿，你哪怕活上一千岁，也听不见骂得那么在行的。哎，从她死后，她这门本事就绝种了。现在还有些模仿她的，可是都小里小气，太没劲儿，算不上真正的骂功。”

帮头叹了口气，听的人也同情地叹息，一种普遍的沮丧情绪暂时降临这一伙人身上，因为连这些硬心肠的流浪者的感情也并没有完全麻木，他们偶然在特别适当的情况下，就会感觉到一阵昙花一现的哀悼和悲伤——譬如这次，他们惋惜着这样一个既有天才又有素养的角色离开了人间，没有留下后继者的时候，就有这种感触。但是这些哀悼者随后一齐畅饮了一番，很快就把精神恢复过来了。

“咱们的伙伴还有别人遭了殃吗？”霍布斯问道。

“有几个——是呀，特别是新入伙的——譬如那些小庄稼人，他们的地让人家夺掉了，变成了牧羊场，他们就弄得无路可走，只好挨饿。他们到外面讨饭吃，让人家抓来捆在大车后面，从腰带往上都脱得精光，被人拿鞭子抽打，打得皮破血流；然后他们被套上脚枷，又被人拿棍子打，后来他们又当叫花子，又挨鞭子，还让人家割掉一只耳朵；他们第三次又去讨饭吃——可怜的倒霉鬼，他们还有什么别的办法呢？——结果让人家拿烧红的烙铁在脸上烙上记号，卖出去当奴隶；他们逃出来，又让人家抓回去，活活地给绞死。这不过说个大概情形，我也说得挺快。我们这伙里有些人没有这么倒霉。喂，约柯尔、朋斯、霍纪，你们站出来——把你们挂的彩都亮出来看看！”

他们三个就站起来，把他们的破衣服脱掉一部分，露出背来，那上面留下了以前挨打的时候留下的横一道竖一道的鞭痕。他们当中有一个把头发拨开，露出原来有左耳朵的地方；另外有一个露出肩膀上的烙印——是个字母V[17]——和一只残缺不全的耳朵；第三个说：

“我叫约柯尔，以前是种庄稼的，家里的日子本来过得挺好，有亲爱的妻子儿女——现在我的境况和行业都有点儿不同了。老婆和孩子都丢了，也许他们上了天堂，也许到……也许到另外那个地方[18]去了——可是我得谢谢仁慈的上帝，因为他们总算不在英国了！我那好心肠的、无罪的老母亲靠伺候病人赚饭吃；后来有一个病人死了，大夫也不知道是怎么死的，于是人家硬说我母亲是个巫婆，活活地把她烧死；我的孩子们就在旁边看着，哭得要命。哼，英国的法律！——大家都站起来吧，拿起酒杯！——大家一起来，还要欢呼一声！——咱们为这仁慈的英国法律干杯，谢谢它把我母亲从这英国地狱里救出去了！谢谢你们，伙计们，谢谢大家。我到处讨饭，挨家挨户地讨——我和我老婆——还背着挨饿的孩子们——可是饿肚子在英国也算是犯罪——于是他们脱掉我们的衣服，拿鞭子打着我们走过三个城市游街。请你们大家再为这仁慈的英国法律干一杯吧！——因为它的鞭子喝饱了我的玛丽的血，很快就把她从这个地狱里救出去了。她在那儿的烂死岗子里躺下了，谁也不能再伤害她。还有那些孩子呢——法律拿鞭子打着我从这个城市到那个城市游街的时候，他们就饿死了。再喝口酒吧，伙计们——只喝一点儿——为那几个孩子喝一点儿，他们可真是没有碍过谁的事呀。后来我又讨饭——讨点儿残汤剩饭吃，结果就让他们套上脚枷，割掉一只耳朵——瞧，这就是剩下的残根；我又去讨饭，瞧，另外这只耳朵又只剩下这么个残根，让我记着它。可是我还是只好讨饭，后来就让他们卖出去当奴隶——我脸上这块脏地方，我要是洗干净的话，你们就可以看见一个通红的S，这是烙铁给我留下的！奴隶！你们懂得这两个字的意思吧！英国的奴隶呀——这就是你们面前站着的这个人。我从主人那儿逃出来了，我要是让人家逮着的话——哼，咱们英国这个法律定出这么凶的刑罚，真是该遭雷打——我得让人家绞死呀！”

阴沉沉的天空中忽然传来一个爽朗的声音：

“你决不会！——那条法律从今天起就作废了！”

大家都转过头去，看见小国王那古怪有趣的身影急匆匆地走过来；等他在火光中出现，大家看得清清楚楚的时候，就纷纷探询起来：

“这是谁？怎么回事？你是谁呀，小家伙？”

这孩子在大家惊讶和怀疑的眼光之中大大方方地站着，以王室的尊严回答说：

“我是英国的国王爱德华。”

于是大家爆发出一阵疯狂的大笑，这一半是表示嘲笑，一半是表示他们喜欢这个开得很好的玩笑。国王生气了，他严厉地说：

“你们这些无礼的游民，我给你们开这么大的恩典，你们就是这样表示感谢的吗？”

他用愤怒的声音说了一些别的话，还做了一些激动的手势，但是他的话被大家的狂笑声和嘲笑的喊声所淹没了。“约翰·霍布斯”大声嚷了好几次，要叫大家在那一阵喧嚣之中听得见他的话，后来总算达到目的了——他说：

“伙计们，他是我的儿子，是个做大梦的家伙，是个傻瓜，地道的疯子——别理他——他真想着他是国王哪。”

“我的确是国王呀，”爱德华转过脸去对他说，“你迟早有一天会知道，那时候就该你倒霉了。你刚才供出了杀人的罪——那就该处你绞刑。”

“你打算去告我呀！——你？我要是抓着你的话……”

“啧！啧！”魁伟的帮头赶快插嘴，才救了国王。他嘴里帮了忙，一面还伸出拳头，把霍布斯打倒，“你对国王和帮头都不尊敬吗？你要是再在我面前这么无礼，我就要亲手把你绞死。”然后他又对国王陛下说，“孩子，你千万不要吓唬自己的伙伴。你到别处去可得当心你的嘴，别说自己人的坏话。只要你这小疯子高兴当国王的话，那你就当吧，可是你别惹出祸来。你快把刚才说出来的称呼甩开吧——那是犯大逆不道的罪，我们虽然犯了些小小的过错，算是坏人，可是我们当中谁也不会坏到背叛国王呀，我们对国王都是很敬爱、很忠心的。你看我说的是不是真话吧——喂，大家一齐喊：‘大英国王爱德华万岁！’”

“大英国王爱德华万岁！”

响应的呼声从那形形色色的一群人当中像响雷一般发出来，以致那歪歪斜斜的房屋随着这阵喊声震动了。小国王脸上暂时露出了喜色，他微微地点一点头，庄严而简洁地说：

“我谢谢你们，我的善良的臣民。”

这个意外的结果又使大家笑得直不起腰来。等到稍微恢复了几分安静的时候，帮头就一本正经而又带着和善的语调说：

“丢开这一套吧，孩子，这不是个聪明的玩笑，并且还不妥当。你要是非得异想天开地开开心不可，那也不要紧，可是你得改个称呼才行。”

有一个补锅匠尖声地喊着，提出一个建议：

“疯子一世，傻子国的国王！”

这个称号立刻就受到了欢迎，每个人都扯开嗓子响应，大家吼成了一片：

“傻子国国王疯子一世万岁！”跟着又是一阵怪声喊叫和喝倒彩的声音，还有一阵又一阵打雷似的哄笑。

“把他拥过来，给他戴上王冠！”

“给他穿上御袍！”

“给他权杖！”

“请他登宝座！”

这些喊声之外，还有二十来种别的喊声，都齐喊出来了。几乎在这个遭殃的小可怜虫还没有来得及透一口气的时候，他就被那些人拿一只铁皮盆当作王冠给他戴上了，身上也让他们披上了一条破毯子，算是御袍；他们还把他拥到一只木桶上登了宝座，又把补锅匠的焊烙铁塞到他手里，当作权杖。然后大家一齐围着他跪下，发出一阵讥讽的哭诉声和嘲笑的哀求声，同时还用他们那又脏又破的袖子和围裙擦着眼睛：

“善心的国王啊，请您给我们开恩吧！”

“高贵的陛下啊，请您宽待我们这些哀求的可怜虫吧！”

“可怜可怜您的奴隶吧，请国王赐我们一脚，叫我们痛快痛快吧！”

“请您把仁慈的光辉照在我们身上，让我们高兴高兴、温暖温暖吧！”

“请您把御脚在地上踩一踩，给它沾上点福气，好让我们吃吃土也能变得高贵一点儿吧！”

“陛下啊，请您开恩，在我们身上啐口唾沫，让我们的子子孙孙说起您的恩典，永远都为此感到骄傲、快快活活吧！”

但是那幽默的补锅匠表演了那天晚上最精彩的节目，把荣誉都夺去了。他跪下来，假装着亲吻国王的脚，结果被国王愤怒地踢了一下；他挨了这一脚，就到处找人讨一块布片，要贴在他脸上被国王的脚踢过的地方。他说那块地方一定要好好地保护起来，不让龌龊的空气接触，还说他可以到大路上去到处走，揭开来给别人看，每回收一百个先令，准能发财。他的笑话说得非常有趣，因此他就成了那一群肮脏的歹徒当中最受人羡慕的角色了。

羞耻和愤怒的眼泪从那小国王的眼睛里迸出来了，他心里这么想：“假如我让他们受了很深的冤屈，他们对我也不能比这更狠心呀——可是我答应给他们施个恩，一点儿也没有亏待他们——他们可偏要这么以怨报德！”

第十八章　王子与游民一同流浪

那一队游民在黎明时候起来，随即就出发远行。头上是阴沉的天，脚下是泥泞的地，空中有冬季的寒气。这一群人的快乐情绪完全消失了，有的垂头丧气、不声不响，有的烦躁而易怒，谁也不轻松愉快，大家都觉得口渴。

帮头给了雨果一些简单的指示，就把“贾克”交给雨果负责，并且命令约翰·康第和这孩子离开一点儿，不要惹他；他还警告雨果，不许对这孩子过于粗暴。

过了一会儿，天气渐渐晴朗起来，天上的黑云稍微散了一些。那一群人不再哆嗦了，他们的精神也开始好转。他们越来越愉快，后来就开始互相戏弄，并且还侮辱大路上的过往行人。这就表示他们渐渐从苦闷中开朗起来，重新欣赏生活和其中的快乐了。人家碰见他们这帮家伙就让路，对他们那种下流的侮辱都温顺地忍受着，简直不敢回嘴，这就分明表示人家对他们怀着畏惧心理。有时候他们把篱笆上晾着的麻布东西抢走，主人尽管睁眼望着，也不敢提出抗议，反而好像因为他们没有连篱笆一起拿走而表示感谢似的。

后来他们就侵入了一个小农庄，在那儿毫不客气地让人家招待他们。这个农家的主人和他一家人战战兢兢地把全部食物都拿出来，供给他们一顿早餐。他们从主妇和她的女儿们手里接过食物来的时候，就要顺手摸摸她们的下巴，对她们开些粗鄙的玩笑，还要给她们取些有意侮辱的绰号，一阵一阵地对她们哈哈大笑。他们把骨头和蔬菜往那农人和他的儿子们身上扔，使他们老是东躲西躲，要是打中了，他们就哄堂大笑。最后有一户人家的女儿对他们的调戏表示愤慨，他们就往她头上抹奶油。临别的时候，他们还警告这家人，如果把他们干的事情传出去，让官家知道了，他们就要回来烧掉这所房子，把他们全家人都烧死。

中午的时候，这帮人经过一段艰苦疲劳的长途步行之后，在一个相当大的村子外面的一道篱笆后面停住了。大家休息了一个钟头，然后就向各处分散，从不同的地点进入这个村庄，各自施展他们的绝技。“贾克”被分派和雨果同去。他们东窜西窜地走了一会儿，雨果老在找机会想打个起发，可是毫无结果——于是后来他说：

“我找不到什么可偷的，这个地方真是糟糕，那么咱们只好去讨钱了。”

“‘咱们’呀，你真说得好！你去干你这本行吧——这对你很相宜。我可不去讨钱。”

“你不讨钱？”雨果用惊讶的眼光盯着国王，大声喊道，“请问你是什么时候改邪归正的？”

“你这是什么意思？”

“什么意思？你不是一辈子在伦敦街上到处讨钱的吗？”

“我？你这糊涂虫！”

“你别随便骂人——留着多使几回吧。你父亲说你向来是讨钱的，也许是他撒谎，也许是你大着胆子说他撒谎吧。”雨果嘲笑地说。

“是你认为是我父亲的那个家伙吗？是呀，是他撒谎。”

“算了，别把你那假装疯子的把戏耍得太过火吧，伙计；你拿它开开心倒不要紧，可别自找苦吃。我要是把你这句话告诉他，他就非狠狠地收拾你一顿不可。”

“用不着你麻烦，我自己会告诉他。”

“我很喜欢你这种精神，实在是喜欢，可是我不佩服你的见识。咱们过的日子本来就够受了，挨揍的机会多得很，犯不着发神经病，自己再去惹到头上来。别再来这一套了吧，我可是相信你父亲。我并不怀疑他会撒谎，我也不怀疑他有时候是要撒一撒谎，因为我们当中最棒的角色也撒谎哩，可是这桩事情他可用不着撒谎。一个聪明人决不会浪费那么多唇舌而一无所获的。好吧，算了，你既然打算不去讨钱，咱们到底干什么才好呢？去抢人家的厨房怎么样？”

国王很不耐烦地说：

“你不要再说这些胡说八道的话了吧——实在叫我听了讨厌得很！”

雨果也动气地说：

“你听着，伙计。你不肯讨钱，又不肯抢东西，那也好吧。可是我得告诉你非干不可的事儿，我来讨钱，你来装相儿哄人。你要是连这个也不干……看你有没有这个胆子！”

国王正打算用鄙视的口气回答，雨果却打断他说：

“别说话！有个人来了，他的样子还挺和气哩。我现在假装发了急病倒在地上。等那个陌生人冲我这儿跑，你就哭起来，跪在地上，装作掉眼泪的样子；跟着你就大声喊叫，好像所有的倒霉鬼都钻到你肚子里去了似的。你说，‘啊，先生，他是我多灾多难的哥哥，我们现在无亲无友，您看在上帝面上，发点慈悲，对这害病的、没人管的、倒霉透了的可怜虫望一眼吧；把您的钱丢一个便士给这遭天罚的、快死的人吧！’——你可得记住，一直哭一直哭，不把他的钱哄到手就哭个不停，要不然就得叫你吃苦头。”

然后雨果马上就开始呻吟、叫喊，同时还直转眼珠子，身子也摇摇晃晃。那个陌生人快到身边的时候，他就惨叫一声，扑倒在他面前，开始装出剧痛的样子，在灰土中翻来覆去直打滚。

“哎呀，哎呀！”那仁慈的陌生人喊道，“啊，可怜的人，可怜的人，他多么痛苦呀——喂，让我把你扶起来吧。”

“啊，好心的先生，您别扶我，上帝保佑您这位高贵的先生吧——我这个病一发作就不能碰，碰一下就痛得要命。我那兄弟会告诉您，大人，我这个急病发作起来，会把我痛成什么样子。给我一个便士吧，亲爱的先生，您给我一个便士，让我买点儿东西吃吧。别的您不用管，让我自己受罪吧。”

“一个便士！我给你三个吧，你这倒霉的人。”——他急急忙忙地在口袋里摸钱，拿出三个便士来。“好吧，可怜的小伙子，你拿着吧，我很愿意帮你的忙。喂，小孩儿，过来吧，你帮我把你这有病的哥哥扶到那边那个房子里去吧，我们可以在那儿——”

“我不是他的兄弟。”国王打断他的话说。

“什么！不是他的兄弟？”

“啊，听哪！”雨果呻吟着说，随后又暗自咬牙切齿。

“他连他的亲哥哥都不认了——眼看着他一只脚已经进了棺材呀！”

“小孩儿，他要是你的哥哥，你可真是心肠太硬了。真丢人！——他简直连手脚都不大能动了。他要不是你哥哥的话，又是谁呢？”

“叫花子和小偷！他拿到你的钱，还扒了你的口袋哩。你要是愿意开个仙方，把他的病治好的话，那就给他肩膀上揍两棍，别的你就不用管，让老天爷安排吧。”

可是雨果并没有等着人家开那个仙方，他立刻就站起来，一阵风似的跑掉了；那位先生在后面直追，一面跑，一面扯开嗓子拼命地嚷着捉贼。国王因为自己得到脱身的机会，真是说不尽的谢天谢地，于是他就往相反的方向逃跑，直到脱离了危险，才把脚步缓下来。他找到第一条大路，就顺着它走，不久就把那个村子甩在背后了。他尽量迅速地往前赶，一直走了几个钟头，老是提心吊胆地回头看看，以防有人追他，后来他终于摆脱了恐惧心理，取而代之的是一种令人爽快的安全感。这时候他才感觉到肚子饿了，而且也非常疲乏。于是他就在一个农家门前停下来，但是他正待开口说话，就被人一声喝住，很粗鲁地撵走了。原来是他那身衣服对他不利。

他继续向前漂泊，心里又委屈又气愤，决计不再让自己这么受人怠慢了。但是饥饿毕竟控制了自尊心，于是天快黑的时候，他就到另一个农家去碰碰运气，可是这回他比上次碰的钉子更大，人家把他臭骂了一顿，还说他如果不马上走开，就要把他当作游民逮捕起来。

黑夜来到了，天又冷又阴沉，然而那走痛了脚的国王仍旧慢慢地勉强往前走。他不得不继续走，因为他每回坐下来休息休息，马上就觉得寒气透入骨髓。他在那阴森森的一片黑暗和空虚的无边夜色里移动着，一切感觉和经历对他都是新奇的。每过一会儿工夫，他就听见一些声音由远而近，再由他身边飘过，渐渐地低下去，变为寂静无声了。他听不出这些声音究竟是由什么东西发出来的，只见一种形象不定的、飘荡的模糊影子，所以他觉得这一切都有一股妖魔作怪似的、阴森恐怖的意味，这不免使他发抖。他偶尔瞥见一道光闪一闪——总是好像离得很远——几乎是在另一个世界似的；如果他听见一只羊儿身上的叮当声，那也是老远的、模糊不清的；牛群闷沉沉的叫声顺着夜间的风飘到他这里来，总是一阵阵飘过去就听不见了，声调也很凄凉；时而有一只狗像哭诉似的嗥叫声，从那看不见的、广阔无边的田野与森林的上空飘过来。一切的声音都是遥远的，它们使这小国王感觉到一切生命和活动都与他相隔很远，感觉到他自己是孤零零的、举目无亲的，站在一片无边无际的旷野的中心。

这前所未有的经历使他毛骨悚然、惊心动魄，他就在这些恐怖之中，东歪西倒地前进。有时候被头上干树叶子的沙沙响声所惊吓，因为那种响声很像悄悄说话的人声。后来，他忽然看见近处一只铁皮灯笼发出的斑斑点点的灯光。他向后退到阴影里等待着，那只灯笼放在一个谷仓敞开的门口。国王等了一会儿——没有什么响声，也没有人动弹。他静立在那儿，简直冷得要命，那准备招待客人的谷仓又对他诱惑力很大，因此后来他终于不顾一切危险，决定要进去。他迅速地、偷偷地迈步往里走，正当他迈过门槛的时候，就听见后面有人说话。他连忙闪避到谷仓里的一只大桶背后，弯下身去。两个农家的长工提着灯笼进来了，一面开始工作，一面谈话。他们提着灯笼到处走动的时候，国王就拼命睁开眼睛四处看，发现这个谷仓另一头好像有个不小的牛栏，他就把它的方位打量清楚，预备等到只剩下他一个人的时候，就摸索着上那儿去。他还看清楚了半路上一堆马毯的位置，打算把它们征用一下，给大英国王使用一夜。

过了一会儿，那两个人就做完了他们的工作出去了，他们随手在外面把门扣上，带着灯笼走了。冷得发抖的国王在黑暗中尽量迅速地往那些毯子那边走；他把它们拿起来，然后小心地摸索着到牛栏里去了。他把两条毯子铺在地上当卧铺，然后把剩下的两条盖在身上。这时候他是个很快乐的国王了，虽然毯子又旧又薄，而且不大暖和；不但如此，还发出一种刺鼻的马臭，这种臭味相当强烈，几乎把人熏得透不过气来。

国王又饿又冷，同时他也疲劳不堪，困倦得要命。最后还是疲惫的感觉占了上风，因此，他随即就打起盹来，进入了半醒半睡的状态。后来正当他将要完全失去知觉的时候，却清清楚楚地感到有个什么东西碰到他身上来了！他立刻就完全清醒过来，吓得直喘气。那个东西在黑暗中神秘地碰了他一下，引起了寒冷的恐惧感，这几乎使他的心停止跳动了。他躺着不动，几乎是憋住气息倾听着。但是并没有什么东西动弹，也没有什么声响。他继续倾听。再等了一阵，好像等了一段很长的时间，仍旧没有什么东西动弹，也没有什么声音。因此他终于又一次打起瞌睡来，但是他突然又觉得那个神秘的东西碰了他一下！这个无声的、看不见的东西这样轻轻地碰到他身上，真是可怕，这使得这孩子充满了怕鬼的心理，很不自在。他怎么办才好呢？问题就在这里，可是他不知道怎样回答这个问题。他是否应该离开这个相当舒适的地方，逃避这不可思议的恐怖呢？可是逃到哪儿去？他被关在这个谷仓里，根本就出不去；他想在黑暗中盲目地东奔西窜，但是他被围困在那四面墙当中，又有这个幽灵在他背后跟着，随时都会伸出那软软的、吓死人的手在他脸上或是肩膀上碰一下，这可实在叫他受不了。那么就在原处待着，通宵忍住这种受活罪的滋味——那是否较好呢？不。那么，还有什么办法呢？啊，只有一条路可走，他知道得很清楚——他必须伸出手去，找到那个东西才行！

这事情想想倒是容易，可是他很难壮起胆来试这一下。他三次畏畏缩缩地向黑暗中稍微把手伸出去一点，每次都吓得喘着气突然缩回来——并不是因为他的手碰到了什么东西，而是因为他觉得一定是快要碰到什么了。但是第四次他再往前一点摸了一下，他的手就轻轻地触到了一个又软又温暖的什么东西。这一下几乎把他吓呆了——他当时的心情使他只能想象着那东西是个刚死的、还有些热气的尸体，而不会是别的。他觉得他宁肯死也不愿意再摸它一下了。他起了这个错误的念头，是因为他不懂得人类的好奇心有一种非凡的力量。过了不久，他的手又战战兢兢地摸索起来了——这是违反他的理智、他的心愿的——但是无论如何，他反正还是坚持摸索着。后来他的手碰到了一绺长头发，他打了个冷战；但是他没有停下，而是顺着那绺头发往上摸，结果就摸到了一个什么东西，好像是一根暖和的绳子；再顺着那根绳子往上摸，终于摸到了一头老老实实的小牛！——刚才他摸到的头发根本就不是什么头发，绳子也不是绳子，而是小牛的尾巴。

国王因为一头酣睡的小牛这么个渺小的东西受了那么大的惊，吃了那么大的苦，不免感到由衷的惭愧；但是他其实无须有这种感觉，因为使他恐怖的并不是那头小牛，而是那头小牛所代表的一种根本不存在的东西；在从前那种迷信的年代，随便哪个小孩儿也会和他有同样的举动，并且也会同样吃苦的。

国王不但很高兴地发现那个东西不过是一头小牛，而且还乐得有这头小牛给他做伴，因为他一直都苦于太孤寂和没有朋友，因此现在连这么一个下贱的畜生和他在一起，他也是很欢迎的。何况他从自己的同类那里受了那么大的打击，遭了他们那么无情的虐待，因此他现在觉得自己终于和这么一个生物相处，虽然它也许没有什么高贵的品德，却至少有一颗柔和的心和温顺的脾性，无论如何，总算使他获得了真正的安慰。所以他就决定抛开他的高贵身份，和这头小牛交朋友。

小牛离他很近，他很容易够着它。他一面抚摸着它那光滑而温暖的背，一面想到他还可以利用这头小牛得点别的好处。于是他就把他的卧铺重新安排了一下，紧紧铺在小牛身边，然后他贴着小牛的背睡觉，扯起毯子把他自己和他的朋友都盖起来。过了一两分钟，他就觉得非常温暖而舒适，简直就和他从前在威斯敏斯特王宫里躺在羽绒被褥上一样。

愉快的念头立刻就来了，生命显得较有趣味了。他摆脱了奴役和罪恶的束缚，摆脱了那些下流和野蛮的盗匪；他获得了温暖，获得了栖身之所；总而言之，他快活了。夜间的风刮起来了，一阵一阵地在外面扫过，把这座老谷仓吹得震动起来，嘎啦嘎啦地响，风力时而减退，绕着墙角和突出的地方呜呜咽咽地往远处去了——但是这在国王听来居然都成了音乐，因为他实在是很舒适、很痛快。让它去吹，让它去吼吧，让它去乱轰乱响吧，让它去呜呜地叫、伤心地哭吧。他都不在乎，反而还觉得有趣。他只向他的朋友更加偎紧一点，心里有一股十足的温暖惬意的滋味，随后就满心快乐地飘出了清醒的境界，进入那充满平和安静气氛的睡乡，获得了酣甜无梦的安眠。远处的狗还在嗥叫，丧气的牛还在哀鸣，狂风还在刮个不停，同时还有一阵一阵的暴雨在屋顶上扫过，可是大英国王陛下仍旧睡得很酣，不受搅扰；小牛也是一样，因为它是个老老实实的畜生，既不容易被狂风暴雨所打搅，也不会因为和国王在一起睡觉而不安。

第十九章　王子在农民家里

国王清早醒来的时候，发现一只淋得很湿而又会打主意的老鼠在夜里爬到这里面来，把他的胸口当作舒适的床铺睡着了。现在它受了惊动，就赶快逃跑了。这孩子笑了一下，说：“可怜的傻子，为什么要这么害怕？我跟你一样倒霉啊！我自己也是走投无路，要是我也欺负走投无路的，那就未免太可耻了。不但如此，我还得谢谢你给我带来的好兆头，因为一个国王竟然沦落到这种地步，连老鼠都在他身上搭铺，那当然就是说他的运气快要好转，因为他显然不能比这更倒霉了。”

他站起来，走出牛栏，正在这时候，他听见了孩子们的声音。谷仓的门打开了，两个小姑娘走进来。她们一看见他，立刻就停止谈话，也不再笑了；她们停住了脚步，站着不动，怀着强烈的好奇心注视着他；她们随即就开始低声交谈，然后又走近一点，又站住盯着他，低声说话。后来她们终于鼓起勇气，大声地谈论起他来了。有一个说：

“他的脸蛋儿长得不错。”

另外那一个接着说：

“头发也挺漂亮。”

“可是衣服穿得够坏的了。”

“瞧他那样子准是饿得够受了。”

她们再走近一点，很害臊地横着步子围着他转，从各方面仔细打量他，好像他是一种什么新奇的动物一般；但是同时她们的举动很小心而警戒，就像她们有些害怕他可能是一种随时都会咬人的动物似的。最后她们还是在他面前站住，互相拉着手，做防御的准备，一面用她们那两双天真的眼睛把他仔细地看个心满意足；然后她们当中有一个鼓足了勇气，直截了当地探询道：

“小孩儿，你是谁？”

“我是国王。”这孩子庄重地回答。

那两个女孩子稍微露出了一点吃惊的神情，她们把眼睛睁得很大，这样持续了半分钟，没有作声。后来还是好奇心打破了沉默：

“国王？什么国王？”

“英国的国王。”

那两个孩子互相望了一下——然后又望着他——然后又互相望着——又怀疑，又慌张——然后有一个说：

“你听见他说的吗，玛吉丽？——他说他是国王哩。这话靠得住吗？”

“这怎能靠不住呢，普丽西？他还会说谎吗？你听我说吧，普丽西，这话要是靠不住，那就是他撒谎。当然不是撒谎喽。你想想吧。因为凡是靠不住的话都是谎话——你反正想不出别的道理来。”

这个道理说得很好，很严密，完全没有漏洞，普丽西本来半信半疑，现在感觉站不住脚了。她想了一会儿，然后说了一句简单的话，就叫国王说了真话：

“你要真是国王，那我就相信你。”

“我真是国王。”

这就把问题解决了。她们再也没有盘问，没有争论，就承认了他的国王身份；那两个小姑娘马上就开始问他怎么会上这儿来的，怎么会穿得这么不像个国王的样子，问他打算上哪儿去，还问了他许多别的事情。他现在可以痛痛快快地把他的不幸遭遇说出来，不致被人嘲笑，也没有谁怀疑，这使他觉得快慰，于是他就很激动地叙述他的故事，暂时甚至连饥饿都忘记了。那两个好心的小姑娘听了他的话，表示了非常深切和真挚的同情。但是后来他说到最近的遭遇，她们听说他已经很久没有吃过东西，就马上止住他的话，赶快叫他到她们家里去，弄一顿早餐给他吃。

现在国王很高兴、很快活了，他心里想：“等我恢复了原来的地位，我一定要时常尊重儿童，记住这两个孩子怎样在我遭难的时候信任我，相信我的话；而他们那些年纪大的、自以为比小孩子聪明的人却拿我开玩笑，把我当作一个撒谎的人。”

那两个小姑娘的母亲很慈祥地接待了国王，对他非常怜恤，因为他那流落的情况和那似乎是神经错乱的头脑感动了她那温柔的心。她是个寡妇，家里相当穷，因此她遭到过不少的苦难，对不幸的人很是同情。她猜想这个疯癫的孩子大概是从他的亲人或是监护人那里跑出来了：于是她就极力想要问清楚，他究竟是从什么地方来的，为的是她好设法把他送回去；但是她提到附近的市镇和村庄，还在这方面问了许多话，完全没有结果——这孩子的神色和他的回答也表示她所谈的事情都是他所不熟悉的。他热心而自然地谈到宫廷里的事情；并且当他谈到他那已故的“父王”的时候，还不止一次痛哭起来；每逢话题转到比较鄙俗的事情，他马上就失去兴趣，一声不吭了。

这妇人困惑不已，但是她还是不肯马虎了事。她在做饭的时候，一面想些主意，要出其不意地引着这孩子把他的真正秘密泄露出来。她谈到牛——他表示漠不关心；又谈到羊——结果还是一样——足见她猜想他原先是个牧童是弄错了。她又谈到磨坊，谈到织布匠、补锅匠、铁匠等各行各业的人；又谈到疯人院、监狱和收容所；可是说来说去，她通通都扑了个空。不过也不算完全白费精神，因为她认为那许多事情都谈过了之后，她总算缩小了范围，只剩下家庭的仆人没有谈到了。不错，她知道现在终于把猜测的方向找对了——他一定是给谁家当过用人。于是她就把话题引到那上面去，但是结果又使她失望了。关于扫地的话似乎使他厌烦，生火也没有能够使他动心，擦地板和洗刷的工作也引不起他的兴趣。然后这位主妇以近于绝望的心情谈到烹调的问题，这就只是形式上的谈话了。谁知出乎她的意料，而且使她非常高兴的是，国王脸上立刻就喜形于色了！哈，她心里想，她终于把他的底细追查出来了，她对于自己达到这个目的所用的迂回的妙计和机智是感到非常得意的。

这时候她那疲惫的唇舌获得了休息的机会，因为国王让饥饿熬得难受，又闻到砂锅和炒锅里喷出来的香味，一听谈到吃的问题，就兴致大增，于是他就打开了话匣子，滔滔不绝地谈了一大套，说出了一些美味的菜，因此只过了三分钟的工夫，那妇人就在心里这么想：“果然我猜对了——他原来是给人家厨房里打过杂的！”后来他又说了许多菜的名称，并且谈得津津有味，劲头十足；于是这位主妇又想道：“我的天哪！他怎么会知道这么多样的菜，并且还都是讲究的呀？只有富贵人家的席上才会摆这些菜哩。啊，我明白了！他虽然是个穿得破破烂烂的流浪儿，从前他没有发疯的时候，准是在王宫里当过差；对，他一定在国王本人的厨房里帮过忙！我得试他一下看。”

她急于要证明她的聪明，于是就吩咐国王替她照应一下做菜的事——暗示他只要愿意的话，还可以另外多做一两样菜——然后她就走出去，还给她那两个女儿打了个招呼，叫她们也跟着出去。国王嘟哝着说：

“古时候，另外有一个英国国王也让人家吩咐着干过这种事情——艾尔弗雷德大帝[19]不嫌下贱，干过这种事情，现在叫我来干，也就不算有损我的尊严。不过我要尽力比他做得好一点儿，因为他让饼子烧煳了。”

他的意图是很好的，但是做起来并不如愿。这位国王也跟从前那一位一样，不久就陷入沉思，一心想着大事，结果就发生了同样的不幸——锅里的菜烧坏了。幸亏那妇人回来得正是时候，挽救了那顿早餐，没有让它完全毁掉。她马上就把国王痛痛快快地骂了一顿，使他从梦想中清醒过来。随后她一看国王因为他把她所吩咐的事情弄糟了非常难过，她也就立刻缓和下来，对他非常和蔼、非常慈祥了。

这孩子心满意足地饱餐了一顿，精神就大大地振作起来，心情也轻松愉快了。这一顿饭有一个稀奇的特点，那就是双方都没有计较身份，可是双方都受了这番盛情而自己根本就不知道。那位主妇本来打算拿些残汤剩菜招待这个流浪儿，叫他到一个角落里去吃，就像她对其他任何一个流浪汉或是一只狗那样；但是她因为刚才骂了他一顿，心里很懊悔，所以她就尽量设法补偿一下，结果就让他跟她一家人坐在一起，和她们这些比他体面的人一同吃饭，表面上算是跟她们平等。国王这方面却因为这家人对他那么好，他偏辜负了别人的信任，觉得很懊悔，于是他就叫自己勉强降格，和这家人处于平等地位，借此弥补那个过失，而不独自占据人家的餐桌，摆出他的出身和尊严所应享的排场，叫那妇人和她的女儿们站在旁边伺候他。有时候少讲点儿规矩，对我们总是有好处的。这个好心的女人暗自称赞自己那么宽厚地降低身份，优待一个流浪儿，因此一整天都很快活；国王也因为自己对一个卑微的农家妇女那么谦虚，而感到同样的自鸣得意。

吃完早饭之后，这位主妇就吩咐国王洗盘子。这个命令使国王为难了一会儿，他几乎要拒绝了，可是他随即这么想：“艾尔弗雷德大帝替人家守过饼子，要是叫他洗盘子的话，他当然也会干——那么我也来试试看吧。”

他洗得很糟糕，这是出乎他意料的，因为他原以为洗洗木头调羹和木头盘子是很容易的哩。谁知这个活儿很讨厌、很麻烦，可是他终于把它做完了。这时候他就渐渐有些着急，想要离开这里，再往前走；可是他要摆脱这个会打算盘的主妇，并没有这么容易。她又给了他一些零星工作，他都规规矩矩替她做了，而且做得相当好。随后她又叫他和那两个小姑娘削几个冬季的苹果，但是他对这个工作干得很笨拙，于是她又拿一把菜刀叫他去磨，后来她又叫他梳了很久的羊毛。他觉得像他目前这种了不起的卧薪尝胆的精神，已经大大地赛过了艾尔弗雷德大帝，将来在故事书里和历史书里可以传为美谈，因此他也就有点儿想要告辞了。后来刚刚吃了午饭，这位主妇叫他把一筐小猫拿去淹死，他就当真告辞了。至少他是打算要告辞——他觉得他老帮那个女人做事，总得有个止境；现在趁着淹小猫的机会就此撒手，似乎是很妥当的——可是正在这时候，偏巧又出了岔子。打岔的是约翰·康第——背上还扛着小贩的包袱——还有雨果！

这两个坏蛋还没有来得及看见国王，他就发现他们走近前门了；于是他就没有提告辞的事，赶快提起那一筐小猫，悄悄地从后面跑出去，一声不响。他把那些小畜生放在外面一个小屋里，急急忙忙地钻到后面一条狭窄的巷子里去了。

第二十一章　亨顿救驾

这老人又弯着腰像只猫似的悄悄地溜开，把矮凳子搬过来。他坐在那上面，身子有一半在那暗淡的、跳动的光线里，有一半在阴影中；他把那双渴望的眼睛低下去望着那酣睡的孩子，耐心地守候着，完全没有注意时间的消逝；他轻轻地磨着刀，一面喃喃自语，一面狞笑着；他那神情和姿态活像一只巨大的灰色蜘蛛，心满意足地望着他的网里那一只倒霉的昆虫。

这老人一直在瞪着眼睛望着——但是他看不见什么，因为他的心专注在一个梦想的境界中了——后来过了很久，他猛然看见这孩子的眼睛是睁开的——睁得很大，并且还直瞪着哩！——恐怖得要命地瞪着那把刀。老人脸上露出一阵微笑，像一个满心欢喜的魔鬼似的，他既不改变姿势，也不移动位置，问那孩子说：

“亨利八世的儿子，你做过祷告了吗？”

这孩子想挣脱他的束缚但徒劳无功，同时从那被堵住的嘴里勉强发出一点闷住的声音，隐士就把这个声音当作这孩子对他的问题所做的正面回答。

“那么你再祷告一回吧，为临死的祷告者祈祷吧！”

一阵冷战震动这孩子的全身，他吓得脸色也惨白了。随后他又极力挣扎，想把自己解脱出来——他东转西扭地翻腾着；疯狂地、猛烈地、拼命地拉，企图挣断手脚上捆着的东西——但是枉然；同时那个老妖怪始终望着他狞笑，一面还点点头，安然地磨着刀，不时嘟哝着说：“时间很宝贵哩，现在没有多久了，宝贵得很——快为临死的祷告者再祈祷一次吧！”

那孩子发出一声绝望的呻吟，停止了挣扎，只是喘气。然后眼泪流出来了，一颗一颗地顺着脸往下滴；但是这幅凄惨的情景并没有对这个野蛮的老人产生使他心软的效果。

这时候黎明来到了；隐士看出了这点，很凶恶地大声嚷起来，声音里还带着几分紧张不安的意味：

“我不能再贪图享受这种得意忘形的心情了！黑夜已经过去了。好像一会儿工夫就过去了似的——简直就像是只过了一会儿；这一夜要是能拖到一年多好啊！教会摧残者的孽种，闭上你那双临终的眼睛，你要是怕看着……”

其余的话就变成了含糊不清的嘟哝声，听不见了。这老人又跪下去，手里拿着刀，向那呻吟的孩子身上弯下腰去——

听！小木屋附近有些人说话的声音——隐士手里的刀掉落了，他把一件羊皮袄盖在那孩子身上，战战兢兢地站起来。外面的声响更大了，说话的声音随即变得粗鲁而愤怒；然后又有打斗的声音和求救声；跟着就是一阵逃跑的急促的脚步声。屋门上立刻就有一连串震耳的敲击声响起来，跟着还有人喊道：

“喂！开门！赶快开门，赶快赶快呀！”

啊，这可是最可喜的声音，国王耳朵里听到过的最悦耳的音乐也赛不过这个：因为这是迈尔斯·亨顿的声音！

隐士枉自生气，咬牙切齿地从卧室里迅速地走出去，随手把门关上了；随即国王就听见“小教堂”里传来这么一段谈话：

“向您致敬，敬爱的神父！那孩子在哪儿？——我那个孩子？”

“什么孩子，朋友？”

“什么孩子！请你别说谎，神父先生，不用哄我！——我不爱听这一套。在这附近，我抓住了那两个流氓，我猜孩子就是他们从我那儿偷去的，所以我就叫他们供出来。他们说他又跑掉了，他们跟着他的脚印找他，一直追到你这门口。他们连他的脚印都指给我看了，现在你别说废话哄人了吧。告诉你，神父先生，你要是不把他交出来，那我就……那孩子在哪儿？”

“啊，好先生，大概您是说在这里住了一夜的那个穿得破破烂烂的王室流浪儿吧。如果像您这样的人物关心他那种孩子的话，那么，我告诉您吧，我派他出去做点儿小事情去了，他不久就会回来。”

“要多久？要多久？快说，别耽搁工夫——我追得上他吗？他得多大工夫回来？”

“您不用动，他很快就会回来。”

“那么就这样吧。我等一等看。可是别忙！你派他出去干点儿小事情呀？——你！不消说，这准是撒谎——他不会去的，你要是对他这么无礼，他就会把你那几根老胡子拽掉。你撒谎了朋友，你一定是撒谎了！他不会为你去跑腿，随便什么人叫他去，他也不会干。”

“随便什么人哪——对，他不会干，或许不会干；不过我并不是个人哪。”

“怎么！那么你究竟是什么？”

“这是个秘密——你千万不要说出去。我是个大天使！”

迈尔斯·亨顿突然惊叫了一声——并不怎么恭敬——接着就说：

“这倒实在是可以说明他为什么这么听话！我的确知道他决不肯动一动手脚，伺候凡人；可是天哪，大天使发出的命令，那就连国王也非遵守不行了！让我——嘘！那是什么声音？”

他们谈话的时候，国王始终在隔壁，一会儿吓得发抖，一会儿又因为怀着希望而颤动。他一直都在使尽全副气力，发出痛苦的呻吟，希望能传到亨顿耳朵里；可是他总是很悲痛地发觉他的声音没有被亨顿听见，至少是没有引起亨顿的注意。所以后来他终于听见他的仆人说了那么一句话，就好像是一阵令人振奋的清风，从生气勃勃的原野吹到了一个垂死的人身上一般。于是他又使尽全副精力，拼命喊了一声，恰好这时候隐士正在说：

“声音？我只听见风在吹。”

“也许是风声。对，一定是。我一直都听见这个声音模模糊糊的——又在响哪！那不是风！这声音真奇怪！喂，我们得把它弄清楚！”

这时候国王的欢喜几乎是叫他受不了了。他那疲乏的肺部鼓足了使劲——而且是满怀希望——但是他的嘴被堵住了，身上盖的那件羊皮袄又把他闷住，这就使他的喊声不响。随后这可怜虫听见隐士说出下面这两句话，他就灰心丧气了：

“啊，那是外面来的声音——我想是从那边的矮树林子里来的。走，我来领路吧。”

国王听见那两个人谈着话往外走，又听见他们的脚步声很快就走得老远，终于听不见了——于是就只剩下他一个人，四周是一片不祥的、阴森可怕的沉寂。

等他再听见脚步声和说话的声音过来的时候，就好像是熬过好久了——这次他听见另外有一种声音——显然是咔嗒咔嗒的蹄声。然后他听见亨顿说：

“我不在这儿等了，我也不能再等了。他准是在这个密树林里走迷了路。他往哪一边走的？快说——指给我看吧。”

“他——你等一等，我陪你去。”

“好吧——好吧！嘿，您实在比您的外表还要好哪。真是，我觉得再没有哪个大天使有您这么好的心肠了。您骑牲口吗？愿意骑我给那孩子预备的小驴呢，还是愿意把您那两条尊腿跨上我给自己预备的这头坏脾气的骡子呢？——我上当了，哪怕我花的钱只有借一个铜板给一个失业的补锅匠所得的月利那么少，那也不值得。”

“不——你骑上你的骡子，牵着小驴走吧；我走路还稳当一点儿，我宁肯走。”

“那么，请您帮帮忙，替我招呼这只小畜生，让我来好好试试，看我能不能骑上这个大家伙。”

随后就听见一阵乱踢乱蹦、东踩西跳的声音，还夹杂着一连串响亮的咒骂声。最后，那头骡子挨了一顿狠揍，准是吓掉了魂，因为之后它就停止反抗了。

那被捆着的小国王听见人声和脚步声渐渐远去，终于听不见了，他真是说不出的难受。这下他觉得一切希望都完了，一阵沉重的绝望笼罩在他心头。“我的唯一的朋友受了骗，被带走了，”他心里想，“隐士会回来，他要——”他想到这里，就急得喘了一口气；于是又拼命地挣扎，要想挣脱他的束缚，结果他终于把那件闷人的羊皮袄甩开了。

这时候他听见门开了！这个声音把他吓得连骨髓都冷透了——他好像已经觉得刀子放在他嗓子上了。恐惧使他闭上了眼睛，恐惧又使他把眼睛睁开——谁知站在他眼前的却是约翰·康第和雨果！

假如他的嘴没有被堵住的话，他一定会喊一声：“谢天谢地！”

一两分钟之后，他的四肢就被松开了，捉他的那两个人每人抓住他的一只胳臂，带着他飞快地从森林中钻出去了。

第二十三章　王子当了囚犯

亨顿勉强向国王微笑了一下，低下头去靠近他的耳朵小声说道：

“小声点儿吧，小声点儿吧，国王，您说话可千万要小心——不，根本就不要开口。相信我吧——一切终归会有好结果的。”然后他又自言自语道：“迈尔斯爵士！哎呀，我完全忘记我是一个爵士了！天哪，这多么奇怪，他那疯疯癫癫的脑子，记性怎么会这么好呀！……我这个头衔是空的，毫无意义的，可是我获得了这么个头衔，倒也很有意思，因为我觉得与其在这人间的某些真正的王国里当个让人轻视的伯爵，还不如在他这个梦想和幻影的王国里当个虚假的受到尊敬的爵士，这反而更有光彩哩。”

人群向两旁闪开，给一个警官让路。警官走过来，正要向国王肩膀上伸过手去的时候，亨顿连忙说：

“慢着，好朋友，不用动手——他自己会老老实实地去，这事情由我负责。你领头，我们跟着走。”

警官带着那个女人和她的包袱在前面走，迈尔斯和国王随后跟着，背后还有那一群人。国王很想反抗，可是亨顿低声对他说：

“您仔细想想吧，陛下——您的法律是天经地义的御旨；难道陛下不遵守自己颁布的法律，还能指望臣民遵守它吗？当然，这些法律已经有一条被违犯了；将来国王回宫，想起他自己被人误认为老百姓的时候，曾经忠诚地把自己国王的身份降为平民，顺从法令，这难道会使陛下痛心吗？”

“你说得很对，无须再多说了。你放心，大英国王要求一个老百姓遵守法律，我保证他自己处在一个老百姓的地位的时候，也一定会遵守的。”

那个女人被传到治安法官面前对证的时候，她发誓说被告席上那个小犯人就是偷东西的人；没有人提供反面的证词，因此国王被宣告有罪了。然后，包袱被打开了，原来那里面包着的是一只肥胖的小烤猪。于是法官就显出为难的神情，亨顿也吓得脸色惨白，他惊慌失措，像触电似的打了一个冷战，透过全身；但是国王因为不懂这有什么要紧，始终处之泰然。法官心神不安地沉思了一会儿，然后转过脸向那女人问道：

“你说这个东西值多少钱？”

那女人请了个安，回答说：

“三先令八便士，大人——要是叫我老老实实地说出价钱来，就不能再少一个便士了。”

法官神色不安地向在场的人扫了一眼，然后向那警官点点头，说：

“叫他们出去，把门关上。”

警官照办了。留下的只有法官和警官、原告和被告，还有迈尔斯·亨顿。亨顿吓得面无人色，额头上凝集了一些大滴的冷汗，随后散开一下又汇拢了，顺着两颊流下去。法官又向那女人转过脸去，用怜恤的声音说：

“这是个可怜的、无知无识的孩子，大概是饿得受不了了，现在这种年头，穷苦人本来也是倒霉。你看，他看起来并不像个坏人的样子——可是饿得难熬的时候——好心的太太！你知道吗，谁要是偷了价值十三个半便士以上的东西，照法律规定就要判处他绞刑！”

小国王大吃一惊，吓得睁大了眼睛，但是他极力保持镇定，不声不响；那女人却不是这样，她猛然跳起来，惊骇得浑身发抖，大声喊道：

“啊，老天爷，这可是不得了！哎呀，我无论如何也不愿意这个可怜的小家伙被绞死呀！啊，您给我想个补救的办法吧，老天——我怎么办，我怎么办才行呀？”

法官保持着他那法官的镇定神色，从容地说：

“当然现在还可以改一改价钱，因为案卷上还没有写上去。”

“那么老天在上，把这只猪算作八个便士吧，谢天谢地，我良心上总算把这桩吓死人的事儿摆脱了！”

迈尔斯·亨顿高兴得要命，简直把一切礼节完全忘掉了，他伸开胳臂，把国王搂住，这使国王吃了一惊，并且还伤了他的尊严。那女人很感激地告别，拿着她的猪走开了；警官替她开门的时候，跟着她走到外面那个狭窄的过道里。法官动手在案卷里写下证词。亨顿向来很机警，他很想出去看看那警官为什么要跟着那个女人出去，于是悄悄地溜进黑暗的过道里，听听动静。结果他听见了下面这么一段对话：

“这只猪挺肥，足够饱吃一顿；我买了它吧；这儿是八个便士。”

“八个便士，你说得真好！你可不能这么干。我花了三先令八便士买来的，那是前一任国王造的钱，一点儿也不假，才死的亨利老王连摸都没有摸过的新钱哪。你那八个便士算什么！”

“你在那里面说的话还算不算数？你发过誓的，足见你说价钱只有八个便士的时候，是起了假誓。马上跟我回去见法官大人，承认这个罪吧！那孩子还是得处绞刑。”

“算了，算了，我的好人，不用多说了，我答应你。你给我那八个便士吧，可别跟别人说呀。”

那女人哭哭啼啼地走了；享顿又悄悄地回到审判室里。警官把他骗来的东西藏在一个方便的地方，也就马上跟着进来了。法官继续写了一会儿，然后向国王念了一篇英明而和善的判词，判决他一个短期监禁，关在普通的监狱里，完了还要当众鞭打一顿。惊骇的国王张开嘴来，大概是要发出命令，把这位好心的法官当场斩头；但是他看见享顿对他做了个警告的手势，于是连忙闭上嘴，没有漏出什么来。享顿牵着他的手，向法官行了个礼，他们两个就跟着警官往监狱那边去了。刚走到街上，愤怒的国王就站住了，他把手甩开，大声喝道：

“蠢东西，难道你认为我还能‘活着’进一个普通的监狱吗？”

享顿弯下腰去，用略带严厉的口气说：

“请你信任我好吗？不要吵！千万别再乱说，弄得我们更逃不掉。上帝的旨意一定要实现才行，你没有办法让它快一些，也没有办法改变它；所以就只好耐心等着——且等将要发生的事情发生了之后，你就有的是工夫，爱骂就骂，爱高兴就高兴。”

第二十四章　脱逃

那一个短促的冬天快要结束了。街上行人稀少，只有很少几个东奔西窜的人，他们匆匆忙忙地一直往前走，一副专注的神情，只急于尽快把事情办完，然后赶回家去舒服舒服，躲避将要刮起来的大风和越来越暗的夜色。他们都不东张西望，大家对这几个人都不注意，甚至好像根本没有看见他们。爱德华六世有些怀疑，不知从前是否有过哪一位国王，上监狱里去的场面遭遇过这种惊人的冷淡。后来警官到了一个没有人的市集场所，继续往对面走。他走到中间的时候，亨顿伸手按在他的胳臂上，低声地说：

“等一等，先生，这里没有人听见，我要跟你说句话。”

“我的职务不许我跟你谈话，先生；请你不要耽误我吧，天快黑了。”

“可你还是要等一下，因为这事跟你有密切的关系。你转过身去，装作没看见，让这可怜的孩子逃掉吧。”

“你跟我说这种话呀，先生！我要逮捕你，这是依——”

“嘿，你不要太性急吧。你千万得小心，不要犯傻头傻脑的错误。”然后他把声音降低，贴近那个人的耳朵说，“你花八个便士买了那只猪，就可以叫你的脑袋搬家呀，伙计！”

那可怜的警官冷不防听到这个，吓了一跳，起初他简直目瞪口呆，后来他终于又说起话来了，于是他就大声地嚷，说些威胁的话；可是亨顿很镇定、耐心地等着，一直等到警官说得气都透不过来的时候，说：

“朋友，我对你很有好感，不愿意看见你遭殃。你当心吧，我都听见了——一字一句都听见了。我可以给你证明一下。”于是他就把那警官和那女人在过道里说的话逐字地背了一遍，完了还补上这么两句：

“怎么样——我背得对不对？如果有必要的话，难道我还不能在法官面前背得清清楚楚吗？”

这个人由于恐惧和苦恼，一时哑口无言；然后他又打起精神，故意装作不在乎的样子说：

“这未免小题大做，把玩笑当起真来了；其实我不过是逗一逗那个女人，给我自己开开心罢了。”

“你把那女人的猪留下来，难道也是开玩笑吗？”

这个人机警地说：

“没有别的意思，好先生——我担保那只是开开玩笑。”

“我真要相信你哩，”亨顿说，他的声调里掺杂着一半讥讽、一半自信的口气，使人捉摸不清，“可是请你在这里等一下，让我跑去问问法官大人——反正他是个对法律有经验的人，对玩笑，对——”

他一面走开，一面继续说话；警官迟疑了一阵，心里烦乱不安，诅咒了一两声，然后喊道：

“站住，站住，好先生——请你稍等一等——法官！嘻，朋友，他对于开玩笑也不会表示同情，就像一具死尸一样——回来吧，我们再商量商量。老天爷！我好像很倒霉——只不过是为了无心地随随便便打趣了一下。我是个有家的人，有老婆孩子——好心的先生，您讲讲道理嘛，您叫我怎么办？”

“只要你装瞎，装哑，装麻痹，要装到从一数到十万那么久——慢慢地数。”亨顿说。看他的表情，好像他只要求这个人帮个近情近理的忙，而且是一件很小的事情似的。

“这可把我毁了！”警官绝望地说，“啊，请你讲讲道理吧，好先生；请你从各方面把这件事情看清楚，你看这是多么小的一个玩笑——这清清楚楚地分明是开玩笑的呀。即使不是开玩笑的话，那也不过是个很小的过错，大不了也只能招致一点小小的责罚，不过是让法官骂几句，警告警告罢了。”

亨顿一本正经地回答他，那严肃的语气使他周围的空气都发冷了：

“你这个玩笑在法律上有个名词——你知道那叫什么吗？”

“我不知道！也许是我太不明智了。我从来没有想到这还有个名称——啊，天哪，我还以为这是别出心裁的哩。”

“的确是有个名称。这在法律上叫作‘乘人之危，诈欺取财’。”

“哎呀，我的天哪！”

“那是犯死罪的！”

“老天保佑我，我犯罪了！”

“你乘人之危，任意摆布，强夺了价值十三个半便士以上的财物，只给了很少一点儿钱；这在法律上是实实在在的受贿罪、隐匿罪、渎职罪，严重的贪赃枉法罪——治这种罪的刑罚是绞死；不得赎身，不得减刑，不得援用优待牧师的恩典。”

“搀着我吧，扶着我吧，好心的先生，我的腿站不住了！请你发发慈悲——饶了我这个死罪吧，我转过背去，出什么事我都装看不见。”

“好！你这才叫聪明，有脑筋。你把猪也归还原主吧。”

“我还她，我还她，一定还——以后再也不动手了，哪怕是天上掉下来的，大天使送给我的，我也不敢要了。走吧——我为了你而瞎眼了——我什么也看不见。我就说你闯进来从我手里强行把犯人抢走了。那扇门是很不结实、很破旧的——等到半夜过后天还不亮的时候，我就自己去把它敲破。”

“就这么办吧，好人，决不会出什么毛病的；法官对这个可怜的孩子很慈善，不会因为他逃掉了而掉眼泪，也不会把看牢的打断骨头，你放心吧。”

第二十五章　亨顿府

亨顿和国王刚走出警官的视线，他就吩咐国王陛下赶快跑到村镇外面去，在某个地方等着，同时他要回到小客栈去把账结清。半小时之后，这两个朋友就骑上亨顿那两头不像话的牲口，欢欢喜喜地慢慢往东走。国王现在又暖和又舒服了，因为他已经甩掉了他那一身破衣服，穿上亨顿在伦敦桥上买的那一套旧衣服了。

亨顿很想让这孩子不要过度疲劳；他估计艰苦的旅行和没有定时的饮食，还有睡眠太不讲究，都会对失常的神经不利；要是能多让他休息休息，生活有规律，再加上适度的运动，那就一定能使他的病快点儿好转；他盼望那被折磨坏了的脑子恢复正常，盼望那些想入非非的幻觉从受过摧残的小脑袋里驱除出去；所以他就决定从从容容地、一段一段慢慢往前走，回他那被迫远离多年的家，而不为他那急切的愿望所指使，日夜兼程地赶回去。

他和国王大约走了十英里路，就到了一个相当大的村镇，于是他们在一个很好的客栈里住下来过夜。从前的关系又恢复了：国王用餐的时候，亨顿就在他背后站着伺候他；他准备睡觉的时候，亨顿就替他脱衣服；然后自己在地板上睡觉，用一条毯子裹着身子，挡住门横卧着。

第二天和之后的一天，他们都懒洋洋地慢慢往前走，一面谈着他们分手之后所遭遇的惊险经历，对彼此所叙述的事情都大感兴趣。亨顿详细地叙述了他东奔西跑寻找国王的经过，还描述了大天使怎样领着他到森林中四处瞎转，后来知道无法摆脱他，才引着他仍旧回到小屋里来。然后——他说——那老头儿就到卧室里去，怪伤心地东歪西倒走出来，说以为那孩子已经回来了，在卧室里躺下来休息，但是他并不在那里。亨顿在小屋里等了一整天，后来因为对国王回来的希望落了空，他就离开了那儿，再往前追寻去了。

“那位圣洁的老隐士的确是因为陛下没有回来，显得很难过哩，”亨顿说，“我从他的脸色看出来了。”

“哎呀，这一点我倒是决不会怀疑！”国王说。于是他把自己的遭遇说了一遍；亨顿听了之后，就说他很懊悔没有把那大天使杀掉。

他们在路上的最后一天，亨顿的情绪非常高涨，他嘴里不断地说个天花乱坠。他谈到他年老的父亲，谈到他哥哥亚赛，还叙述了许多事情，说明他们高尚慷慨的品质；他谈到他的爱迪思，就高兴得眉飞色舞，他心里不知多么欢喜，以至于连提到休吾的时候，也能说出一些温柔的手足之情的话来。他把快要来到的亨顿府那种久别重逢的情景说了一大套；他预料人人都会大为惊喜，热烈地表示谢天谢地。

那是一个风光明媚的地方，到处点缀着一些村舍和果园，大路从广阔的草原中穿过，草原一望无际，向远方伸展，中间有许多坡度不大的小丘和洼地，使人联想到一片波涛起伏的海洋。那天下午，这位回家的浪子常常离开大路，爬到小山丘上，看看是否能够从远处望过去，瞥见他的家。最后他终于如愿以偿，于是他兴奋地喊道：

“那就是我们的村庄，我的王子，亨顿府就在那附近！你从这儿就可以看见那些碉楼，还有那片树林——那就是我父亲的猎园。啊，现在你就会知道那有多大的气派，多么富丽堂皇！那所房子有七十个房间——你想想看！二十七个仆人！那么个地方给我们住，真是漂亮得很，是不是？走，我们赶快吧——我着急得很，再耽搁我简直受不了了。”

于是他们拼命往前赶，结果还是三点过后才赶到那个村镇。这两位旅客从镇上匆匆穿过，亨顿嘴里始终滔滔不绝。“这儿就是那个教堂——还是披着那些藤——一点儿也没减少，一点儿也没增加。”“那儿就是那个客栈，红狮老店——那边儿就是那个市场。”“这儿就是那个五月柱，这儿就是那个抽水机——什么都没改变；只有人才有些变化，十年的工夫使人变了；有些人我似乎还认识，可是谁也不认识我了。”他老是这么说个不停，不久就到了村镇的尽头；然后这两位旅客走上一条弯弯曲曲的狭路，两旁夹着很高的篱笆；他们沿着这条小路轻快地向前跑了半英里，然后穿过一座派头十足的门楼，走进一个巨大的花园，那门楼的高大石柱上刻着纹章的图案。一座豪华的府邸呈现在他们眼前。

“欢迎您到亨顿府来，国王！”迈尔斯欢呼道，“啊，这真是个盛大的日子！我父亲、我哥哥和爱迪思小姐都会高兴得要命，在刚见面的一阵狂喜中，也许会只来得及看着我，和我说话，所以对你就会显得有点儿冷淡——可是你不要见怪，过一会儿就会变了；因为我只要跟他们一说，你是受我监护的，再告诉他们我多么爱你，他们就会看在我迈尔斯·亨顿的面上，把你抱在怀里，让他们的府邸和他们的心成为你永远的家！”

亨顿随即就在大门前跳到地上，再扶着国王下来，然后拉着他的手，连忙往屋里跑。他走了几步，就到了一间宽大的房子里；他走进去，匆忙中顾不得礼节，把国王推到椅子上坐下，随即就向着一个坐在一炉木柴燃起的壁炉火前面的一张写字台旁边的年轻人跑过去。

“跟我拥抱吧，休吾，”他喊道，“看见我回来了很高兴吧！把父亲请来，因为我还没握到他的手，看见他的脸，听见他的声音，这个家还不能算是家哩！”

但是休吾暂时露出了一点惊讶的神色之后，把身子往后躲，同时很严肃地瞪着眼睛望着这个闯进来的人——他那注视的眼光起初表示出几分伤了他的尊严的神情，然后出于他内心的某种念头或是目的，变成了一种惊奇的表情，还掺杂着真正的或是假装的怜恤。随后他就用温和的声调说：

“你的脑袋大概是受过损伤了，可怜的陌生人；不消说，你一定是在人间四处流浪，吃过许多苦头，受过许多粗暴的打击；你的脸色和衣服都表现出来了。你把我当成什么人呢？”

“当成什么人？请问，你不就是你，还能是谁呀？我把你当成休吾·亨顿哪。”迈尔斯高声地说。

对方还是用温和的声调继续说：

“那么你想着你自己是谁？”

“这和什么想不想是不相干的！你难道还装作不认识你的亲哥哥迈尔斯·亨顿吗？”

一阵惊喜的表情在休吾脸上掠过，他大声喊道：

“怎么！你不是开玩笑吗？难道死人还能复活？如果真有这种事，那可要多谢上帝！我们那可怜的、没有音讯的孩子过了这么多年苦命的日子，又回到我们的怀抱了！啊，恐怕不会有这么好的事情，的确不会有这么好的事情——我请你积德，不要跟我开玩笑吧！快点儿——到亮处来——让我仔细看看你！”

他揪住迈尔斯的胳臂，把他拖到窗户跟前，开始从头到脚拼命打量他；把他转来转去，迅速地在他周围来回地走，要从各方面证明究竟是不是他；同时这回家的浪子欢喜得满面红光，一会儿微笑，一会儿大笑，不断地点着头说：

“尽管看吧，兄弟，尽管看吧，不要紧。你总会看出四肢和面孔，无论哪一点都经得住考验。你尽管打量，尽管仔细看，看个够吧，亲爱的兄弟——我的确是你从前那个迈尔斯，一点儿也不错，就是你那没有音讯的哥哥，对不对？啊，这真是个盛大的日子——我早就说过，这是个盛大的日子！跟我握手吧，让我亲亲你的脸吧——天哪，我简直欢喜得要命呀！”

他正想扑过去抱住他的兄弟，但是休吾举起手来表示反对，然后很伤心地把头低下去，垂在胸前，一面很激动地说：

“啊，请上帝开恩，给我一点儿力量，让我能经得住这场伤心的失望吧！”

迈尔斯吃了一惊，一时目瞪口呆，直到他透过气来，才大声说：

“什么失望？难道我不是你的哥哥吗？”

休吾悲伤地摇一摇头，说：

“我希望老天爷能证明你是的，还要叫别人来看看，也许你有些相像的地方，我没有看得出来，他们能看得出吧。哎呀，恐怕那封信说的一点儿也不错哩。”

“什么信？”

“六七年前从海外寄来的。信上说我的哥哥阵亡了。”

“那是谣言！请父亲来——他会认识我。”

“死人是请不来的。”

“死了？”迈尔斯的声音低下去了，他的嘴唇直发抖。“我父亲死了！——啊，这可是个伤心的消息。这把我的快乐消掉一半了。请你让我见见亚赛哥哥吧——他会认识我；他会认识我，还会安慰我哩。”

“他也死了。”

“上帝保佑我吧，我这倒霉的人！死了——两个都死了——老天爷把高尚的人收去了，偏留下我这没出息的活着！啊！我请你积德！——你可不要说爱迪思小姐也——”

“也死了？不，她还活着。”

“那么，谢天谢地，我又快活到极点了！赶快吧，兄弟——让她出来见我！如果她说我不是的话——可是她不会那么说；不会，不会，她一定会认识我，我怎么会怀疑这点，真是太傻了。请她来吧——把那些老用人也叫来，他们也会认识我。”

“全都死了，只剩下五个——彼得、哈尔赛、大卫、柏纳德和玛格丽特。”

休吾一面这么说，一面离开了这间屋子。迈尔斯站着沉思了一会儿，然后开始在屋里走来走去，嘴里嘟哝着：

“只有这五个顶坏的浑蛋活着，其余那二十二个老实忠心的都死掉了——真是怪事。”

他继续来回地走着，喃喃地自言自语，他完全把国王忘记了。后来国王陛下严肃而又略带几分真诚的同情开了口，虽然这几句话听上去好像有意挖苦亨顿一样。

“不要为你的不幸而难受吧，好人；世界上还有别人也弄得身份不明，自己说是什么人，还要受人嘲笑哩。有人和你同病相怜啊。”

“啊，国王，”亨顿脸上稍微红了一下，大声说，“请您不要把我当成坏人吧——等一等，您就会明白。我不是个骗子——她会这么说；您会听见英国最可爱的人嘴里说出这句话来。我是个骗子？噢，我认识这间老客厅，我认识我祖先的这些相片，也认识我周围这许多东西，就像一个小娃娃认识他自己的育儿室一样。我是在这里出生，在这里长大的，陛下；我说的是真话，我不会欺骗您；假如别人都不相信我的话，我请求您千万不要怀疑我——我受不了啊。”

“我不怀疑你。”国王以孩子般的天真和信任的态度说道。

“我真心地感谢您！”亨顿大声说道，他那热情的声调表示他受了感动。国王仍旧用那温和的天真语气接上去问了一句：

“你是不是怀疑我呢？”

亨顿猛然感到一阵内心的狼狈，正在这时候，门开了，休吾走进来，这就给他解了围，使他没有回答的必要，因此他倒觉得很高兴。

一个美丽的女郎穿着华丽的衣服，跟着休吾出来了，她后面还跟了几个穿号衣的仆人。这位女郎低着头，把眼睛望着地板，慢慢地走。她的脸色说不出的阴沉。迈尔斯·亨顿扑向前去，大声喊道：

“啊，我的爱迪思，亲爱的——”

但是休吾严肃地摆一摆手，把他挡回去，一面对那女郎说：

“你看看他。你认识他吗？”

那女人一听迈尔斯的声音，就微微地惊动了一下，脸也涨红了；这时候她浑身发抖。她站着不动，令人感动地踌躇了几分钟；然后慢慢地抬起头来，用一种冷酷而惊骇的眼光注视着亨顿的眼睛；她脸上的血色一滴一滴地消失了，直到后来，满脸只剩下一片死人一般的惨白，然后她说：“我不认识他！”她的声音也是死气沉沉的，正如她的脸色一样；随后她就发出一声呻吟和抑制住的低泣，一歪一倒地走出这间屋子了。

迈尔斯·亨顿倒在一把椅子上，双手把脸蒙住。稍停了一会儿，他的兄弟对仆人们说：

“你们都看见他了。你们认识他吗？”

他们都摇摇头，然后主人就说：

“这些仆人也不认识你，先生。我想你恐怕是弄错了。刚才你看见了，我的妻子也不认识你。”

“你的妻子！”休吾立刻就被推到墙上按住，他的嗓子被一只铁钳似的手掐得紧紧的。“啊，你这狐狸心肠的下流东西，我全都明白了！是你自己写的那封骗人的信，结果就把我的新娘抢过去，把财产也霸占了。好——你赶快滚开，否则我就要杀掉你这可怜的小人，那未免玷污我那光荣的军人身份了！”

休吾满脸通红，几乎被掐死了，歪歪倒倒地跑到最近的一把椅子上坐下，命令仆人们抓住这个行凶的陌生人，把他捆绑起来。他们迟疑着不敢动，其中有一个说：

“休吾爵士，他带着武器哪，我们都是赤手空拳的。”

“带着武器？你们这么多人，那有什么关系？逮住他，我命令你们！”

但是迈尔斯警告他们不要轻举妄动，接着又说一句：

“你们从前都知道我的本领——我现在还是没有变；只要你们高兴，就来试试吧。”

这一句警告的话使这些仆人不大壮得起胆来，他们仍旧不敢上前。

“那么你们去拿武器，把门守住吧，你们这些不中用的胆小鬼，我另外派个人去把卫兵找来。”休吾说。他走到门槛那儿，又回过头来对迈尔斯说：“你可不要打算逃跑，那是没有用的，徒然自找苦吃；你还是老老实实待着，对你才有好处。”

“逃跑？你要是只担心这个的话，那就请你放心吧。因为迈尔斯·亨顿是亨顿府的主人，这里一切都是他的。他要在这里住下去——毫无疑问。”

第二十六章　被否认了

国王坐着沉思了几分钟，然后抬起头来说：

“真是奇怪——太奇怪了。我不懂这是怎么回事。”

“不，这并不奇怪，陛下。我知道这个人，他这种行为是很自然的。他生来就是个坏蛋。”

“啊，我说的不是他呀，迈尔斯爵士。”

“不是说他？那又是说的什么呢？有什么事奇怪？”

“我说的是国王失踪了，大家还不在乎哪。”

“怎么的？哪个国王？我想我不懂你的意思。”

“哼！现在并没有人派信使到全国各地去，到处贴告示，说明我的相貌，四处寻找我，难道你不觉得这是非常奇怪的事吗？国家的元首失踪了——我跑得不知去向了，难道这还不是叫人慌张、叫人着急的事情吗？”

“的确不错，我的国王，我忘记了。”于是亨顿叹了口气，低声自言自语，“可怜的神经错乱的脑子——还在忙着做它那感伤的大梦哪。”

“但是我有一个办法，使我们两个都能够申冤。我来写封信，用三种文字——拉丁文、希腊文和英文——你明天早上就拿着这封信，赶快送到伦敦去。你把它交给我的舅父赫德福伯爵，不要交给别人。他看见这封信，就会知道是我写的，那么他就会派人来找我。”

“陛下，我们是不是最好在此地等一下，让我证明自己的身份，确定我对这份产业的所有权呢？那么一来，我就比较有办法……”

国王迫不及待地打断他的话说：

“住嘴！你这点儿渺小的产业，你这点儿微不足道的财富，比起那有关国家的祸福和王位安危的大事，算得了什么！”然后他好像是因为语气太严厉而抱歉似的，又用温和的声调说道，“你服从我的命令吧，不要害怕；我会恢复你的地位，我会使一切都归还给你——是呀，还不止你原有的一切哩。我不会忘记你，一定要报答你。”

他一面这么说，一面拿起笔来，动手写信。亨顿慈爱地注视了一会儿，然后暗自想道：

“假如是在黑暗的地方，我真会以为这是个国王说话哩；不消说，他发起脾气来的时候，简直就大发雷霆，倒是真像个国王哩——咦，他从哪儿学来了这套把戏？瞧他那么自在地乱涂乱画，写出那些莫名其妙的鬼字，心里想象着那就是拉丁文和希腊文——除非我能想出个好主意来，使他打消这个念头，否则明天我就得被他强迫着走开，假装着赶到伦敦去，办他给我想出的这件疯头疯脑的差事哩。”

迈尔斯爵士的心思随即又回到刚才发生的事件上来了。他非常专心地沉思，以致国王把刚才所写的那封信交给他的时候，他就接过来放在口袋里，自己还不知不觉。“她的举动多么奇怪呀，”他自言自语地嘟哝着，“我想她是认识我——我又觉得她不认识我。这两种想法是互相矛盾的，我看得很清楚；我无法把两者折中起来，也不能用争辩的方法打消其中的一种想法，甚至想要使一方面的道理胜过另一方面都办不到。事情显然是这样的，她一定是认识我的面孔、我的身材和我的声音，她怎么会不认识呢？可是她偏说她不认识我，这也就十足地证明她的确不认识，因为她决不会撒谎。但是等等——我看我渐渐明白了。大概是他笼络她——命令她——强迫她撒的谎。这才弄清楚了！这个谜已经解了。她吓得要死的样子——对，她准是受他强迫的。我要去找她，我会把她找到的；现在他既然走开了，她就会说真心话。她会记得从前我们俩在一起玩耍的光景，这就会使她心里软下来，她就再也不会辜负我，一定会承认我。她的心是没有丝毫诡诈的——她向来就很忠诚老实。她当初是爱我的——这一点我有把握；谁也不肯辜负自己爱过的人。”

他迫切地向门口走过去，正在这时候，门开了。爱迪思小姐进来了。她脸色惨白，但是她走路的脚步很稳，她的举止是充满了高雅和端庄之美的。她的脸还是像原先那么悲伤。

迈尔斯快快活活地满怀着信心，连忙跑上前去迎接她，但是她做了个几乎看不见的手势，把他挡住，于是他在原地站住了。她坐下来，叫他也坐下。她就是这样轻易地使他消除了老交情的感觉，把他变成了一个陌生的客人。这种使人吃惊的接待，这种使人发狂的意外，一时简直使他怀疑自己究竟是不是他所自称的那个人。爱迪思小姐说：

“先生，我来警告你。要想说服疯子摆脱幻想，也许是不可能的；但是奉劝他们避免危险，也许还能说得通吧。我看你这种梦想在你心目中好像是真有其事，所以那也就不算是有罪——可是你千万不要怀着这个梦想留在这里，因为这是个危险的地方。”她向迈尔斯脸上定睛望了一会儿，然后令人感动地接着说，“假如我们那失踪的孩子还活着的话，他长大了一定是跟你这个样子很像，这就使此地对你更加危险了。”

“天哪，夫人，我的确是他呀！”

“我很相信你是那么想，先生。我不怀疑你这是说的老实话——我不过是警告警告你，没有别的意思。我的丈夫是这地方的主人，他的权力几乎是无限的；他叫他手下的人发财就能发财，叫他们挨饿就得挨饿。假如你并不像你所自称的这个人，我的丈夫还可以让你自由自在地做你的大梦，痛快痛快；可是请你相信我吧，我很了解他这个人，我知道他会干出什么事来；他会对大家说，你不过是个疯头疯脑的骗子，所有的人马上就会附和他。”她又向迈尔斯定睛望了一阵，接着说道，“即令你的确是迈尔斯·亨顿，而且他也知道，这带地区的人都知道，那你也还是会遭到同样的危险，对你的惩罚还是会免不了——你考虑考虑我的话，好好地斟酌一下吧——他会否认你，给你加上罪名，谁也不会有胆量支持你。”

“我完全相信你的话，”迈尔斯刻薄地说，“既然他有那么大的威力，能叫一个人俯首听命，出卖她的终身伴侣，剥夺他的继承权，那么要叫那些连吃饭和活命都难保，根本顾不到什么礼义廉耻那一套的人唯命是从，大概是很容易的喽。”

那位女郎脸上隐隐约约地涨红了一会儿，她垂下眼睛望着地板；但是她继续说话的时候，声音里还是没有流露出感情的成分：

“我已经警告过你，现在还是不得不警告你离开这里，否则这个人就会要你的命。他是个昧尽良心的专制魔王。我是让他上了脚镣手铐的奴隶，知道他的狠心肠。可怜的迈尔斯和亚赛，还有我那亲爱的监护人理查爵士，都摆脱了他，长眠不醒了——你宁肯跟他们在一起，也不要留在这里，遭这个坏蛋的毒手。你的要求对他的爵位和财产都是一种威胁，你还在他家里对他动过武——你要是不走，那就完蛋了。去吧——不要迟疑。你要是缺钱用，就把这一袋钱拿去，买通那些用人，让你出去，我央求你。啊，可怜的人，听我的警告吧，趁着还可以逃的时候赶快逃吧。”

迈尔斯做了个手势，谢绝了她的钱，起来在她面前站着。

“请你允许我一件事情吧，”他说，“用你的眼睛望着我，好让我看看你是否沉得住气。好——现在你回答我吧。我是不是迈尔斯·亨顿？”

“不是。我不认识你。”

“你发誓！”

回答的声音很低，却是清清楚楚的：

“我发誓。”

“啊，这真是叫人不相信呀！”

“快跑！你为什么要耽误这宝贵的时间？赶快逃命吧。”

正在这时候，有些军官冲进屋里来了，随后就是一场激烈的格斗；但是亨顿不久就力竭就擒，被拖出去了。国王也被捕了，两人都被捆绑起来，送到监狱里去了。

第二十七章　在狱中

牢房里都挤满了犯人，于是这两个朋友被锁上链子，关在一间看守犯了小罪的人的大屋子里。他们有许多同伴，因为这里有二十来个上了脚镣手铐的男男女女、老老少少的犯人——这是一群下流的、吵吵闹闹的家伙。国王因为他的王权受到如此巨大的侮辱，切齿痛恨地大发脾气；亨顿更是憋住一肚子气，不声不响，他简直莫名其妙。他这个兴高采烈的浪子回到了家里，原是指望着人人都为了他的归来而狂喜，结果反而遭到了冷待，进了牢狱。原来的期望和实际的结果竟至相差这么远，因此就产生了令人万分惊骇的效果；他简直说不清这究竟是一幕悲剧，还是一场大笑话。他的感觉和一个欢欢喜喜跳出去看彩虹，结果却遭了雷打的人的感觉很相似。

但是他那纷乱的、苦痛的心思渐渐平静下来，有了几分头绪，然后他的脑筋就集中在爱迪思身上了。他把她的行为翻来覆去地想了一阵，以各种看法把它仔细研究了一下，但是他简直得不到什么满意的结论。她究竟是认识他呢，还是不认识他呢？这是个令人难解的谜，在他心头萦绕了很久；但是最后他还是深信她认识他，却为了自私自利的原因而否认了他。这时候他很想指着她的名字乱骂一通，但是这个名字在他的心目中向来就是神圣的，以致他觉得自己要想玷污它，简直说不出口来。

亨顿和国王盖着监狱里那种肮脏和破烂的毯子，熬过了喧嚣的一夜。狱吏受了几个犯人的贿，给他们弄了一些酒来；结果自然就是那些人唱些下流的歌，还乱打乱嚷，狂呼痛饮。后来半夜刚过，有一个男人袭击了一个女人，用他的手铐打她的头，几乎把她打死，幸亏狱吏赶紧过来，才救了她的命。狱吏拿短棍在那男人头上和肩膀上狠狠地敲了一顿，才恢复了平静——于是狂呼痛饮也就停止了，此后，谁要是不怕那两个受伤的人痛苦呻吟的打搅，就有睡眠的机会了。

此后一个礼拜，日日夜夜所发生的事情都是非常单调的。白天有些人进来瞪着眼睛望着这个“骗子”，否认他的身份，并且侮辱他，而这些人的面孔，亨顿还大致记得清楚；一到夜里，狂饮和吵闹就很有规律地持续不停。但是后来终于有了一个变化——狱吏带进来一个老年人，对他说：

“那个坏蛋在这间屋子里——用你那双老眼四处望望，看你能不能认出他是哪一个吧。”

亨顿抬头望了一眼，马上就起了一阵愉快的感觉，这是他关进牢里以后第一次意识到的。他心里想：“这是布莱克·安德鲁，他一辈子在我父亲家里当仆人——一个老老实实的好人，很正直。那是说，从前他是这样，可是现在谁也靠不住了，大家都是些撒谎的家伙。这个人一定会认识我——而且也会像别人一样否认我哩。”

那老头儿在屋子里东张西望，把每个人的脸都看了一眼，最后他说：

“这儿我只看见一些小流氓，都是街上的渣滓。他是哪一个？”

狱吏大笑起来。

“这儿，”他说，“你仔细瞧瞧这个大畜生，再把你的意见告诉我吧。”

这老头儿走到亨顿跟前，很认真地把他上下打量了很久，然后摇摇头，说：

“哎呀，这可不是亨顿家里的人——向来就不是！”

“对！你这双老眼还挺不错哪。我要是休吾爵士的话，就会把这个肮脏的坏蛋抓去，给他……”

狱吏说到这里，踮起脚尖，假装有一根绞索把自己吊起来似的，同时他嗓子里还发出咯咯的声音，表示透不过气的样子。那老头儿很仇恨地说：

“他要是不遭更严厉的处罚，那真得感谢上帝。如果叫我来处置这个坏蛋，那就得把他烤死，要不然我就不算好汉！”

狱吏阴险地大笑了一阵，然后说：

“你也臭骂他一顿吧，老头儿——他们都这么做哩。你会觉得那是怪好玩儿的。”

于是他就逍遥自在地往他那休息室里走去，不见了。

这老人双膝跪下来，悄悄地说：

“多谢上帝，您又回来了，我的主人！这七年来，我一直相信您已经死了，可是你瞧，您还活着在这儿哪！我一看见您，马上就认出了；我必须装出一副冷酷的神情，好像只看见一些下流的坏蛋和街上的流氓杂碎，那可真是挺费劲哩。迈尔斯爵士，我又老又穷，可是请您吩咐一声，我就去把事实宣布出来，哪怕我因此让人绞死，我也不在乎。”

“不行，”亨顿说，“你不要这么做。这会把你毁了，对我的事情还没有什么好处。可是我感谢你，本来我对人类已经丧失了信心，现在你又把我这种信心恢复几分了。”

这个老仆人对亨顿和国王都很有用处，因为他每天进来“骂”亨顿好几次，每回都偷着带几样美味的食物来，丰富牢饭；同时他还提供一些新消息。亨顿把这些好吃的东西留给国王。要是没有这些食物，国王陛下就会活不下去，因为他吃不下狱吏送来的那种糟糕的粗糙伙食。安德鲁不得不约束自己，只做短时间的探访，以避嫌疑；但是他每次都想方设法传递了相当多的消息——为了替亨顿打算，这些消息都是低声传给他听的，当中还夹杂着一些大声的辱骂，故意叫别人听见。

于是亨顿家里的情况就一点一滴地泄露出来了。亚赛死去已经六年了。失去了亚赛，再加上迈尔斯杳无音讯，使老父亲的身体更坏了，他相信自己快死了，于是他希望休吾和爱迪思在他去世之前成亲；但是爱迪思极力恳求延期，希望迈尔斯回来，然后就来了那封报告迈尔斯的噩耗的信；这个打击就使理查爵士一病不起了；他相信死期已近，于是他和休吾就坚决主张赶快促成这桩婚事；爱迪思苦苦哀求，才获得一个月的延期，然后又推迟了一个月，再推迟了一个月；后来终于在理查爵士临终的病床前面举行了婚礼。这个婚姻是不幸的。邻近一带的人悄悄地传说，婚礼过后不久，新娘就在她丈夫的文件当中发现那封报告噩耗的信的几份潦草而不完全的草稿，因此就指责他恶意地伪造了这封信，借此促成婚事——还加速了理查爵士的死亡。四面八方都听到了关于休吾残酷对待爱迪思和仆人们的消息；自从父亲去世之后，休吾爵士已经完全抛弃了温和的假面具，对待所有依靠他和他的领邑吃饭的人都铁石心肠。

安德鲁的闲谈当中有一点，国王听了特别感兴趣：

“外面谣传国王疯了。可是请您积德，千万不要说是我谈了这个消息，因为人家都说谁要是传出这个消息就得处死刑。”

国王陛下瞪着眼睛望着这老头儿说：

“好人，国王并没有发疯呀——你与其在这里说这些淆惑视听的废话，还不如去忙一些与你更有切身利害的事情，那对你是有好处的。”

“这孩子是什么意思？”安德鲁说，他受到这个意外的角色突如其来的尖锐攻击，不免大吃一惊。亨顿对他做了个手势，他就没有再追问下去，又继续做他的汇报：

“一两天之内，已故的国王就要在温莎下葬——本月十六日——新王将在二十日在威斯敏斯特宫举行加冕礼。”

“我觉得他们必须先把他找到才行，”国王陛下嘟哝着说；然后他又很有信心地说，“可是他们一定会注意这件事情——我也要注意的。”

“看在——”

但是老头儿没有再说下去——亨顿做了个警告的手势，就把他这句话打断了。于是他又继续说他的闲话。

“休吾爵士会去参加加冕礼——他存着很大的奢望哩。他很自信地指望着被封为男爵回来，因为他是很受摄政王的宠信的。”

“什么摄政王？”国王陛下问道。

“桑莫赛公爵殿下。”

“什么桑莫赛公爵？”

“哎呀，只有一个嘛——就是原来的赫德福伯爵赛莫尔呀。”

国王严厉地问：

“他是什么时候当了公爵和摄政王的？”

“从今年一月底起。”

“请问是谁让他当的？”

“他自己和国务会议——还有国王也帮了忙。”

国王陛下猛吃了一惊。“国王！”他喊道，“什么国王呀，老先生？”

“什么国王，真问得怪！天哪，这孩子有什么毛病？我们既然只有一个国王，当然不难回答——就是神圣的爱德华六世陛下——愿上帝保佑他！是呀，他还是个仁慈可亲的小孩子哩；不管他是不是疯了——他们都说他的毛病天天都在好转——反正大家嘴里都在赞美他；大家都为他祝福，并且还祷天祝地，希望他长寿，多统治英国几年；因为他一开始就很仁道地救了诺阜克公爵的命，现在他还打算废除那些折磨和压迫老百姓的最残酷的法律哩。”

这个消息使国王陛下惊讶得哑口无言，他马上就陷入深沉而忧郁的沉思中，以致再也没有听见老人的闲谈了。国王怀疑那个“小孩子”是不是自己当初给他穿上了御服，留在宫里的那个小乞丐。这似乎是不可能的，因为他如果冒充太子，他的举动和谈话一定会叫他露马脚——然后他就会被撵出去，人们就会寻找真正的王子。难道是朝里另外立了一个贵族的子孙代替自己继承王位吗？不会的，因为他的舅父决不会答应这么办——他是操大权的，当然可以制止这种行动，而且一定会制止。这孩子想了半天，一点用处也没有；他越是想要解开这个谜，就越觉得莫名其妙，他的头也越痛，睡眠也越不安了。他急于想到伦敦去的心思时时刻刻都在增长，于是他的囚禁生活就几乎使他无法忍受了。

亨顿千方百计都不能使国王宽怀——他根本不接受安慰，但是他附近有两个套着锁链的女人劝他的话反而更为有效。他在她们温柔的劝慰之下，终于安静下来，学得了几分忍耐的本领。他非常感激，渐渐对她们热爱起来，乐于和她们在一起，受那温柔体贴的影响。他问她们为什么进了监狱，一听说她们是浸礼会教友，他就微笑着问道：

“这难道也是犯了罪，应该关到牢里来吗？我很难过，因为你们快跟我分手了——你们只犯了这点儿小罪，他们不会把你们关得太久。”

她们没有回答；她们脸上的神色使他不安。于是他急切地说：

“你们不作声——给我说老实话吧，告诉我——该不会给你们别的处罚吧？请你们对我说，这是不用担心的吧。”

她们想变换话题，但是她们已经引起了他的不安，于是他就追询下去：

“他们会鞭打你们吗？不会，不会，他们不至于这么残忍！你们说不至于吧。喂，他们不会，是不是？”

那两个女人露出慌张和痛苦的神色，但是她们无法避免回答，于是其中有一个用激动得哽住嗓子的声音说：

“啊，你这善良的心灵，你会叫我们心都要碎了！上帝会帮助我们，让我们能受得了我们这——”

“这就是说出实话来了！”国王插嘴说，“那么他们还是要鞭打你们呀，这些铁石心肠的浑蛋！可是，啊，你们千万不要哭，我受不了。鼓起勇气吧——我一定会恢复身份，来得及救你们，不让你们吃这个苦头，我一定会这么做！”

第二天早上国王醒来的时候，那两个女人已经不见了。

“她们得救了！”他高兴地说，随后他又丧气地接着说了一声，“可是我真倒霉！——因为她们是安慰我的人。”

她们各自留下了一小块丝带，用别针别在他的衣服上，作为纪念品。他说他要把这点儿东西永远保存起来，不久他就要找到他这两位亲爱的好朋友，好好地照顾她们。

正在这时候，狱吏带着他手下几个人进来，吩咐他们把犯人都领到监狱的院子里去。国王高兴极了——能够再到外面见见蓝天，呼吸新鲜空气，那是很痛快的事情。他因为这些看守动作迟缓，心里很烦躁，也很生气，但是后来终于轮到他了。他们打开他那个U型锁，把他放出来，叫他和亨顿跟在其他的犯人后面走。

那个四方院子铺着石板，上面是露天的。囚犯们穿过一条高大的石砌拱道，被安排着站成一排，把背靠着墙壁。他们前面拦着一根绳子，同时还被那些看守的人监视着。那是个寒冷而阴沉的早晨，夜里下过的一场小雪把这一大块空地铺上了一层白色，使这里整个的情景更加显得凄惨了。时而有一阵寒风嗖嗖地吹过这个院子，吹得雪花到处飞舞。

院子正当中站着两个女人，被链子拴在柱子上。国王望了一眼，就看出这是他那两个好朋友。他哆嗦了一下，心里想：“哎呀，她们并不如我所料，还没有被放出去哩。像这样的人居然要挨鞭子，真叫人想想都难受！——这是在英国呀！哎，这实在是可耻——并不是在邪教的国家，而是在基督教的英国啊！她们将要遭鞭打；她们安慰过我，好心地待我，而我现在不得不袖手旁观，看着她们遭这种莫大的冤屈；我这应掌大权的一国之主，居然毫无办法，不能保护她们，真是奇怪，太奇怪了！可是这些浑蛋还是要当心他们自己才行，因为不久就会有一天，我要叫他们把这笔账算清楚。现在他们打一下，将来我要让他们挨一百下才行。”

一扇大门敞开了，有一群老百姓涌进来。他们拥挤在那两个女人周围，把她们遮住，使国王看不见了。一个牧师走进来，从人群中穿过，也被遮住了。这时候国王听见有人对话，好像是有人发问，有人回答，可是他听不清他们说的是什么。随后是一阵忙乱的准备工作，在那两个女人周围站着的人群中，一些官员一次又一次地钻过；这一切进行着的时候，一阵深沉的寂静笼罩着那些人。

后来一声命令，人群向两旁站开了，于是国王看见一个可怕的情景，把他吓得连骨髓都冷透了。那两个女人周围堆起了许多柴把，有一个跪着的人正在把它们点着！

那两个女人低下头来，双手蒙住脸；黄色的火焰开始从那些噼噼啪啪直响的柴堆当中往上升，一圈一圈的蓝烟顺着风飘开；牧师举起双手，开始祈祷——正在这时候，两个年轻的姑娘从大门外面飞跑着冲进来，一面发出凄惨的尖叫声，扑倒在火刑柱前的两个女人身上。她们立刻就被狱卒们拉开了，其中有一个被抓得很紧，另外那一个却挣脱了，她说要和她的母亲死在一起；人家还没有来得及阻止她，她又抱住了她母亲的脖子。她又一次被拖开了，这一回她的长衣已经着了火。有两三个男人抓住她，把她的长衣烧着了的那一块揪掉，甩到一边，还在冒着火焰。她始终挣扎着要跑开，说她从此就要成为孤儿，恳求让她跟她母亲一同死去。两个姑娘都不断地哀号，拼命要挣脱出去，但是这一阵喧嚣忽然被一连串钻透人心的临死的惨叫所淹没了。国王把视线从那两个疯狂的姑娘身上转到火刑柱那边，然后又向一边转过身去，把他那死灰色的脸对着墙上，再也不看了。他说：“我在刚才那片刻的时间里所看到的，会永远留在我心里，忘记不了；我一直到死，天天都会看见这幅惨象——每天夜里都会梦见它。上帝还不如让我瞎了眼睛啊！”

亨顿注意看着国王。他很满意地想道：“他的毛病好些了，他已经改变了性格，不那么暴躁了。要是依着他的老脾气，他一定要痛骂这班狗东西，说他是国王，命令他们放掉那两个女人，不许伤害她们。现在他的幻想不久就会消掉，被他忘记。他那可怜的脑子就要恢复健全了。但愿上帝让这个日子快点来吧！”

那一天又有几个犯人被带进来过夜，他们都由卫兵押解到全国各地去，受他们所犯的罪应受的惩罚。国王和这些犯人谈话——他从头起就打定了主意，只要一有机会，就要询问那些囚犯，借此给自己增长见识，以后好把国王的职务做好——他们的悲惨故事简直使他伤心透了。其中有一个呆头呆脑的女人，她从一个织布匠那儿偷了一两码布——因此她就要被处绞刑。另外有一个男人，被人控告偷了一匹马，他说证据不能成立，所以他以为可以免掉绞刑了；可是不行——他刚被释放，就有人告他打死了国王猎园里的一只鹿，于是他又被传讯了；这回庭上证明了他有罪，现在他就要上绞刑架去了。另外还有一个匠人的徒弟，他的案子特别使国王难受；这个青年说，他有天晚上发现一只猎鹰从它的主人那儿逃掉了，就把它捉回家来，以为那应该归他所有；但是法院给他定了偷窃的罪，判了他死刑。

国王对这些残暴的惩罚大为震怒，于是就叫亨顿越狱，跟他一同跑到威斯敏斯特宫去，好让他坐上宝座，举起权杖来恩赦这些不幸的人，救他们的性命。“可怜的孩子，”亨顿叹息着想道，“这些悲惨的故事又使他的毛病发作了。哎呀，要不是为了这个意外的倒霉事情，他本来是很快就可以好的。”

这些犯人之中有一个年老的律师——他长了一张坚强的脸，一副无所畏惧的样子。三年前，他曾经写过一篇反对大法官的政论文章，攻击他不公正，结果因此受了惩罚，被上了颈手枷，割掉了耳朵，还被取消了律师的资格，另外还被处罚三千英镑，判了无期徒刑。近来他又犯了那个罪，结果就被判处割掉耳朵剩下的部分，还要付五千英镑罚金，两边脸上都要烙上火印，继续执行终身监禁。

“这都是光荣的疤痕。”他一面说，一面把他那灰白的头发向后拨开，露出他两只耳朵被割掉之后的残根。

国王的眼睛里因愤怒而冒火。他说：

“谁都不相信我——你也不信；可是这没关系——不出一个月，你就可以恢复自由；不但如此，那些使你受了耻辱，还把英国的名声玷污了的法律，都要从法令全书里去除。世界上的事情都安排错了，有时候国王应该尝一尝自己的法律的滋味，学习学习仁慈才行。”

第二十八章　牺牲

同时，迈尔斯也对那种闲得无聊的监禁生活渐渐感到十足的厌烦了。现在临到他受审的时候了，这使他非常欣慰，他觉得他可以接受任何判决，只要不再把他关在牢里就行了，但是这一点他想错了。他在法庭上被称为一个“顽强的流氓”，并且因为他具有这种身份，又袭击过亨顿府的主人，结果被判头和手脚戴上枷，当众坐两个钟头。他听到这些，感到非常愤怒。他声明他和控诉人是弟兄关系，并且依法应该由他继承亨顿家族的爵位和财产，但是他的话被轻蔑地忽视，简直就像是根本不值得调查真假似的。

他被领着去受刑的时候，大发脾气，还说了些威胁的话，但是都没有用；他被狱卒们粗暴地拖着走，偶尔还要为了他那不敬的举动挨一个耳光。

国王无法从后面拥挤着的一群乌七八糟的人当中钻过去，所以他就只好在后面跟着，和他那位好朋友和仆人离得很远。国王因为交了这种坏朋友，也差点被判受足枷的刑罚，但是法官考虑到他还小，只给了他一番教训和警告，就把他释放了。后来人群终于站住了，他急切地在外围东奔西窜，要找个地方钻进去；他历经了许多困难，费了很大工夫，最后还是钻进去了。他那可怜的忠实侍从被套上了枷坐在那里，任凭那一群流民戏弄——他这么一位英国国王的随身侍从！爱德华是听见了宣判的，但是这里面有一半的意思他没有弄清楚。他所感到的这种新的侮辱的情绪深入他的心底的时候，他的愤怒就开始高涨了；随后他又看见空中有一个蛋飞过去，在亨顿脸上打碎了，还听见那一群人乱吼，表示欣赏这个节目，于是他的怒火就上升到极点了。他向那块圆形空地当中飞跑过去，面对着行刑的狱吏，大声喊道：

“真丢脸！这是我的仆人——快把他放了吧！我是——”

“啊，别说了！”亨顿惊慌地喊道，“你会把你自己毁了！不要理会他吧，执行官，他是个小疯子。”

“理不理会他的问题，你不用操心，我并没有什么心思理会他；可是多少得给他一点儿教训，这倒是我很感兴趣的。”执行官对一个手下的人说，“给这小傻子尝一两下鞭子的味道，好叫他改改态度吧。”

休吾爵士为了要看看用刑的情况，骑着马到这里来了。这时候刚好才到一会儿，他提议说：“抽他五六鞭子，还更合适一点儿。”

国王被捉住了。他一想到居然有人胆敢主张对他的御体施行这种骇人听闻的凌辱，简直气得神经都麻木了，因此他根本就没有抗拒。史书上曾经记载过用鞭子责罚一个英国国王的事情，把历史都玷污了——现在他想起自己不得不把那可耻的一页复制一份，简直难以容忍。现在他既已落难，也就无可奈何；他只好接受这种刑罚，否则就必须求饶。那可是太不像话了，他还是挨一顿鞭子吧——当国王的挨打还可以，反正不能告饶。

但是与此同时，迈尔斯·亨顿正在给他解决这个困难。“放了这孩子吧，”他说，“你们这些没心肝的狗东西，难道你们看不见他多么小，身体多么脆弱吗？把他放了——让我来替他挨鞭子吧。”

“哎呀，好主意——这倒是要向你道谢才行，”休吾说，脸上显出了讥笑的快意神色，“把这小叫花子放走，让这个家伙替他挨十几鞭子吧——不折不扣的十几鞭，使劲打吧。”国王正要提出强烈抗议，可是休吾爵士说了一句有力的话，就使他沉默下来了，“好吧，尽管说，不要紧，爱说什么就说什么吧——不过你得记住，你每说一个字，他就得多挨六下。”

亨顿从枷上被放下来，他的背上光着；鞭子抽下去的时候，可怜的小国王把脸转开，让那有失国王体面的眼泪顺着两颊流个不停。“啊，勇敢的、好心肠的人，”他心里想，“你这种忠心的行为永远会铭记在我心头。我决不会忘记——也不许他们忘记！”他愤怒地添上了后面这一句。他一面沉思，对亨顿的豪爽行为的赞赏就越来越在他心中高涨，他的感激之情也随着增加了。随后他又想：“救护国王，使其免于受伤甚至死亡的人，是有很大功劳的——这一点他已经为我做到了；但是这和救护国王，使他免于受辱的功劳比较起来，就显得微乎其微——算不了什么！——啊，简直是太微不足道了！”

亨顿在鞭挞之下并不叫喊，以军人承当苦难的坚韧精神熬过了那一顿毒打。他这种精神加上他替那孩子挨打，免得他遭殃的高尚行为，使得周围看热闹的那些无聊的、下流的、一堆乌七八糟的人都不能不对他肃然起敬；他们的嘲笑和叫骂消失了，剩下的只有鞭子打下去的声音。后来亨顿再被套上刑具的时候，那地方笼罩着一片沉寂，这与很短的时间以前那种侮辱的叫嚣比较起来，形成了一种强烈的对比。国王悄悄地走到亨顿身边，向他耳朵里低声说道：

“你这善良的、伟大的人啊，当国王的是不足以表扬你的高贵品质的，因为已经有比国王更崇高的上帝给你表扬过了；但是做国王的可以向凡人证实你的高贵。”他从地上拾起鞭子，轻轻地碰一碰亨顿流血的肩膀，低声说道，“英王爱德华封你为伯爵！”

亨顿大为感动，泪水涌到眼眶里来了。但是当时那种滑稽可笑的情景简直使他很难保持严肃，以致他竭尽全力才没有把他忍不住要笑的心情表现出来。他这样光着脊梁，血淋淋的，突然一下子从套着刑具的普通犯人提升到伯爵的高位和荣耀，在他看来，好像是荒唐至极了。他心里想：“现在我可是打扮得满身金光灿烂了，真的！我这个梦想和幻影的王国里的空头爵士居然又成了个空头伯爵——真像是羽毛未全的翅膀糊里糊涂地飞上了天！如果再像这样下去，我不久就会像一根五月柱似的，浑身挂满幻想的装饰和假的花彩。但是这些装饰虽然都没有什么价值，我为了赠给我的人的那番好意，还是要把它们当成宝贝。我这些可怜的、开玩笑的爵位并不是出于我的要求，就从一只洁净的手和一颗正直的心那里送来了，比起那些仗着奴颜婢膝，从那吝啬的、偏私的国王手里换来的真正的爵位，还要可贵哩。”

大家畏惧的休吾爵士把他的马转过头去，他赶着马飞跑出去的时候，那道活人的墙就沉默地分开，让他过去，然后又同样沉默地合拢来了。大家就是这样沉默地围着，谁也不敢大胆地说句话对犯人表示好感，或是称赞他，但是这没有关系，只要没有人骂他，就已经是表示十足的敬意了。有一个后来的人不明白当时的情况，对这个“骗子”说了一句嘲笑的话，并且还预备把一只死猫向他扔过去，但是马上就被在场的人不声不响地打倒，踢了出去，然后深沉的寂静又恢复了。

第二十九章　到伦敦去

亨顿受完枷刑之后，就被释放了，执行官命令他离开这个地方永远不许再回来。他的剑归还了他，骡子和毛驴也归还了他。他骑上骡子走了，国王跟在后面；人群肃然起敬地分开，让他们过去，他们走了之后，大家就分散了。

亨顿不久就陷入了沉思。一些意义重大的问题必须得到解答。他怎么办呢？上哪儿去呢？他必须到什么地方去获得有力的援助才行，否则他就只好放弃他的继承权，而且还要背着一个骗子的罪名。他到什么地方去才有希望得到这种有力的援助呢？什么地方啊，真是！这实在是个难题。后来他心里忽然起了一个念头，那好像是有点儿希望的想法——当然是微弱的希望中最微弱的希望，不过还是值得考虑，因为此外根本就没有任何有希望的办法。他记得安德鲁老头儿谈到过那年轻的国王如何如何善良，还说他对那些受了冤屈和遭遇不幸的人给予慷慨的保障。何不设法找他谈一谈，请求他申冤呢？啊，不错，但是像自己这么一个怪模怪样的穷光蛋，能有机会到庄严的国王面前吗？不要紧——这件事情且听其自然吧，船到桥头自然直。他是从军的老手，曾经常常想到一些临机应变的奇方妙计；不消说，他是能够想出办法来的。对了，他还是去伦敦吧。也许他父亲的老朋友汉弗莱·马洛爵士会帮他的忙——“好心的老汉弗莱爵士，前王的厨房还是马厩或其他什么的总管。”——迈尔斯记不起头衔究竟是什么了。现在他既然有了一个努力的方向，有了一个清清楚楚的追求目标，原来笼罩在他心灵上的羞辱和沮丧的暗影就烟消云散、随风飘去了。于是他就抬起头来，向四周张望一下，他惊讶地发觉自己已经走了很远，那村镇早已被他甩在后面了。国王低着头在他后面慢慢地跟着走，因为他也有他的心事，此刻正在沉思。亨顿心头刚刚产生的愉快情绪又蒙上了一层焦虑的云雾，这孩子在他过去短暂的生活中，在那大城市里除了遭到虐待和恼人的穷困而外，什么也没有享受过，现在他是否情愿再到那儿去呢？这个问题非问清楚不可，这是无法避免的，所以亨顿就勒住缰绳，大声问道：

“我忘记问我们究竟上哪儿去了。听您的命令吧，陛下。”

“到伦敦去！”

亨顿又继续往前走，他对这个回答非常满意——但是也觉得很惊奇。

他们一直走，路上并没有遭遇什么重大的事情。但是最后遭到了一件事。在二月十九日晚上十点钟左右，他们在万头攒动、熙熙攘攘、狂呼乱吼的人众中踏上了伦敦桥，那些人都喝够了啤酒，他们那些醉醺醺的面孔在那五花八门的无数火把的照耀之下，都显得特别清楚——正在这时候，某一位原先的公爵或是别的贵族的腐烂的头忽然掉下来，落在他们当中，恰好打中了亨顿的胳臂肘，然后跳落在那些乱跑乱窜的脚当中打起滚来。人们在世间的事业是多么虚幻无常，多么不可靠啊！——已故的那位好国王才死了三个礼拜，下葬还不过三天，而他煞费苦心从那些显要人物当中挑选出来给他这座伟大的桥做装饰品的东西已经在往下掉了。有一个市民踩着那个人头摔了一跤，把自己的头撞在前面一个人的背上，那个人就回过头来，把身边最顺手的一个人打倒在地，而他又立刻就被那个人的朋友打倒了。那正是最适于乱斗乱打的时候，因为第二天的盛典——加冕礼——的庆祝已经开始了。每个人都装满了一肚子烈酒和爱国的热情；五分钟之内，那场乱斗就占了很大的一块地盘；过了十几分钟，就波及了大约一英亩地的地方，结果就成为一场暴动了。这时候，亨顿和国王被那喧嚣拥挤的人潮冲散了，谁也找不着谁。那么，我们暂时就不谈他们吧。

第三十章　汤姆的进步

真正的国王穿着寒碜的衣服，吃着粗糙的饮食，一度被游民们殴打，受他们奚落，还跟盗贼和凶手们一同坐牢，大家都毫无偏见地把他叫作白痴和骗子；当他这样在各地流浪的时候，假王汤姆·康第却享受着一种完全不同的生活。

上次我们和他分手的时候，皇家生活对他刚刚开始展示光明的一面。这个光明的一面每天都越来越放出光彩，没过多久，就几乎成了一片阳光普照和无限欣喜的气象。他的恐惧消失了，焦虑也渐渐无影无踪了；他的窘态也离开了他，换了一副自然而大胆的风度。他把那代鞭童当作一个矿山来开采，所得的好处越来越大了。

他想要玩耍或是谈话的时候，就吩咐伊丽莎白公主和洁恩·格雷公主到他面前来，他和她们玩够了的时候，就打发她们出去，他那神气就像是向来习惯于这一套似的。这些高贵的人物临别时亲吻他的手，也不再使他慌张了。

他渐渐喜欢在晚间派头十足地被人引着去睡觉，早晨穿衣打扮经过烦琐而庄重的仪式。由一长串衣着华丽、光彩夺目的大官和卫士服侍着，堂而皇之地走去用餐，已经成为他一种很得意的痛快事情了；他因为过于欣赏这种排场，竟至把卫士增加了一倍，加到了一百人。他喜欢听见号角顺着长廊吹响的声音和远处响应的“给国王让路”的呼声。

他甚至还开始对坐朝很感兴趣，故意装作自己并不单只是摄政王的传声筒。他喜欢接见各国大使和他们的盛装的随从，倾听他们从那些称他为“兄弟”的有名的国王那里带来的亲切问候。啊，垃圾大院出身的汤姆·康第多么快乐！

他很欣赏他那些华丽的衣服，并且还添置了一些；他觉得他那四百个仆人还不够配合他的威风，又把他们增加了两倍。那些毕恭毕敬的官臣的阿谀之词渐渐成了他的悦耳的音乐。他始终是仁慈而宽厚的，对于一切被压迫的人，他始终是一个坚决的保卫者，他与那些不公平的法律进行不倦的斗争；但是在某些场合，他要是被触怒了，就会很严厉地对待一个伯爵，甚至对公爵也不客气，他把人家瞪一眼，就能使那个人发抖。有一次，他那严酷对待异教的“皇姊”玛丽公主和他据理力争，认为他赦免了那么多应该囚禁、绞死或烧死的人不是贤明的措施，还提醒他说，他们那已故的威严的父亲曾在同一时期内把六万个犯人关在监狱里，在其出色的统治时期里，曾把七万二千个小偷和强盗交给刽子手处死[22]。这孩子听了大为震怒，命令她回到自己的私室里去，恳求上帝取掉她胸膛里那块石头并给她换上一颗人心。

难道汤姆·康第从来就不惦念那可怜的真正的小王子，完全忘记了他那么和善地对待自己，满腔热忱地飞跑出去，替自己向王宫大门口那无礼的卫士报复的情景吗？不，在他起初在王宫里的那些日子，他日日夜夜很伤心地怀念着那失踪的王子，诚恳地渴望他回来，恢复他原有的权利和荣华。但是后来日子过得久了，王子并没有回来，汤姆心里就越来越沉醉于他那迷人的新生活，失踪的王子就渐渐在他脑子里淡去，以至于几乎无影无踪了；直到最后，即令那不幸的王子偶尔闯入他的记忆里，也就成了一个不受欢迎的幽灵，因为那使汤姆觉得有罪，感到惭愧。

汤姆那可怜的母亲和姐姐也经过同样的历程，从他心里跑出去了。起初他很伤心地惦念她们，为她们而悲痛，渴望着和她们相见；但是后来，他一想起她们不知在哪一天穿着又破又脏的衣服来找他，和他亲吻，以致拆穿他的西洋镜，把他从那高贵的地位拉下来，拖回去过那极度穷苦和卑贱的日子，再到贫民窟里去住——他一想起这些，就不禁浑身打冷战。最后她们几乎完全不再打搅他的心思了。于是他就觉得很满足，甚至还很欢喜；因为现在每逢她们那几副愁苦和怨望的面孔在他脑子里出现的时候，就使他觉得比蠕动的蛆虫还更加可鄙了。

二月十九日午夜时分，汤姆·康第在王宫里躺在他那阔气的床铺上，进入了梦乡，他身边有那些忠心的仆人卫护着，还有一切皇家的讲究排场，真是个幸福的孩子；因为明天就是预定给他举行庄严的加冕礼、使他当英国国王的日子了。在这同一时刻，真正的国王爱德华却又饿又渴，浑身油泥，又因长途旅行而疲劳不堪，身上穿着撕成了碎片的破衣服——这是他在那一场骚乱中的收获——他挤在一群看热闹的人当中站着，那些人正在兴致很浓地望着一队一队奔忙的工人从威斯敏斯特大教堂川流不息地跑进跑出，忙得像蚂蚁似的；他们正在为国王的加冕礼进行最后的准备工作哩。

第三十一章　新王出巡受贺

汤姆·康第第二天早晨醒来的时候，空中到处一片震耳的人声，远近四方都充满了这种声音。这在他听来，就像音乐一般，因为这表示，英国全国臣民都在兴高采烈地对这个盛大的日子表示由衷的欢迎。

不久，汤姆就在泰晤士河上又一次成了一个辉煌的御艇出巡的主要角色。按照自古以来的习惯，穿过伦敦城的“出巡受贺”的行列必须从伦敦塔出发，现在他就是到那儿去。

他到了那儿的时候，那个庄严的堡垒的四面好像忽然在无数地方裂开了似的，每一条裂缝中都跳出一条通红的火舌和一道白烟来；随后是一阵震耳欲聋的爆炸声，把人群的欢呼声都压倒了，震得地都发抖；火焰和白烟一次又一次出现，爆炸声一次又一次响起来，都迅速得令人惊奇，以至几分钟内那座古塔就被它自己放出的烟雾所笼罩了，只剩下最高的一层叫作白塔的塔顶，还可以看得见；白塔上插着旗子，在那一片浓烟之上突出地耸立着，就像一座山的高峰突出于浮云一般。

汤姆·康第穿着华丽的盛装，骑着一匹雄赳赳的战马，马身上的讲究装饰几乎垂到地上；他的“舅父”摄政王桑莫赛也骑着一匹类似的马，跟在他后面；国王的卫队披着晃亮的盔甲，在他两旁排成竖行；摄政王后面跟着一长串好像是无穷无尽的光彩夺目的贵族行列，都有他们的仆人随侍着；跟在他们后面来的是市长和市参议员的队伍，都穿着天鹅绒的大红袍，胸前挂着金链子；他们后面是伦敦各行会的职员和会员，也都穿得很讲究，举着各个行会的鲜艳旗帜。此外，在这个游行队伍中，还有那古老的名誉炮兵连，算是穿过城区时的特种仪仗队——这个部队当时已经有三百年的历史了，它是英国唯一享有特权、不受国会命令支配的队伍（这种特权它现在还享受着）。这真是壮丽的场景，队伍威风凛凛地从那万头攒动的人群中走过的时候，沿途一直都受到欢呼和祝贺。史官记载道：“国王入城时，民众夹道欢迎，都向他祝福，致欢迎词，或是向他欢呼，说些亲切的话，还有各种证明百姓热爱君主的表示；国王满面喜色，抬起头来向远处的市民微笑示意，并对身边的观众说些非常亲切的话，这就是表示他接受百姓的一片好意，对所有祝福他的人，他都表达了谢意。有些人说‘愿上帝保佑陛下’，他就回答说，‘愿上帝保佑你们大家！’接着还说一声‘诚心诚意地感谢你们’。百姓听到他们的国王这种仁爱的回答，看见他那亲切的表情，都感到万分欢喜。”

芬秋奇街上有一个“服装华贵的美貌幼童”站在一个台子上欢迎国王陛下入城。他的颂词最后一节是这样的：

御驾光临，万众欢迎；

欢迎御驾，情意难言；

口舌欢迎，心也欢迎；

天佑吾王，福寿无边。

民众发出一阵欢呼，齐声和唱那孩子念出的颂词。汤姆·康第向四处注视着那波涛汹涌的大海似的一片热切的面孔，他心中就充满了狂喜的情绪；他觉得人生最有意义的事情莫过于当国王，做全国崇拜的偶像。随后他就一眼望见远处有他两个垃圾大院的玩伴，都穿得破破烂烂——其中有一个是他当初模仿的那个朝廷里的海军大臣，另一个是同一假想中的御寝大臣；于是他那得意的情绪就更加高涨了。啊，假如他们现在还能认识他，那多么好！假如他们知道当初那个贫民窟和背巷里的被人嘲笑的假国王现在成了真正的国王，还有那些煊赫的公爵和亲王做他的服服帖帖的臣仆，整个英国都拜倒在他脚下，那该是多么无法形容的荣耀！但是他不得不抑制自己的欲望，因为他如果被那两个孩子认出来，结果就难免使他遭受意想不到的损失；因此他就把头转开，让那两个肮脏的孩子继续欢呼，继续说那些奉承国王的话，毫不怀疑他们所欢迎的对象有什么问题。

人群中时而发出一阵喊声：“给赏钱呀！给赏钱呀！”汤姆就响应这种要求，向周围撒出一把亮晃晃的新钱币去，让大家抢夺。

史官记载道：“城内市民在格雷斯秋奇街西头那个大鹰招牌前面建了一座华丽的拱门，拱门下面搭了一个戏台，从街道的一边横跨到对面。这是个历史人物展览台，上面陈列着国王最近几代的先人。台上有约克皇族的伊丽莎白，坐在一朵巨大的白玫瑰花当中，花瓣在她周围形成精致的裙褶；她旁边是亨利七世，从一朵巨大的红玫瑰花里伸出身子来，姿势也和她一样；这对皇家配偶是手挽着手的，他们的结婚戒指很显著地露在外面。从那两朵红白玫瑰花上伸出一枝花茎，伸到第二层台子上，上面坐着亨利八世，他的身子是从一朵红白两色的玫瑰花里伸出来的，旁边有新王的母亲洁恩·赛莫尔的造像。从这对配偶身上又发出一条枝，伸到第三层台子上，那上面坐着爱德华六世本人的造像，穿着国王的盛装坐在宝座上。全部展览台都有红白两种玫瑰花的花环包围着。”

这个奇妙而艳丽的展览使狂欢的人们极感兴趣，因此他们欢声如雷，把那个用歌功颂德的诗句来解释这些人物的小孩子的微小声音完全压倒了。但是汤姆·康第并不觉得难过，因为这种忠诚的吼声无论它的性质究竟怎样，在他听来都比任何诗歌更为悦耳。汤姆随便把他那快乐而年轻的面孔向哪一边转，大家都看出那造像和他本人是非常相似的，他自己简直就是那个造像的一份活标本，于是新的喝彩声又像旋风似的一阵一阵爆发出来。

盛大的游行队伍继续前进又前进，从一座又一座的庆祝拱门底下走过。道旁还陈列着连续不断的许多壮观的、含有象征意义的连环画，使人看了眼花缭乱；这些连环画每一套都代表这位小国王的某种品德、才能或特长，含有表扬的意思。“在契普赛街上，从头到尾，家家户户都在屋檐下和窗户上挂着旗子和飘带，最讲究的绒毡、毛料和金丝缎垂在街道两旁作为装饰——这都是那些商店里面的大量财富的象征；别的街道也和这条大街一样壮观，有的甚至还超过了。”

“原来这许多珍奇宝贵的东西都是摆出来欢迎我的——欢迎我的呀！”汤姆·康第喃喃地说。

这个假国王脸上因兴奋而发红，眼睛里闪着光，完全陶醉在愉快的情绪中，有一种飘飘然的感觉。这时候，他正待举起手来，再抛出一把赏钱，恰好一眼瞥见一副苍白而吃惊的面孔，从人群的第二排里拼命探出来，用那双专注的眼睛盯住他。一阵极不愉快的惊慌失措的感觉侵袭了他的全身，他认出了他的母亲！于是他立刻就把手往上一举，掌心向外，遮住眼睛——这是他老早就有的一种不由自主的动作，本来是由一件早已忘记的事情引起的，后来就习惯成自然了。一转眼的工夫，她已经从人群中挤出来，冲过卫士的警戒线，跑到他身边了。她抱着他的腿，在它上面到处亲吻，一面还大声喊道：“啊，我的孩子，我的心肝宝贝！”她抬头望着他，脸上因欢喜和慈爱而改变神色了。国王的卫队里有一个军官马上就大骂一声，把她揪住，用他那强壮的胳臂猛推了一下，把她推得一摇一摆地滚回原处去了。这件惨事发生的时候，汤姆·康第嘴里正在说：“我不认识你呀，你这个女人！”但是他看见她受到这种侮辱，良心上非常难受；后来人群把她吞没，使她看不见他的时候，她转过头来望了他最后一眼；看她那样子，似乎非常委屈、非常伤心，因此他突然感到一阵耻辱，把他的得意情绪完全化成了灰烬，他那盗窃而来的国王的威风也烟消云散了。他的荣华一下子变得一钱不值，好像一些碎布片似的从他身上脱落下去了。

出巡的队伍继续前进再前进，经过的地方越来越华丽，民众的欢呼也越来越响亮；但是这一切对于汤姆·康第毫无作用，好像根本没有这回事一般。他什么也没有看见，什么也没有听见。国王的身份已经失去了光彩，失去了甜蜜的滋味，那些威风凛凛的排场已经成了一种羞辱。悔恨正在啃着他的良心。他说：“但愿上帝让我摆脱这种束缚吧！”

他不知不觉地恢复了他最初被迫做了国王的那些日子里的说话语调。

辉煌的出巡队伍继续前进，像一条发光的绵延不断的长蛇似的，穿过这座古雅的城市里那些弯弯曲曲的街巷，从那些欢呼的人群中走过；但是国王始终骑在马上低着头，无精打采，他只看见他母亲的脸和她脸上那副委屈的神色。

“给赏钱呀！给赏钱呀！”这种喊声钻进了一双对此毫不在意的耳朵里。

“英王爱德华万岁！”这种呼声好像把大地都震动了，但是国王仍然没有反应。他听到这种呼声，也不过是像听见远处随风飘来的波涛声一样，因为它被另一种更近的声音压倒了——那是他自己胸膛中那颗兴师问罪的良心所发出来的声音，这个声音老是重复那一句可耻的话：“我不认识你呀，你这个女人！”

这句话刺痛着假国王的心，正如一个用阴谋诡计害死了自己的朋友的人听到死者的丧钟的时候，良心上受到谴责一般。

每到一处，都有新的壮丽场面展现出来，新的奇观和新的奇景在眼前迸发；憋了很久的欢呼像放炮似的爆发出来，等待着的群众从他们嗓子里倾泻出新的狂喜；但是国王毫无表示，他所听见的只有他那不安的胸膛里不断呻吟的那个谴责的声音。

后来群众脸上的喜色稍微起了一点变化，换上了几分关切的表情；喝彩的声音也显而易见地减弱了。摄政王很快就注意到这种情况，他也很快就找出了原因。他赶着马跑到国王身边，在鞍子上深深鞠躬致敬，一面说：

“陛下，现在是不宜于幻想的。老百姓看见您低着头，郁郁不乐，会把这当成不好的预兆哩。请您听我的劝告吧，皇家的御颜要像太阳那样发出光来，照耀这种不祥之气，把它驱散。请您抬起头来，向百姓微笑吧。”

公爵一面这么说，一面向左右撒出一把钱币，然后退回原位。假国王机械地依照公爵的吩咐行事。他的微笑是没有感情成分的，但是大家的眼睛都离得远，并且也不仔细看，所以很少有人能看出破绽。他向百姓答礼的时候，他那戴着翎毛的头一点一点的，显得非常文雅而慈祥；他手里撒出去的赏钱相当慷慨，很适合国王的身份。于是群众的焦虑就消失了，大家的欢呼声又像原先那样响亮地爆发出来了。

但是临到出巡将近结束的时候，公爵不得不再一次驱马上前去，提醒国王。他低声说：

“啊，令人敬畏的君主！请您甩掉这种扫兴的神情吧，全世界的眼睛都在望着您哪。”然后他又极为烦躁地接着说了一句，“那个疯子叫花婆真该死！就是她搅扰了陛下的心情。”

那漂亮的角色把一双无精打采的眼睛转过去望着公爵，用一种死气沉沉的声调说：

“她本是我的母亲呀！”

“我的天哪！”摄政王一面拉着缰绳把他的马退回原位，一面呻吟着说，“那个预兆果然灵验，他又发疯了！”

第三十二章　加冕大典

我们现在且倒退几小时，在这值得纪念的加冕大典的日子，清早四点钟到威斯敏斯特大教堂去看看吧。我们并不是没有同伴；因为那时候虽然还是夜里，我们却已经看见那些点着火把的看台上挤满了人，他们都情愿在那儿规规矩矩地坐着，等待七八个钟头，一直等到他们可以看到国王加冕的时候——这个大典也许是他们终身难得再看到的。是呀，自从清早三点钟预告的炮声响过之后，伦敦和威斯敏斯特就忙乱起来了。那时候已经有一群一群的没有官爵的阔人拥进那些专为他们保留的看台的入口，这些阔人是早就花钱打点好了，可以到看台上找座位的。

时间慢慢地熬过，相当沉闷。骚动已经停止了一段时间，因为每个看台早就挤满了。现在我们可以坐下来，逍遥自在地看一看，想一想。我们到处可以透过那教堂里暗淡的微光，瞥见许多看台和楼厢的一部分，每个都挤满了人，这些看台和楼厅的其他部分被隔在当中的柱子和建筑上的突出部分遮住了。我们看得见北边的大袖廊的全部，空着等英国的特权人物来坐。另外还看得见那宽大的教坛，铺着材料讲究的地毯，国王的宝座就摆在那上面。宝座占据着教坛的正当中，有一个四级的台子把它垫高了一些。宝座里放着一块粗糙的扁石头——这就是斯康石[23]，从前有许多世代的苏格兰王坐在那上面加冕，所以后来它成了一块神圣的石头，给英国国王做同一用途也很够资格了。宝座和它的踏脚凳上都蒙着金丝缎。

大教堂里寂静无声，火把在昏暗之中闪烁着，时间慢得难受地熬过去。但是姗姗来迟的晨光终于露面了，于是大家熄掉火把，柔和的阳光把教堂里各处宽大的空间都照遍了。这座雄伟建筑的全部轮廓现在都看得清楚了，但是还有些朦朦胧胧、如梦如幻的感觉，因为太阳被薄云微微遮住了。

七点钟的时候，那呆滞的单调气氛第一次被打破了。因为时钟刚敲过七点，头一个贵族夫人就走进了大袖廊，她的服装若以华丽而论，简直像所罗门王穿的一样；有一位穿着缎子和天鹅绒衣服的官员把她引到她的专席上，同时另外有一位像他一样的官员提起这位贵妇的长裙在她背后跟着，等她坐下之后，又替她把这条衣裙叠在她膝上。然后他又依照她的旨意把她的踏脚凳放好，再把她的花冠放在最适当的地方，好让她在贵族们一齐复冠的时候，顺手就可以拿到。

这时候，贵族妇女们像一道金光闪闪的流水似的源源而来，许多穿缎子衣服的官员们到处来来往往，照顾她们入座，把她们伺候得舒舒服服。现在的场面是相当热闹了，处处都有活动和生气，处处都是变幻的色彩。过了一会儿，又是满场寂静，因为贵族妇女们通通来到，各自就座了——这是一大片人的花朵，五光十色，非常耀眼，她们满身的钻石连成一片，活像天上的银河。这里有各种年龄的人：有肤色棕黄、皱纹满面的白发贵族寡妇，她们可以一代一代地往上回溯，还记得起理查三世加冕的光景和那早已被人忘却的年代里那些动荡的日子；另外还有一些漂亮的中年妇女；还有一些可爱的、娴雅的年轻贵妇；还有一些温柔美丽的年轻姑娘，她们两眼发光，面容清秀，到了举行大典的时候，她们也许会把镶着宝石的花冠戴成古怪的样子，因为这种事情对她们还是生疏的，她们的兴奋不免使她们的举动很不自然。但是也许不会这样，因为这些少女们梳头的时候，都特别注意把头发梳成适当的样式，以便号声一响，很快就可以把花冠恰到好处地戴在头上。

我们已经看到这些成排坐在一起的一大片贵族妇女都是满身钻石，还看到这是一个了不起的场面——但是现在我们才当真要感到惊奇了。在九点钟左右，天上的云忽然散开，一道阳光划破那柔和的天空，慢慢地顺着那一排一排的女宾照射过来；凡是它射到之处，都像火焰似的，放出多种颜色的耀眼的光彩；于是我们就好像浑身触了电似的，直到指尖都因这个场面所引起的惊奇和美丽的感觉而隐隐地震动起来！随后有一个来自东方某一偏远地方的特使和全体外国大使们一同前进，走过这道阳光，他周身放射出来的一闪一闪的光彩简直使人眼花缭乱，以至我们惊讶得连气都透不过来；因为他从头顶到脚跟都戴满了宝石，他稍微动一下都会向四面八方洒出一片跳跃的光彩。

闲话少叙，言归正传。时间不知不觉地过去了——一个钟头——两个钟头——两个半钟头，然后深沉的隆隆炮声报告国王和他那堂皇的队伍终于来到了；于是等待的人们都很欢喜。大家都知道随后还有一阵耽搁，因为国王还要经过一番打扮，穿好礼袍来参加这个隆重的典礼；但是这一段拖延的时间是不会寂寞的，全国的贵族穿着派头十足的礼袍，就在这时候入场。官员们把他们按照礼节引到座位上，还把他们的冠冕放在身边顺手的地方；同时看台上那许多人都兴致勃勃，因为他们大多数都是第一次看到一些公爵、伯爵和男爵，这些头衔已经流传五百年了。后来这些贵族通通坐定了之后，在看台上和一切有利位置上就可以把他们看得清清楚楚；这个豪华的场面实在是很好看，而且是令人难忘的。

这时候那几位穿着法衣、戴着法冠的教会首领和他们的随从依次走上教坛，坐上各自的座位；他们后面跟着摄政王和他的大臣，再后面还来了一队钢盔钢甲的皇家卫队。

又等了一段时间；一声号角之后，突然响起了一阵喜气洋洋的奏乐声，于是汤姆·康第穿着一件金丝缎的长袍在门口出现，走上了教坛。全体在场的人都站起来，随即就举行了承认国王的仪式。

然后一首庄严的赞美歌响起，它洪亮的声浪扫过大教堂全场；汤姆·康第就在这阵歌声的先导和欢迎之下，被引到宝座上去了。古老的仪式进行着，那种庄严的气氛给人很深的印象，观众都定睛注视着。仪式越来越接近结束的时候，汤姆·康第脸色渐渐发白，而且越来越白得厉害，一阵不断地逐渐加深的苦恼和沮丧的情绪笼罩着他的心灵，笼罩着他那懊悔不安的良心。

后来，终于临到最后一项仪式了。坎特伯雷大主教把英国的王冠从垫子上捧起来，举在那发抖的假国王头上。同时在一瞬之间，宽大的袖廊上闪过一片彩虹似的光辉，因为那贵族群中每个人都动作整齐地举起了一顶冠冕，在各自的头上举着——大家都保持着这种姿势不动了。

深沉的寂静遍布了整个大教堂。正在这令人难忘的时刻，一个惊人的鬼影闯入场内来了——这个鬼影在全场聚精会神的人们当中没有被发现，直到后来，他突然出现了，顺着中间那条大过道往前走。那是个男孩子，没戴帽子，鞋袜都不像样子，身上穿着一套到处破成了布片的粗布平民衣服。他庄严地举起手来，那种神情与他那副满身油污的可怜相是很不相称的，同时他发出了一声警告。

“我不许你们把英国的王冠戴在那个假冒的国王头上，我才是国王！”

立刻就有几个愤怒的人伸手抓住了这个孩子；但在同一瞬间，汤姆·康第穿着他那一身帝王的服装，迅速地向前走了一步，用响亮的声音喊道：

“快放了他，不许乱动！他的确是国王！”

一种惊慌失措的气氛扫遍全场，有一部分人从座位上站起来，用惶惑的神色瞪着眼睛互相望着，再望一望这一场戏里面的两个主角，他们的神情好像那些恍恍惚惚的人，简直不知道自己究竟是清醒的，还是睡着觉在做梦哩。摄政王也和别人一样吃惊，但是他很快就恢复了镇静，用一种权威的声调喊道：

“不要听陛下的话吧，他的毛病又发作了，把那野孩子抓起来！”

有人正要听从他的命令，但是假国王跺着脚大声喝道：

“抗命者死！不许动他，他是国王！”

伸出去的手又缩了回去，全场都吓瘫痪了，谁也不动，谁也不说话；事实上，逢着这种稀奇而惊人的紧张场面，谁也不知道该怎么办，或是说什么话才好。大家心里正在极力恢复正常的时候，那孩子沉着地继续往前走，他表现出高贵的风度和自信的神态；他从开始就没有踌躇过；大家心里乱成一团，还在无可奈何地胡思乱想的时候，他却走上了教坛，假国王满脸喜色地跑过去迎接他，在他面前跪下来说：

“啊，国王陛下，让可怜的汤姆·康第首先向您宣誓效忠吧，让我向您说，‘请您戴上王冠，恢复王位吧！’”

摄政王的眼睛严厉地盯着这新来的孩子的脸，但是他严厉的神色马上就消失了，换上了一副惊奇的表情。其他的大官也出现了这种现象。他们互相望了一眼，出于一种共同的、不知不觉的冲动，后退了一步。每个人心里都起了同样的念头：

“这么相像真是奇怪啊！”

摄政王不知如何是好地沉思了一两分钟，然后以严肃而尊敬的态度说：

“请您恕我冒昧，我想问您几个问题，都是……”

“我可以回答，公爵。”

公爵就问了许多问题，有关于朝廷的，有关于先王的，有关于王子和公主们的。这孩子都回答得很正确，而且毫不迟疑。他把宫里那些举行朝见的房子和前王所住的房间和太子的房间都描述了一番。

真是奇怪，真是神妙！是呀，这未免太不可思议了——凡是听见了的人都是这么说。形势开始转变了，汤姆·康第的希望也就随着高涨起来，但是摄政王摇摇头说：

“这固然是非常神奇——可是这些事毕竟没有什么了不起，国王陛下也能说得清楚的。”汤姆·康第一听这句话，并且听见自己还是被称为国王，心里就很发愁，他觉得他的希望垮了。“这都不能算是证明。”摄政王又添了这么一句。

现在形势又在迅速地转向，实在是快得很——但是转变的方向错了；这把可怜的汤姆·康第搁浅在宝座上，把另外那个孩子冲进大海去。摄政王沉思了一会儿——他摇摇头——后来他不由自主地想道：“如果老让这么一个不幸的谜解不开，那对国家很有危险，对我们大家都有危险；结果可能使国家分裂，使王位颠覆。”于是他转过身去说：

“汤玛斯爵士，逮住这个——不，住手！”他脸上露出了喜色，随即他就对这个衣衫褴褛的候补国王提出这么一个问题：

“国玺在什么地方？只要能把这个问题回答得对，就可以解开这个谜了，因为只有真正的前太子才能回答得对。这么小的东西上可悬着宝座和王朝的命运呢！”

有这个想法很幸运，令人开心。大臣们在他们那个圈子里互相望一望，大家眼睛里都流露出赞成的神色，表示无声的喝彩，这就足见他们的看法都是那样。是的，除了真正的王子，谁也不能解开国玺失踪这个难解的谜——这个倒霉的小骗子是有人教过他不少的事情，可是遇到这个难关，他那一套就不灵了，因为连教他的人自己也不能回答这个问题——啊，妙极了，真是妙极了：现在我们很快就可以把这个麻烦和危险的问题解决了！于是大家纷纷点头，心里都很满意地微笑着，他们指望看到这个糊涂的孩子会露出张皇失措的、犯罪的神色，吓得不知如何是好。但是他们所看到的完全不是这么回事，这真使他们大为吃惊——他们听见他立刻就用自信的、从从容容的声音回答，都觉得非常惊奇。他说：

“这个谜根本没有什么难解。”然后他对谁也不说一声客气话，就转过脸去发出一个命令，他那自自然然的态度表示他是个惯于对人下命令的人，“圣约翰勋爵，你进宫去到我的房间里——因为别人对那个地方都不如你清楚——在靠近地板的地方，离那扇通着前厅的门最远的左边那个角落里，你在墙上会找到一个黄铜的钉头形的装饰；你按它一下，就会有一个小宝石箱敞开，这是连你都不知道的——不但是你，除了我自己和替我设计的那个可靠的工匠以外，世界上再没有谁知道。你第一眼看到的就是国玺——把它拿到这里来。”

在场的人一听这些话，都觉得惊奇，尤其是看见这个小叫花子毫不迟疑地指出这位贵族来，一点也不怕弄错，并且还很自然地直呼他的名字，令人信服地显出一辈子就认识他的神气，大家就更加觉得惊奇了。这个突如其来的命令，几乎吓得这位贵族要服从了。他甚至动了一下，好像是要走的样子，但是他赶快恢复了镇定的态度，脸上红了一下，表示承认自己的错误。汤姆·康第转过脸来向他严厉地说：

“你为什么还要迟疑？难道没有听见国王的命令吗？快去！”

圣约翰勋爵深深地行了一个鞠躬——大家看出了他这个鞠躬是特别小心而含糊的，因为他不是向这两个国王之中任何一个行礼，而是对着两者之间那块中立地带行的——然后他就告辞了。

现在那一群华丽的大官里面的组成分子开始移动起来，动得很慢，几乎看不出，但是持续不断地在动——好像我们在一个慢慢转动的万花筒里所看到的情形一样，那里面一个艳丽的花团的组成分子散开，与另一个花团结合起来——在目前这个场面中，这种移动就使汤姆·康第周围站着的那一群光彩夺目的角色解体了，又在那个新来的孩子附近聚拢了。汤姆·康第几乎是独自站着的。随后是一阵短时间的惴惴不安和焦心等待——在这段时间里，连那留在汤姆·康第身边的少数胆小的人也渐渐鼓足了勇气，一个一个地溜到多数那边去了。于是汤姆·康第穿着他那帝王的礼袍，戴着满身钻石，终于完全孤单地站着，与整个世界隔绝了。现在他成了个孤家寡人，占着一大片空地，真是意味深长。

现在，大家看见圣约翰勋爵回来了。他顺着当中的过道往前走的时候，大家的兴趣非常浓厚，因此广大的会众当中的低声谈话停息了，随后是一阵深沉的寂静，大家静得连气都不敢出；在这种气氛中，他的脚步轻轻地发出一阵沉闷的、遥远的声响。他一直往前走，每个人的眼睛都盯着他。

他走到教坛上，踌躇了一会儿，然后向汤姆·康第走过去，行了个深深的鞠躬礼，说：

“陛下，国玺不在那里！”

那一群吓得脸色惨白的大臣马上就从那个要求王位的衣着肮脏的孩子身边连忙散开，即令是躲开一个害瘟疫的病人，也不能比这更快了。片刻之间，他就独自站着，谁也不跟他接近，谁也不支持他了，于是他就成了大家轻视和愤怒的眼光的焦点。摄政王凶恶地喊道：

“把这个叫花子撵到街上去，拿鞭子打着他游街吧——这个小流氓不值得我们再理会了！”

卫队的军官急忙往前去执行命令，但是汤姆·康第挥手把他们挡开，一面说：

“回去！谁敢动他，就处死刑！”

摄政王狼狈到了极点，他对圣约翰勋爵说：

“你仔细找过了吗？——不过问这个毫无好处。这似乎太奇怪了。无关紧要的小东西是可能失踪的，谁也不会因此吃惊；但是像英国的国玺这么个大东西怎么会不见了，还没有谁能找得出一点线索呢？——那么大个金的圆饼子——”

汤姆·康第眼睛里闪出光来，他连忙走上前去，大声嚷道：

“行了，这就够了！是圆的吗？——很厚吗？——是不是上面刻着字母和花纹？——对吗？啊，现在我才知道，你们那么急得要命、大惊小怪地要找的这个国玺，原来是这么个东西呀！要是你们早给我说明了是个什么样子，那你们在三个礼拜以前就找到了。我清清楚楚地知道它在什么地方，不过并不是我把它放在那里——起先不是我放的。”

“那么是谁放的，陛下？”摄政王问道。

“就是那边站着的人——英国的合法国王。让他自己告诉你们放在什么地方吧——那么你们就会相信他是本来就知道的。您想一想吧，国王——动动脑筋吧——那天您穿着我那身破衣服，从王宫里冲出去，要处罚那个侮辱我的卫兵，临走之前干的最后一件事情就是收起国玺，那是您最后干的事情呀。”

随后是一阵沉寂，没有任何动作或是声音来打搅，所有的人都把眼睛注视着那个新来的孩子；他垂着头、皱着眉头站着，从他的脑子里乱七八糟的一大堆毫无价值的回忆中追寻一件小小的、不可捉摸的事情，这件事要是记清楚了，就可以使他登王位——如果想不起来，他就只好永远是现在这样——当个叫花子和流浪儿。时间一点一滴地过去了——慢慢熬过了好几分钟——但是这孩子始终不声不响地拼命在想，毫无表示。最后他叹了一口气，慢慢地摇摇头，用颤抖的嘴唇和沮丧的声音说：

“我回想了当初的情形——通通想过了——可是始终想不起国玺的事。”他停了一会儿，然后抬起头来望着，温和而有尊严地说，“各位大臣和侍从，你们如果为了你们的合法的国王提不出这个证据来，就剥夺他的继承权，我也许不能阻挡你们，因为我毫无权力。但是……”

“啊，我的国王，这太傻了，简直是发疯！”汤姆·康第惊慌地说，“等一等！——再想想！不要放弃！——这事情还没有失败！并且也决不许让它失败呀！您听我说吧——每个字都听清楚——我要把那天早晨的事情说一遍，每样事情都照当初的经过说。我们谈了一阵话——我给您谈到我的姐姐南恩和白特——啊，对了，您还记得；我又谈到我那老奶奶——还谈到垃圾大院的孩子们玩的那些粗野的游戏——对了，这些事情您也都记得；好极了，再听我说下去吧，您什么都会想得起来的。您给了我吃的和喝的，还大开王子的恩典，把仆人打发出来，免得我因那低微的出身在他们面前感到羞耻了——啊，对了，这个您也记得。”

汤姆把当初的详细情形一样样说出来对证，另外那个孩子点头表示同意的时候，在场的广大听众和那些大官都莫名其妙地瞪着眼睛望着他们。这些话听起来好像是真有其事，可是一个王子和一个乞丐居然会凑到一起，这种不可能的事情究竟是怎么发生的呢？现在这么些人在一处，弄得这样莫名其妙，这样感到兴致勃勃，这样目瞪口呆，真是从来没有见过的事情。

“王子，我们为了好玩儿，彼此换了衣服。然后我们在一面大镜子前面站着，我们俩长得一模一样，所以我们都说好像没有换过衣服似的——对，您还记得这个。后来您发现那个卫兵扭伤了我的手——瞧！就在这儿，我现在还不能写字哪，手指头老弯不过来。陛下一看见这个，马上就跳起来，发誓要向那个卫兵报仇，于是就往门口跑——您走过一张桌子——您叫作国玺的那个东西就放在那张桌子上——您把它一下子拿起来，很着急地东张西望，好像是要找个地方把它藏起来——您一眼看见了……”

“得了，这就够了！——多谢上帝！”那要求王位的衣衫褴褛的孩子万分兴奋地喊道，“快去吧，我的圣约翰勋爵——你到墙上挂着的一副米兰盔甲的护臂里就可以找到国玺了！”

“对了，我的国王！对了！”汤姆·康第喊道，“现在英国的权杖归您了。如果再有谁否认，那就不如叫他生来就是个哑巴！快去吧，圣约翰爵士，让你的腿长上翅膀吧！”

现在全场的人都站起来了，大家都深感不安，非常着急，兴奋得要命，几乎因此神经错乱了。台下和台上都爆发了一阵震耳的、疯狂似的谈话声，一时大家都只听见身边的人向自己耳朵里嚷出来的话，或是自己向别人耳朵里嚷出去的话；此外谁也不知道别的什么事情，什么也听不见，什么也不在意。时间在不知不觉之中飞快地过去了——谁也不知道究竟过了多久。后来终于全场鸦雀无声，同时圣约翰走上教坛，手里拿着国玺，高高举起。于是全场就欢呼起来了。

“真正的国王万岁！”

欢呼声和乐器的嘈杂声在空中震动了五分钟，同时一片飞舞的手巾弄得满场像下雪一般。在这阵狂欢中，一个衣衫褴褛的孩子站在那宽大的教坛的中心，他是全英国最引人注目的人物，满脸绯红，喜气洋洋，非常得意，全国的大臣跪在他周围。

然后全体起立，汤姆·康第大声喊道：

“啊，我的国王，现在请您收回这身国王的礼袍，把那些破烂衣服还给您的可怜的奴仆汤姆吧。”

摄政王高声地说：

“把这个小流氓的衣服剥掉，给他关到塔里去吧。”

但真正的新王说：

“我不赞成这么办。如果不是他帮忙，我就不能恢复王位哩——谁也不许动手，不许伤害他。至于您呢，我的好舅舅，我的摄政王，您这种行为对这个可怜的孩子未免太忘恩负义，因为我听说他已经把您封为公爵了。”——摄政王涨红了脸——“但是他并不是国王，所以您那个漂亮头衔现在有什么价值呢？明天您再请求批准这个爵位吧——要托他替您申请才行——否则您就不算什么公爵，仍旧只是一个伯爵。”

桑莫赛公爵挨了这顿骂，连忙从国王面前退后了一点。国王转过身来向着汤姆，很和蔼地对他说：

“可怜的孩子，国玺藏在什么地方，连我自己都想不起来了，你怎么反而记得呢？”

“啊，我的国王，那很容易，因为我把它使了好几天。”

“你使了几天，还说不出它在什么地方吗？”

“我不知道他们要的是这个东西呀。他们并没有说明它是个什么样子哩，陛下。”

“那么你使它做什么呢？”

汤姆脸上的血液悄悄地升上来了，他把眼睛朝下看，一声不响。

“大胆说吧，好孩子，不用害怕，”国王说，“你用英国的国玺干什么来着？”

汤姆慌张得可怜，结结巴巴地说了一会儿，才说出口来：

“用它砸栗子！”

可怜的孩子啊，他这句话引起的一阵山崩似的狂笑几乎把他冲倒了。但是如果还有谁心里有点儿怀疑，不相信汤姆·康第不是英国国王，认为他熟悉皇家的那些尊贵的东西，现在一听他这句回答，就完全把怀疑扫清了。

同时那件华丽的礼袍已经从汤姆身上换到国王身上，把他的破衣服完全遮盖住了。然后加冕礼又继续举行，真正的国王接受了涂油的仪式，王冠也戴在他头上了，同时礼炮的轰隆声把这个消息报告给全城，于是整个伦敦城似乎是被欢呼喝彩的声音所震撼了。

第三十三章　爱德华当了国王

迈尔斯·亨顿在卷入伦敦桥上那一场骚乱之前，他那副样子已经够好看的了——他从那里面摆脱出来之后，就更加好看了。他卷入纠纷的时候，身上的钱本来就很少，出来的时候就分文没有了。扒手把他最后剩下的几个钱通通掏光了。

但是不要紧，只要他能找到他那个孩子就行了。他是个军人，所以他并没有乱七八糟地找，而是首先动脑筋，把寻找的计划安排妥当。

这孩子必然会怎么办呢？他必然要到什么地方去呢？

嗯——迈尔斯推想着——他当然会回到他的老窝去，因为那是神经不健全的人的本能，这种人到了无家可归和没人理睬的时候，一定是回老窝，也跟神经健全的人一样。可是他的老窝在什么地方呢？从他那一身破衣服，从那个好像认识他并且还自称是他父亲的那个下流的坏蛋，都可以看出他的家是在伦敦的某一个最穷、最糟的地区。去找他是不是困难，或是要很久呢？不，大概是很容易的，用不着多久就能找到。他不用去找那孩子，只要找成堆的人就行；他迟早一定会找到他那个小朋友。围在一大堆人或是一小堆人当中，这孩子还是会像往常那样，自称是国王，那些肮脏的家伙一定会作弄他，惹他生气，借此拿他开心。然后迈尔斯·亨顿就要把这些人打伤几个，再把这个受他保护的孩子抱走，对他说些亲密的话来安慰他，使他高兴，他们俩从此以后就再也不分离了。

于是迈尔斯就动身去寻找。他在那些偏僻的巷子和肮脏的街道上钻进钻出，寻找成群成堆的人，找了一个钟头又一个钟头，结果他找到无数处成堆的人，可是始终没有那孩子的踪影。这使他大为惊奇，但是并没有使他丧气。在他看来，他的寻找计划并没有什么不对，唯一估计错误的地方就是寻找的时间大概是要拖长了，而他原来是指望着只需要短时间就行的。

后来终于到了天亮的时候，他已经走了好几英里路，查找过许多处成群的人，但是唯一的结果就是把他累得筋疲力尽，而且又饿又困。他很想吃点早饭，可是没有办法。讨饭吃他又不情愿；至于当掉他那把剑，他又会联想到那是丧失体面的事情；他的衣服倒是可以少穿一点——不错，可是那种衣服如果也能卖得出去的话，那就连出卖疾病也容易找到主顾了。

直到中午，他还在到处游荡——这时候是混在那些跟在国王出巡的队伍后面的乌七八糟的人当中，因为他推断这个堂皇的场面对他那个小疯子的吸引力一定很大。他跟着这个游行队伍，穿过伦敦许多迂回的街巷，一直跟到威斯敏斯特宫和大教堂。他混在那些聚集在游行队伍附近的群众当中到处游荡了很久，走得很累，心里懊丧而烦乱，后来他终于想着心事离开了人群，打算想个办法，修改他的寻找计划。过了一会儿，他从沉思中清醒过来，才发现城市已经被他甩在后面很远，天色也渐近黄昏了。他离河很近，并且是在乡间，那是讲究的乡村别墅所在的地区——这种地方对他所穿的那种衣服是不大欢迎的。

天气一点也不冷，他就在一道篱笆背风的一面躺在地上来休息休息，想想事情。困倦很快就控制了他的神经，远处微弱的轰隆炮声随风飘到他耳朵里来了，他就自言自语地说：“新王加冕了。”随即他就入了梦乡。在这以前，他已经有三十多个钟头没有睡眠和休息了。一直到第二天上午快过了一半的时候，他才醒过来。

他又瘸又僵地爬起来，饿得半死，勉强到河里去洗了洗脸，喝了一升来水，顶住饥饿，又很吃力地往威斯敏斯特宫走，一面嘟哝着埋怨自己耽搁了这么大的工夫。饥饿逼着他想出了一个新办法：他要设法找汉弗莱·马洛老爵士谈谈，向他借几个马克，再——可是目前只要打这么个主意就行了；且等这第一步实现了之后，就会有充分的时间来扩大这个计划。

快到十一点钟的时候，他走近了王宫。虽然他身边有许多衣冠华丽的人往同一方向走，他却并不见得不引人注意——他那一身服装帮了他的忙。他仔细打量这些人的面孔，希望找到一个好心的人，愿意替他把名字传达给那位老副官——至于他自己进宫去，那是根本不可能的。

随后我们的代鞭童从对面走过他身边，然后又转过身来，仔细打量他那样子，一面想道：“这要不是陛下急于要找到的那个流浪汉，我就是个傻瓜——虽然我从前也许是有些傻。他恰好和陛下说的那个人一模一样，丝毫不差——如果上帝造出两个这样的角色，那就未免是一种重复的浪费，使奇迹太不值价了。我很想能找出一个借口，跟他说说话才好哩。”

迈尔斯·亨顿替这孩子省了麻烦，因为他正在这时候回转身来——一个人要是被人从后面拼命盯住，对他施催眠术的时候，他就总是要回转身来；他一看这孩子眼睛里充满了浓厚的兴趣，就向他走上前去，说：

“你刚从宫里出来，你是宫里的吗？”

“是的，阁下。”

“你认识汉弗莱·马洛爵士吗？”

那孩子吃了一惊，他心里想：“天哪！就是我那去世了的老父亲呀！”然后他大声回答说：“很熟哩，阁下。”

“那很好——他在里面吗？”

“在里面。”那孩子说，然后他又接着在心里想：“在坟墓里面哩。”

“我请你帮个忙，把我的名字给他传进去，说我希望跟他当面说句话，行不行？”

“我很情愿马上替你办这件事情，先生。”

“那么请你告诉他，理查爵士的儿子迈尔斯·亨顿在外面等着，我非常感谢你，小朋友。”

那孩子显得有点儿失望——“国王不是这样称呼他的，”他心里想，“可是这不要紧，这大概是他的双胞弟兄，我相信他一定能给陛下说出另外那个什么爵士的消息来。”于是他对迈尔斯说：“你上那里面去等一会儿，先生，等我去给你带个话来。”

亨顿走进那孩子所指的地方——那是宫墙上一个凹进去的小屋子，里面有一条石头长凳——是天气不好的时候警卫避风雨的地方。他刚刚坐下，就有一个军官领着几个戟兵走过。那军官看见了他，就叫士兵站住，命令亨顿出来。他遵命出来了，那军官认为他是个可疑的家伙，偷偷地跑到王宫附近来干坏事，马上就把他逮捕起来。情形显得很不妙，可怜的迈尔斯正想解释一下，但是那军官很粗暴地不许他说话，随即叫士兵解除了他的武装，搜查他身上。

“但愿老天显灵，让他们搜出一点儿什么东西来，”可怜的迈尔斯想道，“我自己搜遍了全身，什么也没有找到，我倒是比他们更希望找出点东西来哩。”

什么也没有找到，只有一封信。军官把它撕开，亨顿认出了他那失踪的小朋友在那遭殃的一天在亨顿府写的那些鬼画符的字，就笑了一笑。但是那军官念了用英文写的一段，脸色就发黑，同时迈尔斯听着他念，却吓得脸色惨白。

“又来了一个要求王位的！”军官喊道，“现在这种人简直像兔子似的繁殖得快哩。弟兄们，抓住这个坏蛋吧，你们千万要把他抓得紧紧的，好让我把这封宝贵的信送到宫里去，交给国王。”

他把犯人让戟兵们抓着，自己赶紧走开了。

“现在我的厄运终归走到头了，”亨顿嘟哝着说，“因为我为了那封信，准会吊在绳子上打秋千。我那可怜的孩子会遭到什么结局啊！——哎，只有仁慈的上帝才知道。”

过了不久，他就看见那个军官又匆匆忙忙地回来了，于是他就鼓起勇气来，准备以大丈夫的气概承当他的灾难。那军官命令士兵们放开犯人，把他的剑还他，然后很恭敬地行了个鞠躬礼，说：

“大人，请您跟我去吧。”

亨顿跟着他走，心里想：“我是去接受死刑和天罚的，所以必须少犯点儿罪才行，否则这个浑蛋故意对我这么恭敬，跟我开玩笑，我非掐死他不可。”

他们两个穿过一个人多的庭院，走到王宫的大门口，那军官又对亨顿行了个鞠躬礼，把他交给一个服装华丽的大官手里，这个大官非常恭敬地接待了他，引着他穿过一个大厅往前走。大厅两旁站着一排一排穿得很漂亮的仆人（这些人在他们两个走过的时候，都恭恭敬敬地行礼，但是等我们这个稻草人似的贵人刚一转背，他们就开始闷声闷气地笑得要命），后来又引着他上了一道很宽的楼梯，在一群一群的体面人物当中走过，最后把他领到一个顶大的房间里，从那些聚集在一起的英国贵族当中替他辟开一条路，然后又鞠了一躬，提醒他脱掉帽子，让他一人站在屋子当中；于是他就成了大家注目的对象，并且还有许多人愤愤不平地对他皱着眉头，许多人很开心、很鄙视地对他微笑。

迈尔斯·亨顿狼狈极了。五步以外坐着那年轻的国王，在一把堂皇的华盖之下，向旁边低着头、跟一个极乐鸟似的人物说话——那大概是个公爵；亨顿心里想着，正当壮年有为的时候被判死刑，即令不添上这种当众的羞辱，已经就够不幸的了。他希望国王赶快给自己定罪——他身边有些服装俗艳的人简直使他恶心起来了。正在这时候，国王微微抬起头来，亨顿就把他的面孔看得清清楚楚。这一下几乎使他惊讶得连气都透不过来了！他站在那儿注视着这个年轻的漂亮面孔，自己好像变成了石头人似的，随即他就突然喊道：

“瞧，梦与幻影国的国王居然登了宝座！”

他嘟哝着说了些不连贯的话，还是瞪着眼睛，非常惊奇；然后他向四周张望，仔细打量那一群华丽的人物和那豪华的大厅，一面低声自言自语地说：“可是这些都是真的——的确是真的——当然不是个梦呀。”

他又向国王注视了一下，心想：“这究竟是不是个梦呢？……他究竟是不是真正的英国国王，而不是我所认为的疯人院里的无亲无友的穷孩子呢？——谁能给我解开这个谜？”

他忽然灵机一动，想出了一个主意。他迈着大步走到墙边，拿起一把椅子搬回来，放在地板上，在那上面坐下了！一阵愤怒的声音爆发了，有一只粗暴的手按在他身上，同时有一个声音喊道：

“站起来，你这个不懂礼的野人！你怎么竟敢在国王面前坐下？”

这阵纷扰引起了国王陛下的注意，他伸出手去，大声喊道：

“不许动他，他有这种权利！”

众人大吃一惊，退回去了。国王继续说：

“我告诉你们，小姐和夫人们，大臣和侍从们，这是我的亲信和最亲近的仆人迈尔斯·亨顿，他伸出他那把好剑，救了他的王子，免得他受到伤害，也许还救了他的命——因此国王宣布，封他为爵士。你们还要知道，他立了个更大的功劳，那就是他使国王免了挨鞭子打，免了受羞辱，由他自己代替受了刑罚，因此我封他为英国的贵族，肯特伯爵，还要封给他与这个爵位相称的钱财和土地。还有一点——他刚才行使的这种特权也是国王钦准归他享有的，我已经颁布过命令，特许他一家子子孙孙，凡为首的都有权在大英国王面前坐下，世世代代，王位一日存在，这种特权永不取消。不许干涉他。”

有两个人因为耽误了时间，今天早晨才从乡下赶到，来到这间屋子里还只有五分钟；他们站着听了这些话，望着国王，又望着那个衣衫褴褛的人，再望着国王，有些惊慌失措的样子。这两个人就是休吾爵士和爱迪思小姐，但是新封的伯爵并没有看见他们。他还在心神恍惚地瞪着眼睛望着国王，嘟哝着自言自语地说：

“啊，我的天哪！这就是我那个小叫花子！这就是我那个小疯子！我还打算让他看看我那所七十间屋子和二十七个仆人的府邸多么豪华哪！这就是那个一辈子只穿过破衣服，只挨过脚踢，只吃过残汤剩菜，什么舒服日子也没见过的穷孩子呀！这就是我收养过来，要把他弄成个体面人的流浪儿！我真希望上帝给我一只口袋，我好把脑袋套起来！”

然后他忽然想起了礼貌，于是他就跪下来，把手放到国王手中，对国王宣誓效忠，并为他受封的土地和爵位谢恩。然后他就站起来，毕恭毕敬地站在旁边，还是个大家注目的对象——而且使人非常羡慕。

这时候国王发现了休吾爵士，于是他眼睛里闪出激动的光，用暴怒的声音说：

“剥掉这个强盗的伪装，取消他强占的产业吧，把他关起来，且等我来找他算账。”

原来的休吾爵士被押走了。

现在这个房间的另一头有一阵骚动，在场的人向两边后退，汤姆·康第穿着一身特别而又讲究的衣服，由一个前导官引着，在这两道人墙当中走过来。他在国王面前跪下，国王说：

“我已经听说了过去这几个礼拜的经过情形，对你很满意。你以正确的王室的慈爱和仁义之心治理了国家。你又找到了你的母亲和姐姐吗？好，我们一定要照顾她们——至于你的父亲，如果你同意，法律也允许的话，就要给他处绞刑。现在你们所有听见我的话的人都要知道，从今天起，住在基督教养院里享受国王恩惠的人，除了要使他们吃饱穿暖以外，还要让他们的心灵得到营养；我要这个孩子到那里去住着，终身担任该院管理人员的主管。因为他当过国王，大家对他应该比对一般人更恭敬，所以你们要注意他这套特别的服装，因为他就靠这样的服装表示他与别人的区别，谁也不许模仿；以后无论他到什么地方，他这种服装都可以提醒大家，使大家知道他曾经当过国王，谁也不许对他免掉应有的尊敬，必须对他敬礼。他有国王保护，他有国王支持，现在宣布他为‘国王的受惠人’，从此大家就用这个头衔称呼他。”

得意而快乐的汤姆·康第站起来，吻了吻国王的手，随即就被前导官引着出去了。他一点也没有耽搁时间，赶紧就跑去找他的母亲，把一切情形告诉她和南恩、白特，让她们听到这个好消息，可以助他的兴，大家共同欢乐一番。

尾声 赏罚分明

全部秘密被揭穿的时候，才从休吾·亨顿的招供中知道，他的妻子那天在亨顿府否认迈尔斯，是出自他的命令——他对她发出了这个命令，同时还非常严厉地威胁她，如果她不坚持否认迈尔斯·亨顿，他就要她的命；她一听这话，就说他尽管要她的命，她并不稀罕——反正她不肯否认迈尔斯；于是她的丈夫就说要饶了她的命，而要暗杀迈尔斯！这可是另一回事了，于是她就答应了他的要求，并且实践了诺言。

休吾并没有因为他的威胁行为和他窃取他哥哥的产业和爵位而受到惩罚，因为他的妻子和哥哥都不肯证实他的罪状——即使爱迪思要揭发他，迈尔斯也不会同意她这样做。后来休吾遗弃了他的妻子，跑到大陆上去，不久就死了；过了不久，肯特伯爵就跟他的寡妇结了婚。他们这对夫妇第一次回到亨顿府的时候，那个村里大大地庆祝了一番。

汤姆·康第的父亲再也没有什么消息了。

国王找到了那个烙了火印被卖为奴隶的农民，把他和帮头那一伙人都从罪恶的生活中拯救出来，使他们过着舒适的生活。

他还把那个老律师从监狱里释放出来，退还了他的罚金。他替他亲眼看见在火刑柱上烧死的那两个浸礼会女教友的女儿安顿了很好的家，严厉地惩罚了那个毫无道理地鞭打了迈尔斯·亨顿的军官。

他救了那个捉了逃鹰的小孩和那个偷了织布匠一截布头的女人，使他们免于绞刑；他想救那个被控打死了御猎场里的鹿的人，却已经来不及了。

他当初犯了偷烤猪的嫌疑，法官很怜恤他，现在他对那个法官也施了一些恩惠，结果他很高兴地看到这位法官更加受到公众的尊敬，成了一个伟大的、光荣的人物。

国王终身都爱把他的历险经过从头到尾讲给人家听，从那卫兵把他从王宫门口打出去的时候说起，一直说到最后他在那天半夜里很机警地混进一群匆匆忙忙往里面跑的工人当中，溜到大教堂里时为止；他混进去了之后，就爬到爱德华王的坟墓上藏起来。第二天他在那儿睡了很久，等他醒来的时候，几乎错过了加冕礼的机会。他说他常常把这个宝贵的教训搬出来讲一讲，就可以使他永远抱定决心，借着这些教训给人民多造一些福利；因此他一日在世，就要继续讲这个故事，使他所经历的那些悲惨景象在他脑海中永远留下鲜明的印象，并使他心中重新充满慈爱的源泉。

国王在位的短时期中，迈尔斯·亨顿和汤姆·康第始终是他最欢喜的人，他死后他们也是最真切的哀悼者。善良的肯特伯爵是个很有见识的人，因此他并没有滥用他那稀奇的特权；但是他从我们在前面说过的那次之后，到他离开人间以前，曾经行使过两次这种特权，一次是玛丽女王登基的时候，另一次是伊丽莎白女王登基的时候。他有一个后裔在詹姆士一世即位的时候使用了一次。后来这个后裔的儿子打算使用这种特权的时候，已经相隔二十五年，“肯特家族的特权”在人们的记忆中已经渐渐淡薄了；因此当时的肯特伯爵朝见查理一世，在国王面前坐下来，行使他家里那种权利的时候，就引起了很大的惊扰。但是这件事情经过一番解释，这种特权仍旧被肯定了。这个家族的最后一个伯爵在共和政治时代为国王出征，结果阵亡在外，这个古怪的特权也就随着他的去世而终止了。

汤姆·康第很长寿，他后来成了一个很漂亮的白发老人，态度庄严而仁慈。他在世的时候，始终是受人尊重的；他也很受人敬爱，因为他那显眼的奇特服装老是提醒人家，使他们想起“他曾经当过国王”；所以他无论走到什么地方，人们就向两边后退，给他让路，同时互相耳语，“脱下帽子吧，这是国王的受惠人！”——于是他们就对他行礼，他也温和地微笑着，表示答礼——大家都觉得他的微笑很宝贵，因为他一生的事迹是很光荣的。

爱德华王只活了几年——这不幸的孩子——但是他活得很有价值。曾经不止一次，有某一位大官，国王的大臣，为了反对国王的宽大，和他争论。这位大官说，某一条法律国王有意加以修订，其实那条法律是够宽大的，并不致使人感到痛苦或是压迫，谁也不会十分介意。但是年轻的国王把他那双充满同情的眼睛转过去，露出十足凄凉的神情，回答说：

“你知道什么痛苦和压迫？我和我的老百姓是知道的，你可不知道。”

在那严酷的时代，爱德华六世在位那几年是一个特别仁慈的时期。现在我们要和他告别了，最好是把这一点记在心里，纪念他的功德吧。

译后记

《王子与贫儿》是马克·吐温的童话式讽刺小说，发表于一八八一年。故事以十六世纪英国的生活情况为背景，讲一个衣衫褴褛的贫儿汤姆·康第和太子爱德华同时出生，相貌极为相似；他们由于一个偶然的机会，戏剧性地互换了服装和身份。汤姆登上国王的宝座，当了一国之主后，废除了一些残酷的法律和刑罚，赦免了一些无辜的“犯人”，颁布了一些合乎情理的命令；而王子爱德华则流落在民间，经历了君主专制统治下人民生活的种种苦难。小说通过一个虚构的故事，生动地反映了英国资本主义原始积累时期劳动人民生活的穷困和悲惨，反映了封建统治者的豪奢和凶残。

作品的字里行间流露出作者对统治者的不满和对受苦受难的人民的同情。本书第一百一十页通过一个受难者之口把当时的暴政统治下的英国比作一个人间地狱，为惨遭迫害的穷苦人民打抱不平。

《王子与贫儿》虽然写的是十六世纪英国的事情，却影射着马克·吐温所处的现实环境，即十九世纪资本主义的美国，使人们对资产阶级民主自由的假象不存幻想。所以这部作品与马克·吐温的《汤姆·索亚历险记》《哈克贝利·费恩历险记》有同样的现实意义。

在写这部书时，由于作者对于阶级矛盾日益加剧的美国社会认识逐渐深刻，小说的基调已不仅是轻松的幽默而是辛辣的讽刺。在艺术表现上，《王子与贫儿》也较作者以往的作品有所发展；作者的想象更加自由，对主人公生活的时代和环境也做了生动的描述。

马克·吐温本人认为这部书是他最满意的作品之一，但有些评论家认为此书的风格不高，比《哈克贝利·费恩历险记》和《傻瓜威尔逊》较为逊色，一般作家也能写得出来。

马克·吐温对人吃人的社会给予了无情的揭露和批判，但因囿于资产阶级民主的幻想，他始终摆脱不了改良主义的立场。《王子与贫儿》的结尾还是把仁慈公正的新国王描写成苦难中的人民的救世主，这个弱点是批判现实主义作家所共有的。

译者

一九八二年六月

Chapter VIII.The Question of the Seal

About five o'clock Henry VIII awoke out of an unrefreshing nap, and muttered to himself，“Troublous dreams, troublous dreams！Mine end is now at hand：so say these warnings, and my failing pulses do confirm it.”Presently a wicked light flamed up in his eye, and he muttered，“Yet will not I die till he go before.”

His attendants perceiving that he was awake, one of them asked his pleasure concerning the Lord Chancellor, who was waiting without.

“Admit him, admit him！”exclaimed the king eagerly.

The Lord Chancellor entered, and knelt by the king's couch, saying：

“I have given order, and, according to the king's command, the peers of the realm, in their robes, do now stand at the bar of the House, where, having confirmed the Duke of Norfolk's doom, they humbly wait his majesty's further pleasure in the matter.”

The king's face lit up with a fierce joy.Said he：

“Lift me up！In mine own person will I go before my Parliament, and with mine own hand will I seal the warrant that rids me of—”

His voice failed；an ashen pallor swept the flush from his cheeks；and the attendants eased him back upon his pillows, and hurriedly assisted him with restoratives.Presently he said sorrowfully：

“Alack, how have I longed for this sweet hour！and lo, too late it cometh, and I am robbed of this so coveted chance.But speed ye, speed ye！let others do this happy office sith 'tis denied to me.I put my Great Seal in commission：choose thou the lords that shall compose it, and get ye to your work.Speed ye, man！Before the sun shall rise and set again, bring me his head that I may see it.”

“According to the king's command, so shall it be.Will't please your majesty to order that the Seal be now restored to me, so that I may forth upon the business?”

“The Seal?Who keepeth the Seal but thou?”

“Please your majesty, you did take it from me two days since, saying it should no more do its office till your own royal hand should use it upon the Duke of Norfolk's warrant.”

“Why, so in sooth I did：I do remember it……What did I with it?……I am very feeble……So oft these days doth my memory play the traitor with me……'Tis strange, strange—”

The king dropped into inarticulate mumblings, shaking his grey head weakly from time to time, and gropingly trying to recollect what he had done with the Seal.At last my Lord Hertford ventured to kneel and offer information：

“Sire, if that I may be so bold, here be several that do remember with me how that you gave the Great Seal into the hands of his highness the Prince of Wales to keep against the day that—”

“True, most true！”interrupted the king.“Fetch it！Go：time flieth！”

Lord Hertford flew to Tom, but returned to the king before very long, troubled and empty-handed.He delivered himself to this effect：

“It grieveth me, my lord the king, to bear so heavy and unwelcome tidings；but it is the will of God that the prince's affliction abideth still, and he cannot recall to mind that he received the Seal.So came I quickly to report, thinking it were waste of precious time, and little worth withal, that any should attempt to search the long array of chambers and saloons that belong unto his royal high—”

A groan from the king interrupted the lord at this point.After a little while his majesty said, with a deep sadness in his tone：

“Trouble him no more, poor child.The hand of God lieth heavy upon him, and my heart goeth out in loving compassion for him, and sorrow that I may not bear his burden on mine old trouble-weighted shoulders, and so bring him peace.”

He closed his eyes, fell to mumbling, and presently was silent.After a time he opened his eyes again, and gazed vacantly around until his glance rested upon the kneeling Lord Chancellor.Instantly his face flushed with wrath：

“What, thou here yet！By the glory of God, an'thou gettest not about that traitor's business, thy mitre shall have holiday the morrow for lack of a head to grace withal！”

The trembling Chancellor answered：

“Good your majesty, I cry you mercy！I but waited for the Seal.”

“Man, hast lost thy wits?The small Seal which aforetime I was wont to take with me abroad lieth in my treasury.And, since the Great Seal hath flown away, shall not it suffice?Hast lost thy wits?Begone！And hark ye—come no more till thou do bring his head.”

The poor Chancellor was not long in removing himself from this dangerous vicinity；nor did the commission waste time in giving the royal assent to the work of the slavish Parliament, and appointing the morrow for the beheading of the premier peer of England, the luckless Duke of Norfolk.

Chapter XIII.The Disappearance of the Prince

A heavy drowsiness presently fell upon the two comrades.The king said：

“Remove these rags.”—meaning his clothing.

Hendon disapparelled the boy without dissent or remark, tucked him up in bed, then glanced about the room, saying to himself, ruefully，“He hath taken my bed again, as before—marry, what shall I do?”The little king observed his perplexity, and dissipated it with a word.He said, sleepily：

“Thou wilt sleep athwart the door, and guard it.”In a moment more he was out of his troubles, in a deep slumber.

“Dear heart, he should have been born a king！”muttered Hendon, admiringly；“he playeth the part to a marvel.”

Then he stretched himself across the door, on the floor, saying contentedly：

“I have lodged worse for seven years；'twould be but ill gratitude to Him above to find fault with this.”

He dropped asleep as the dawn appeared.Toward noon he rose, uncovered his unconscious ward—a section at a time—and took his measure with a string.The king awoke just as he had completed his work, complained of the cold, and asked what he was doing.

“'Tis done now, my liege，”said Hendon；“I have a bit of business outside, but will presently return；sleep thou again—thou needest it.There—let me cover thy head also—thou'lt be warm the sooner.”

The king was back in dreamland before this speech was ended.Miles slipped softly out, and slipped as softly in again, in the course of thirty or forty minutes, with a complete secondhand suit of boy's clothing, of cheap material, and showing signs of wear；but tidy, and suited to the season of the year.He seated himself, and began to overhaul his purchase, mumbling to himself：

“A longer purse would have got a better sort, but when one has not the long purse one must be content with what a short one may do—

“‘There was a woman in our town，

In our town did dwell’—

“He stirred, methinks—I must sing in a less thunderous key；'tis not good to mar his sleep, with this journey before him and he so wearied out, poor chap……This garment—'tis well enough—a stitch here and another one there will set it aright.This other is better, albeit a stitch or two will not come amiss in it, likewise……These be very good and sound, and will keep his small feet warm and dry—an odd new thing to him, belike, since he has doubtless been used to foot it bare, winters and summers the same……Would thread were bread, seeing one getteth a year's sufficiency for a farthing, and such a brave big needle without cost, for mere love.Now shall I have the demon's own time to thread it！”

And so he had.He did as men have always done, and probably always will do, to the end of time—held the needle still, and tried to thrust the thread through the eye, which is the opposite of a woman's way.Time and time again the thread missed the mark, going sometimes on one side of the needle, sometimes on the other, sometimes doubling up against the shaft；but he was patient, having been through these experiences before, when he was soldiering.He succeeded at last, and took up the garment that had lain waiting, meantime, across his lap, and began his work.“The inn is paid—the breakfast that is to come, included—and there is wherewithal left to buy a couple of donkeys and meet our little costs for the two or three days betwixt this and the plenty that awaits us at Hendon Hall—

“‘She loved her hus’—

“Body o me！I have driven the needle under my nail！……It matters little—'tis not a novelty—yet 'tis not a convenience, neither……We shall be merry there, little one, never doubt it！Thy troubles will vanish there, and likewise thy sad distemper—

“‘She loved her husband dearilee，

But another man’—

“These be noble large stitches！”—holding the garment up and viewing it admiringly—“they have a grandeur and a majesty that do cause these small stingy ones of the tailorman to look mightily paltry and plebeian—

“‘She loved her husband dearilee，

But another man he loved she，’—

“Marry，'tis done—a goodly piece of work, too, and wrought with expedition.Now will I wake him, apparel him, pour for him, feed him, and then will we hie us to the mart by the Tabard Inn in Southwark and—be pleased to rise, my liege！—he answereth not—what ho, my liege！—of a truth must I profane his sacred person with a touch, sith his slumber is deaf to speech.What！”

He threw back the covers—the boy was gone！

He stared about him in speechless astonishment for a moment；noticed for the first time that his ward's ragged raiment was also missing, then he began to rage and storm and shout for the innkeeper.At that moment a servant entered with the breakfast.

“Explain, thou limb of Satan, or thy time is come！”roared the man of war, and made so savage a spring toward the waiter that this latter could not find his tongue, for the instant, for fright and surprise.“Where is the boy?”

In disjointed and trembling syllables the man gave the information desired.

“You were hardly gone from the place, your worship, when a youth came running and said it was your worship's will that the boy come to you straight, at the bridge-end on the Southwark side.I brought him thither；and when he woke the lad and gave his message, the lad did grumble some little for being disturbed ‘so early，'as he called it, but straightway trussed on his rags and went with the youth, only saying it had been better manners that your worship came yourself, not sent a stranger—and so—”

“And so thou'rt a fool！—a fool and easily cozened—hang all thy breed！Yet mayhap no hurt is done.Possibly no harm is meant the boy.I will go fetch him.Make the table ready.Stay！the coverings of the bed were disposed as if one lay beneath them—happened that by accident?”

“I know not, good your worship.I saw the youth meddle with them—he that came for the boy.”

“Thousand deaths！'twas done to deceive me—'tis plain 'twas done to gain time.Hark ye！Was that youth alone?”

“All alone, your worship.”

“Art sure?”

“Sure, your worship.”

“Collect thy scattered wits—bethink thee—take time, man.”

After a moment's thought, the servant said：

“When he came, none came with him；but now I remember me that as the two stepped into the throng of the Bridge, a ruffian-looking man plunged out from some near place；and just as he was joining them—”

“What then ?—out with it！”thundered the impatient Hendon, interrupting.

“Just then the crowd lapped them up and closed them in, and I saw no more, being called by my master, who was in a rage because a joint that the scrivener had ordered was forgot, though I take all the saints to witness that to blame me for that miscarriage were like holding the unborn babe to judgment for sins com—”

“Out of my sight, idiot！Thy prating drives me mad！Hold！whither art flying?Canst not bide still an instant?Went they toward Southwark?”

“Even so, your worship—for, as I said before, as to that detestable joint, the babe unborn is no whit more blameless than—”

“Art here yet！And prating still！Vanish, lest I throttle thee！”The servitor vanished.Hendon followed after him, passed him, and plunged down the stairs two steps at a stride, muttering，“'Twas that scurvy villain that claimed he was his son.I have lost thee, my poor little mad master—it is a bitter thought—and I had come to love thee so！No！by book and bell, not lost！Not lost, for I will ransack the land till I find thee again.Poor child, yonder is his breakfast—and mine, but I have no hunger now—so, let the rats have it—speed, speed！that is the word！”As he wormed his swift way through the noisy multitudes upon the Bridge he several times said to himself—clinging to the thought as if it were a particularly pleasing one：“He grumbled, but he went—he went, yes, because he thought Miles Hendon asked it, sweet lad—he would ne'er have done it for another, I know it well！”

Chapter XXV.Hendon Hall

As soon as Hendon and the king were out of sight of the constable, his majesty was instructed to hurry to a certain place outside the town, and wait there, whilst Hendon should go to the inn and settle his account.Half an hour later the two friends were blithely jogging eastward on Hendon's sorry steeds.The king was warm and comfortable now, for he had cast his rags and clothed himself in the secondhand suit which Hendon had bought on London Bridge.

Hendon wished to guard against over-fatiguing the boy；he judged that hard journeys, irregular meals, and illiberal measures of sleep would be bad for his crazed mind；while rest, regularity, and moderate exercise would be pretty sure to hasten its cure；he longed to see the stricken intellect made well again and its diseased visions driven out of the tormented little head；therefore he resolved to move by easy stages toward the home whence he had so long been banished, instead of obeying the impulse of his impatience and hurrying along night and day.

When he and the king had journeyed about ten miles, they reached a considerable village, and halted there for the night, at a good inn.The former relations were resumed；Hendon stood behind the king's chair while he dined, and waited upon him；undressed him when he was ready for bed；then took the floor for his own quarters, and slept athwart the door, rolled up in a blanket.

The next day, and the next day after, they jogged lazily along talking over the adventures they had met since their separation, and mightily enjoying each other's narratives.Hendon detailed all his wide wanderings in search of the king, and described how the archangel had led him a fool's journey all over the forest, and taken him back to the hut finally, when he found he could not get rid of him.Then—he said—the old man went into the bedchamber and came staggering back looking broken-hearted, and saying he had expected to find that the boy had returned and laid down in there to rest, but it was not so.Hendon had waited at the hut all day；hope of the king's return died out then, and he departed upon the quest again.

“And old Sanctum Sanctorum was truly sorry your highness came not back，”said Hendon；“I saw it in his face.”

“Marry, I will never doubt that ！”said the king—and then told his own story；after which Hendon was sorry he had not destroyed the archangel.

During the last day of the trip, Hendon's spirits were soaring.His tongue ran constantly.He talked about his old father, and his brother Arthur, and told of many things which illustrated their high and generous characters；he went into loving frenzies over his Edith, and was so glad-hearted that he was even able to say some gentle and brotherly things about Hugh.He dwelt a deal on the coming meeting at Hendon Hall；what a surprise it would be to everybody, and what an outburst of thanksgiving and delight there would be.

It was a fair region, dotted with cottages and orchards, and the road led through broad pasturelands whose receding expanses, marked with gentle elevations and depressions, suggested the swelling and subsiding undulations of the sea.In the afternoon the returning prodigal made constant deflections from his course to see if by ascending some hillock he might not pierce the distance and catch a glimpse of his home.At last he was successful, and cried out excitedly：

“There is the village, my prince, and there is the Hall close by！You may see the towers from here；and that wood there—that is my father's park.Ah, now thou'lt know what state and grandeur be！A house with seventy rooms—think of that！—and seven and twenty servants！A brave lodging for such as we, is it not so?Come, let us speed—my impatience will not brook further delay.”

All possible hurry was made；still, it was after three o'clock before the village was reached.The travellers scampered through it, Hendon's tongue going all the time.“Here is the church—covered with the same ivy—none gone, none added.”“Yonder is the inn, the old Red Lion—and yonder is the market-place.”“Here is the Maypole, and here the pump—nothing is altered；nothing but the people, at any rate；ten years make a change in people；some of these I seem to know, but none know me.”So his chat ran on.The end of the village was soon reached；then the travellers struck into a crooked, narrow road, walled in with tall hedges, and hurried briskly along it for a half-mile, then passed into a vast flower garden through an imposing gateway, whose huge stone pillars bore sculptured armorial devices.A noble mansion was before them.

“Welcome to Hendon Hall, my king！”exclaimed Miles.“Ah，'tis a great day！My father and my brother and the Lady Edith will be so mad with joy that they will have eyes and tongue for none but me in the first transports of the meeting, and so thou'lt seem but coldly welcomed—but mind it not；'twill soon seem otherwise；for when I say thou art my ward, and tell them how costly is my love for thee, thou'lt see them take thee to their breasts for Miles Hendon's sake, and make their house and hearts thy home forever after！”

The next moment Hendon sprang to the ground before the great door, helped the king down, then took him by the hand and rushed within.A few steps brought him to a spacious apartment；he entered, seated the king with more hurry than ceremony, then ran toward a young man who sat at a writing-table in front of a generous fire of logs.

“Embrace me, Hugh，”he cried，“and say thou'rt glad I am come again！and call our father, for home is not home till I shall touch his hand, and see his face, and hear his voice once more！”

But Hugh only drew back, after betraying a momentary surprise, and bent a grave stare upon the intruder—a stare which indicated somewhat of offended dignity at first, then changed, in response to some inward thought or purpose, to an expression of marvelling curiosity, mixed with a real or assumed compassion.Presently he said, in a mild voice：

“Thy wits seem touched, poor stranger；doubtless thou hast suffered privations and rude buffetings at the world's hands；thy looks and dress betoken it.Whom dost thou take me to be?”

“Take thee?Prithee, for whom else than whom thou art?I take thee to be Hugh Hendon，”said Miles, sharply.

The other continued, in the same soft tone：

“And whom dost thou imagine thyself to be?”

“Imagination hath naught to do with it！Dost thou pretend thou knowest me not for thy brother Miles Hendon?”

An expression of pleased surprise flitted across Hugh’s face, and he exclaimed：

“What！thou art not jesting?can the dead come to life?God be praised if it be so！Our poor lost boy restored to our arms after all these cruel years！Ah, it seems too good to be true, it is too good to be true—I charge thee, have pity, do not trifle with me！Quick—come to the light—let me scan thee well！”

He seized Miles by the arm, dragged him to the window, and began to devour him from head to foot with his eyes, turning him this way and that, and stepping briskly around him and about him to prove him from all points of view；whilst the returned prodigal, all aglow with gladness, smiled, laughed, and kept nodding his head and saying：

“Go on, brother, go on, and fear not；thou'lt find nor limb nor feature that cannot bide the test.Scour and scan me to thy content, my dear old Hugh—I am indeed thy old Miles, thy same old Miles, thy lost brother, is't not so?Ah，'tis a great day—I said 'twas a great day！Give me thy hand, give me thy cheek—lord, I am like to die of very joy！”

He was about to throw himself upon his brother；but Hugh put up his hand in dissent, then dropped his chin mournfully upon his breast, saying with emotion：

“Ah, God of his mercy give me strength to bear this grievous disappointment！”

Miles, amazed, could not speak for a moment；then he found his tongue, and cried out：

“What disappointment?Am I not thy brother?”

Hugh shook his head sadly, and said：

“I pray heaven it may prove so, and that other eyes may find the resemblances that are hid from mine.Alack, I fear me the letter spoke but too truly.”

“What letter?”

“One that came from oversea, some six or seven years ago.It said my brother died in battle.”

“It was a lie！Call thy father—he will know me.”

“One may not call the dead.”

“Dead?”Miles's voice was subdued, and his lips trembled.“My father dead！—oh, this is heavy news.Half my new joy is withered now.Prithee let me see my brother Arthur—he will know me；he will know me and console me.”

“He, also, is dead.”

“God be merciful to me, a stricken man！Gone—both gone—the worthy taken and the worthless spared in me！Ah！I crave your mercy！—do not say the Lady Edith—”

“Is dead?No, she lives.”

“Then, God be praised, my joy is whole again！Speed thee, brother—let her come to me！An'she say I am not myself—but she will not；no, no, she will know me, I were a fool to doubt it.Bring her—bring the old servants；they, too, will know me.”

“All are gone but five—Peter, Halsey, David, Bernard, and Margaret.”

So saying, Hugh left the room.Miles stood musing awhile, then began to walk the floor, muttering：

“The five arch villains have survived the two-and-twenty leal and honest—'tis an odd thing.”

He continued walking back and forth, muttering to himself；he had forgotten the king entirely.By and by his majesty said gravely, and with a touch of genuine compassion, though the words themselves were capable of being interpreted ironically：

“Mind not thy mischance, good man；there be others in the world whose identity is denied, and whose claims are derided.Thou hast company.”

“Ah, my king，”cried Hendon, colouring slightly，“do not thou condemn me—wait, and thou shalt see.I am no impostor—she will say it；you shall hear it from the sweetest lips in England.I an impostor?Why I know this old hall, these pictures of my ancestors, and all these things that are about us, as a child knoweth its own nursery.Here was I born and bred, my lord；I speak the truth；I would not deceive thee；and should none else believe, I pray thee do not thou doubt me—I could not bear it.”

“I do not doubt thee，”said the king, with a childlike simplicity and faith.

“I thank thee out of my heart！”exclaimed Hendon, with a fervency which showed that he was touched.The king added, with the same gentle simplicity：

“Dost thou doubt me?”

A guilty confusion seized upon Hendon, and he was grateful that the door opened to admit Hugh, at that moment, and saved him the necessity of replying.

A beautiful lady, richly clothed, followed Hugh, and after her came several liveried servants.The lady walked slowly, with her head bowed and her eyes fixed upon the floor.The face was unspeakably sad.Miles Hendon sprang forward, crying out：

“Oh, my Edith, my darling—”

But Hugh waved him back, gravely, and said to the lady：

“Look upon him.Do you know him?”

At the sound of Miles's voice the woman had started slightly, and her cheeks had flushed；she was trembling now.She stood still, during an impressive pause of several moments；then slowly lifted up her head and looked into Hendon’s eyes with a stony and frightened gaze；the blood sank out of her face, drop by drop, till nothing remained but the gray pallor of death；then she said, in a voice as dead as the face，“I know him not！”and turned, with a moan and a stifled sob, and tottered out of the room.

Miles Hendon sank into a chair and covered his face with his hands.After a pause, his brother said to the servants：

“You have observed him.Do you know him?”

They shook their heads；then the master said：

“The servants know you not, sir.I fear there is some mistake.You have seen that my wife knew you not.”

“Thy wife！”In an instant Hugh was pinned to the wall, with an iron grip about his throat.“Oh, thou fox-hearted slave, I see it all！Thou'st writ the lying letter thyself, and my stolen bride and goods are its fruit.There—now get thee gone, lest I shame mine honourable soldiership with the slaying of so pitiful a mannikin！”

Hugh, red-faced and almost suffocated, reeled to the nearest chair, and commanded the servants to seize and bind the murderous stranger.They hesitated, and one of them said：

“He is armed, Sir Hugh, and we are weaponless.”

“Armed?What of it, and ye so many?Upon him, I say！”

But Miles warned them to be careful what they did, and added：

“Ye know me of old—I have not changed；come on, an'it like you.”

This reminder did not hearten the servants much；they still held back.

“Then go, ye paltry cowards, and arm yourselves and guard the doors, while I send one to fetch the watch，”said Hugh.He turned, at the threshold, and said to Miles，“You'll find it to your advantage to offend not with useless endeavours at escape.”

“Escape?Spare thyself discomfort, an'that is all that troubles thee.For Miles Hendon is master of Hendon Hall and all its belongings.He will remain—doubt it not.”

[1]指1485—1603年，是英国的都铎王朝时代。

[2]五月柱是欧洲五朔节的时候用花或彩带装饰起来，让男女青年围着跳舞的柱子。

[3]伦敦塔是从前英国囚禁重要政治犯的监狱。这个塔是一座堡寨，早已成为一处古迹。

[4]上塔里去就是关进伦敦塔去坐牢。

[5]洗马池一般是洗马和饮马用的，但被众人厌恶的人有时也被丢到洗马池去，叫他吃苦头。

[6]《圣经·新约》里所说的耶稣的忠实女信徒。

[7]爱杯是一种有好几个柄的大酒杯，可以几个人用来轮流喝酒。

[8]市会厅是伦敦市举行各种盛大集会的公共会场。

[9]这里指的是从男爵的位序。与男爵不同，从男爵是较晚形成的阶层。

[10]德库西的后代依然享有这种古怪的特权。

[11]见休谟的《英国史》。

[12]见休谟的《英国史》。

[13]出自利·亨特的《京城》，这是引用一位古代游览家的话。

[14]选自《英国流氓史》。伦敦，1665。

[15]“溜门子的”是溜进人家里行窃的小偷；“二仙传道的”是两人合伙行窃的贼；“溜兜儿的”是扒手；“追孙儿的”是追随行乞的乞丐；“讨百家饭的”是挨家挨户行乞的乞丐。这些名称都是贼帮和乞丐们自己当中通用的。

[16]“打起发”是贼话，意思是行乞、行窃或抢劫。

[17]当时英国实行“圈地法”，把农民弄得没有生路，逼得他们四处流浪，又给他们加上“游荡”的罪名。

[18]指地狱。

[19]艾尔弗雷德大帝（Alfred the Great，849—899），英国国王。他有一次被丹麦人打败了，逃到一个农民家里，主妇不知道他是国王，叫他照应火上烤着的饼子，但是他因为一心想着战事，结果让饼子煳了，被人撵走。

[20]亚伯拉罕、以撒是希伯来人的先辈，即上文所说的“圣祖”。雅各是以撒的儿子。

[21]选自《英国流氓史》。伦敦，1665。

[22]见休谟的《英国史》。

[23]斯康石，史称“定命石”，从前苏格兰的国王都坐在上面举行加冕礼，曾长期置于威斯敏斯特大教堂。

[24]He refers to the order of baronets, or baronettes；the barones minores, as distinct from the parliamentary barons；—not, it need hardly be said, the baronets of later creation.

[25]The lords of Kingsale, descendants of De Courcy, still enjoy this curious privilege.

[26]Hume.

[27]Hume.

[28]Leigh Hunt’s The Town, p.408.Quotation from an early tourist.

[29]From “The English Rogue”：London，1665.

[30]Canting terms for various kinds of thieves, beggars, and vagabonds and their female companions.

[31]From “The English Rogue”：London，1665.

[32]Hume’s England.

第一章　老实人在一座美丽的宫堡中怎样受教育，怎样被驱逐

从前威斯发里地方，森特—登—脱龙克男爵大人府上，有个年轻汉子，天生性情最是和顺。看他相貌，就可知道他的心地。他颇识是非，头脑又简单不过；大概就因为此，人家才叫他作老实人。府里的老用人暗中疑心，他是男爵的姊妹和邻近一位安分善良的乡绅养的儿子；那小姐始终不肯嫁给那绅士，因为他旧家的世系只能追溯到七十一代，其余的家谱因为年深月久，失传了。

男爵是威斯发里第一等有财有势的爵爷，因为他的宫堡有一扇门、几扇窗，大厅上还挂着一幅毡幕，养牲口的院子里所有的狗随时可以编成狩猎大队，那些马夫是现成的领队——村里的教士是男爵的大司祭。他们都称男爵为大人；他一开口胡说八道，大家就跟着笑。

男爵夫人体重在三百五十斤上下，因此极有声望，接见宾客时那副威严，越发显得她可敬可佩。她有个十七岁的女儿居内贡，面色鲜红，又嫩又胖，教人看了馋涎欲滴。男爵的儿子样样都跟父亲并驾齐驱。教师邦葛罗斯是府里的圣人，老实人年少天真，一本诚心地听着邦葛罗斯的教训。

邦葛罗斯教的是一种包罗玄学、神学、宇宙学的学问。他很巧妙地证明天下事有果必有因，又证明在此最完美的世界上，男爵的宫堡是最美的宫堡，男爵夫人是天底下好到不能再好的男爵夫人。

他说：“显而易见，事无大小，皆系定数；万物既皆有归宿，此归宿自必为最美满的归宿。岂不见鼻子是长来戴眼镜的吗？所以我们有眼镜。身上安放两条腿是为穿长裤的，所以我们有长裤。石头是要人开凿，盖造宫堡的，所以男爵大人有一座美轮美奂的宫堡；本省最有地位的男爵不是应当住得最好吗？猪是生来给人吃的，所以我们终年吃猪肉；谁要说一切皆善简直是胡扯，应当说尽善尽美才对。”

老实人一心一意地听着，好不天真地相信着；因为他觉得居内贡小姐美丽无比，虽则从来没胆子敢对她这么说。他认定第一等福气是生为男爵；第二等福气是生为居内贡小姐；第三等福气是天天看到小姐；第四等福气是听到邦葛罗斯大师的高论，他是本省最伟大的，所以是全球最伟大的哲学家。

有一天，居内贡小姐在宫堡附近散步，走在那个叫作猎场的小树林中，忽然瞥见丛树之间，邦葛罗斯正替她母亲的女仆，一个很俊俏、很和顺的棕发姑娘，上一课实验物理学。居内贡小姐素来好学，便屏气凝神，把她亲眼看到的、三番四复搬演的实验，观察了一番。她清清楚楚看到了博学大师的根据，看到了结果和原因，然后浑身紧张、胡思乱想地回家，巴不得做个博学的才女；私忖自己大可作青年老实人的根据，老实人也大可作她的根据。

回宫堡的路上，她遇到老实人，不由得脸红了；老实人也脸红了。她跟他招呼，语不成声；老实人和她答话，不知所云。第二天，吃过中饭，离开饭桌，居内贡和老实人在一座屏风后面，居内贡把手帕掉在地上，老实人捡了起来；她无心地拿着他的手，年轻人无心地吻着少女的手，那种热情，那种温柔，那种风度，都有点异乎寻常。两人嘴巴碰上了，眼睛射出火焰，膝盖直打哆嗦，手往四下里乱动。森特—登—脱龙克男爵打屏风边过，一看这个原因、这个结果，立刻飞起大腿，踢着老实人的屁股，把他赶出大门。居内贡当场晕倒，醒来挨了男爵夫人一顿巴掌。于是在这最美丽最愉快的宫堡里，大家为之惊惶失措。

第二章　老实人在保加利亚人中的遭遇

老实人被赶出了地上的乐园，茫无目的，走了好久，一边哭一边望着天，又常常回头望那座住着最美的男爵小姐的最美的宫堡。晚上饿着肚子，睡在田里；又遇着大雪。第二天，老实人冻僵了，挣扎着走向近边一个市镇，那市镇叫作代特勃谷夫—脱拉蒲克—狄克陶夫。他一个钱也没有，饿得要死，累得要死，好不愁闷地站在一家酒店门口。

两个穿蓝衣服[1]的人把他看在眼里，其中一个对另外一个说：“喂，伙计，这小伙子长得怪不错，身量也合格。”他们过来很客气地邀他吃饭。

老实人挺可爱挺谦逊地答道：“承蒙相邀，不胜荣幸，无奈我囊空如洗，付不出份头啊。”

两个穿蓝衣服的人之中的一个说：“啊，先生，凭你这副品貌才具，哪有破钞之理！你不是身长五尺半吗？”

老实人鞠了一躬，道：“不错，我正是五尺半高低。”

“啊，先生，坐下吃饭吧；我们不但要替你惠钞，而且决不让你这样一个人物缺少钱用；患难相助，人之天职，可不是吗？”

老实人回答：“说得有理；邦葛罗斯先生一向这么告诉我的；我看明白了，世界真是安排得再好没有。”

两人要他收下几块银洋，他接了钱，想写一张借据，他们执意不要。宾主便坐下吃饭。

他们问：“你不是十分爱慕……？”

老实人答道：“是啊，我十分爱慕居内贡小姐。”

两人之中的一个忙说：“不是这意思；我们问你是否爱慕保加利亚国王。”

老实人道：“不，我从来没见过他。”

“怎么不？他是天底下最可爱的国王，应当为他干杯。”

“好吧，我遵命就是了。”说着便干了一杯。

两人就说：“得啦得啦，现在你已经是保加利亚的柱石、股肱、卫士、英雄了；你利禄也到手了，功名也有望了。”随即把老实人上了脚镣，带往营部，叫他向左转，向右转，扳上火门，扳下火门，瞄准，开放，快步跑，又赏他三十军棍。第二天他操练略有进步，只挨了二十棍；第三天只吃了十棍，弟兄们都认为他是天才。

老实人莫名其妙，弄不清他怎么会成为英雄的。一日，正是美好的春天，他想出去溜溜，便信步前行，满以为随心所欲地调动两腿，是人和动物共有的权利。还没走上七八里地，四个身长六尺的英雄追上来，把他捆起，送进地牢。他们按照法律规定，问他喜欢哪一样：是让全团弟兄鞭上三十六道呢，还是脑袋里同时送进十二颗子弹？

他声明意志是自由的，他两样都不想要；只是枉费唇舌，非挑一样不可。他只能利用上帝的恩赐，利用所谓自由，决意挨受三十六道鞭子。

他挨了两道。团里共有两千人，两道就是四千鞭子：从颈窝到屁股，他的肌肉与神经统统露在外面了。第三道正要开始，老实人忍受不住，要求额外开恩，干脆砍掉他的脑袋。他们答应了，用布条蒙住他的眼睛，教他跪下。

恰好保加利亚国王在旁走过，问了犯人的罪状；国王英明无比，听了老实人的情形，知道他是个青年玄学家，世事一窍不通，便把他赦免了；这宽大的德政，将来准会得到每份报纸每个世纪的颂扬。一位热心的外科医生，用希腊名医狄俄斯戈里传下的伤药，不出三星期就把老实人治好。他已经长了些新皮，能够走路了，保加利亚王和阿伐尔[2]王却打起仗来。

第三章　老实人怎样逃出保加利亚人的掌握，以后又是怎样的遭遇

两支军队的雄壮、敏捷、辉煌和整齐，可以说无与伦比。喇叭、横笛、长箫、军鼓、大炮，合奏齐鸣，连地狱里也从来没有如此和谐的音乐。先是大炮把每一边的军队轰倒六千左右；排枪又替最美好的世界扫除了九千到一万名玷污地面的坏蛋。刺刀又充分说明了几千人的死因。总数大概有三万上下。老实人像哲学家一样发抖，在这场英勇的屠杀中尽量躲藏。

两国的国王各自在营中叫人高唱吾主上帝，感谢神恩；老实人可决意换一个地方去推敲因果关系了。他从已死和未死的人堆上爬过去，进入一个邻近的村子，只见一片灰烬。那是阿伐尔人的村庄，被保加利亚人依照公法焚毁了。这儿是戳满窟窿的老人，眼睁睁地看着他们被杀的妻子，怀中还有婴儿衔着血污的奶头；那儿是满足了英雄们的需要，被开肠破肚的姑娘，正在咽最后一口气；又有些烧得半死不活的，嚷着求人结果他们的性命。地下是断臂折腿，旁边淌着脑浆。

老实人拔步飞奔，逃往另外一个村子：那是保加利亚人的地方；阿伐尔人对付他们的手段也一般无二。老实人脚下踩着的不是瓦砾，便是还在扭动的肢体。他终于走出战场，褡裢内带着些干粮，念念不忘地想着居内贡小姐。到荷兰境内，干粮吃完了；但听说当地人人皆是富翁，并且是基督徒，便深信他们待客的情谊决不亚于男爵府上，就是说和他没有为了美丽的居内贡而被逐的时代一样。

他向好几位道貌岸然的人求布施。他们一致回答，倘若他老干这一行，就得送进感化院，教教他做人之道。

接着他看见一个人在大会上演讲，一口气讲了一个钟点，题目是乐善好施。他讲完了，老实人上前求助。演说家斜视着他，问道：“你来干什么？你是不是排斥外道，拥护正果的？”

老实人很谦卑地回答：“噢！天下事有果必有因；一切皆如连锁，安排得再妥当没有。我必须从居内贡小姐那边被赶出来，必须挨鞭子。我必须讨面包，讨到我能自己挣面包为止。这都是必然之事。”

演说家又问：“朋友，你可相信教皇是魔道吗[3]？”

老实人回答：“我还没听见这么说过；他是魔道也罢，不是魔道也罢，我缺少面包是真的。”

那人道：“你不配吃面包；滚开去，坏蛋；滚，流氓；滚，别走近我。”

演说家的老婆在窗口探了探头，看到一个不信教皇为魔道的人，立刻向他倒下一大……噢，天！妇女的醉心宗教竟会到这个地步！

一个未受洗礼的再浸礼派[4]信徒，名叫雅各，看到一个同胞，一个没有羽毛而有灵魂的两足动物，受到这样野蛮无礼的待遇，便带他到家里，让他洗澡，给他面包、啤酒，送他两个弗洛冷[5]，还打算教老实人进他布厂学手艺，布厂的出品是在荷兰织造而叫作波斯呢的一种印花布。

老实人差不多扑在他脚下，叫道：“邦葛罗斯老师早告诉我了，这个世界上样样都十全十美；你的慷慨豪爽，比着那位穿黑衣服的先生和他太太的残酷，使我感动多了。”

第四章　老实人怎样遇到从前的哲学老师邦葛罗斯博士，和以后的遭遇

第二天，他在街上闲逛，遇到一个花子，身上长着脓包，两眼无光，鼻尖烂了一截，嘴歪在半边，牙齿乌黑，说话逼紧着喉咙，咳得厉害，呛一阵就掉一颗牙。

老实人一见之下，怜悯胜过了厌恶，把好心的雅各送的两个弗洛冷给了可怕的花子。那鬼一样的家伙定睛瞧着他，落着眼泪，向他的脖子直扑过来。老实人吓得后退不迭。

“唉！”那个可怜虫向这个可怜虫说道，“你认不得你亲爱的邦葛罗斯了吗？”

“什么！亲爱的老师，是你？你会落到这般悲惨的田地？你碰上了什么倒霉事呀？干么不住在最美的宫堡里了？居内贡小姐，那女中之宝，天地的杰作，又怎么了呢？”

邦葛罗斯说道：“我支持不住了。”老实人便带他上雅各家的马房，给他一些面包。

等到邦葛罗斯有了力气，老实人又问：“那么居内贡呢？”

“她死了。”

老实人一听这话就晕了过去。马房里恰好有些坏醋，邦葛罗斯拿来把老实人救醒了。

他睁开眼叫道：“居内贡死了！啊，最美好的世界到哪里去了？她害什么病死的？莫非因为看到我被她令尊大人一边踢，一边赶出了美丽的宫堡吗？”

邦葛罗斯答道：“不是的；保加利亚兵先把她蹂躏得不像样了，又一刀戳进她肚子；男爵上前救护，被乱兵砍了脑袋；男爵夫人被人分尸，割作几块；我可怜的学生和他妹妹的遭遇完全一样；宫堡变了平地，连一所谷仓、一头羊、一只鸭子、一棵树都不留了；可是人家代我们报了仇，阿伐尔人对近边一个保加利亚男爵的府第也如法炮制。”

听了这番话，老实人又昏迷了一阵；等到醒来，把该说的话说完了，便追问是什么因，什么果，什么根据，把邦葛罗斯弄成这副可怜的形景。

邦葛罗斯答道：“唉，那是爱情啊；是那安慰人类，保存世界，为一切有情人的灵魂的、甜蜜的爱情啊。”

老实人也道：“噢！爱情，这个心灵的主宰，灵魂的灵魂，我也领教过了。所得的酬报不过是一个亲吻，还有屁股上挨了一二十下。这样一件美事，怎会在你身上产生这样丑恶的后果呢？”

于是邦葛罗斯说了下面一席话：

“噢，亲爱的老实人！咱们庄严的男爵夫人有个俊俏的侍女，叫作巴该德，你不是认识的吗？我在她怀中尝到的乐趣，赛过登天一般；乐趣产生的苦难却像堕入地狱一样，使我浑身上下受着毒刑。巴该德也害着这个病，说不定已经死了。巴该德的那件礼物，是一个芳济会神父送的；他非常博学，把源流考证出来了：他的病是得之于一个老伯爵夫人，老伯爵夫人得之于一个骑兵上尉，骑兵上尉得之于一个侯爵夫人，侯爵夫人得之于一个侍从，侍从得之于一个耶稣会神父，耶稣会神父当修士的时候，直接得之于哥伦布的一个同伴。至于我，我不会再传给别人了，我眼看要送命的了。”

老实人嚷道：“噢，邦葛罗斯！这段家谱可离奇透了！祸根不都在魔鬼身上吗？”

“不是的，”那位大人物回答，“在十全十美的世界上，这是无可避免的事，必不可少的要素。固然这病不但毒害生殖的本源，往往还阻止生殖，和自然界的大目标是相反的；但要是哥伦布没有在美洲一座岛上染到这个病，我们哪会有巧克力，哪会有做胭脂用的胭脂虫颜料？还得注意一点：至此为止，这病和宗教方面的争论一样，是本洲独有的。土耳其人、印度人、波斯人、中国人、暹罗人、日本人都还没见识过；可是有个必然之理，不出几百年，他们也会领教的。目前这病在我们中间进步神速，尤其在大军之中，在文雅、安分、操纵各国命运的佣兵所组成的大军之中；倘有三万人和员额相等的敌军作战，每一方面必有两万人身长毒疮。”

老实人道：“这真是妙不可言。不过你总得医啊。”

邦葛罗斯回答：“我怎么能医？朋友，我没有钱呀。不付钱，或是没有别人代付钱，你走遍地球也不能放一次血[6]、洗一个澡。”

听到最后几句，老实人打定了主意；他去跪在好心的雅各面前，把朋友落难的情形说得那么动人，雅各竟毫不迟疑，招留了邦葛罗斯博士，出钱给他治病。治疗的结果，邦葛罗斯只损失了一只眼睛和一只耳朵。他笔下很了得，又精通算术。雅各派他当账房。过了两月，雅各为了生意上的事要到里斯本去，把两位哲学家带在船上。邦葛罗斯一路向他解释，世界上一切都好得无以复加。雅各不同意。

他说：“无论如何，人的本性多少是变坏了，他们生下来不是狼，却变了狼。上帝没有给他们二十四磅的大炮[7]，也没有给他们刺刀；他们却造了刺刀大炮互相毁灭。多少起的破产，和法院攫取破产人财产、侵害债权人利益的事，我可以立一本清账。”

独眼博士回答道：“这些都是应有之事，个人的苦难造成全体的幸福；个人的苦难越多，全体越幸福。”

他们正在这么讨论，忽然天昏地黑，狂风四起，就在望得见里斯本港口的地方，他们的船遇到了最可怕的飓风。

第五章　飓风，覆舟，地震；邦葛罗斯博士、老实人和雅各的遭遇

船身颠簸打滚，人身上所有的液质[8]和神经都被搅乱了：这些难以想象的痛苦使半数乘客软瘫了，快死了，没有气力再为眼前的危险着急。另外一半乘客大声叫喊，做着祷告。帆破了，桅断了，船身裂了一半。大家忙着抢救，七嘴八舌，各有各的主意，谁也指挥不了谁。雅各帮着做点儿事；他正在舱面上，被一个发疯般的水手狠狠一拳打倒在地；水手用力过猛，也摔出去倒挂着吊在折断的桅杆上。好心的雅各上前援救，帮他爬上来；不料一使劲，雅各竟冲下海去，水手让他淹死，看都不屑一看。老实人瞧着恩人在水面上冒了一冒，不见了。他想跟着雅各跳海；哲学家邦葛罗斯把他拦住了，引经据典地说：为了要淹死雅各，海上才有这个里斯本港口的。他正在高谈因果以求证明的当口，船裂开了，所有的乘客都送了性命，只剩下邦葛罗斯、老实人和淹死善人雅各的野蛮水手，那坏蛋很顺利地泅到了岸上；邦葛罗斯和老实人靠一块木板把他们送上陆地。

他们惊魂略定，就向里斯本进发；身边还剩几个钱，只希望凭着这点儿盘缠，他们从飓风中逃出来的命，不至于再为饥饿送掉。

一边走一边悼念他们的恩人；才进城，他们觉得地震了[9]。港口里的浪像沸水一般往上直冒，停泊的船给打得稀烂。飞舞回旋的火焰和灰烬，盖满了街道和广场；屋子倒下来，房顶压在地基上，地基跟着坍毁；三万名男女老幼都给压死了。

水手打着呼哨，连咒带骂地说道：“哼，这儿倒可以发笔财呢。”

邦葛罗斯说：“这现象究竟有何根据呢？”

老实人嚷道：“啊！世界末日到了！”

水手闯进瓦砾场，不顾性命，只管找钱，找到了便揣在怀里；喝了很多酒，醉醺醺地睡了一觉，在倒坍的屋子和将死已死的人中间，遇到第一个肯卖笑的姑娘，他就掏出钱来买。

邦葛罗斯扯着他袖子，说道：“朋友，使不得，使不得，你违反理性了，干这个事不是时候。”

水手答道：“天杀的，去你的吧！我是当水手的，生在巴太维亚；到日本去过四次，好比十字架上爬过四次。理性，理性，你的理性找错人了！”

几块碎石头砸伤了老实人；他躺在街上，埋在瓦砾中间，和邦葛罗斯说道：“唉，给我一点儿酒和油吧；我要死了。”

邦葛罗斯答道：“地震不是新鲜事儿；南美洲的利马去年有过同样的震动；同样的因，同样的果；从利马到里斯本，地底下准有一道硫黄的伏流。”

“那很可能，”老实人说，“可是看在上帝分上，给我一些油和酒呀。”

哲学家回答：“怎么说可能？我断定那是千真万确的事。”

老实人晕过去了，邦葛罗斯从近边一口井里拿了点儿水给他。

第二天，他们在破砖碎瓦堆里爬来爬去，弄到一些吃的，略微长了些气力。他们跟旁人一同救护死里逃生的居民。得救的人中有几个请他们吃饭，算是大难之中所能张罗的最好的一餐。不用说，饭桌上空气凄凉得很；同席的都是一把眼泪，一口面包。邦葛罗斯安慰他们，说那是定数：“因为那安排得不能再好了；里斯本既然有一座火山，这座火山就不可能在旁的地方。因为物之所在，不能不在，因为一切皆善。”

旁边坐着一位穿黑衣服的矮个子，是异教裁判所的一个小官；他挺有礼貌地开言道：“先生明明不信原始罪恶了；倘使一切都十全十美，人就不会堕落，不会受罚了[10]。”

邦葛罗斯回答的时候比他礼貌更周到：“敬请阁下原谅，鄙意并非如此。人的堕落和受罚，在好得不能再好的世界上，原是必不可少的事。”

那小官儿又道：“先生莫非不信自由吗？”

邦葛罗斯答道：“敬请阁下原谅；自由与定数可以并存不悖；因为我们必须自由，因为坚决的意志……”

邦葛罗斯说到一半，那小官儿对手下的卫兵点点头，卫兵便过来替他斟包多酒或是什么奥包多酒。

第六章　怎样地举办功德大会禳解地震，老实人怎样地被打板子

地震把里斯本毁了四分之三，地方上一般有道行的人，觉得要防止全城毁灭，除了替民众办一个大规模的功德会，别无他法。科印勃勒大学[11]的博士们认为，在庄严的仪式中用文火活活烧死几个人，是阻止地震万试万灵的秘方。

因此他们抓下一个波斯加伊人，两个葡萄牙人。波斯加伊人供认娶了自己的干妈[12]，葡萄牙人的罪名是吃鸡的时候把同煮的火腿扔掉。刚吃过饭的邦葛罗斯和他的门徒老实人也被捕了，一个是因为说了话，一个是因为听的神气表示赞成。两人被分别带进一间十分凉快、永远不会受到阳光刺激的屋子。八天以后，他们俩穿上特制的披风，头上戴着尖顶纸帽：老实人的披风和尖帽，画的是倒垂的火焰，一些没有尾巴、没有爪子的魔鬼；邦葛罗斯身上的魔鬼又有尾巴又有爪子，火焰是向上的。他们装束停当[13]，跟着大队游行，听了一篇悲壮动人的讲道，紧跟着又是很美妙的几部合唱的音乐。一边唱歌，一边就有人把老实人按着节拍打屁股。波斯加伊人和两个吃鸡没吃火腿的葡萄牙人被烧死了，邦葛罗斯是被吊死的，虽然这种刑罚与习惯不合。当天会后，又轰隆隆地来了一次惊心动魄的地震[14]。

老实人吓得魂不附体，目瞪口呆，头里昏昏沉沉，身上全是血迹，打着哆嗦，对自己说道：“最好的世界尚且如此，别的世界还了得？我挨打屁股倒还罢了，保加利亚人也把我打过的；可是亲爱的邦葛罗斯！你这个最伟大的哲学家！我连你罪名都不知道，竟眼看你被吊死，难道是应该的吗？噢，亲爱的雅各，你这个最好的好人，难道应该淹死在港口里吗？噢，居内贡小姐，你这女中之宝，难道应当被人开肠剖肚吗？”

老实人听过布道，打过屁股，受了赦免，受了祝福，东倒西歪，挣扎着走回去，忽然有个老婆子过来和他说：“孩子，鼓起勇气来，跟我走。”

第七章　一个老婆子怎样地照顾老实人，老实人怎样地重遇爱人

老实人谈不到什么勇气，只跟着老婆子走进一所破屋：她给他一罐药膏叫他搽，又给他饮食；屋内有一张还算干净的床，床边摆着一套衣服。

她说：“你尽管吃喝；但愿阿多夏的圣母、巴杜的圣·安东尼、刚波斯丹的圣·雅各，一齐保佑你：我明儿再来。”

老实人对于见到的事、受到的灾难，始终莫名其妙，老婆子的慈悲尤其使他诧异。他想亲她的手。

老婆子说道：“你该亲吻的不是我的手；我明儿再来。你搽着药膏，吃饱了好好地睡吧。”

老实人虽则遭了许多横祸，还是吃了东西，睡着了。第二天，老婆子送早点来，看了看他的背脊，替他涂上另外一种药膏；过后又端中饭来；傍晚又送夜饭来。第三天，她照常办事。

老实人紧盯着问：“你是谁啊？谁使你这样大发善心的？教我怎么报答你呢？”

好心的女人始终不出一声；晚上她又来了，却没有端晚饭，只说：“跟我走，别说话。”

她扶着他在野外走了半里多路，到一所孤零零的屋子，四周有花园，有小河。老婆子在一扇小门上敲了几下。门开了，她带着老实人打一座暗梯走进一个金漆小房间，叫他坐在一张金银铺绣的便榻上，关了门，走了。老实人以为是做梦，他把一生看作一个噩梦，把眼前看作一个好梦。

一忽儿老婆子又出现了，好不费事地扶着一个浑身发抖的女子，庄严魁伟，戴着面网，一派的珠光宝气。

老婆子对老实人说：“你来，把面网揭开。”

老实人上前怯生生地举起手来。哪知不揭犹可，一揭就出了奇事！他以为看到了居内贡小姐；他果然看到了居内贡小姐，不是她是谁！老实人没了气力，说不出话，倒在她脚下。居内贡倒在便榻上。老婆子灌了许多酒，他们才醒过来，谈话了：先是断断续续的一言半语，双方同时发问，同时回答，不知叹了多少气，流了多少泪，叫了多少声。老婆子教他们把声音放低一些，丢下他们走了。

老实人和居内贡说：“怎么，是你！你还活着！怎么会在葡萄牙碰到你？邦葛罗斯说你被人强奸，被人开肠剖肚，都是不确的吗？”

美丽的居内贡答道：“一点儿不假。可是一个人受了这两种难，不一定就死的。”

“你爸爸妈妈被杀死，可是真的？”

“真的。”居内贡哭着回答。

“那么你的哥哥呢？”

“他也被杀死了。”

“你怎么在葡萄牙的？怎么知道我也在这里？你用了什么妙计，教人带我到这屋子来的？”

那女的说道：“我等会儿告诉你。你先讲给我听：从你给了我纯洁的一吻、被踢了一顿起，到现在为止，经过些什么事？”

老实人恭恭敬敬听从了她的吩咐。虽则头脑昏沉，声音又轻又抖，脊梁还有点儿作痛，他仍是很天真地把别后的事统统告诉了她。居内贡眼睛望着天；听到雅各和邦葛罗斯的死，不免落了几滴眼泪。接着她和老实人说了后面一席话，老实人一字不漏地听着，目不转睛地瞅着她，仿佛要把她吞下去似的。

第八章　居内贡的经历

“我正躺在床上，睡得很熟，不料上天一时高兴，打发保加利亚人到我们森特—登—脱龙克美丽的宫堡中来；他们把我父亲和哥哥抹了脖子，把我母亲割作几块。一个高大的保加利亚人，身长六尺，看我为了父母的惨死昏迷了，就把我强奸；这一下我可醒了，立刻神志清楚，大叫大嚷，拼命挣扎，口咬，手抓，恨不得挖掉那保加利亚高个子的眼睛；我不知道我父亲宫堡中发生的事原是常有的。那蛮子往我左腋下戳了一刀，至今还留着疤。”

天真的老实人道：“哎哟！我倒很想瞧瞧这疤呢。”

居内贡回答：“等会儿给你瞧。先让我讲下去。”

“好，讲下去吧。”老实人说。

她继续她的故事：“那时一个保加利亚上尉闯进来，看我满身是血，那兵若无其事，照旧干他的。上尉因为蛮子对他如此无礼，不禁勃然大怒，就在我身上把他杀了；又叫人替我包扎伤口，带往营部作为俘虏。我替他煮饭洗衣，其实也没有多少内衣可洗。不瞒你说，他觉得我挺美；我也不能否认他长得挺漂亮，皮肤又白又嫩；除此以外，他没有什么思想，不懂什么哲学；明明没受过邦葛罗斯博士的熏陶。过了三个月，他钱都花完了，对我厌倦了，把我卖给一个犹太人，叫作唐·伊萨加，在荷兰与葡萄牙两地做买卖的，极好女色。他对我很中意，可是占据不了；我抗拒他不像抗拒保加利亚兵那样软弱。一个清白的女子可能被强奸一次，但她的贞操倒反受了锻炼。犹太人想收服我，送我到这座乡下别墅来。我一向以为森特—登—脱龙克宫堡是世界上最美的屋子，现在才发觉我错了。

“异教裁判所的大法官有天在弥撒祭中见到我，用手眼镜向我瞄了好几回，叫人传话，说有机密事儿和我谈。我走进他的府第，说明我的出身；他解释给我听，让一个以色列人霸占对我是多么有失身份。接着有人出面向唐·伊萨加提议，要他把我让给法官大人。唐·伊萨加是宫廷中的银行家，很有面子，一口回绝了。大法官拿功德会吓他。犹太人受不了惊吓，讲妥了这样的条件：这所屋子跟我作为他们俩的共有财产，星期一、三、六归犹太人，余下的日子归大法官。这协议已经成立了六个月。争执还是有的；因为决不定星期六至星期日之间的那一夜应该归谁。至于我，至今对他们俩一个都不接受，大概就因为此，他们对我始终宠爱不衰。

“后来为了禳解地震，同时为了吓吓唐·伊萨加，大法官办了一个功德大会。我很荣幸地被邀观礼，坐着上席；弥撒祭和行刑之间的休息时期，还有人侍候女太太们喝冷饮。看到两个犹太人和娶了干妈的那个老实的波斯加伊人被烧死，我的确非常恐惧，但一见有个身穿披风、头戴纸帽的人，脸孔很像邦葛罗斯，我的诧异、惊惧、惶惑更不消说了。我抹了抹眼睛，留神细看；他一吊上去，我就昏迷了。我才苏醒，又看到你剥得精赤条条的；我那时的恐惧、错愕、痛苦、绝望真是达于极点。可是老实说，你的皮肤比我那保加利亚上尉的还要白，还要红得好看。我一见之下，那些把我煎熬把我折磨的感觉更加强了。我叫着嚷着，想喊：‘喂，住手呀！你们这些蛮子！’只是喊不出声音，而且即使喊出来也未必有用。等你打完了屁股，我心里想：怎么大智大慧的邦葛罗斯和可爱的老实人会在里斯本，一个挨了鞭子，一个被吊死？而且都是把我当作心肝宝贝的大法官发的命令！邦葛罗斯从前和我说，世界上一切都十全十美；现在想来，竟是残酷的骗人话。

“紧张，慌乱，一忽儿气得发疯，一忽儿四肢无力，快死过去了；我头脑乱糟糟的，想的无非是父母兄长的惨死，下流的保加利亚兵的蛮横，他扎我的一刀，我的沦为奴仆、身为厨娘，还有那保加利亚上尉，无耻的唐·伊萨加，卑鄙的大法官，邦葛罗斯博士的吊死，你挨打屁股时大家合唱的圣诗，尤其想着我最后见到你的那天，在屏风后面给你的一吻。我感谢上帝教你受尽了折磨仍旧回到我身边来。我吩咐侍候我的老婆子照顾你，能带到这儿来的时候就带你来。她把事情办得很妥当。现在能跟你相会，听你说话，和你谈心，我真乐死了。你大概饿极了吧；我肚子闹饥荒了；来，咱们先吃饭吧。”

两人坐上饭桌；吃过晚饭，又回到上文提过的那张便榻上；他们正在榻上的时候，两个屋主之中的一个，唐·伊萨加大爷到了。那天是星期六，他是来享受权利、诉说他的深情的。

第九章　居内贡、老实人、大法官和犹太人的遭遇

自从以色列国民被移置巴比伦到现在，这伊萨加是性情最暴烈的希伯来人了[15]。

他说：“什么！你这加利利[16]的母狗，养了大法官还不够，还要我跟这个杂种平分吗？”

说着抽出随身的大刀，直扑老实人，没想到老实人也有武器。咱们这个威斯发里青年，从老婆子那儿得到衣服的时候也得了一把剑。他虽是性情和顺，也不免拔出剑来，教以色列人直挺挺地横在美丽的居内贡脚下。

她嚷起来：“圣母玛丽亚！怎么办呢？家里出了人命了！差役一到，咱们就完啦。”

老实人说：“邦葛罗斯要没有吊死，在这个危急的关头，一定能替咱们出个好主意，因为他是大哲学家。既然他死了，咱们去跟老婆子商量吧。”

她非常乖巧，刚开始发表意见，另外一扇小门又开了。那时已经半夜一点，是星期日了。这一天是大法官的名分。他进来，看见打过屁股的老实人握着剑，地下躺着个死人，居内贡面无人色，老婆子正在出主意。

那时老实人转的念头是这样的：“这圣徒一开口叫人，我就万无侥幸，一定得被活活烧死；他对居内贡也可能如法炮制。他多狠心，叫人打我屁股；何况又是我的情敌；现在我杀了人，被他当场撞见，不能再三心二意了。”

这些念头来得又快又清楚；他便趁大法官还在发愣的当口，马上利剑一挥，把他从前胸戳到后背，刺倒在犹太人旁边。

“啊，又是一个！”居内贡说，“那还有宽赦的希望吗？我们要被驱逐出教，我们的末日到了。你性子多和顺，怎么不出两分钟会杀了一个犹太人、一个主教的[17]？”

老实人答道：“美丽的小姐，一个人动了爱情，起了妒性，被异教裁判所打了屁股，竟变得连自己也认不得了。”

老婆子道：“马房里有三匹安达鲁齐马，鞍辔俱全；叫老实人去套好牲口；太太有的是金洋钻石；快快上马，奔加第士去；我只有半个屁股好骑马，也顾不得了；天气很好，趁夜凉赶路也是件快事。”

老实人立刻把三匹马套好。居内贡、老婆子和他三人一口气直赶了四五十里。他们在路上逃亡期间，公安大队到了那屋子；他们把法官大人葬在一所华丽的教堂内，把犹太人扔在垃圾堆上。

老实人、居内贡和老婆子到了莫雷那山中的一个小镇，叫作阿伐赛那。他们在一家酒店里谈了下面一段话。

第十章　老实人、居内贡和老婆子怎样一贫如洗地到加第士，怎样地上船

居内贡一边哭一边说：“啊，谁偷了我的比斯多[18]和钻石？教咱们靠什么过活呢？怎么办呢？哪里再能找到大法官和犹太人，给我金洋和钻石呢？”

老婆子道：“唉！昨天晚上有个芳济会神父，在巴大育和我们宿在一个客栈里，我疑心是他干的事；青天在上，我决不敢冤枉好人，不过那神父到我们房里来过两次，比我们早走了不知多少时候。”

老实人道：“哎啊！邦葛罗斯常常向我证明，尘世的财富是人类的公产，人人皆得而取之。根据这原则，那芳济会神父应当留下一部分钱，给我们作路费。美丽的居内贡，难道他什么都不留给我们吗？”

她说：“一个子儿都没留。”

老实人道：“那怎么办呢？”

老婆子道：“卖掉一匹马吧；我虽然只有半个屁股，还是可以骑在小姐背后；这样我们就可以到加第士了。”

小客栈中住着一个本多会修院的院长，花了很低的价钱买了马。老实人、居内贡和老婆子，经过罗赛那、基拉斯、莱勃列克撒，到了加第士。加第士正在编一个舰队，招募士兵，预备教巴拉圭的耶稣会神父[19]就范，因为有人告他们煽动某个部落反抗西班牙与葡萄牙的国王。老实人在保加利亚吃过粮，便到那支小小的远征军中，当着统领的面表演保加利亚兵操，身段、动作那么高雅、迅速、利落、威武、矫捷，统领看了，立即分拨一连步兵归他统率。他当了上尉，带着居内贡小姐、老婆子、两名当差和葡萄牙异教裁判所大法官的两匹安达鲁齐马，上了船。

航行途中，他们一再讨论可怜的邦葛罗斯的哲学。

“现在咱们要到另外一个世界去了；大概那个世界是十全十美的。因为老实说，我们这儿的物质生活和精神生活，的确有点儿可悲可叹。”居内贡道，“我真是一心一意地爱你，可是我所看到的、所经历的，使我还惊慌得很呢。”

“以后就好啦，”老实人回答，“这新世界的海洋已经比我们欧洲的好多了；浪更平静，风也更稳定。最好的世界一定是新大陆。”

居内贡说：“但愿如此！可是在我那世界上，我遭遇太惨了，几乎不敢再存什么希望。”

老婆子说：“你们都怨命，唉！你们还没受过我那样的灾难呢。”

居内贡差点儿笑出来，觉得老婆子自称为比她更苦命，未免可笑；她道：“哎！我的老妈妈，除非你被两个保加利亚兵强奸，除非你肚子上挨过两刀，除非你有两座宫堡毁掉，除非人家当着你的面杀死了你两个父亲两个母亲，除非你有两个情人在功德会中挨打，我就不信你受的灾难会超过我的；还得补上一句：我是七十二代贵族之后，身为男爵的女儿，结果竟做了厨娘。”

“小姐，”老婆子回答，“你不知道我的出身；你要是看到我的屁股，就不会说这种话，也不会下这个断语了。”这两句话大大地引起了居内贡和老实人的好奇心。老婆子便说出下面一番话来。

第十一章　老婆子的身世

“我不是一向眼睛里长满红筋、眼圈这么赤红的；鼻子也不是一向碰到下巴的，我也不是一向当用人的。我是教皇厄尔彭十世和巴莱斯德利那公主生的女儿；十四岁以前住的王府，把你们日耳曼全体男爵的宫堡做它的马房还不配；威斯发里全省的豪华，还抵不上我一件衣衫。我越长越美，越风流，越多才多艺；我享尽快乐，受尽尊敬，前程远大。我很早就能挑动人家的爱情了。乳房慢慢地变得丰满，而且是何等样的乳房！又白，又结实，模样儿活像梅迭西斯的《维纳斯》[20]身上的。还有多美的眼睛！多美的眼皮！多美的黑眉毛！两颗眼珠射出来的火焰，像当地的诗人们说的，直盖过了天上的星光。替我更衣的女用人们，常常把我从前面看到后面，从后面看到前面，看得出神了，所有的男人都恨不得做她们的替工呢。

“我跟玛沙—加拉的王子订了婚。啊！一位多么体面的王子！长得跟我一样美，说不尽的温柔、风雅，而且才华盖世，热情如火。我爱他的情分就像初恋一样，对他五体投地、如醉若狂。婚礼已经开始筹备了。场面的盛大是空前的；连日不断的庆祝会，骑兵大操，滑稽歌剧；全意大利争着写十四行诗来歌颂我，我还嫌没有一首像样的。

“我快要大喜的时候，一个做过王子情妇的老侯爵夫人，请他到家里去喝巧克力茶。不到两小时，他抽搐打滚，形状可怕，竟自死了。

“这还不算一回事。我母亲绝望之下——其实还不及我伤心——想暂时离开一下那个不祥之地。她在迦伊埃德附近有块极好的庄田。我们坐着一条本国的兵船，布置得金碧辉煌，好比罗马圣·比哀教堂的神龛。谁知海盗半路上来袭击，上了我们的船。我们的兵不愧为教皇的卫队，他们的抵抗是丢下枪械，跪倒在地，只求饶命。

“海盗立即把他们剥得精光，像猴子一般；我的母亲，我们的宫女，连我自己都在内。那些先生剥衣服手法的神速，真可佩服。但我还有更诧异的事呢：他们把手指放在我们身上的某个部分，那是女人平日只让医生安放套管的。这个仪式，我觉得很奇怪。一个人不出门就难免少见多怪。不久我知道，那是要瞧瞧我们有没有隐藏什么钻石。在往来海上的文明人中间，这风俗由来已久，从什么时代开始已经不可考了。我知道玛德会的武士们[21]俘获土耳其人的时候，不论男女，也从来不漏掉这个手续；这是没有人违反的一条公法。

“一个年轻公主，跟着母亲被带往摩洛哥去当奴隶，那种悲惨也不必细说了。在海盗船上受的罪，你们不难想象。我母亲还非常好看；我们的宫女，连一个普通女仆的姿色，也是全非洲找不出来的。至于我，长得那么迷人，赛过天仙下凡，何况还是个处女。但我的童贞并没保持多久：我替俊美的王子保留的一朵花，给海盗船上的船长硬摘了去。他是一个奇丑无比的黑人，自以为大大抬举了我呢。不必说，巴莱斯德利那公主和我，身体都很壮健，因此受尽折磨，还能挨到摩洛哥。闲言少叙；这些事也太平常了，不值一提。

“我们到的时节，摩洛哥正是一片血海。摩莱·伊斯玛伊皇帝的五十个儿子各有党派；那就有了五十场内战；黑人打黑人，黑人打半黑人[22]，半黑人打半黑人，黑白混血种人打黑白混血种人。全个帝国变了一个日夜开工的屠宰场。

“才上岸，与我们的海盗为敌的一帮黑人，立刻过来抢他的战利品。最贵重的东西，除了钻石与黄金，就要算到我们了。我那时看到的厮杀，你们休想在欧洲地面上看到；这是水土关系。北方人没有那种热血，对女人的疯劲也不像在非洲那么普遍。欧洲人血管里仿佛羼着牛奶；阿特拉斯山[23]一带的居民，血管里有的是硫酸，有的是火。他们的厮杀就像当地的狮虎毒蛇一般猛烈，目的是要抢我们。一个摩尔人抓着我母亲的右臂，我船上的大副抓着她的左臂，一个摩尔兵拽着她的一条腿，我们的一个海盗拽着另外一条。全体妇女几乎同时都被四个兵扯着。船长把我藏在他身后，手里握着大弯刀；敢冒犯他虎威的，他都来一个杀一个。临了，所有的意大利妇女，连我母亲在内，全被那些你争我夺的魔王撕裂了，扯作几块。海盗、俘虏、兵、水手、黑人、半黑人、白人、黑白混血种人，还有我那船长，全都死了；我压在死人底下，只剩一口气。同样的场面出现在一千多里的土地上，可是穆罕默德规定的一天五次祈祷，他们从来没耽误。

“我费了好大气力，从多少鲜血淋漓的尸首下面爬出来，一步一步，挨到附近一条小溪旁边，一株大橘树底下：又惊又骇，又累又饿，不由得倒下去了。我疲倦已极，一忽儿就睡着；那与其说是休息，不如说是晕厥。正当我困惫昏迷、半死半活的时候，忽然觉得有件东西压在我身上乱动。睁开眼来，只见一个气色很好的白种人，叹着气，含含糊糊说出几个意大利字：多倒霉啊，一个人没有了……”

第十二章　老婆子遭难的下文

“我听到本国的语言惊喜交集，那句话也同样使我诧异。我回答他说，比他抱怨的更倒霉的事儿，多得很呢。我三言两语，说出我才经历的悲惨事儿，但我精神又不济了。他抱我到邻近一所屋子里，放在床上，给我吃东西，殷勤服侍，好言相慰，恭维我说，他从来没见过我这样的美人儿，他对自己那个无可补救的损失，也从来没有这样懊恼过。

“他道：‘我生在拿波里；地方上每年要阉割两三千儿童：有的割死了，有的嗓子变得比女人的还好听，又有的大起来治理国家大事[24]。我的手术非常成功，在巴莱斯德利那公主府上当教堂乐师。’

“我叫起来：‘那是我的母亲啊！’

“‘你的母亲！’他哭着嚷道，‘怎么！你就是我带领到六岁的小公主吗？你现在的才貌，那时已经看得出了。’

“‘是我呀；我母亲就在离开这儿四百步的地方，被人剁了几块，压在一大堆死尸底下……’

“我告诉了他前前后后的遭遇；他也把他的经历告诉了我。某基督教强国派他来见摩洛哥王，商量一项条约，规定由某强国供给火药、大炮、船只，帮助摩洛哥王破坏别个基督教国家的商业。

“那太监说：‘我的使命已经完成，正要到葛太去搭船，可以带你回意大利。可是多倒霉啊，一个人没有……’

“我感动得流下泪来，向他千恩万谢。但他并不带我回意大利，而是带往阿尔泽，把我卖给当地的总督。我刚换了主人，蔓延欧、亚、非三洲的那场大瘟疫，就在阿尔泽发作了，来势可真不小。你们见过地震，可是，小姐，你可曾见过鼠疫？”

“没有。”男爵小姐回答。

老婆子又道：“要是见过，你们就会承认比地震可怕得多。鼠疫在非洲是常事；我也被传染了。你们想想吧：一个教皇的女儿，只有十五岁，短短三个月时间就变作赤贫，变作奴隶，几乎天天被强奸，眼看母亲的肢体四分五裂，自己又尝遍饥饿和战争的味道，在阿尔泽得了九死一生的鼠疫。可是我竟没有死。不过我那个太监和总督，以及总督的姬妾，都送了命。

“可怕的鼠疫第一阵袭击过了以后，总督的奴隶被一齐出卖。有个商人把我买下来，带往突尼斯，转卖给另一个商人；他带我上的黎波里，又把我卖了；从的黎波里卖到亚历山大，从亚历山大卖到斯麦那，从斯麦那卖到君士坦丁堡。最后我落入苏丹御林军一个军官手里，不久他奉派出去，帮阿左夫抵抗围困他们的俄罗斯人[25]。

“那军官是个多情种子，把全部姬妾都带着走，安置在阿左夫海口上一个小炮台里，拨两个黑人太监和二十名士兵保护。我们这边杀了无数俄罗斯人，俄罗斯人也照样回敬我们。阿左夫变成了一片火海血海，男女老幼无一幸免，只剩下我们的小炮台；敌人打算教我们活活饿死；可是二十名卫兵早就赌神发咒，决不投降。他们饿极了，没有办法，只得拿两名太监充饥，生怕违背他们发的愿。几天以后，他们决意吃妇女了。

“我们有个很虔诚很慈悲的回教祭司，对卫兵恳切动人地讲了一次道，劝他们别把我们完全杀死。他说：‘你们只消把这些太太们割下半个屁股，就可大快朵颐；倘若再有需要，过几天还有这么丰盛的一餐等着你们。你们这种大慈大悲的行为，足以上感苍天，得到救助的。’

“他滔滔雄辩，把卫兵说服了。我们便受了这个残酷的手术。祭司拿阉割的儿童用的药膏，替我们敷上。我们差不多全要死了。

“卫兵们刚吃完我们供应的筵席，俄罗斯人已经坐了平底船冲进来，把卫兵杀得一个不留。俄罗斯人对我们的情形不加理会。幸而世界上到处都有法国军医；其中有个本领挺高强的来救护我们，把我们治好了。我一辈子也不会忘记，我的伤疤完全结好的那天，他就向我吐露爱意。同时还劝我们大家别伤心；说好几次围城的战争都发生同样的事，那是战争的定律。

“等到我的同伴们都能走路了，就被带往莫斯科。分派之下，我落在一个贵族手里；他叫我种园地，每天赏我二十鞭子。两年之后，宫廷中互相倾轧的结果，我那位爵爷和三十来个别的贵族，都被凌迟处死。我乘机逃走，穿过整个俄罗斯，做了多年酒店侍女，先是在里加，后来在罗斯托克、维斯玛、来比锡、卡塞尔、攸德累克德、来顿、海牙、罗忒达姆。贫穷和耻辱，磨得我人也老了；我只剩着半个屁股，永远忘不了是教皇之女；几百次想自杀，却始终丢不下人生。这个可笑的弱点，大概就是我们的致命伤：时时刻刻要扔掉的枷锁，偏偏要继续背下去；一面痛恨自己的生命，一面又死抓不放；把咬你的毒蛇搂在怀里抚摩，直到它吃掉你的心肝为止。这不是愚不可及是什么？

“在我命里要漂流过的地方上，在我当过侍女的酒店里，诅咒自己生命的人，我不知见过多少；但自愿结束苦命的，只见到十二个：三个黑人、四个英国人、四个日内瓦人，还有一个叫作罗贝克的德国教授。最后我在犹太人唐·伊萨加家当老妈子；他派我服侍你，美丽的小姐；我关切着你的命运，对你的遭遇比对我自己的还要操心。我永远不会提到自己的苦难，要不是你们把我激了一下，要不是船上无聊，照例得讲些故事消遣消遣。

“总而言之，小姐，我有过经验，见过世面；你不妨请每个乘客讲一讲他们的历史，借此解闷；只要有一个人不自怨其生，不常常自命为世界上最苦的人，你尽管把我倒提着摔下海去。”

第十三章　老实人怎样地不得不和居内贡与老婆子分离

美丽的居内贡听了老婆子的故事，便按照她的身份与品德，向她施礼。居内贡也听了老婆子的主意，邀请全体乘客挨着次序讲自己的身世。老实人和居内贡听着，承认老婆子有理。

老实人说：“可惜葡萄牙的功德大会不照规矩，把大智大慧的邦葛罗斯吊死了；要不然他对于海陆两界的物质与精神的痛苦，准能发表一套妙论，而我也觉得颇有胆气，敢恭恭敬敬地向他提出几点异议。”

每个乘客讲着他的故事，不觉航行迅速，已经到了布韦诺斯·爱累斯[26]。居内贡、老实人上尉和老婆子，一同去见唐·斐南多总督，他有伊巴拉、腓加罗阿、玛斯卡林、朗波尔陶和索萨[27]五处封邑。那位大人拥有这么多头衔，自然有一副高傲的气概，配合他的身份。他和人说话，用的是鄙夷不屑的态度，鼻子举得那么高，嗓子喊得那么响，口吻那么威严，神情那么傲慢，使晋见的人都恨不得揍他一顿。他好色若命，觉得居内贡是他生平第一次见到的美人儿，一开口便问她是不是上尉的老婆。老实人看了问话的神气吓了一跳：他既不敢说是老婆，因为她其实不是；又不敢说是姊妹，因为她其实也不是；虽则这一类的谎话在古人中很通行[28]，对今人也有很多方便，但老实人太纯洁了，不敢有半点儿隐瞒，便道：“承蒙居内贡小姐不弃，已经答应下嫁小人，我们还要请大人屈尊，主持婚礼呢。”

唐·斐南多·特·伊巴拉翘起胡子，狞笑了一下，吩咐老实人去检阅部队。老实人只得遵命；总督留下居内贡小姐，向她表示热情，宣布第二天就和她成婚，不管在教堂里行礼还是用别的仪式，他太喜欢她的姿色了。居内贡要求宽限一刻钟，让她定定神，跟老婆子商量一下，而她自己也得打个主意。

老婆子对居内贡说：“小姐，你没有一个小钱，空有七十二代的家谱；总督是南美洲最有权势的爵爷，长着一绺漂亮胡子；要做总督夫人只在你自己手里。莫非你还心高气傲，打算苦熬苦守，从一而终吗？你已经被保加利亚人强奸；一失身于犹太人，再失身于大法官。吃苦吃多了，也该尝尝甜头。换了我，决不三心二意，一定嫁给总督大人，一方面提拔老实人，帮他升官发财。”

老婆子正凭着年龄与经验，说着这番考虑周详的话，港口里却驶进一条小船，载着一个法官和几名差役。事情是这样的：

老婆子原没猜错，当初居内贡和老实人匆匆忙忙逃走，在巴大育镇上失落的珠宝的确是一个宽袍大袖的芳济会神父偷的。他想把一部分宝石卖给一个珠宝商，珠宝商识破是大法官的东西。神父被吊死以前，供认珠宝是偷来的，说出失主的面貌行踪。官方发觉了居内贡和老实人逃亡的路线，一直追踪到加第士，到了加第士，立即派一条船跟着来。那船已经进入布韦诺斯·爱累斯港，外面纷纷传说，有个法官就要上岸，缉捕谋杀大主教的凶手。

机灵的老婆子当下心生一计，对居内贡说道：“你不能逃，也不用怕，杀大主教的不是你；何况总督喜欢你，决不让人家得罪你的，你尽管留在这儿。”

她又赶去找老实人，说道：“快快逃吧；要不然一小时之内，你就得上火刑台。”

事情果然紧急，一刻都耽误不得；可是老实人怎么舍得下居内贡呢？又投奔哪儿去呢？

第十四章　老实人与加刚菩在巴拉圭的耶稣会士中受到怎样的招待[29]

老实人曾经在加第士雇了一个人当差。在西班牙沿海和殖民地，那种人是很多的。他名叫加刚菩，四分之一是西班牙血统，父亲是图库曼[30]地方的一个混血种。他当过助祭童子、圣器执事、水手、修士、乐器工匠、大兵、跟班。加刚菩非常喜欢他的东家，因为东家待人宽厚。当下他抢着把两匹安达鲁齐马披挂停当，说道：“喂，大爷，咱们还是听老婆子的话，三十六着走为上。”

老实人掉着泪说：“噢！我亲爱的居内贡！总督大人正要替我们主婚了，我倒反而把你扔下来吗？路远迢迢地来到这里，你如今怎么办呢？”

加刚菩道：“由她去吧，女人家自有本领，她有上帝保佑；咱们快走吧。”

“你把我带往哪儿呢？咱们上哪里去呢？没有了居内贡，咱们如何是好呢？”

“哎，”加刚菩回答，“你原本是要去攻打耶稣会士的，现在不妨倒过来，去替他们出力。我认得路，可以送你到他们国内；他们手下能有个会保加利亚兵操的上尉，要不高兴才怪！你将来一定飞黄腾达。这边不得意，就上那边去。何况广广眼界，干点儿新鲜事也怪有趣的。”

老实人问：“难道你在巴拉圭耽过吗？”

加刚菩道：“怎么没耽过？我在阿松西翁学院做过校役，我对于耶稣会政府，跟加第士的街道一样熟。那政府真是了不起。国土纵横千余里，划作三十行省。神父们无所不有，老百姓一无所有；那才是理智与正义的杰作。以我个人来说，我从来没见过像那些神父一样圣明的人，他们在这里跟西班牙王、葡萄牙王作战，在欧洲听西班牙王葡萄牙王的忏悔；在这里他们见到西班牙人就杀，在玛德里把西班牙人送上天堂；我觉得有意思极了；咱们快快赶路吧。包你此去成为世界上第一个有福的人。神父们知道有个会保加利亚兵操的上尉投奔，不知要怎样快活哩！”

到了第一道关塞，加刚菩告诉哨兵，说有个上尉求见司令。哨兵把话传到守卫本部，守卫本部的一个军官亲自去报告司令。老实人和加刚菩的武器先被缴掉，两匹安达鲁齐马也被扣下。两个陌生人从两行卫兵中间走过去，行列尽头便是司令：他头戴三角帽，撩起着长袍，腰里挂着剑，手里拿着短枪。他做了一个手势，二十四个兵立刻把两个生客团团围住。一个班长过来传话，要他们等着，司令不能接见，因为省长神父不在的时节，不许任何西班牙人开口，也不许他们在本地逗留三小时以上。

加刚菩问：“那么省长神父在哪儿呢？”

班长答道：“他做了弥撒，阅兵去了；要过三个钟点，你们才能亲吻他的靴尖。”

“可是，”加刚菩说，“敝上尉是德国人，不是西班牙人。他和我一样饥肠辘辘；省长神父没到以前，能不能让我们吃顿早饭？”

班长立即把这番话报告司令。

司令说：“感谢上帝！既然是德国人，我就可以跟他说话了。带他到我帐下来。”

老实人便进入一间树荫底下的办公厅，四周是绿的云石和黄金砌成的列柱，十分华丽；笼内养着鹦鹉、蜂雀、小纹鸟和各种珍异的飞禽。黄金的食器盛着精美的早点；巴拉圭土人正捧着木盅在大太阳底下吃玉蜀黍，司令官却进了办公厅。

司令少年英俊，脸颊丰满，白皮肤，好血色，眉毛吊得老高，眼睛极精神，耳朵绯红，嘴唇红里带紫，眉宇之间有股威武的气概，但不是西班牙人的，也不是耶稣会士的那种威武。老实人和加刚菩的兵器马匹都发还了；加刚菩把牲口拴在办公厅附近，给它们吃燕麦，时时刻刻瞟上一眼，以防万一。

老实人先亲吻了司令的衣角，然后一同入席。

耶稣会士用德文说道：“你原来是德国人？”

老实人回答：“是的，神父。”

两人这么说着，都不由自主地觉得很惊奇，很激动。

耶稣会士又问：“你是德国哪个地方的？”

“敝乡是该死的威斯发里省。我的出生地是森特—登—脱龙克宫堡。”

“噢，天！怎么可能呢？”那司令嚷着。

老实人也叫道：“啊！这不是奇迹吗？”

司令问：“难道竟是你吗？”

老实人道：“这真是哪里说起！”

两人往后仰了一跤，随即互相拥抱，眼泪像小溪一般直流。

“怎么，神父，你就是美人居内贡的哥哥吗？就是被保加利亚人杀死的，就是男爵大人的儿子吗？怎么又在巴拉圭做了耶稣会神父？这世界真是太离奇了。噢，邦葛罗斯！邦葛罗斯！你要不是吊死的话，又该怎么高兴啊！”

几个黑奴和巴拉圭人端着水晶盂在旁斟酒，司令教他们回避了。他对上帝和圣·伊涅斯[31]千恩万谢，把老实人搂在怀里；两人哭作一团。

老实人道：“再告诉你一件事，你还要诧异，还要感动，还要莫名其妙哩。你以为令妹居内贡被人戳破肚子，送了性命；其实她还在人世，健康得很呢。”

“在哪里？”

“就在近边，在布韦诺斯·爱累斯的总督府上；我是特意来帮你们打仗的。”

他们那次长谈，每句话都是奇闻。两人的心都跳上了舌尖，滚到了耳边，在眼内发光。因为是德国人，他们的饭老吃不完；一边吃一边等省长神父回来。司令官又对老实人讲了下面一番话。

第十五章　老实人怎样杀死他亲爱的居内贡的哥哥

“我一世也忘不了那悲惨的日子，看着父母被杀，妹妹被强奸。等到保加利亚人走了，大家找来找去，找不到我心爱的妹子。七八里以外，有一个耶稣会的小教堂：父亲、母亲、我、两个女用人和三个被杀的男孩子，都给装上一辆小车，送往那儿埋葬。一位神父替我们洒圣水，圣水咸得要命，有几滴洒进了我的眼睛；神父瞧见我眼皮眨了一下，便摸摸我的心，觉得还在跳，就把我救了去。三个星期以后，我痊愈了。亲爱的老实人，你知道我本来长得挺好看，那时出落得越发风流倜傥；所以那修院的院长，克罗斯德神父，对我友谊深厚，给我穿上候补修士的法衣；过了一晌又送我上罗马。总会会长正在招一批年轻的德国耶稣会士。巴拉圭的执政不欢迎西班牙的耶稣会士，喜欢用外国籍教士，觉得容易管理。总会会长认为我宜于到那方面去传布福音。所以我们出发了，一共是三个人，一个波兰人，一个提罗尔人，一个就是我。一到这儿，我就荣任少尉和助理祭司之职；现在已经升了中校，做了神父。我们对待西班牙王上的军队毫不客气；我向你担保，他们早晚要被驱逐出教，被我们打败的。你是上帝派来帮助我们的。告诉我，我的妹子可是真的在近边，在布韦诺斯·爱累斯总督那儿？”

老实人赌神发咒，回答说那是千真万确的事。于是两人又流了许多眼泪。

男爵再三再四地拥抱老实人，把他叫作兄弟，叫作恩人。他说：“啊，亲爱的老实人，说不定咱们俩将来打了胜仗，可以一同进城去救出我的妹子来。”

老实人回答：“这正是我的心愿；我早打算娶她的，至今还抱着这个希望。”

“怎么！浑蛋！”男爵抢着说，“我妹妹是七十二代贵族之后，你好大胆子，竟想娶她？亏你有这个脸，敢在我面前说出这样狂妄的主意！”

老实人听了这话呆了一呆，答道：“神父，家谱有什么用？我把你妹妹从一个犹太人和一个大法官怀中救出来，她很感激我，愿意嫁给我。老师邦葛罗斯常说的，世界上人人平等；我将来非娶她不可。”

“咱们走着瞧吧，流氓！”那森特—登—脱龙克男爵兼耶稣会教士一边说，一边拿剑背往老实人脸上狠狠地抽了一下。

老实人马上拔出剑来，整个儿插进男爵神父的肚子；等到把剑热腾腾地抽出来，老实人却哭着嚷着：“哎哟！我的上帝！我杀了我的旧主人，我的朋友，我的舅子了；我是天底下最好的好人，却已经犯了三条人命，内中两个还是教士！”

在办公厅门口望风的加刚菩立刻赶进来。

主人对他道：“现在只有跟他们拼命了，多拼一个好一个。他们一定要进来的，咱们杀到底吧。”

加刚菩事情见得多，镇静非凡；他剥下男爵的法衣穿在老实人身上，把死人头上的三角帽也给他戴了，扶他上马。这些事，一眨眼之间就安排停当了。

“大爷，快走吧；他们会当你是神父出去发布命令；即使追上来，咱们也早过了边境了。”

说话之间，加刚菩已经长驱而出，嘴里用西班牙文叫着：“闪开！闪开！中校神父来啦！”

第十六章　两个旅客遇到两个姑娘、两只猴子和叫作大耳朵的野蛮人

老实人和他的当差出了关塞，那边营里还没人知道德国神父的死。细心的加刚菩办事周到，把行囊装满了面包、巧克力、火腿、水果，还有几升酒。他们骑着两匹安达鲁齐马，进入连路都没有的陌生地方。后来发现一片青葱的草原，中间夹着几条小溪。两位旅客先让牲口在草地上大嚼一顿。加刚菩向主人提议吃东西，他自己以身作则，先吃起来了。

老实人说道：“我杀了男爵大人的儿子，又一世见不到美人儿居内贡，教我怎么吃得下火腿呢？和她离得这么远，又是悔恨，又是绝望，这样悲惨的日子，过下去还有什么意思？德雷甫的《见闻录》[32]又要怎样说我呢？”

他这么说着照旧吃个不停。太阳下山了。两位迷路的人听见几声轻微的呼叫，好像是女人的声音。他们辨不出是痛苦的叫喊，还是快乐的叫喊。一个人在陌生地方不免提心吊胆；他们俩便急忙站起。叫喊的原来是两个赤身露体的姑娘，在草原上奔跑，身子非常轻灵；两只猴子紧跟在后面，咬她们的屁股。老实人看了大为不忍。他在保加利亚军中学会了放枪，能够在树林中打下一颗榛子，决不碰到两旁的叶子。他便拿起他的西班牙双膛枪，一连两响，把两只猴子打死了，说道：“亲爱的加刚菩，我真要感谢上帝，居然救了两个可怜的姑娘的命。杀掉一个大法官和一个耶稣会士，固然罪孽不轻；这一来也可以将功赎罪了。或许她们是大人家的女儿，可能使我们在本地得到不少方便呢。”

他还想往下说，不料两个姑娘不胜怜爱地抱着两只猴子，放声大恸，四下里只听见一片凄惨的哭声。老实人顿时张口结舌，愣住了。

终于他对加刚菩道：“想不到有这样好心肠的人。”

加刚菩答道：“大爷，你做的好事；你把这两位小姐的情人打死了。”

“她们的情人！怎么可能？加刚菩，你这是说笑话吧？教我怎么能相信呢？”

加刚菩回答说：“大爷，你老是这个脾气，对什么事都大惊小怪。有些地方，猴子会博得女人欢心，有什么稀奇！它们也是四分之一的人，正如我是四分之一的西班牙人。”

老实人接着道：“不错，老师邦葛罗斯讲过，这一类的事从前就有，杂交的结果，生下那些半羊半人的怪物；古时几位名人还亲眼见过，但我一向以为是无稽之谈。”

加刚菩道：“现在你该相信了吧！你瞧，没有教育的人会做出什么事来。我只怕这两个女的捣乱，暗算我们。”

这番中肯的议论使老实人离开草原，躲到一个树林里去。他和加刚菩吃了晚饭；两人把葡萄牙异教裁判所的大法官，布韦诺斯·爱累斯的总督，森特—登—脱龙克男爵，咒骂了一顿，躺在藓苔上睡着了。一早醒来，他们觉得动弹不得了；原来当地的居民大耳人[33]，听了两个女子的密告，夜里跑来用树皮把他们捆绑了。周围有五十来个大耳人，拿着箭、棍、石斧之类；有的烧着一大锅水；有的在端整烤炙用的铁串；他们一齐喊着：“捉到了一个耶稣会士！捉到了一个耶稣会士！我们好报仇了，我们有好东西吃了；大家来吃耶稣会士呀，大家来吃耶稣会士呀！”

加刚菩愁眉苦脸，嚷道：“亲爱的大爷，我不是早告诉你吗？那两个女的要算计我们的。”

老实人瞧见锅子和铁串，叫道：“我们不是被烧烤，就得被白煮。啊！要是邦葛罗斯看到人的本性如此这般，不知又有什么话说！一切皆善！好，就算一切皆善，可是我不能不认为，失去了居内贡小姐，又被大耳人活烤，总是太残忍了。”

加刚菩老是不慌不忙，对发愁的老实人道：“我懂得一些他们的土话，让我来跟他们说吧。”

老实人道：“千万告诉他们，吃人是多么不人道，而且不大合乎基督的道理。”

加刚菩开言道：“诸位，你们今天打算吃一个耶稣会士，是不是？好极了，对付敌人理当如此。天赋的权利就是教我们杀害同胞，全世界的人都是这么办的。我们没有运用吃人的权利，只因为我们有旁的好菜可吃；但你们不像我们有办法。把胜利的果实扔给乌鸦享受，当然不如自己把敌人吃下肚去。可是诸位，你们决不吃你们的朋友的。你们以为要烧烤的是一个耶稣会士，其实他是保护你们的人，你们要吃的是你们敌人的敌人。至于我，我是生在你们这里的；这位先生是我的东家，非但不是耶稣会士，还杀了一个耶稣会士，他穿的便是从死人身上剥下来的衣服，所以引起了你们的误会。为了证明我的话，你们不妨拿他穿的袍子送往神父们的边境，打听一下我的主人是不是杀了一个耶稣会军官。那要不了多少时间；倘若我是扯谎，你们照旧可以吃我们。但要是我并无虚言，那么你们对于公法、风俗、法律的原则，认识太清楚了，我想你们决不会不饶赦我们的。”

大耳人觉得这话入情入理，派了两位有声望的人士做代表，立即出发去调查真假；两位代表多才多智，不辱使命，很快就回来报告好消息。大耳人解了两个俘虏的缚，对他们礼貌周到，供给他们冷饮、妇女，把他们送出国境，欢呼道：“他们不是耶稣会士！他们不是耶稣会士！”

老实人对于被释放的事赞不绝口。他道：“嗬！了不起的民族！了不起的人！了不起的风俗！我幸而把居内贡小姐的哥哥一剑刺死，要不然决无侥幸，一定给吃掉的了。可是，话得说回来，人的本性毕竟是善的，这些人非但不吃我，一知道我不是耶稣会士，还把我奉承得无微不至。”

第十七章　老实人和他的随从怎样到了黄金国，见到些什么[34]

到了大耳人的边境，加刚菩和老实人说：“东半球并不胜过西半球，听我的话，咱们还是抄一条最近的路回欧洲去吧。”

“怎么回去呢？”老实人道，“又回哪儿去呢？回到我本乡吧，保加利亚人和阿伐尔人正在那里见一个杀一个；回葡萄牙吧，要给人活活烧死；留在这儿吧，随时都有被烧烤的危险。可是居内贡小姐住在地球的这一边，我怎有心肠离开呢？”

加刚菩道：“还是往开颜[35]那方面走。那儿可以遇到法国人，世界上到处都有他们的踪迹；他们会帮助我们，说不定上帝也会哀怜我们。”

到开颜去可不容易：他们知道大概的方向；可是山岭、河流、悬崖绝壁、强盗、野蛮人，遍地都是凶险的关口。他们的马走得筋疲力尽，死了；干粮吃完了；整整一个月全靠野果充饥；后来到了一条小河旁边，两旁长满椰子树，这才把他们的性命和希望支持了一下。

加刚菩出计划策的本领一向不亚于老婆子；他对老实人道：“咱们撑不下去了，两条腿也走得够了；我瞧见河边有一条小船，不如把它装满椰子，坐在里面顺流而去；既有河道，早晚必有人烟。便是遇不到愉快的事，至少也能看到些新鲜事儿。”

老实人道：“好，但愿上帝保佑我们。”

他们在河中漂流了十余里，两岸忽而野花遍地，忽而荒瘠不毛；忽而平坦开朗，忽而危崖高耸。河道越来越阔，终于进入一个险峻可怖、岩石参天的环洞底下。两人大着胆子，让小艇往洞中驶去。河身忽然狭小，水势的湍急与轰轰的巨响令人心惊胆战。过了一昼夜，他们重见天日；可是小艇触着暗礁，撞坏了，只得在岩石上爬，直爬了三四里地。最后，两人看到一片平原，极目无际，四周都是崇山峻岭，高不可攀。土地的种植，是生计与美观同时兼顾的；没有一样实用的东西不是赏心悦目的。车辆赛过大路上的装饰品，式样新奇，构造的材料也灿烂夺目；车中男女都长得异样的俊美；驾车的是一些高大的红绵羊，奔驰迅速，便是安达鲁齐、泰图安、美基内斯的第一等骏马，也望尘莫及。

老实人道：“啊，这地方可胜过威斯发里了。”

他和加刚菩遇到第一个村子就下了地。几个村童，穿着稀烂的金银铺绣衣服，在村口玩着丢石片的游戏。从另一世界来的两位旅客，一时高兴，对他们瞧了一会儿：他们玩的石片又大又圆，光芒四射，颜色有黄的，有红的，有绿的。两位旅客心中一动，随手捡了几块，原来是黄金，是碧玉，是红宝石，最小的一块也够蒙古大皇帝做他宝座上最辉煌的装饰。

加刚菩道：“这些孩子大概是本地国王的儿女，在这里丢着石块玩儿。”

村塾的老师恰好出来唤儿童上学。

老实人道：“啊，这一定是内廷教师了。”

那些顽童马上停止游戏，把石片和别的玩具一齐留在地下。老实人赶紧捡起，奔到教师前面，恭恭敬敬地捧给他，用手势说明，王子和世子们忘了他们的金子与宝石。塾师微微一笑，接过来扔在地下，很诧异地对老实人的脸瞧了一会儿，径自走了。

两位旅客少不得把黄金、碧玉、宝石捡了许多。

老实人叫道：“这是什么地方呀？这些王子受的教育太好了，居然会瞧不起黄金宝石。”

加刚菩也和老实人一样惊奇。他们走到村中第一家人家，建筑仿佛欧洲的宫殿。一大群人都向门口拥去，屋内更挤得厉害，还传出悠扬悦耳的音乐，一阵阵珍馐美馔的异香。加刚菩走近大门，听讲着秘鲁话；那是他家乡的语言；早先交代过，加刚菩是生在图库曼的，他的村子里只通秘鲁话。他便对老实人说：“我来替你当翻译；咱们进去吧，这是一家酒店。”

店里的侍者，两男两女，穿着金线织的衣服，用缎带束着头发，邀他们入席。先端来四盘汤，每盘汤都有两只鹦鹉；接着是一盘白煮神鹰，直有两百磅重，然后是两只香美异常的烤猴子；一个盘里盛着三百只蜂雀；另外一盘盛着六百只小雀；还有几道烧烤，几道精美的甜菜；食器全部是水晶盘子。男女侍者来斟了好几种不同的甘蔗酒。

食客大半是商人和赶车的，全都彬彬有礼，非常婉转地向加刚菩问了几句，又竭诚回答加刚菩的问话，务必使他满意。

吃过饭，加刚菩和老实人一样，以为把捡来的大块黄金丢几枚在桌上，是尽够付账的了。不料铺子的男女主人见了哈哈大笑，半天直不起腰来。

后来他们止住了笑。店主人开言道：“你们两位明明是外乡人；我们却是难得见到的。抱歉得很，你们拿大路上的石子付账，我们见了不由得笑起来。想必你们没有敝国的钱，可是在这儿吃饭不用惠钞。为了便利客商，我们开了许多饭店，一律归政府开支。敝处是个小村子，地方上穷，没有好菜敬客；可是别的地方，无论上哪儿你们都能受到应有的款待。”

加刚菩把主人的话统统解释给老实人听，老实人听的时候，和加刚菩讲的时候同样的钦佩、惊奇。

两人都说：“外边都不知道有这个地方；究竟是什么国土呢？这儿的天地跟我们的完全不同！这大概是尽善尽美的乐土了，因为无论如何，世界上至少应该有这样一块地方。不管邦葛罗斯怎么说，我总觉得威斯发里样样不行。”

第十八章　他们在黄金国内的见闻

加刚菩把心中的惊异告诉店主人，店主人回答说：“我无知无识，倒也觉得很快活；可是这儿有位告老的大臣，是敝国数一数二的学者，最喜欢与人交谈。”

说完带着加刚菩去见老人。那时老实人退为配角，只能陪陪他的当差了。他们进入一所顶朴素的屋子，因为大门只是银的，屋内的护壁只是金的，但镂刻的古雅，比着最华丽的护壁也未必逊色。固然，穿堂仅仅嵌着红宝石与碧玉，但镶嵌的式样补救了质料的简陋。

老人坐在一张蜂鸟毛垫子的沙发上，接见两位来宾，叫人端酒敬客，酒瓶是钻石雕的。接着他说了下面一席话，满足他们的好奇心：

“我今年一百七十二岁；先父做过王上的洗马，亲眼见到秘鲁那次惊人的革命，把情形告诉了我。我们现在的国土原是古印加族疆域的一部分，印加族当初冒冒失失地出去扩张版图，结果却亡于西班牙人之手。

“留在国内的王族比较明哲；他们征得老百姓的同意，下令任何居民不得越出我们小小的国境，这才保证了我们的纯洁和快乐。西班牙人对这个地方略有所知，不得其详；他们把它叫作黄金国。还有一个叫作拉莱爵士的英国人，一百年前差不多到了这儿附近；幸亏我们四面都是高不可攀的峻岭和峭壁，所以至今没有遭到欧洲各民族的馋吻；他们酷爱我们的石块和泥巴，爱得发疯一般，为了抢那些东西，可能把我们杀得一个不留的。”

他们谈了很久，谈到政体、风俗、妇女、公共娱乐、艺术。素好谈玄说理的老实人，要加刚菩探问国内有没有宗教。

老人红了红脸，说道：“怎么你们会有这个疑问呢？莫非以为我们是无情无义的人吗？”

加刚菩恭恭敬敬请问黄金国的宗教是哪一种。老人又红了红脸，答道：“难道世界上还有两个宗教不成？我相信我们的宗教是跟大家一样的；我们从早到晚敬爱上帝。”

加刚菩始终替老实人当着翻译，说出他心中的疑问：“你们只崇拜一个上帝吗？”

老人道：“上帝总不见得有两个、三个、四个吧？我觉得你们世界上的人问的问题怪得很。”

老实人絮絮不休，向老人问长问短；他要知道黄金国的人怎样祈祷上帝的。那慈祥可敬的哲人回答说：“我们从来不祈祷，因为对他一无所求，我们所需要的，他全给了我们了；我们只是不断地感谢他。”

老实人很希望看看他们的教士，问他们在哪儿。老人微微一笑，说道：“告诉两位，我们国内人人都是教士，每天早上，王上和全国人民的家长都唱着感谢神恩的赞美诗，庄严肃穆，由五六千名乐师担任伴奏。”

“怎么！你们没有修士专管传教、争辩、统治、弄权窃柄、把意见不同的人活活烧死吗？”

老人道：“那我们不是发疯了吗？我们这儿大家都意见一致，你说的你们那些修士的勾当，我完全莫名其妙。”

老实人听着这些话出神了，心上想：“那跟威斯发里和男爵的宫堡完全不同；倘若邦葛罗斯见到了黄金国，就不会再说森特—登—脱龙克宫堡是世界上的乐土了；可见一个人非游历不可。”

长谈过后，慈祥的老人吩咐套起一辆六羊驾驶的四轮轿车，派十二名仆役送两位旅客进宫。他说：“抱歉得很，我年纪大了，不能奉陪。但王上接见两位的态度，决不至于得罪两位；敝国倘有什么风俗习惯使两位不快，想必你们都能原谅的。”

老实人和加刚菩上了轿车，六头绵羊像飞一样，不消四个钟点，已经到达京城一端的王宫前面。宫门高二十二丈，宽十丈；说不出是什么材料造的。可是不难看出，那材料比我们称为黄金珠宝的石子沙土，不知要贵重多少倍。

老实人和加刚菩一下车，就有二十名担任御前警卫的美女迎接，带他们去沐浴，换上蜂鸟毛织成的袍子；然后另有男女大臣引他们进入内殿，按照常例，两旁各站着一千名乐师。走近御座所在的便殿，加刚菩问一位大臣，觐见王上该用何种敬礼：“应当双膝下跪，还是全身伏在地下？应当把手按在额上，还是按着屁股？或者用舌头舐地下的尘土？总而言之，究竟是怎样的仪式？”

大臣回答：“惯例是拥抱王上，亲吻他的两颊。”

老实人和加刚菩便扑上去勾着王上的脖子，王上对他们优礼有加，很客气地请他们晚间赴宴。

宴会之前，有人陪他们去参观京城，看那些高入云表的公共建筑、千百列柱围绕的广场、日夜长流的喷泉：有的喷射清澈无比的泉水，有的喷射蔷薇的香水，有的喷射甘蔗酒；规模宏大的广场，地下铺着一种宝石，散出近乎丁香与肉桂的香味。老实人要求参观法院和大理院；据说根本没有这些机关，从来没有人打官司。老实人问有没有监狱，人家也回答说没有。但他看了最惊异最高兴的是那个科学馆，其中一个走廊长两百丈，摆满了数学和物理仪器。

整个下午在京城里逛了大约千分之一的地方，他们回到王宫。席上老实人坐在国王、加刚菩和几位太太之间。他们从来没有享受过更美的筵席，国王在饭桌上谈笑风生的雅兴，也从来没有人能相比。加刚菩把陛下的妙语一一解释给老实人听，虽然经过了翻译，还照样趣味盎然。这一点和旁的事情一样使老实人惊异赞叹。

两人在此宾馆中住了一个月。老实人再三和加刚菩说：“朋友，我生长的宫堡固然比不上这个地方；可是，究竟居内贡不在此地；或许你也有个把情人在欧洲。住在这里，我们不过是普通人，不如回到我们的世界中去，单凭十二头满载黄金国石子的绵羊，我们的财富就能盖过普天之下的国王，也不必再害怕异教裁判所，而要接回居内贡小姐也易如反掌了。”

这些话正合加刚菩的心意：人多么喜欢奔波，对自己人炫耀，卖弄游历的见闻，所以两个享福的人决意不再享福，去向国王要求离境。

国王答道：“你们这是发傻了。敝国固是蕞尔小邦，不足挂齿，但我们能苟安的地方，就不应当离开。我自然无权羁留外客；那种专制手段不在我们的风俗与法律之内；每个人都是自由的；你们随时可以动身，但出境不是件容易的事。你们能从岩洞底下的河里进来，原是奇迹，不可能再从原路出去。环绕敝国的山岭高逾千仞，陡若城墙，每座山峰宽三四十里，除了悬崖之外，别无他路可下。你们既然执意要走，让我吩咐机械司造一架机器，务必很方便地把你们运送出去。一朝到了山背后，可没有人能奉陪了；我的百姓发誓不出国境，他们不会那么糊涂，违反自己发的愿的。现在你们喜欢什么东西，尽管向我要吧。”

加刚菩说：“我们只求陛下赏几头绵羊，驮些干粮、石子和泥巴。”

国王笑道：“你们欧洲人这样喜欢我们的黄土，我简直弄不明白；好吧，你们爱带多少就带多少，但愿你们因此得福。”

国王随即下令，要工程师造一架机器把两个怪人举到山顶上，送他们出境。三千名优秀的物理学家参加工作；半个月以后，机器造好了，照当地的钱计算，只花了两千多万镑。老实人和加刚菩坐在机器上，带着两头鞍辔俱全的大红绵羊，给他们翻过山岭以后代步的；二十头载货的绵羊驮着干粮；三十头驮着礼品，都是当地最稀罕的宝物；五十头驮着黄金、钻石、宝石。国王很亲热地拥抱了两个流浪汉。

他们动身了，连人带羊举到山顶上的那种巧妙方法确是奇观。工程师们送他们到了安全地方，便和他们告别。此时老实人心中只有一个愿望，一个目的，就是把羊群献给居内贡小姐。他说：“倘若人家肯把居内贡小姐标价，我们的财力尽够向布韦诺斯·爱累斯总督纳款了。咱们上开颜去搭船，再瞧瞧有什么王国可以买下来。”

第十九章　他们在苏利南的遭遇，老实人与玛丁的相识

路上第一天过得还愉快。想到自己的财富比欧、亚、非三洲的总数还要多，两人不由得兴致十足。老实人兴奋之下，到处把居内贡的名字刻在树上。第二天，两头羊连着货物陷入沼泽；过了几日，另外两头不堪劳顿，倒毙了；接着又有七八头在沙漠中饿死；几天之后，又有些堕入深谷。走了一百天，只剩下两头羊。

老实人对加刚菩道：“你瞧，尘世的财富多么脆弱；只有德行和重见居内贡小姐的快乐才可靠。”

加刚菩答道：“对。可是我们还剩下两头羊，西班牙王一辈子也休想有它们身上的那些宝物。我远远地看到一个市镇，大概就是荷兰属的苏利南。好啦，咱们苦尽甘来了。”

靠近市镇，他们瞧见地下躺着一个黑人，衣服只剩一半，就是说只穿一条蓝布短裤：那可怜虫少了一条左腿，缺了一只右手。

老实人用荷兰话问他：“唉，天哪！你这个样子好不凄惨，待在这儿干什么呢？”

黑人回答：“我等着我的东家，大商人范特登杜[36]先生。”

老实人说：“可是范特登杜先生这样对待你的？”

“是的，先生；这是老例章程。他们每年给我们两条蓝布短裤，算是全部衣着。我们在糖厂里给磨子碾去一个手指，他们就砍掉我们的手；要是想逃，就割下一条腿：这两桩我都碰上了。我们付了这代价，你们欧洲人才有糖吃。可是母亲在几尼亚海边得了十块钱把我卖掉的时节，和我说：‘亲爱的孩子，你得感谢我们的神道，永远向他们礼拜，他们会降福于你；你好大面子，当上咱们白大人的奴隶；你爹妈也靠着你发迹了。’

“唉！我不知他们有没有靠着我发迹。反正我没有托他们的福。狗啊，猴子啊，鹦鹉啊，都不像我们这么苦命。人家教我改信荷兰神道，每星期日告诉我们，说我们不分黑白，全是亚当的孩子。我不懂家谱；但布道师说得不错，我们都是嫡堂兄弟。可是你得承认，对待本家不能比他们更辣手了。”

“噢，邦葛罗斯！”老实人嚷道，“你可没想到这种惨无人道的事。得啦得啦，我不再相信你的乐天主义了。”

“什么叫作乐天主义？”加刚菩问。

“唉！就是吃苦的时候一口咬定百事顺利。”

老实人瞧着黑人，掉下泪来。他一边哭一边进了苏利南。

他们第一先打听，港内可有船把他们载往布韦诺斯·爱累斯。问到的正是一个西班牙船主，答应跟他们公平交易，约在一家酒店里谈判。老实人和加刚菩便带着两头羊上那边去等。

老实人心直口快，把经过情形向西班牙人和盘托出，连要抢走居内贡小姐的计划也实说了。

船主回答：“我才不送你们上布韦诺斯·爱累斯去呢；我要被吊死，你们俩也免不了。美人居内贡如今是总督大人最得宠的外室。”

老实人听了好比晴天霹雳，哭了半日，终于把加刚菩拉过一边，说道：“好朋友，还是这么办吧：咱们每人口袋里都有价值五六百万的钻石；你比我精明；你上布韦诺斯·爱累斯去接居内贡小姐。要是总督作难，给他一百万；再不肯，给他两百万。你没杀过主教，他们不会防你的。我另外包一条船，上佛尼市等你；那是个自由地方，不用怕保加利亚人，也不用怕阿伐尔人，也不必担心犹太人和异教裁判所。”

加刚菩一听这妙计，拍手叫好；但要跟好东家分手，不由得悲从中来，因为他们俩已经成为知心朋友了。幸而他还能替主人出力，加刚菩想到这一点，就转悲为喜，忘了分离的痛苦。两人抱头大哭了一场；老实人又吩咐他别忘了那老妈子。加刚菩当日就动身。他可真是个好人哪。

老实人在苏利南又住了一晌，希望另外有个船主，肯把他和那硕果仅存的两头绵羊载往意大利。他雇了几个用人，把长途航行所需要的杂物也办齐了。终于有一天，一条大帆船的主人，范特登杜先生，来找他了。

老实人道：“你要多少钱，才肯把我、我的下人、行李还有两头绵羊，一径载往佛尼市？”

船主讨价一万银洋。老实人一口答应了。

机灵的范特登杜在背后说：“噢！噢！这外国人一出手就是一万！准是个大富翁。”过了一会便回去声明，少了两万不能开船。

老实人回答：“两万就两万。”

“哎啊！”那商人轻轻地自言自语，“这家伙花两万跟一万一样的满不在乎。”

他又回去，说少了三万不能把他送往佛尼市。

老实人回答：“好，依你三万就是了。”

“噢！噢！”荷兰人对自己说，“三万银洋还不在他眼里；可见两头绵羊一定驮着无价之宝。别多要了，先教他付了三万，再瞧着办。”

老实人卖了两颗小钻，其中一颗很小的，价值就不止船主所要的数目。他先付了钱。两头绵羊装上去了。老实人跟着坐了一条小艇，预备过渡到港中的大船上。船长认为时机已到，赶紧扯起篷来，解缆而去，又遇着顺风帮忙。老实人看着，目瞪口呆，一刹那就不见了帆船的踪影。他叫道：“哎哟！这一招倒比得上旧大陆的杰作。”他回到岸上，说不出多么痛苦，因为抵得上一二十位国王财富的宝物，都白送了。

他跑去见荷兰法官；性急慌忙，敲门不免敲得太粗暴了些；进去说明案由，叫嚷的声音不免太高了些。法官因为他闹了许多声响，先罚他一万银洋，方始耐性听完老实人的控诉，答应等那商人回来，立即审理。末了又要老实人缴付一万银洋讼费。

这种作风把老实人气坏了；不错，他早先遇到的倒霉事儿，给他的痛苦还百倍于此；但法官和船主这样不动声色地欺负人，使他动了肝火，悲观到极点。人心的险毒丑恶，他完全看到了，一肚子全是忧郁的念头。后来有条开往波尔多的法国船：他既然丢了满载钻石的绵羊，便花了很公道的代价，包下一间房舱。他又在城里宣布，要找一个诚实君子做伴，船钱饭食，一应归他，再送两千银洋酬劳。但这个人必须是本省遭遇最苦、最怨恨自己的行业的人。

这样就招来一大群应征的人，便是包一个舰队也容纳不下。老实人存心要在最值得注目的一批中去挑，当场选出一二十个看来还和气，又自命为最有资格入选的人，邀到酒店里，请他们吃饭；条件是要他们发誓，毫不隐瞒地说出自己的历史。老实人声明，他要挑一个他认为最值得同情、最有理由怨恨自己行业的人；其余的一律酌送现金，作为酬报。

这个会直开到清早四点。老实人听着他们的遭遇，一边想着老婆子当初来的时候说的话，赌的东道，断定船上没有一个人不受过极大的灾难。每听一个故事，他必想着邦葛罗斯，他道：“恐怕邦葛罗斯不容易再证明他的学说了吧！可惜他不在这里。世界上果真有什么乐土，那一定是黄金国，决不在别的地方。”末了他挑中一个可怜的学者，在阿姆斯特登的书店里做过十年事。他认为世界上没有一个职业比他的更可厌的了。

那学者原是个好好先生，被妻子偷盗，被儿子殴打，被跟着一个葡萄牙人私奔的女儿遗弃。他靠着过活的小差事，最近也丢了；苏利南的牧师还迫害他，说他是索星尼派[37]。其实别的人至少也跟他一样倒霉；但老实人暗中希望这学者能在路上替他消愁解闷。其余的候选人认为老实人极不公平，老实人每人送了一百银洋，平了大家的气。

第二十章　老实人与玛丁在海上的遭遇

老学者名叫玛丁，跟着老实人上船往波尔多。两人都见多识广，饱经忧患；即使他们的船要从苏利南绕过好望角开往日本，他们对于物质与精神的痛苦也讨论不完。

老实人比玛丁占着很大的便宜：他始终希望和居内贡小姐相会，玛丁却一无希望；并且老实人有黄金钻石；虽然丢了一百头满载世界最大财富的大绵羊，虽然荷兰船主拐骗他的事始终不能忘怀，但一想到袋里剩下的宝物，一提到居内贡小姐，尤其在酒醉饭饱的时候，他又倾向邦葛罗斯的哲学了。

他对学者说：“玛丁先生，你对这些问题有何意见？你对物质与精神的苦难又有怎样的想法？”

玛丁答道：“牧师们指控我是索星尼派，其实我是马尼教[38]徒。”

“你这是说笑话吧？马尼教徒早已绝迹了。”

“还有我呢，”玛丁回答，“我也不知道信了这主义有什么用，可是我不能有第二个想法。”

老实人说：“那你一定是魔鬼上身了。”

玛丁道：“魔鬼什么事都要参预；既然到处有他的踪迹，自然也可能附在我身上。老实告诉你，我瞧着地球——其实只是一颗小珠子——我觉得上帝的确把它交给什么恶魔了；当然黄金国不在其内。我没见过一个城市不巴望邻近的城市毁灭的，没见过一个家庭不希望把别的家庭斩草除根的。弱者一面对强者卑躬屈膝，一面暗中诅咒；强者把他们当作一群任凭宰割的绵羊。上百万编号列队的杀人犯在欧洲纵横驰骋，井井有条地干着焚烧掳掠的勾当，为的是糊口，为的是干不了更正当的职业。而在一些仿佛太平无事、文风鼎盛的都市中，一般人心里的妒羡、焦虑、忧急，便是围城中大难当头的居民也不到这程度。内心的隐痛比外界的灾难更残酷。一句话说完，我见得多了，受的折磨多了，所以变了马尼教徒。”

老实人回答道：“究竟世界上还有些好东西呢。”

玛丁说：“也许有吧，可是我没见识过。”

辩论之间，他们听见一声炮响，接着越来越紧密。各人拿起望远镜，瞧见三海里以外有两条船互相轰击；风把它们越吹越近，法国船上的人可以舒舒服服地观战。后来，一条船放出一阵排炮，不偏不倚，正打在另外一条的半中腰，把它轰沉了。老实人和玛丁清清楚楚看到甲板上站着一百多人，向天举着手臂，呼号之声惨不忍闻。一忽儿他们都沉没了。

玛丁道：“你瞧，人与人就是这样相处的。”

老实人道：“不错，这简直是恶魔干的事。”言犹未了，他瞥见一堆不知什么鲜红的东西在水里游泳。船上放下一条小艇，瞧个究竟，原来是老实人的一头绵羊。老实人找回这头羊所感到的喜悦，远过于损失一百头满载钻石的绵羊所感到的悲伤。

不久，法国船长看出打胜的一条船，船主是西班牙人；沉没的那条，船主是一个荷兰海盗，便是拐骗老实人的那个。他抢去的偌大财宝，跟他一齐葬身海底，只逃出了一头羊。

老实人对玛丁道：“你瞧，天理昭彰，罪恶有时会受到惩罚的，这也是荷兰流氓的报应。”

玛丁回答：“对。可是船上的搭客，难道应当和他同归于尽吗？上帝惩罚了恶棍，魔鬼淹死了无辜。”

法国船和西班牙船继续航行，老实人和玛丁继续辩论，一连辩了半个月，始终没有结果。可是他们总算谈着话，交换着思想，互相安慰着。

老实人抚摩着绵羊，说道：“我既然能把你找回来，一定也能找回居内贡的。”

第二十一章　老实人与玛丁驶近法国海岸，他们的议论

终于法国海岸在望了。老实人问：“玛丁先生，你到过法国吗？”

玛丁回答：“到过，我去过好几州。有的州里，半数居民都害着狂疾，有几州民风奸刁得很，有几州的人性情和顺，相当愚蠢；又有几州的人喜欢卖弄才情。全国一致的风气是：第一，谈情说爱；第二，恶意中伤；第三，胡说八道。”

“玛丁先生，你可曾到过巴黎？”

“到过的，那儿可是各色人等，一应俱全了；只看见一片混乱，熙熙攘攘，人人都在寻求快乐，结果没有一个人找到，至少我觉得如此。我没耽搁多久；才到巴黎，身边的钱就给圣·日耳曼节场上的小偷扒光了。人家还把我当作小偷，抓去关了八天牢；以后我进印刷所当校对，想挣一笔路费，拼着两腿走回荷兰。我认识一批写文章的，掀风作浪的，为宗教入迷的，都不是东西。有人说巴黎也有些挺文雅的君子；但愿这话是真的。”

老实人道：“我没兴致游历法国；你不难想象，在黄金国待过一个月的人，除了居内贡小姐之外，世界上什么东西都不想再看了。我要经过法国到意大利，上佛尼市等她；你不陪我走一遭吗？”

玛丁道：“一定奉陪；听说那地方，只有佛尼市的贵族才住得；可是本地人待外乡人很客气，只要外乡人十二分有钱。我没有钱，你有的是；不论你上哪儿，我都跟着走。”

老实人道：“我想起一件事要问你，我们的船主有一本厚厚的书，书中说咱们的陆地原本是海洋，你相信吗？”

玛丁回答：“我才不信呢，近年来流行的那些梦话，我全不信。”

老实人道：“那么干吗要有这个世界呢？”

“为了气死我们的。”玛丁回答。

老实人又说：“我给你讲过大耳人那里有两个姑娘爱上猴子的事，你不觉得奇怪吗？”

“我才不呢，”玛丁说，“我不觉得这种情欲有什么可怪；怪事见得多了，就什么都不以为怪了。”

老实人道：“你可相信人一向就互相残杀，像现在这样的吗？一向就是扯谎、欺诈、反复无常、忘恩负义、强取豪夺、懦弱、轻薄、卑鄙、妒羡、馋痨、酗酒、吝啬、贪婪、残忍、毁谤、淫欲无度、执迷不悟、虚伪、愚妄的吗？”

玛丁回答说：“你想鹞子看到鸽子是否一向都吃的？”

“那还用说吗？”

玛丁道：“既然鹞性不改，为什么希望人性会改呢？”

“噢！那是大不相同的；因为人的意志可以自由选择……”议论之间，他们到了波尔多。

第二十二章　老实人与玛丁在法国的遭遇

老实人在波尔多办了几件事就走了。他在当地卖掉几块黄金国的石子，包定一辆舒服的双人座的驿车，因为他和哲学家玛丁成了形影不离的好友。他不得不把绵羊忍痛割爱，送给波尔多的科学院；科学院拿这头羊作为当年度悬赏征文的题目，要人研究为什么这头羊的毛是红的。得奖的是一个北方学者，他用A加B，减C，用Z除的算式，证明这头羊应当长红毛，也应当害疱疮[39]而死。

可是，老实人一路在酒店里遇到的旅客都告诉他：“我们上巴黎去。”那股争先恐后的劲，终于打动了老实人的兴致，他也想上京城去观光一番了；好在绕道巴黎到佛尼市，并没有多少冤枉路。

他从圣·玛梭城关进城，当下竟以为到了威斯发里省内一个最肮脏的村子。

老实人路上辛苦了些，一落客店便害了一场小病。因为他手上戴着一只其大无比的钻戒，行李中又有一口重得非凡的小银箱，所以立刻来了两名自告奋勇的医生，几位寸步不离的好友，两个替他烧汤煮水的虔婆。

玛丁说：“记得我第一次到巴黎也害过病；我穷得很，所以既没有朋友，也没有虔婆，也没有医生；结果我病好了。”

又是吃药，又是放血，老实人的病反而重了。一个街坊上的熟客，挺和气地来问他要一份上他世界去的通行证[40]。老实人置之不理；两位虔婆说这是新时行的规矩。老实人回答，他不是一个时髦人物。玛丁差点儿把来客摔出窗外。教士赌咒说，老实人死了，决不给他埋葬。玛丁赌咒说，他倒预备埋葬教士，要是教士再纠缠不清。你言我语，越吵越凶。玛丁抓着教士的肩膀，使劲撵了出去。这事闹得沸沸扬扬，连警察局都动了公事。

老实人复原了，养病期间，颇有些上流人士来陪他吃晚饭，另外还赌钱，输赢很大。老实人从来抓不到爱司[41]，觉得莫名其妙；玛丁却不以为怪。

老实人的向导中间，有个矮小的班里戈登神父。巴黎不少像他那样殷勤的人，老是机灵乖巧，和蔼可亲，面皮既厚，说话又甜，极会趋奉人，专门巴结过路的外国人，替他们讲些本地的丑闻秘史，帮他们花大价钱去寻欢作乐。这位班里戈登神父先带老实人和玛丁去看戏。那日演的是一出新编的悲剧。老实人座位四周都是些才子；但他看到表演精彩的几幕，仍禁不住哭了。

休息期间，旁边有位辩士和他说：“你落眼泪真是大错特错了：这女戏子演得很糟，搭配的男戏子比她更糟，剧本比戏子还要糟。剧情明明发生在阿拉伯，剧作者却不懂一句阿拉伯文；并且他不信先天观念论[42]。明天我带二十本攻击他的小册子给你看。”

老实人问神父：“先生，法国每年有多少本新戏？”

“五六千本。”

老实人说：“那很多了，其中有几本好的呢？”

神父道：“十五六本。”

玛丁接着道：“那很多了。”

有一位女戏子，在一出偶尔还上演的、平凡的悲剧中，串伊丽莎白王后，老实人看了很中意，对玛丁道：“我很喜欢这演员，她颇像居内贡小姐；倘使能去拜访她一次，倒也是件乐事。”

班里戈登神父自告奋勇，答应陪他去。老实人是从小受的德国教育，便请问当地的拜见之礼，不知在法国应当怎样对待英国王后。

神父说：“那要看地方而定。在内地呢，带她们上酒店；在巴黎，要是她们相貌漂亮，大家便恭而敬之，死了把她们摔在垃圾堆上。”[43]

老实人嚷起来：“怎么，把王后摔在垃圾堆上！”

玛丁接口道：“是的，神父说得一点儿不错。从前莫尼末小姐，像大家说的从此世界转到他世界去的时候，我正在巴黎；那时一般人不许她享受所谓丧葬之礼，所谓丧葬之礼，是让死人跟街坊上所有的小子，躺在一个丑恶不堪的公墓里一同腐烂；莫尼末小姐只能孤零零地埋在蒲高涅街的转角上；她的英魂一定因此伤心透顶的，因为她生前思想很高尚。”

老实人道：“那太没礼貌了。”

玛丁道：“有什么办法！这儿的人便是这样。在这个荒唐的国内，不论是政府、法院、教堂、舞台，凡是你想象得到的矛盾都应有尽有。”

老实人问：“巴黎人是不是老是嘻嘻哈哈的？”

神父回答：“是的。他们一边笑，一边生气；他们对什么都不满意，而抱怨诉苦也用打哈哈的方式；他们甚至一边笑一边干着最下流的事。”

老实人又道：“那混账的胖子是谁？我为之感动下泪的剧本，我极喜欢的演员，他都骂得一文不值。”

“那是个无耻小人，所有的剧本，所有的书籍，他都要毁谤；他是靠此为生的。谁要有点儿成功，他就咬牙切齿，好比太监怨恨作乐的人；那是文坛上的毒蛇，把凶狠仇恨做粮食的；他是个报屁股作家。”

“什么叫作报屁股作家？”

“专门糟蹋纸张的，所谓弗莱隆[44]之流。”神父回答。

成群的看客涌出戏院；老实人、玛丁、班里戈登却在楼梯高头大发议论。

老实人道：“虽则我急于跟居内贡小姐相会，倒也很想和格兰龙小姐吃顿饭；我觉得她真了不起。”

格兰龙小姐只招待上等人，神父没资格接近。他说：“今天晚上她有约会；但是我可以带你去见一位有身份的太太，你在她府上见识了巴黎，就赛过在巴黎住了四年。”

老实人天性好奇，便跟他到一位太太府上，坐落在圣·奥诺雷城关的尽里头，有人在那儿赌法老[45]：十二个愁眉不展的赌客各自拿着一叠牌，好比一本登记他们噩运的账册。屋内鸦雀无声，赌客脸上暗淡无光，庄家脸上焦急不安，女主人坐在铁面无情的庄家身边，用尖利的眼睛瞅着赌客的加码；谁要把纸牌折个小角儿，她就教他们把纸角展开，神色严厉，态度却很好，决不因之生气，唯恐得罪了主顾。那太太自称为特·巴洛里涅侯爵夫人。她的女儿十五岁，也是赌客之一；众人为了补救牌运而做的手脚，她都眨着眼睛做报告。班里戈登神父、老实人和玛丁走进屋子，一个人也没站起来，一个人也没打招呼，甚至瞧都不瞧一眼；大家一心都在牌上。

老实人说：“哼，森特—登—脱龙克男爵夫人还比他们客气一些。”

神父凑着侯爵夫人耳朵说了几句，她便略微抬了抬身子，对老实人嫣然一笑，对玛丁很庄严地点点头，教人端一张椅子，递一副牌给老实人。玩了两局，老实人输了五万法郎。然后大家一团高兴地坐下吃晚饭。在场的人都奇怪老实人输了钱毫不介意，当差们用当差的俗谈，彼此说着：“他准是一位英国的爵爷。”

和巴黎多数的饭局一样，桌上先是静悄悄的，继而你一句我一句，谁也听不清谁；最后是说笑打诨，无非是没有风趣的笑话、无稽的谣言、荒谬的议论，略为谈几句政治，缺德话说上一大堆。也有人提到新出的书。

班里戈登神父问道：“神学博士谷夏先生的小说，你们看到没有？”

一位客人回答：“看到了，只是没法念完。荒唐的作品，咱们有的是；可是把全体坏作品加起来，还及不上神学博士谷夏的荒唐。这一类恶劣的书泛滥市场，像洪水一般，我受不了，宁可到这儿来赌法老的。”

神父说：“教长T某某写的随笔，你觉得怎么样？”

巴洛里涅太太插嘴道：“噢！那个可厌的俗物吗？他把老生常谈说得非常新奇；把不值一提的东西讨论得酸气冲天；剽窃别人的才智，手段又笨拙透顶，简直是点金成铁！他教我讨厌死了！可是好啦，现在用不着我讨厌了，教长的大作只要翻过几页就够了。”

桌上有位风雅的学者，赞成侯爵夫人的意见。接着大家谈到悲剧；女主人问，为什么有些悲剧还能不时上演，可是剧本念不下去。那位风雅的人物，把一本戏可能还有趣味而毫无价值的道理，头头是道地解释了一番。他很简括地说明，单单拿每部小说都有的、能吸引观众的一二情节搬进戏文，是不够的，还得新奇而不荒唐，常常有些崇高的境界而始终很自然，识透人的心而教这颗心讲话，剧作者必须是个大诗人而剧中并不显得有一个诗人；深得语言三昧，文字精练，从头至尾音韵铿锵，但决不让韵脚妨碍意义。他又补充说：“谁要不严格遵守这些规则，他可能写出一两部悲剧博得观众掌声，却永远算不得一个好作家。完美的悲剧太少了。有些是文字写得不差，韵押得很恰当的牧歌；有些是教人昏昏欲睡的政论，或者是令人作恶的夸张；又有些是文理不通、中了邪魔的梦呓；再不然是东拉西扯，因为不会跟人讲话，便长篇大论地向神道大声疾呼；还有似是而非的格言，张大其辞的陈言俗套。”

老实人聚精会神地听着，以为那演说家着实了不起。既然侯爵大人特意让他坐在身旁，他便凑到女主人耳畔，大着胆子问，这位能言善辩的先生是何等人物。她回答说：“他是一位学者，从来不入局赌钱，不时由神父带来吃顿饭的。他对于悲剧和书本非常内行；自己也写过一出悲剧，被人大喝倒彩；也写过一部书，除掉题赠给我的一本之外，外边从来没有人看到过。”

老实人道：“原来是个大人物！不愧为邦葛罗斯第二。”

于是他转过身去，朝着学者说道：“先生，你大概认为物质世界和精神领域都十全十美，一切都是不能更改的吧？”

学者答道：“我才不这么想呢；我觉得我们这里一切都倒行逆施；没有一个人知道他自己的身份，自己的责任，知道他做些什么，应当做什么；除了在饭桌上还算痛快，还算团结以外，其余的时候大家都喧呶争辩，无理取闹：扬山尼派攻击莫利尼派[46]，司法界攻击教会，文人攻击文人，幸臣攻击幸臣，金融家攻击老百姓，妻子攻击丈夫，亲戚攻击亲戚；简直是一场无休无歇的战争。”

老实人回答说：“我见过的事比这个恶劣多呢；可是有位倒了霉被吊死的哲人，告诉我这些都十全十美，都是一幅美丽的图画的影子。”

玛丁道：“你那吊死鬼简直是嘲笑我们；你所谓影子其实是丑恶的污点。”

老实人说：“污点是人涂上去的，他们也是迫不得已。”

玛丁道：“那就不能怪他们了。”

大半的赌客完全不懂他们的话，只顾喝酒；玛丁只管和学者辩论，老实人对主妇讲了一部分自己的经历。

吃过晚饭，侯爵夫人把老实人带到小房间里，让他坐在一张长沙发上，问道：“喂，这么说来，你是一往情深，永远爱着居内贡小姐了？”

“是的。”老实人回答。

侯爵夫人对他很温柔地一笑，说：“你这么回答，表示你真是一个威斯发里的青年；换了一个法国人，一定说：‘我果然爱居内贡小姐；可是见了你，太太，我恐怕要不爱她了。’”

老实人说：“好吧，太太，你要我怎样回答都行。”

侯爵夫人又道：“你替居内贡小姐捡了手帕才动情的；现在我要你替我捡吊袜带。”

“敢不遵命。”老实人说着，便捡了吊袜带。

那太太说：“我还要你替我扣上去。”

老实人就替她扣上了。

太太说：“你瞧，你是个外国人；我常常教那些巴黎的情人害上半个月的相思病，可是我第一夜就向你投降了，因为对一个威斯发里的年轻人，我们应当竭诚招待。”

美人看见外国青年两手戴着两只大钻戒，不由得赞不绝口；临了两只钻戒从老实人手上过渡到了侯爵夫人手上。

老实人做了对不起居内贡小姐的事，和班里戈登神父一路回去，一路觉得良心不安：神父对他的痛苦极表同情。老实人在赌台上输的五万法郎和两只半送半骗的钻戒，神父只分润到一个小数目；他存心要利用结交老实人的机会，尽量捞一笔，便和他大谈其居内贡。老实人对他说，将来在佛尼市见了爱人，一定要求她饶恕他的不忠实。

班里戈登变得格外恭敬、格外体贴了，老实人说什么，做什么，打算做什么，神父都表示热心和关切。

他问老实人：“那么先生，你是在佛尼市有约会了？”

老实人答道：“是啊，神父，我非到佛尼市去跟居内贡小姐相会不可。”他能提到爱人真是太高兴了，所以凭着心直口快的老脾气，把自己和大名鼎鼎的威斯发里美人的情史讲了一部分。

神父说：“大概居内贡小姐极有才气，写的信也十分动人吧？”

老实人道：“我从来没收到过；你想，我为了钟情于她而被赶出爵府的时候，我不能写信给她；不久听说她死了，接着又和她相会，又和她分手；最后我在离此一万多里的地方，派了一个当差去接她。”

神父留神听着，若有所思。不一会他和两个外国人亲热地拥抱了一下，告辞了。第二天，老实人睁开眼来就收到一封信，措辞是这样的：

“我最亲爱的情人，我病在此地已有八天了；听说你也在城中。要是我能动弹，早已飞到你怀抱里来了。我知道你路过波尔多；我把忠心的加刚菩和老婆子留在那边，让他们随后赶来。布韦诺斯·爱累斯总督把所有的宝物都拿去了，可是我还有你的一颗心。快来吧，见了你，我就有命了，要不然我也会含笑而死。”

这封可爱的信，这封意想不到的信，老实人看了说不出的欢喜；心爱的居内贡病倒的消息又使他痛苦万分。老实人被两种情绪搅乱了，急忙拿着黄金钻石，教人把他和玛丁两个带往居内贡的旅馆。他走进去，紧张得全身打战，心儿乱跳，说话带着哭声；他想揭开床上的帐幔，教人拿支蜡烛过来。

“不行，见了光她就没有命了。”女用人说着，猛地把帐幔放下了。

老实人哭道：“亲爱的居内贡，你觉得好些了吗？你不能见我的面，至少跟我说句话呀。”

女用人道：“她不能说话。”接着她从床上拉出一只滚圆的手，让老实人把眼泪浇在上面，浇了半天，他拿几颗钻石塞在那只手里，又在椅子上留下一袋黄金。

他正在大动感情，忽然来了一个差官，后面跟着班里戈登神父和几名差役。差官道：“嘿！这两个外国人形迹可疑！”随即喝令手下的人把他们逮捕，押往监狱。

老实人道：“黄金国的人可不是这样对待外客的。”

玛丁道：“啊！我更相信马尼教了。”

老实人问：“可是，先生，你把我们带往哪儿去呢？”

“进地牢去。”差官回答。

玛丁定下心神想了想，断定冒充居内贡的是个女骗子，班里戈登神父是个男骗子，他看出老实人天真不过，急于下手；差官又是一个骗子，可是容易打发的。

为了避免上公堂等等的麻烦，老实人听了玛丁劝告，又急于和货真价实的居内贡相会，便向差官提议送他三颗小钻，每颗值三千比斯多。差官说道：“啊，先生，哪怕你十恶不赦，犯尽了所有的罪，你也是世界上第一个规矩人；三颗钻石！三千比斯多一颗！我替你卖命都来不及，怎么还会把你送地牢？公家要把外国人全部抓起来，可是我有办法；我有个兄弟住在诺曼地的第埃普海港，让我带你去；只要你有几颗钻石给他，他会像我一样地侍候你。”

老实人问：“为什么要把外国人都抓起来呢？”

班里戈登神父插嘴道：“因为有个阿德雷巴西的光棍[47]，听了混账话，做了大逆不道的事，不是像一六一〇年五月的案子，而是像一五九四年十二月的那件[48]。还有像别的一些案子，是别的光棍听了混账话，在别的年份别的月份犯的。”

差官把案情[49]解释给老实人听，老实人叫道：“啊！这些野兽！一个整天唱歌跳舞的国家，竟有这样惨无人道的事！这简直是猴子耍弄老虎的地方，让我快快逃出去吧。我在本乡见到的是大熊；只有在黄金国才见过人！差官先生，看在上帝分上，带我上佛尼市吧，我要在那儿等居内贡小姐。”

差官道：“我只能送你上诺曼地。”

当下教人开了老实人和玛丁的脚镣，说是误会了，打发了手下的人，亲自把两人送往诺曼地，交给他兄弟。

那时港中泊着一条荷兰船。靠了另外三颗钻石帮忙，诺曼地人马上成为天下第一个热心汉，把老实人和玛丁送上船，开往英国的朴次茅斯海港。那不是到佛尼市去的路；但老实人以为这样已经逃出了地狱，打算一有机会就取道上佛尼市。

第二十三章　老实人与玛丁在英国海岸上见到的事

“啊，邦葛罗斯！邦葛罗斯！啊，玛丁！玛丁！啊，亲爱的居内贡！这是什么世界呀？”老实人在荷兰船上这么叫着。

玛丁答道：“都是些疯狂丑恶的事儿。”

“你到过英国，那边的人是不是跟法国人一样疯狂的？”

玛丁道：“那是另外一种疯狂。英法两国正为了靠近加拿大的几百亩雪地打仗，为此英勇地战争，所花的钱已经大大超过了全加拿大的价值。该送疯人院的人究竟哪一国更多，恕我资质愚钝，无法奉告。我只知道我们要遇到的人性情忧郁，肝火很旺。”

说话之间，他们进了朴次茅斯港；港内泊着舰队；岸上人山人海，睁着眼睛望着一个胖子；他跪在一条兵船的甲板上，四个兵面对着他，每人若无其事地朝他脑袋放了三枪；岸上的看客便心满意足地回去了。

老实人道：“怎么回事呀？哪个魔鬼这样到处发威的？”他向人打听，那个在隆重的仪式中被枪毙的胖子是谁。

“是个海军提督[50]。”有人回答。

“为什么要杀他呢？”

“因为他杀人杀得不够，他和一个法国海军提督作战，离开敌人太远了。”

老实人道：“可是法国提督离开英国提督不是一样远吗？”

旁边的人回答：“不错；可是这个国家，每隔多少时候总得杀掉个把海军提督，鼓励一下别的海军提督。”

老实人对于所见所闻，又惊骇，又厌恶，简直不愿意上岸；当下跟荷兰船主讲妥价钱，把船直放佛尼市；哪怕这船主会像苏利南的那个一样地拐骗他，也顾不得了。

两天以后，船主准备停当，把船沿着法国海岸驶去；远远望见里斯本的时候，老实人吓得直打哆嗦。接着进了海峡，驶入地中海；终于到了佛尼市。

老实人搂着玛丁叫道：“哎啊！谢谢上帝！这儿我可以和美人居内贡相会了。我相信加刚菩跟相信我自己一样。苦尽甘来，否极泰来，不是样样都十全十美了吗？”

第二十四章　巴该德与奚罗弗莱的故事

老实人一到佛尼市，就着人到所有的酒店、咖啡馆、妓院去找加刚菩，不料影踪全无。他每天托人去打听大小船只，只是没有加刚菩的消息。

他对玛丁说：“怎么的！我从苏利南到波尔多，从波尔多到巴黎，从巴黎到第埃普，从第埃普到朴次茅斯，绕过了葡萄牙和西班牙的海岸，穿过地中海，在佛尼市住了几个月：这么长久的时间，我的美人儿和加刚菩还没到！我非但没遇到居内贡，倒反碰上了一个女流氓和一个班里戈登神父！她大概死了吧，那我也只有一死了事。啊！住在黄金国的乐园里好多了，不应当回到这该死的欧洲来的。亲爱的玛丁，你说得对，人生不过是些幻影和灾难。”

他郁闷不堪，既不去看时行的歌剧，也不去欣赏狂欢节的许多游艺节目，也没有一个女人使他动心。

玛丁说：“你太傻了，你以为一个混血种的当差，身边带着五六百万，真会到天涯海角去把你的情妇接到佛尼市来吗？要是找到的话，他就自己消受了。要是找不到，他也会另找一个。我劝你把你的当差和你的情人居内贡，一齐丢开了吧。”

玛丁的话只能教人灰心。老实人愈来愈愁闷，玛丁还再三向他证明，除了谁也去不了的黄金国，德行与快乐在世界上是很少的。

一边讨论这个大题目，一边等着居内贡，老实人忽然瞧见一个年轻的丹阿德会[51]修士，搀着一位姑娘在圣·马克广场上走过。修士年富力强，肥肥胖胖，身体精壮结实，眼睛很亮，神态很安详，脸色很红润，走路的姿势也很威武。那姑娘长得很俏，嘴里唱着歌，脉脉含情地瞧着修士，常常拧他的大胖脸表示亲热。

老实人对玛丁道：“至少你得承认，这两人是快活的了。至此为止，除了黄金国以外，地球上凡是人住得的地方，我只看见苦难；但这个修士和这个姑娘，我敢打赌是挺幸福的人。”

玛丁道：“我打赌不是的。”

老实人说：“只要请他们吃饭，就可知道我有没有看错了。”

他过去招呼他们，说了一番客套话，请他们同到旅馆去吃通心粉、龙巴地鹧鸪、鲟鱼蛋，喝蒙德毕岂阿诺酒、拉克利玛—克利斯底酒、希普酒、萨摩酒。小姐红了红脸，修士却接受了邀请；女的跟着他，又惊异又慌张地瞧着老实人，甚至于含着一包眼泪。才跨进老实人的房间，她就说：“怎么，老实人先生认不得巴该德了吗？”

老实人原来不曾把她细看，因为一心想着居内贡；听了这话，回答说：“唉！可怜的孩子，原来是你把邦葛罗斯博士弄到那般田地的？”

巴该德道：“唉，先生，是呀。怪道你什么都知道了。我听到男爵夫人和居内贡小姐家里遭了横祸。可是我遭遇的残酷也不相上下。你从前看见我的时候，我还天真烂漫。我的忏悔师是一个芳济会修士，轻易就把我勾搭上了。结果可惨啦；你被男爵大人踢着屁股赶走以后，没几天我也不得不离开爵府。要不是一个本领高强的医生可怜我，我早死了。为了感激，我做了这医生的情妇。他老婆妒忌得厉害，天天下毒手打我，像发疯一样。医生是天底下顶丑的男人，我是天底下顶苦的女人，为了一个自己并不喜欢的男人整天挨打。先生，你知道，泼妇嫁给医生是很危险的。他受不了老婆的凶悍，有天给她医小伤风，配了一剂药，灵验无比。她吃下去抽搐打滚，好不怕人，两小时以内就送了命。太太的家属把先生告了一状，说他谋杀；他逃了，我坐了牢。倘不是我还长得俏，尽管清白无辜也救不了我的命。法官把我开脱了，条件是由他来顶医生的缺。不久，一位情敌又补了我的缺，把我赶走，一个钱也没给。我只得继续干这个该死的营生；你们男人以为是挺快活的勾当，我们女人只觉得是人间地狱。我到佛尼市来也是做买卖的。啊！先生，不管是做生意的老头儿，是律师，是修士，是船夫，是神父，我都得赔着笑脸侍候；无论什么耻辱，什么欺侮，都是准备挨受；往往衣服都没有穿了，借着别人的裙子走出去，让一个混账男人撩起来；从东家挣来的钱给西家偷去；衙门里的差役还要来讹诈你；前途有什么指望呢？还不是又老又病，躺在救济院里，扔在垃圾堆上！先生，你要想想这个滋味，就会承认我是天底下最苦命的女人了。”

巴该德在小房间里，当着玛丁对老实人说了这些知心话。玛丁和老实人道：“你瞧，我赌的东道已经赢了一半。”

奚罗弗莱修士坐在饭厅里，喝着酒等开饭。

老实人和巴该德道：“可是我刚才碰到你，你神气多快活，多高兴，你唱着歌，对教士那么亲热，好像是出于真心的，你自己说苦得要命，我看你倒是乐得很呢。”

巴该德答道：“啊！先生，那又是我们这一行的苦处呀。昨天一个军官抢了我的钱，揍了我一顿，今天就得有说有笑地讨一个修士喜欢。”

老实人不愿意再听了；他承认玛丁的话不错。他们跟巴该德和丹阿德会修士一同入席；饭桌上大家还高兴，快吃完的时候，说话比较亲密了。

老实人道：“神父，我觉得你的命很不差，大可羡慕；你的脸色表示你身体康健，心中快乐；又有一个挺漂亮的姑娘陪你散心，看来你对丹阿德会修士这个职业是顶满意的了。”

奚罗弗莱修士答道：“嘿，先生，我恨不得把所有的丹阿德会修士都沉到海底去呢。我几次三番想把修道院一把火烧掉，去改信回教。我十五岁的时候，爹娘逼我披上这件该死的法衣，好让一个混账的、天杀的哥哥多得一份产业。修道院里只有妒忌、倾轧、疯狂。我胡乱布几次道，挣点儿钱，一半给院长克扣，一半拿来养女人。但我晚上回到修道院，真想一头撞在卧房墙上；而我所有的同道都和我一样。”

玛丁转身朝着老实人，照例很冷静地说道：“喂，我赌的东道不是全赢了吗？”

老实人送了两千银洋给巴该德，送了一千给奚罗弗莱修士，说道：“我担保，凭着这笔钱，他们就快乐了。”

玛丁道：“我可不信，这些钱说不定把他们害得更苦呢。”

老实人道：“那也管不了；可是有件事我觉得很安慰：你以为永远不会再见的人竟会再见。既然红绵羊和巴该德都遇到了，很可能也会遇到居内贡。”

玛丁说：“但愿她有朝一日能使你快活；可是我很怀疑。”

“你的心多冷。”老实人说。

“那是因为我事情经得多了。”玛丁回答。

老实人道：“你瞧那些船夫，不是老在唱歌吗[52]？”

玛丁道：“你没瞧见他们在家里，跟老婆和小娃娃们在一起的情形呢。执政[53]有执政的烦恼，船夫有船夫的烦恼。固然，通盘算起来，还是船夫的命略胜一筹，可是也相差无几，不值得计较。”

老实人道：“外边传说这里有位元老，叫作波谷居朗泰，住着勃朗泰河上那所华丽的王府，招待外国人还算客气。听说他是一个从来没有烦恼的人。”

玛丁说：“这样少有的品种，我倒想见识见识。”

老实人立即托人向波谷居朗泰大人致意，要求准许他们第二天去拜访。

第二十五章　佛尼市贵族波谷居朗泰访问记

老实人和玛丁坐着游艇，驶进勃朗泰河，到了元老波谷居朗泰的府上。花园布置得很雅，摆着美丽的白石雕像。王府建筑极其宏丽。主人年纪六十左右，家财巨万；接见两位好奇的来客颇有礼貌，可并不热烈；老实人不免有点儿局促，玛丁倒还觉得满意。

两个相貌漂亮、衣着大方的姑娘，先端上泡沫很多的巧克力敬客。老实人少不得把她们的姿色、风韵和才干称赞一番。

元老说道：“这两个姑娘还不错，有时我让她们睡在我床上；因为我对城里的太太们，对她们的风情、脾气、妒忌、争吵、狭窄、骄傲、愚蠢，还有非给她们写不可的或者非教人写不可的十四行诗，都厌倦透顶；可是这两个姑娘也教我起腻了。”

吃过早点，老实人在画廊中散步，看着美不胜收的画惊叹不已。他问那开头的两幅是谁的作品。

主人说：“那是拉斐尔的。几年前，为了虚荣我花大价钱买了来；据说是全意大利最美的东西，我却一点儿不喜欢，颜色已经暗黄了，人体不够丰满，表现得不够有力；衣褶完全不像布帛。总而言之，不管别人怎么说，我觉得这两幅画不够逼真。一定要像看到实物一样的画，我才喜欢；但这种作品简直没有。我藏着不少画，早就不看了。”

饭前，波谷居朗泰教人来一支合奏曲。老实人觉得音乐美极了。

波谷居朗泰道：“这种声音可以让你消遣半个钟点，再多，大家就听厌了，虽然没有一个人敢说出来。现在的音乐，不过是以难取胜的艺术；仅仅是难奏的作品，多听几遍就没人喜欢。

“我也许更爱歌剧，要不是人家异想天开，把它弄成怪模怪样的教我生气。那些谱成音乐的要不得的悲剧，一幕一幕只是没来由地插进几支可笑的歌，让女戏子卖弄嗓子：这种东西，让爱看的人去看吧。一个被阉割的男人哼哼唧唧，扮演恺撒或加东，在台上愣头傻脑地踱方步：谁要愿意，谁要能够，对这种东西低徊叹赏，尽管去低徊叹赏；至于我，我久已不愿领教了；这些浅薄无聊的玩意儿，如今却成为意大利的光荣，各国的君主还不惜重金罗致呢。”

老实人很婉转地略微辩了几句。玛丁却完全赞成元老的意见。

他们吃了一餐精美的饭，走进书房。老实人瞥见一部装订极讲究的《荷马全集》，便恭维主人趣味高雅。

他说：“这一部是使伟大的邦葛罗斯，德国最杰出的哲学家，为之陶醉的作品。”

波谷居朗泰冷冷地答道：“我并不为之陶醉。从前人家硬要我相信这作品很有趣味；可是那些翻来覆去讲个不休的大同小异的战争；那些忙忙碌碌而一事无成的神道；那战争的祸根，而还够不上做一个女戏子的海伦；那老是围困而老是攻不下的特洛伊城，都教我厌烦得要死。有时候我问几位学者，是不是看了这书跟我一样发闷。凡是真诚的都承认看不下去，但书房中非有一部不可，好比一座古代的纪念碑，也好比生锈而市面上没人要的古徽章。”

老实人问：“大人对维琪尔的见解不是这样吧？”

波谷居朗泰答道：“我承认他的《埃奈伊特》[54]第二、第四、第六各卷都很精彩；但是那虔诚的埃奈伊、勇武的格劳昂德、好友阿夏德、小阿斯加尼于斯、昏君拉底奴斯、庸俗的阿玛太、无聊的拉维尼亚，却是意趣索然，令人生厌。我倒更喜欢塔索和阿利渥斯托笔下那些荒诞不经的故事[55]。”

老实人道：“恕我冒昧，先生读荷拉斯是不是极感兴趣呢？”

波谷居朗泰回答：“不错，他写了些格言，对上流人物还能有点儿益处；而且是用精悍的诗句写的，比较容易记。可是他描写勃兰特的旅行，吃得挺不舒服的饭，两个粗人的口角，说什么一个人好比满口脓血，另外一个好比一嘴酸醋等等，我都懒得理会。他攻击老婆子和女巫的诗，粗俗不堪，我只觉得恶心。他对他的朋友曼塞纳说，如果自己能算得一个抒情诗人，一定高傲得昂然举首，上触星辰：这等话我也看不出有什么价值[56]。愚夫愚妇对于一个大名家的东西，无有不佩服的。可是我读书只为我自己，只有合我脾胃的才喜欢。”

老实人所受的教育，使他从来不会用自己的眼光判断，听了主人的话不由得大为惊奇；玛丁却觉得波谷居朗泰的思想方式倒还合理。

老实人忽然叫道：“噢！这儿是一部西塞罗[57]；这个大人物的作品，阁下想必百读不厌吧？”

那佛尼市元老说：“我从来不看的。他替拉皮里于斯辩护也罢，替格鲁昂丢斯辩护也罢，反正跟我不相干。我自己经手的案子已经多得很了。我比较惬意的还是他的哲学著作；但看到他事事怀疑，我觉得自己的知识跟他相差不多，也用不着别人再来把我教得愚昧无知了。”

“啊！”玛丁叫道，“这儿还有科学院出版的二十四册丛刊，也许其中有些好东西吧？”

波谷居朗泰说道：“哼，只要那些作家中间有一个，能发明做别针的方法，就算是好材料了；可是这些书里只有空洞的学说，连一种实用的学识都找不到。”

老实人道：“这里又是多少剧本啊！有意大利文的，有西班牙文的，有法文的。”

元老回答：“是的，一共有三千种，精彩的还不满三打。至于这些说教的演讲，全部合起来还抵不上一页赛纳克[58]，还有那批卷帙浩繁的神学书；你们想必知道我是从来不翻的，不但我，而且谁也不翻的。”

玛丁看到书架上有好几格都插着英文书，便道：“这些书多半写得毫无顾忌，阁下既是共和城邦的人，想必喜欢的吧？”

波谷居朗泰回答说：“不错，能把自己的思想写出来是件美事，也是人类独有的权利；我们全意大利的人，笔下写的却不是心里想的；恺撒与安东尼的同乡，没有得到多明我会修士的准许，就不敢自己转一个念头。启发英国作家灵感的那种自由，倘不是被党派的成见与意气，把其中一切有价值的部分糟蹋了，我一定会喜爱的。”

老实人看见一部《弥尔敦诗集》，便问在他眼里，这作家是否算得大人物。

波谷居朗泰说道：“谁？他吗？这野蛮人用生硬的诗句，为《创世记》第一章写了十大章注解。这个模仿希腊作家的俗物把创造世界的本事弄得面目全非：摩西明明说上帝用言语造出世界的，那俗物却教弥赛亚到天堂的柜子里，去拿一个圆规来画出世界的轮廓[59]！我会把他当作大人物吗？塔索笔下的魔鬼和地狱都给他糟蹋了[60]，吕西番一忽儿变了癞蛤蟆，一忽儿变了小矮子，一句话讲到上百次；还要辩论神学；阿利渥斯托说到火枪的发明，原是个笑话，他却一本正经地去模仿，教魔鬼们在天上放大炮[61]：这样的人我会敬重吗？不用说我，全意大利也没有人喜欢这种沉闷乏味、无理取闹的作品。什么罪恶与死亡的结合，什么罪恶生产的毒蛇[62]，只要品味比较文雅一些的人都会看了作呕，他描写病院的长篇大论，只配筑坟墓的工人去念[63]。这部晦涩、离奇、丑恶的诗集，一出世就教人瞧不起；我现在对待他的态度，跟他同时代的本国人一样。并且，我只知道说出自己的思想，决不理会别人是否跟我一般思想。”

老实人听了这话大为懊丧；他是敬重荷马，也有点儿喜欢弥尔敦的。他轻轻地对玛丁道：“唉，我怕这家伙对我们的德国诗人也不胜鄙薄呢。”

玛丁道：“那也何妨？”

老实人又喃喃说道：“噢！了不起的人物！这波谷居朗泰竟是个大天才！他对什么都不中意。”

他们把书题过目完了，下楼到花园里去。老实人把园子的美丽极口称赞了一番。

主人道：“这花园恶俗不堪；只有些无聊东西；明儿我就叫人另起一所，布置得高雅一些。”

两位好奇的客人向元老告辞了，老实人对玛丁说：“喂！这一回你总得承认见到了一个最快乐的人吧？因为他一无所惑，超脱一切。”

玛丁道：“你不看见他对自己所有的东西都厌恶吗？柏拉图早说过，这个不吃那个不受的胃，决不是最强健的胃。”

老实人道：“能批评一切，把别人认为美妙的东西找出缺点来，不也是一种乐趣吗？”

玛丁回答：“就是说把没有乐趣当作乐趣，是不是？”

老实人叫道：“啊！世界上只有我是快乐的，只要能和居内贡小姐相会。”

“能够有希望总是好的。”玛丁回答。

可是几天过去了，几星期过去了，加刚菩始终不回来。老实人陷在痛苦之中；甚至巴该德和奚罗弗莱修士谢都没来谢一声，他也不以为意。

第二十六章　老实人与玛丁和六个外国人同席，外国人的身份

一天晚上，老实人和玛丁两人正要和几个同寓的外国人吃饭，一个皮色像煤烟似的人从后面过来，抓着他的手臂，说道：“请你准备停当，跟我们一起走，别错过了。”

老实人掉过头来，一看是加刚菩。他惊喜交集的情绪，只比见到居内贡差一点儿。他几乎快乐得发疯，把朋友拥抱着，叫道：“啊！居内贡一定在这里了，在哪儿呢？快点儿带我去，让我跟她一块儿欢天喜地地快活一阵。”

加刚菩道：“居内贡不在这里，她在君士坦丁堡。”

“啊！天哪！在君士坦丁堡！不过哪怕她在中国，我也要插翅飞去；咱们走吧。”

加刚菩答道：“我们吃过晚饭才走，现在不能多谈；我做了奴隶，主人等着我；我得侍候他用餐；别多讲话；快去吃饭，准备出发。”

老实人一半快乐一半痛苦：高兴的是遇到了他忠心的使者，奇怪的是加刚菩变了奴隶；他只想着跟情人相会，心乱得很，头脑搅昏了。当下他去吃饭，同桌的是玛丁——他看到这些事，态度是很冷静的——还有到佛尼市来过狂欢节的六个外国人。

加刚菩替内中的一个外国人管斟酒，席终走近他的主人，凑着耳朵说道：“陛下随时可以动身了，船已经准备停当。”说完便出去了。

同桌的人诧异之下，一声不出，彼此望了望。另外一个仆人走近他的主人，说道：“陛下的包车在巴杜等着，渡船已经准备好了。”主人点点头，仆人走了。

同桌的人又彼此望了望，觉得更奇怪了。第三个用人也走近第三个外国人，说道：“陛下不能多留了：我现在就去准备一切。”说完也马上走了。

老实人和玛丁，以为那是狂欢节中乔装取笑的玩意儿。第四个仆人和第四个主人说：“陛下随时可以动身了。”然后和别人一样，出去了。第五个用人对第五个主人也是这一套。但第六个用人，对坐在老实人旁边的第六个主人说的话大不相同：“陛下，人家不肯再赊账了；今天晚上我和陛下都可能被关进监狱；我现在去料理一些私事，再见吧。”

六个仆人都走了，老实人、玛丁和六个外国人都肃静无声。最后，老实人忍不住开口道：“诸位，这个取笑的玩意儿真怪，为什么这个那个，你们全是国王呢？老实说，我和玛丁两个可不是。”

加刚菩的主人一本正经用意大利文说道：“我不是开玩笑，我是阿赫美特三世，做过好几年苏丹；我篡了我哥哥的王位，我的侄儿又篡了我的王位；我的宰相都被砍了头，我如今在冷宫里养老。我的侄儿穆罕默德苏丹有时让我出门疗养，这一回是到佛尼市来过狂欢节的。”

阿赫美特旁边的一个青年接着说：“我叫作伊凡，从前是俄罗斯皇帝，在摇篮中就被篡位了；父母都被幽禁，我是在牢里长大的；有时我可以由看守的人陪着，出门游历；这一回是到佛尼市来过狂欢节的。”

第三个人说道：“我是英王查理—爱德华；父亲把王位让给我，我奋力作战维持我的权力；人家把我手下的八百党羽挖出心来，打在他们脸上，把我下了狱。现在我要上罗马去看我的父王，他跟我和我的祖父一样是被篡位的。这回我到佛尼市来过狂欢节。”

第四个接着说：“我是波拉葛[64]的王；因为战事失利，丢了世袭的国土；我父亲也是同样的遭遇，如今我听天由命，像阿赫美特苏丹、伊凡皇帝、英王查理—爱德华一样，但愿上帝保佑他们长寿；这回我是到佛尼市来过狂欢节的。”

第五个说：“我也是波拉葛的王，丢了两次王位；但上帝给了我另外一个行业，我做的好事，超过所有萨尔玛德王在维斯丢拉河边做的全部好事；我也是听天由命；这一回是到佛尼市来过狂欢节的。”

那时轮到第六个王说话了。他说道：“诸位，我不是像你们那样的天潢贵胄；但也做过王，像别的王一样。我叫作丹沃陶，高斯人立我为王。当初人家称我陛下，现在称我先生都很勉强。我铸过货币，如今囊无分文；有过两位国务大臣，结果只剩一个跟班；我登过宝座，后来却在伦敦坐了多年的牢，睡在草垫上。我很怕在这儿会受到同样的待遇，虽则我和诸位陛下一样，是到佛尼市来过狂欢节的。”

其余五个王听了这番话非常同情，每人送了二十金洋给丹沃陶添置内外衣服。老实人送了价值两千金洋的一枚钻石。

五个王问道：“这位是谁？一个平民居然拿得出一百倍于你我的钱，而且肯随便送人！”

离开饭桌的时候，旅馆里又到了四位太子殿下，也是因战事失利，丢了国家，到佛尼市来过最后几天的狂欢节的。老实人对新来的客人根本没注意。他一心只想到君士坦丁堡去见他心爱的居内贡。

第二十七章　老实人往君士坦丁堡

忠心的加刚菩，和载送阿赫美特苏丹回君士坦丁堡的船主讲妥，让老实人和玛丁搭船同行。老实人和玛丁向落难的苏丹磕过头，便出发上船。一路老实人对玛丁说：“你瞧，和我们一同吃饭的竟有六个废王，内中一个还受我布施。更不幸的王侯，说不定还有许多。我啊，我不过丢了一百头绵羊，现在却是飞到居内贡怀抱中去了。亲爱的玛丁，邦葛罗斯毕竟说得不错：万事大吉。”

玛丁道：“但愿如此。”

老实人道：“可是我们在佛尼市遇到的事也真怪。六位废王在客店里吃饭，不是见所未见、闻所未闻吗？”

玛丁答道：“也未必比我们别的遭遇更奇。国王被篡位是常事；我们叨陪末座，和他们同席，也没什么了不起，不足挂齿。”

老实人一上船，就搂着他从前的当差、好朋友加刚菩的脖子。他说：“哎，居内贡怎么啦？还是那么姿容绝世吗？照旧爱我吗？她身体怎样？你大概在君士坦丁堡替她买了一所行宫吧？”

加刚菩回答：“亲爱的主人，居内贡在普罗篷提特海边洗碗，在一位并没多少碗盏的废王家里当奴隶；废王名叫拉谷斯基，每天从土耳其皇帝手里领三块钱过活；更可叹的是，居内贡变得奇丑无比了。”

老实人道：“啊，美也罢，丑也罢，我是君子人，我的责任是对她始终如一。但你带着五六百万，怎么她还会落到这般田地？”

加刚菩道：“唉，我不是先得送布韦诺斯·爱累斯总督两百万，赎出居内贡吗？余下的不是全给一个海盗好不英勇地抢了去吗？那海盗不是把我们带到马塔班海角，带到弥罗，带到尼加利阿，带到萨摩斯，带到彼特拉，带到达达尼尔，带到斯康塔里吗？临了，居内贡和老婆子两人落在我刚才讲的废王手里，我做了前任苏丹的奴隶。”

老实人道：“哎哟，祸不单行，一连串的倒霉事儿何其多啊！幸而我还有几颗钻石，不难替居内贡赎身。可惜她人变丑了。”

他接着问玛丁：“我跟阿赫美特苏丹、伊凡皇帝、英王查理—爱德华，你究竟觉得哪一个更可怜？”

玛丁道：“我不知道，除非我钻在你们肚里。”

老实人说：“啊，要是邦葛罗斯在这里，就能告诉我了。”

玛丁道：“我不知道你那邦葛罗斯用什么秤，称得出人的灾难和痛苦。我只相信地球上有几千几百万的人，比英王查理—爱德华、伊凡皇帝和阿赫美特苏丹不知可怜多少倍。”

“那很可能。”老实人说。

不多几天，他们进入黑海的运河。老实人花了很大的价钱赎出加刚菩，随即带着同伴改搭一条苦役船，到普罗篷提特海岸去寻访居内贡，不管她丑成怎样。

船上的桨手队里有两名苦役犯，划桨的手艺很差；船主是个小亚细亚人，不时用牛筋鞭子抽着那两个桨手的赤露的背。老实人无意中把他们特别细瞧了一会，不胜怜悯地走近前去。他觉得他们完全破相的脸上，某些地方有点儿像邦葛罗斯和那不幸的耶稣会士，就是那位男爵，居内贡小姐的哥哥。这印象使他心中一动，而且很难过，把他们瞧得更仔细了。他和加刚菩道：“真的，要不是我眼看邦葛罗斯被吊死，要不是我一时糊涂，亲手把男爵杀死，我竟要相信这两个划桨的就是他们了。”

听到男爵和邦葛罗斯的名字，两个苦役犯大叫一声，放下了桨，呆在凳上不动了。船主奔过来，越发鞭如雨下。

老实人叫道：“先生，别打了，别打了；你要多少钱我都给。”

一个苦役犯嚷道：“怎么！是老实人！”

另外一个也道：“怎么！是老实人！”

老实人道：“我莫非做梦不成？我究竟醒着还是睡着？我是在这条船上吗？这是我杀死的男爵吗？这是我眼看被吊死的邦葛罗斯大师吗？”

两人回答：“是我们啊，是我们啊。”

玛丁问：“怎么，那位大哲学家就在这儿？”

老实人道：“喂，船主，我要赎出森特—登—脱龙克男爵，日耳曼帝国最有地位的一个男爵，还有全日耳曼最深刻的玄学家邦葛罗斯先生。你要多少钱？”

船主答道：“狗东西的基督徒！既然这两条苦役狗是什么男爵，什么玄学大家，那一定是他们国内的大人物了；我要五万金洋！”

“行！先生；赶快送我上君士坦丁堡，越快越好，到了那里我马上付钱。啊，不，你得带我上居内贡小姐那儿。”

船主听到老实人要求赎出奴隶，早已掉转船头，向君士坦丁堡进发，教手下的人划得比飞鸟还快。

老实人把男爵和邦葛罗斯拥抱了上百次——“亲爱的男爵，怎么我没有把你杀死的？亲爱的邦葛罗斯，怎么你吊死以后还活着的？你们俩又怎么都在土耳其船上做苦役的？”

男爵道：“我亲爱的妹妹果真在这里吗？”

“是的。”加刚菩回答。

邦葛罗斯嚷道：“啊，我又见到我亲爱的老实人了。”

老实人把玛丁和加刚菩向他们介绍了。他们都互相拥抱，抢着说话。船飞一般地向前，已经到岸了。他们叫来一个犹太人，老实人把一颗价值十万的钻石卖了五万，犹太人还用亚伯拉罕的名字赌咒，说无论如何不能多给了。老实人立刻付了男爵和邦葛罗斯的身价。邦葛罗斯扑在地下，把恩人脚上洒满了眼泪；男爵只点点头表示谢意，答应一有机会就偿还这笔款子。他说：“我的妹子可是真的在土耳其？”

加刚菩答道：“一点儿不假，她在一位德朗西未尼阿的废王家里洗碗。”

他们又找来两个犹太人，老实人又卖了两颗钻，然后一齐搭着另外一条船去赎居内贡。

第二十八章　老实人、居内贡、邦葛罗斯和玛丁等等的遭遇

老实人对男爵道：“对不起，男爵，对不起，神父，请你原谅我把你一剑从前胸戳到后背。”

男爵道：“别提了；我承认当时我火气大了一些；但你既然要知道我怎么会罚做苦役的，我就告诉你听。我的伤口经会里的司药修士医好之后，一队西班牙兵来偷袭，把我活捉了，下在布韦诺斯·爱累斯牢里，那时我妹妹正好离开那儿。我要求遣回罗马总会。总会派我到驻君士坦丁堡的法国大使身边当随从司祭。到任不满八天，有个晚上遇到一位宫中侍从，年纪很轻，长得很美。天热得厉害，那青年想洗澡；我也借此机会洗澡。谁知一个基督徒和一个年轻的回教徒光着身子在一起，算是犯了大罪。法官教人把我脚底打了一百板子，罚做苦役。我不信世界上还有比这个更冤枉的事。但我很想知道，为什么我妹妹替一个亡命在土耳其的德朗西未尼阿废王当厨娘？”

老实人道：“那么你呢，亲爱的邦葛罗斯，怎么我又会见到你呢？”

邦葛罗斯道：“不错，你是看我吊死的；照例我是应当烧死的；可是你记得，他们正要动手烧我，忽然下起雨来；雨势猛烈，没法点火；他们无可奈何，只得把我吊死了事。一个外科医生买了我的尸体，拿回去解剖。他先把我从肚脐到锁骨，一横一直划了两刀。我那次吊死的手续，做得再糟糕没有。执行异教裁判所救世大业的是个副司祭，烧死人的本领的确天下无双，但吊人的工作没做惯：绳子浸饱了雨水，不大滑溜了，中间又打了结；因此我还有一口气。两刀划下来，我不禁大叫一声，那外科医生仰面朝天摔了一跤，以为解剖到一个魔鬼了，吓得掉过身了就逃，在楼梯上又栽了一个筋斗。他的女人听见叫喊，从隔壁房里跑来，看我身上划着两刀躺在桌上，比她丈夫吓得更厉害，赶紧逃走，跌在丈夫身上。等到他们惊魂略定，那女的对外科医生说，‘朋友，怎么你心血来潮，会解剖一个邪教徒的？你不知道这些人老有魔鬼附身吗？让我马上去找个教士来念咒退邪。’一听这话，我急坏了，拼着最后一些气力叫救命。终于那葡萄牙理发匠[65]大着胆子，把我伤口缝起来，连他的女人也来照顾我了；半个月以后我下了床。理发匠帮我谋了一个差事，荐给一个玛德会修士做跟班，随他上佛尼市；但那主人付不出工钱，我就去侍候一个佛尼市商人，跟他到君士坦丁堡。

“有一天我一时高兴，走进一座清真寺。寺中只有一个老法师，还有一个年轻貌美的信女在那里念念有词。她袒着胸部，两个乳头之间缀着一个美丽的花球，其中有郁金香，有蔷薇，有白头苗，有土大黄，有风信子，有莲馨花。她一不留神，把花球掉在地下，我急忙捡起，恭恭敬敬替她放回原处。我放回原处的时间太久了些，恼了老法师；他一知道我是基督徒，就叫出人来，带我去见法官。法官着人把我脚底打了一百板子，罚做苦役。我恰好和男爵同时锁在一条船上，一条凳上。同船有四个马赛青年、五个拿波里教士、两个科孚岛上的修士，都说这一类的事每天都有。男爵认为他的案子比我的更冤枉；我呢，我认为替一个女人把花球放回原处，不像跟一个侍从官光着身子在一起那样有失体统。我们为此争辩不已，每天要挨二十鞭子；不料凡事皆有定数，你居然搭着我们的船，把我们赎了出来。”

老实人问他：“那么，亲爱的邦葛罗斯，你被吊死、解剖、鞭打、罚做苦工的时候，是不是还认为天下事尽善尽美呢？”

邦葛罗斯答道：“我的信心始终不变，因为我是哲学家，不便出尔反尔。莱布尼兹的话不会错的，先天谐和的学说，跟空间皆是实体和奇妙的物质等等，同样是世界上的至理名言[66]。”

第二十九章　老实人怎样和居内贡与老婆子相会

老实人、男爵、邦葛罗斯、玛丁和加刚菩，讲着他们的经历，谈着世界上一切偶然的或非偶然的事故，讨论着因果关系，精神痛苦与物质痛苦，自由与命运，在土耳其商船上如何自慰等等，终于到了普罗篷提特海边上，德朗西未尼阿王的屋子前面。一眼望去，先就看到居内贡和老婆子在绳上晾饭巾。

男爵一见，脸就白了。多情的老实人，看到他美丽的居内贡皮肤变成棕色，眼中全是血筋，乳房干瘪了，满脸皱纹，通红的手臂长满着鱼鳞般的硬皮，不由得毛发悚然，倒退了几步；然后为了礼貌关系，只得走近前去。居内贡把老实人和她的哥哥拥抱了；大家也拥抱了老婆子。老实人把她们俩都赎了出来。

附近有一块分种田；老婆子劝老实人暂且拿下，等日后大家时来运转，再做计较。居内贡不知道自己变丑了，也没有一个人向她道破：她和老实人提到当年的婚约，口气那么坚决，忠厚的老实人竟不敢拒绝。他便通知男爵，说要和他的妹子结婚了。

男爵道：“像她那样的下流，像你那样的狂妄，我万万不能容忍；我决不为这桩玷辱门楣的事分担责任，我妹妹的儿女将来永远不能写上德国的贵族谱。告诉你，我的妹子只能嫁给一个德国的男爵。”

居内贡倒在他脚下，哭着哀求；他执意不允。

老实人对他说：“你疯了；我把你救出苦役，付了你的身价，付了你妹妹的身价；她在这儿替人洗碗，变得这么丑，我好心娶她为妻，你倒胆敢拒绝；逞我性子，恨不得把你再杀一次才好！”

男爵道：“再杀就再杀；要我活着答应你娶我的妹子，可是休想。”

第三十章　结局

老实人其实绝无意思和居内贡结婚。但男爵的蛮横恼了他，觉得非结婚不可了。何况居内贡逼得那么紧，他也不便翻悔。他跟邦葛罗斯、玛丁和忠心的加刚菩商量。邦葛罗斯写了一篇出色的论文，证明男爵绝无权干涉妹子的事；她依照德国所有的法律，尽可嫁给老实人。玛丁主张把男爵扔在海里；加刚菩主张送还给小亚细亚船主，仍旧教他做苦工；有了便船，再送回罗马，交给他的总会会长。大家觉得这主意挺好，老婆子也赞成，便瞒着妹子，花了些钱把这件事办妥了：教一个耶稣会士吃些苦，把一个骄傲的德国男爵惩罚一下，谁都觉得高兴。

经过了这许多患难，老实人和情人结了婚，跟哲学家邦葛罗斯、哲学家玛丁、机灵的加刚菩和老婆子住在一起，又从古印加人那儿带了那么多钻石回来，据我们想象，老实人应当过着世界上最愉快的生活了。但他被犹太人一再拐骗，除掉那块分种田以外已经一无所有。他的女人一天丑似一天，变得性情暴戾，谁都见了头痛；老婆子本来是残废的人，那时比居内贡脾气更坏。加刚菩种着园地，挑菜上君士坦丁堡去卖，操劳过度，整天怨命。邦葛罗斯因为不能在德国什么大学里一露锋芒，苦闷不堪。玛丁认定一个人到处都是受罪，也就耐着性子。

老实人、玛丁、邦葛罗斯，偶尔谈玄说理，讨论讨论道德问题。窗下常常看见一些船只，载着当地的贵族、官员、祭司，充军到来姆诺斯、米底兰纳、埃斯卢姆。又看见一些别的祭司、贵族、官员来接任，然后再受流配。也看到一些包扎得挺好的人头送往大苏丹的宫门。这些景象增加了他们辩论的题材；不辩论的时候，大家就厌烦得要死，甚至有一天老婆子问他们：“我要知道，被黑人海盗强奸一百次，割掉半个屁股，被保加利亚人鞭打，在功德大会中挨板子，上吊，被解剖，在苦役船上划桨，受尽我们大家所受的苦难，跟住在这儿一无所事比起来，究竟哪一样更难受？”

老实人道：“嗯，这倒是个大问题。”

这一席话又引起众人新的感想。玛丁下了断语，说人天生只有两条路：不是在忧急骚动中讨生活，便是在烦闷无聊中挨日子。老实人不同意这话，但提不出别的主张。邦葛罗斯承认自己一生苦不堪言；可是一朝说过了世界上样样十全十美，只能一口咬定，坚持到底，虽则骨子里完全不信。

那时又出了一件事，使玛丁那种泄气的论调多了一个佐证，使老实人更加彷徨，邦葛罗斯更不容易自圆其说。有一天他们看见巴该德和奚罗弗莱修士狼狈不堪，走到他们的分种田上来。两人把三千银洋很快就吃完了，一忽儿分手，一忽儿讲和，一忽儿吵架，坐牢，越狱，奚罗弗莱终于改信了回教。巴该德到处流浪，继续做她的买卖，一个钱也挣不到了。

玛丁对老实人道：“我早跟你说的，你送的礼不久就会花光，他们的生活倒反更苦。你和加刚菩发过大财，有过几百万银洋，却并没比巴该德和奚罗弗莱更快活。”

邦葛罗斯和巴该德说：“啊，啊，可怜的孩子，你又到我们这儿来了，大概是天意吧！你知道没有，你害我损失了一个鼻尖、一只眼睛和一只耳朵？如今你也完啦！这世界真是怎么回事啊！”

这件新鲜事儿，使众人对穷通祸福越发讨论不完。

附近住着一位大名鼎鼎的回教修士，被公认为土耳其最有智慧的哲学家；他们去向他请教，由邦葛罗斯代表发言，说道：“师傅，请你告诉我们，世界上为什么要生出人这样一种古怪的动物？”

修道士回答：“你问这个干什么？你管它做什么？”

老实人道：“可是，大法师，地球上满目疮痍，到处都是灾祸啊。”

修道士说：“福也罢，祸也罢，有什么关系？咱们的苏丹打发一条船到埃及去，可曾关心船上的耗子舒服不舒服？”

邦葛罗斯道：“那么应当怎办呢？”

修道士说：“闭上你的嘴。”

邦葛罗斯道：“我希望和你谈谈因果，谈谈十全十美的世界、罪恶的根源、灵魂的性质、先天的谐和。”

修道士听了这话，把门劈面关上了。

谈话之间，听到一个消息，说君士坦丁堡绞死了两个枢密大臣、一个大司祭；他们不少朋友都受了木柱洞腹的极刑。几小时以内，这桩可怕的事沸沸扬扬，传遍各地。邦葛罗斯、老实人、玛丁在回去的路上遇到一个和善的老人，在门外橘树荫下乘凉。邦葛罗斯好奇不亚于好辩，向老人打听那绞死的大司祭叫甚名字，老人回答：“我素来不知道大司祭等等姓甚名谁。你说的那件事，我根本不晓得。我认为顾问公家事情的人，有时会死于非命，这也是他们活该。我从来不打听君士坦丁堡的事；我不过把园子里种出来的果子送去卖。”

他说着把这几个外乡人让进屋子，两个儿子和两个女儿端出好几种自制的果子露敬客，还有糖渍的佛手、橘子、柠檬、菠萝、花生，纯粹的莫加咖啡，不羼一点儿巴太维亚和中美洲群岛的坏咖啡的。回教徒的两个女儿又替老实人、邦葛罗斯、玛丁胡子上喷了香水。

老实人问土耳其人：“想必你有一大块良田美产了？”

土耳其人回答：“我只有二十阿尔邦地[67]；我亲自和孩子们耕种；工作可以使我们免除三大害处：烦闷，纵欲，饥寒。”

老实人回到自己田庄上，把土耳其人的话深思了一番，对邦葛罗斯和玛丁说道：“那个慈祥的老头儿安排的生活，我觉得比和我们同席的六位国王好多了。”

邦葛罗斯道：“根据所有哲学家的说法，荣华富贵、权势地位，都是非常危险的；摩阿布的王埃格隆被阿奥特所杀；阿布萨隆被吊着头发缢死，身上还戳了三枪；泽罗菩阿姆的儿子内达布王，死于巴萨之手；伊拉王死于萨勃利之手；奥谷齐阿斯死于奚于；阿太里亚死于约伊阿达；约金、奚谷尼阿斯、赛台西阿斯诸王，都沦为奴隶[68]。至于克雷絮斯、阿斯蒂阿琪、大流士、西拉叩斯的特尼、彼拉斯、班尔赛、汉尼拔、朱革塔、阿利俄维斯塔、恺撒、庞培、尼罗、奥东、维德卢维阿斯、多密喜安[69]，英王理查二世、爱德华二世、亨利四世、理查三世、玛丽·斯丢阿德、查理一世，法国的三个亨利，罗马日耳曼皇帝亨利四世，他们怎样结局，你是都知道的。你知道……”

老实人说：“是的，我还知道应当种我们的园地。”

邦葛罗斯道：“你说得很对。上帝把人放进伊甸园是叫他当工人，要他工作的；足见人天生不是能清闲度日的。”

玛丁道：“少废话，咱们工作吧；唯有工作，日子才好过。”

那小团体里的人一致赞成这个好主意，便各人拿出本领来。小小的土地出产很多。居内贡固然奇丑无比，但变了一个做糕饼的能手；巴该德管绣作；老婆子管内衣被褥。连奚罗弗莱也没有闲着，他变了一个很能干的木匠，做人也规矩了。

有时邦葛罗斯对老实人说：“在这个十全十美的世界上，所有的事情都是互相关联的；你要不是为了爱居内贡小姐，被人踢着屁股从美丽的宫堡中赶出来，要不是受到异教裁判所的刑罚，要不是徒步跋涉美洲，要不是狠狠地刺了男爵一剑，要不是把美好的黄金国的绵羊一齐丢掉，你就不能在这儿吃花生和糖渍佛手。”

老实人道：“说得很妙；可是种咱们的园地要紧。”

Chapter 3 How Candide Escaped from the Bulgarians and What Befell Him Afterward

Never was anything so gallant, so well accoutred, so brilliant, and so fnely disposed as the two armies. The trumpets, ffes, hautboys, drums, and cannon made such harmony as never was heard in Hell itself.The entertainment began by a discharge of cannon, which, in the twinkling of an eye, laid flat about 6，000 men on each side.The musket bullets swept away, out of the best of all possible worlds, nine or ten thousand scoundrels that infested its surface.The bayonet was next the suffcient reason of the deaths of several thousands.The whole might amount to thirty thousand souls.Candide trembled like a philosopher, and concealed himself as well as he could during this heroic butchery.

At length, while the two kings were causing Te Deums to be sung in their camps, Candide took a resolution to go and reason somewhere else upon causes and effects. After passing over heaps of dead or dying men, the frst place he came to was a neighboring village, in the Abarian territories, which had been burned to the ground by the Bulgarians, agreeably to the laws of war.Here lay a number of old men covered with wounds, who beheld their wives dying with their throats cut, and hugging their children to their breasts, all stained with blood.There several young virgins, whose bodies had been ripped open, after they had satisfed the natural necessities of the Bulgarian heroes, breathed their last；while others, half-burned in the flames, begged to be dispatched out of the world.The ground about them was covered with the brains, arms, and legs of dead men.

Candide made all the haste he could to another village, which belonged to the Bulgarians, and there he found the heroic Abares had enacted the same tragedy. Thence continuing to walk over palpitating limbs, or through ruined buildings, at length he arrived beyond the theater of war, with a little provision in his budget, and Miss Cunegund's image in his heart.When he arrived in Holland his provision failed him；but having heard that the inhabitants of that country were all rich and Christians, he made himself sure of being treated by them in the same manner as the Baron's castle, before he had been driven thence through the power of Miss Cunegund's bright eyes.

He asked charity of several grave-looking people, who one and all answered him, that if he continued to follow this trade they would have him sent to the house of correction, where he should be taught to get his bread.

He next addressed himself to a person who had just come from haranguing a numerous assembly for a whole hour on the subject of charity. The orator, squinting at him under his broadbrimmed hat, asked him sternly, what brought him thither and whether he was for the good old cause?

“Sir，”said Candide, in a submissive manner，“I conceive there can be no effect without a cause；everything is necessarily concatenated and arranged for the best. It was necessary that I should be banished from the presence of Miss Cunegund；that I should afterwards run the gauntlet；and it is necessary I should beg my bread, till I am able to get it.All this could not have been otherwise.”

“Hark ye, friend，”said the orator，“do you hold the Pope to be Antichrist?”

“Truly, I never heard anything about it，”said Candide，“but whether he is or not, I am in want of something to eat.”

“Thou deservest not to eat or to drink，”replied the orator，“wretch, monster, that thou art！Hence！Avoid my sight, nor ever come near me again while thou livest.”

The orator's wife happened to put her head out of the window at that instant, when, seeing a man who doubted whether the Pope was Antichrist, she discharged upon his head a utensil full of water. Good heavens, to what excess does religious zeal transport womankind！

A man who had never been christened, an honest Anabaptist named James, was witness to the cruel and ignominious treatment showed to one of his brethren, to a rational, two-footed, unfledged being. Moved with pity he carried him to his own house, caused him to be cleaned, gave him meat and drink, and made him a present of two forins, at the same time proposing to instruct him in his own trade of weaving Persian silks, which are fabricated in Holland.

Candide, penetrated with so much goodness, threw himself at his feet, crying，“Now I am convinced that my Master Pangloss told me truth when he said that everything was for the best in this world；for I am infnitely more affected with your extraordinary generosity than with the inhumanity of that gentleman in the black cloak and his wife.”

Chapter 4 How Candide Found His Old Master Pangloss Again and What Happened to Him

The next day, as Candide was walking out, he met a beggar all covered with scabs, his eyes sunk in his head, the end of his nose eaten off, his mouth drawn on one side, his teeth as black as a cloak, snuffing and coughing most violently, and every time he attempted to spit out dropped a tooth.

Candide, divided between compassion and horror, but giving way to the former, bestowed on this shocking figure the two florins which the honest Anabaptist, James, had just before given to him. The specter looked at him very earnestly, shed tears and threw his arms about his neck.Candide started back aghast.

“Alas！”said the one wretch to the other，“don't you know dear Pangloss?”

“What do I hear?Is it you, my dear master！You I behold in this piteous plight?What dreadful misfortune has befallen you?What has made you leave the most magnifcent and delightful of all castles?What has become of Miss Cunegund, the mirror of young ladies, and Nature's masterpiece?”

“Oh, Lord！”cried Pangloss，“I am so weak I cannot stand，”upon which Candide instantly led him to the Anabaptist's stable, and procured him something to eat.

As soon as Pangloss had a little refreshed himself, Candide began to repeat his inquiries concerning Miss Cunegund.

“She is dead，”replied the other.

“Dead！”cried Candide, and immediately fainted away；his friend restored him by the help of a little bad vinegar, which he found by chance in the stable.

Candide opened his eyes, and again repeated：“Dead！Is Miss Cunegund dead?Ah, where is the best of worlds now?But of what illness did she die?Was it of grief on seeing her father kick me out of his magnifcent castle?”

“No，”replied Pangloss，“her body was ripped open by the Bulgarian soldiers, after they had subjected her to as much cruelty as a damsel could survive；they knocked the Baron, her father, on the head for attempting to defend her；My Lady, her mother, was cut in pieces；my poor pupil was served just in the same manner as his sister；and as for the castle, they have not left one stone upon another；they have destroyed all the ducks, and sheep, the barns, and the trees；but we have had our revenge, for the Abares have done the very same thing in a neighboring barony, which belonged to a Bulgarian lord.”

At hearing this, Candide fainted away a second time, but, not withstanding, having come to himself again, he said all that it became him to say；he inquired into the cause and effect, as well as into the suffcing reason that had reduced Pangloss to so miserable a condition.

“Alas，”replied the preceptor，“it was love；love, the comfort of the human species；love, the preserver of the universe；the soul of all sensible beings；love！Tender love！”

“Alas，”cried Candide，“I have had some knowledge of love myself， this sovereign of hearts, this soul of souls；yet it never cost me more than a kiss and twenty kicks on the backside. But how could this beautiful cause produce in you so hideous an effect?”

Pangloss made answer in these terms：

“O my dear Candide, you must remember Pacquette, that pretty wench, who waited on our noble Baroness；in her arms I tasted the pleasures of Paradise, which produced these Hell torments with which you see me devoured. She was infected with an ailment, and perhaps has since died of it；she received this present of a learned Franciscan, who derived it from the fountainhead；he was indebted for it to an old countess, who had it of a captain of horse, who had it of a marchioness, who had it of a page, the page had it of a Jesuit, who, during his novitiate, had it in a direct line from one of the fellow adventurers of Christopher Columbus；for my part I shall give it to nobody, I am a dying man.”

“O sage Pangloss，”cried Candide，“what a strange genealogy is this！Is not the devil the root of it?”

“Not at all，”replied the great man，“it was a thing unavoidable, a necessary ingredient in the best of worlds；for if Columbus had not caught in an island in America this disease, which contaminates the source of generation, and frequently impedes propagation itself, and is evidently opposed to the great end of nature, we should have had neither chocolate nor cochineal. It is also to be observed, that, even to the present time, in this continent of ours, this malady, like our religious controversies, is peculiar to ourselves.The Turks, the Indians, the Persians, the Chinese, the Siamese, and the Japanese are entirely unacquainted with it；but there is a suffcing reason for them to know it in a few centuries.In the meantime, it is making prodigious havoc among us, especially in those armies composed of well disciplined hirelings, who determine the fate of nations；for we may safely affrm, that, when an army of thirty thousand men engages another equal in size, there are about twenty thousand infected with syphilis on each side.”

“Very surprising, indeed，”said Candide，“but you must get cured.”

“Lord help me, how can I?”said Pangloss.“My dear friend, I have not a penny in the world；and you know one cannot be bled or have an enema without money.”

This last speech had its effect on Candide；he few to the charitable Anabaptist, James；he fung himself at his feet, and gave him so striking a picture of the miserable condition of his friend that the good man without any further hesitation agreed to take Dr. Pangloss into his house, and to pay for his cure.The cure was effected with only the loss of one eye and an ear.As he wrote a good hand, and understood accounts tolerably well, the Anabaptist made him his bookkeeper.At the expiration of two months, being obliged by some mercantile affairs to go to Lisbon he took the two philosophers with him in the same ship；Pangloss, during the course of the voyage, explained to him how everything was so constituted that it could not be better.James did not quite agree with him on this point.

“Men，”said he“must, in some things, have deviated from their original innocence；for they were not born wolves, and yet they worry one another like those beasts of prey. God never gave them twenty-four pounders nor bayonets, and yet they have made cannon and bayonets to destroy one another.To this account I might add not only bankruptcies, but the law which seizes on the effects of bankrupts, only to cheat the creditors.”

“All this was indispensably necessary，”replied the one-eyed doctor，“for private misfortunes are public benefits；so that the more private misfortunes there are, the greater is the general good.”

While he was arguing in this manner, the sky was overcast, the winds blew from the four quarters of the compass, and the ship was assailed by a most terrible tempest, within sight of the port of Lisbon.

Chapter 6 How the Portuguese Made a Superb Auto-De-Fe to Prevent Any Future Earthquakes, and How Candide Underwent Public Flagellation

After the earthquake, which had destroyed three-fourths of the city of Lisbon, the sages of that country could think of no means more effectual to preserve the kingdom from utter ruin than to entertain the people with an auto-da-fe, it having been decided by the University of Coimbra, that the burning of a few people alive by a slow fre, and with great ceremony, is an infallible preventive of earthquakes.

In consequence thereof they had seized on a Biscayan for marrying his godmother, and on two Portuguese for taking out the bacon of a larded pullet they were eating；after dinner they came and secured Dr. Pangloss, and his pupil Candide, the one for speaking his mind, and the other for seeming to approve what he had said.They were conducted to separate apartments, extremely cool, where they were never incommoded with the sun.Eight days afterwards they were each dressed in a sanbenito, and their heads were adorned with paper mitres.The mitre and sanbenito worn by Candide were painted with flames reversed and with devils that had neither tails nor claws；but Dr.Pangloss's devils had both tails and claws, and his fames were upright.In these habits they marched in procession, and heard a very pathetic sermon, which was followed by an anthem, accompanied by bagpipes.Candide was fogged to some tune, while the anthem was being sung；the Biscayan and the two men who would not eat bacon were burned, and Pangloss was hanged, which is not a common custom at these solemnities.The same day there was another earthquake, which made most dreadful havoc.

Candide, amazed, terrifed, confounded, astonished, all bloody, and trembling from head to foot, said to himself，“If this is the best of all possible worlds, what are the others?If I had only been whipped, I could have put up with it, as I did among the Bulgarians；but, not withstanding, oh my dear Pangloss！My beloved master！Thou greatest of philosophers！That ever I should live to see thee hanged, without knowing for what！O my dear Anabaptist, thou best of men, that it should be thy fate to be drowned in the very harbor！O Miss Cunegund, you mirror of young ladies！That it should be your fate to have your body ripped open！”

He was making the best of his way from the place where he had been preached to, whipped, absolved and blessed, when he was accosted by an old woman, who said to him，“Take courage, child, and follow me.”

Chapter 9 What Happened to Cunegund, Candide, the Grand Inquisitor, and the Jew

This same Issachar was the most choleric little Hebrew that had ever been in Israel since the captivity of Babylon.

“What，”said he，“thou Galilean slut?The Inquisitor was not enough for thee, but this rascal must come in for a share with me?”

In uttering these words, he drew out a long poniard, which he always carried about him, and never dreaming that his adversary had any arms, he attacked him most furiously；but our honestWestphalian had received from the old woman a handsome sword with the suit of clothes. Candide drew his rapier, and though he was very gentle and sweet-tempered, he laid the Israelite dead on the foor at the fair Cunegund's feet.

“Holy Virgin！”cried she，“what will become of us?A man killed in my apartment！If the peace-offcers come, we are undone.”

“Had not Pangloss been hanged，”replied Candide，“he would have given us most excellent advice, in this emergency；for he was a profound philosopher. But, since he is not here, let us consult the old woman.”

She was very sensible, and was beginning to give her advice, when another door opened on a sudden. It was now one o'clock in the morning, and of course the beginning of Sunday, which, by agreement, fell to the lot of My Lord Inquisitor.Entering he discovered the fagellated Candide with his drawn sword in his hand, a dead body stretched on the floor, Cunegund frightened out of her wits, and the old woman giving advice.

At that very moment, a sudden thought came into Candide's head.“If this holy man，”thought he，“should call assistance, I shall most undoubtedly be consigned to the fames, and Miss Cunegund may perhaps meet with no better treatment：besides, he was the cause of my being so cruelly whipped；he is my rival；and as I have now begun to dip my hands in blood, I will kill away, for there is no time to hesitate.”

This whole train of reasoning was clear and instantaneous；so that, without giving time to the Inquisitor to recover from his surprise, he ran him through the body, and laid him by the side of the Jew.

“Here's another fine piece of work！”cried Cunegund.“Now there can be no mercy for us, we are excommunicated；our last hour is come. But how could you, who are of so mild a temper, despatch a Jew and an Inquisitor in two minutes'time?”

“Beautiful maiden，”answered Candide，“when a man is in love, is jealous, and has been fogged by the Inquisition, he becomes lost to all refection.”

The old woman then put in her word：

“There are three Andalusian horses in the stable, with as many bridles and saddles；let the brave Candide get them ready. Madam has a parcel of moidores and jewels, let us mount immediately, though I have lost one buttock；let us set out for Cadiz；it is the finest weather in the world, and there is great pleasure in traveling in the cool of the night.”

Candide, without any further hesitation, saddled the three horses；and Miss Cunegund, the old woman, and he, set out, and traveled thirty miles without once halting. While they were making the best of their way, the Holy Brotherhood entered the house.My Lord, the Inquisitor, was interred in a magnifcent manner, and Master Issachar's body was thrown upon a dunghill.

Candide, Cunegund, and the old woman, had by this time reached the little town of Avacena, in the midst of the mountains of Sierra Morena, and were engaged in the following conversation in an inn, where they had taken up their quarters.

Chapter 11 The History of the Old Woman

“I have not always been blear-eyed. My nose did not always touch my chin；nor was I always a servant.You must know that I am the daughter of Pope Urban X, and of the Princess of Palestrina.To the age of fourteen I was brought up in a castle, compared with which all the castles of the German barons would not have been ft for stabling, and one of my robes would have bought half the province of Westphalia.I grew up, and improved in beauty, wit, and every graceful accomplishment；and in the midst of pleasures, homage, and the highest expectations.I already began to inspire the men with love.My breast began to take its right form, and such a breast！White, frm, and formed like that of the Venus de'Medici；my eyebrows were as black as jet, and as for my eyes, they darted fames and eclipsed the luster of the stars, as I was told by the poets of our part of the world.My maids, when they dressed and undressed me, used to fall into an ecstasy in viewing me before and behind；and all the men longed to be in their places.

“I was contracted in marriage to a sovereign prince of Massa Carrara. Such a prince！As handsome as myself, sweet-tempered, agreeable, witty, and in love with me over head and ears.I loved him, too, as our sex generally do for the first time, with rapture, transport, and idolatry. The nuptials were prepared with surprising pomp and magnifcence；the ceremony was attended with feasts, carousals, and burlesques：all Italy composed sonnets in my praise, though not one of them was tolerable.

“I was on the point of reaching the summit of bliss, when an old marchioness, who had been mistress to the Prince, my husband, invited him to drink chocolate. In less than two hours after he returned from the visit, he died of most terrible convulsions.

“But this is a mere trife. My mother, distracted to the highest degree, and yet less afficted than I, determined to absent herself for some time from so fatal a place.As she had a very fne estate in the neighborhood of Gaeta, we embarked on board a galley, which was gilded like the high altar of St.Peter's, at Rome.In our passage we were boarded by a Sallee rover.Our men defended themselves like true Pope's soldiers；they fung themselves upon their knees, laid down their arms, and begged the corsair to give them absolution in articulo mortis.

“The Moors presently stripped us as bare as ever we were born. My mother, my maids of honor, and myself, were served all in the same manner.It is amazing how quick these gentry are at undressing people.But what surprised me most was, that they made a rude sort of surgical examination of parts of the body which are sacred to the functions of nature.I thought it a very strange kind of ceremony；for thus we are generally apt to judge of things when we have not seen the world.I afterwards learned that it was to discover if we had any diamonds concealed.This practice had been established since time immemorial among those civilized nations that scour the seas.I was informed that the religious Knights of Malta never fail to make this search whenever any Moors of either sex fall into their hands.It is a part of the law of nations, from which they never deviate.

“I need not tell you how great a hardship it was for a young princess and her mother to be made slaves and carried to Morocco. You may easily imagine what we must have suffered on board a corsair.My mother was still extremely handsome, our maids of honor, and even our common waiting-women, had more charms than were to be found in all Africa.As to myself, I was enchanting；I was beauty itself, and then I had my virginity.But, alas！I did not retain it long；this precious fower, which had been reserved for the lovely Prince of Massa Carrara, was cropped by the captain of the Moorish vessel, who was a hideous Negro, and thought he did me infnite honor.Indeed, both the Princess of Palestrina and myself must have had very strong constitutions to undergo all the hardships and violences we suffered before our arrival at Morocco.But I will not detain you any longer with such common things；they are hardly worth mentioning.

“Upon our arrival at Morocco we found that kingdom deluged with blood. Fifty sons of the Emperor Muley Ishmael were each at the head of a party.This produced ffty civil wars of blacks against blacks, of tawnies against tawnies, and of mulattoes against mulattoes.In short, the whole empire was one continued scene of carnage.

“No sooner were we landed than a party of blacks, of a contrary faction to that of my captain, came to rob him of his booty. Next to the money and jewels, we were the most valuable things he had.I witnessed on this occasion such a battle as you never beheld in your cold European climates.The northern nations have not that fermentation in their blood, nor that raging lust for women that is so common in Africa.The natives of Europe seem to have their veins flled with milk only；but fre and vitriol circulate in those of the inhabitants of Mount Atlas and the neighboring provinces.They fought with the fury of the lions, tigers, and serpents of their country, to decide who should have us.A Moor seized my mother by the right arm, while my captain's lieutenant held her by the left；another Moor laid hold of her by the right leg, and one of our corsairs held her by the other.In this manner almost all of our women were dragged by four soldiers.

“My captain kept me concealed behind him, and with his drawn scimitar cut down everyone who opposed him；at length I saw all our Italian women and my mother mangled and torn in pieces by the monsters who contended for them. The captives, my companions, the Moors who took us, the soldiers, the sailors, the blacks, the whites, the mulattoes, and lastly, my captain himself, were all slain, and I remained alone expiring upon a heap of dead bodies.Similar barbarous scenes were transacted every day over the whole country, which is of three hundred leagues in extent, and yet they never missed the fve stated times of prayer enjoined by their prophet Mahomet.

“I disengaged myself with great difficulty from such a heap of corpses, and made a shift to crawl to a large orange tree that stood on the bank of a neighboring rivulet, where I fell down exhausted with fatigue, and overwhelmed with horror, despair, and hunger. My senses being overpowered, I fell asleep, or rather seemed to be in a trance.Thus I lay in a state of weakness and insensibility between life and death, when I felt myself pressed by something that moved up and down upon my body.This brought me to myself.I opened my eyes, and saw a pretty fair-faced man, who sighed and muttered these words between his teeth，'O che sciagura d'essere senza coglioni！''

Chapter 14 The Reception Candide and Cacambo Met with among the Jesuits in Paraguay

Candide had brought with him from Cadiz such a footman as one often meets with on the coasts of Spain and in the colonies. He was the fourth part of a Spaniard, of a mongrel breed, and born inTucuman.He had successively gone through the profession of a singing boy, sexton, sailor, monk, peddler, soldier, and lackey.His name was Cacambo；he had a great affection for his master, because his master was a very good man.He immediately saddled the two Andalusian horses.

“Come, my good master, let us follow the old woman's advice, and make all the haste we can from this place without staying to look behind us.”

Candide burst into a flood of tears，“O my dear Cunegund, must I then be compelled to quit you just as the Governor was going to honor us with his presence at our wedding！Cunegund, so long lost and found again, what will now become of you?”

“Lord！”said Cacambo，“she must do as well as she can；women are never at a loss. God takes care of them, and so let us make the best of our way.”

“But whither wilt thou carry me?Where can we go?What can we do without Cunegund?”cried the disconsolate Candide.

“By St. James of Compostella，”said Cacambo，“you were going to fght against the Jesuits of Paraguay；now let us go and fght for them；I know the road perfectly well；I'll conduct you to their kingdom；they will be delighted with a captain that understands the Bulgarian drill；you will certainly make a prodigious fortune.If we cannot succeed in this world we may in another.It is a great pleasure to see new objects and perform new exploits.”

“Then you have been in Paraguay?”asked Candide.

“Ay, marry, I have，”replied Cacambo.“I was a scout in the College of the Assumption, and am as well acquainted with the new government of the Los Padres as I am with the streets of Cadiz. Oh, it is an admirable government, that is most certain！The kingdom is at present upwards of three hundred leagues in diameter, and divided into thirty provinces；the fathers there are masters of everything, and the people have no money at all；this you must allow is the masterpiece of justice and reason.For my part, I see nothing so divine as the good fathers, who wage war in this part of the world against the troops of Spain and Portugal, at the same time that they hear the confessions of those very princes in Europe；who kill Spaniards in America and send them to Heaven at Madrid.This pleases me exceedingly, but let us push forward；you are going to see the happiest and most fortunate of all mortals.How charmed will those fathers be to hear that a captain who understands the Bulgarian military drill is coming to them.”

As soon as they reached the first barrier, Cacambo called to the advance guard, and told them that a captain wanted to speak to My Lord, the General. Notice was given to the main guard, and immediately a Paraguayan officer ran to throw himself at the feet of the Commandant to impart this news to him.Candide and Cacambo were immediately disarmed, and their two Andalusian horses were seized.The two strangers were conducted between two fles of musketeers, the Commandant was at the further end with a three-cornered cap on his head, his gown tucked up, a sword by his side, and a half-pike in his hand；he made a sign, and instantly four and twenty soldiers drew up round the newcomers.A sergeant told them that they must wait, the Commandant could not speak to them；and that the Reverend Father Provincial did not suffer any Spaniard to open his mouth but in his presence, or to stay above three hours in the province.

“And where is the Reverend Father Provincial?”said Cacambo.

“He has just come from Mass and is at the parade，”replied the sergeant，“and in about three hours'time you may possibly have the honor to kiss his spurs.”

“But，”said Cacambo，“the Captain, who, as well as myself, is perishing of hunger, is no Spaniard, but a German；therefore, pray, might we not be permitted to break our fast till we can be introduced to His Reverence?”

The sergeant immediately went and acquainted the Commandant with what he heard.

“God be praised，”said the Reverend Commandant，“since he is a German I will hear what he has to say；let him be brought to my arbor.”

Immediately they conducted Candide to a beautiful pavilion adomed with a colonnade of green marble, spotted with yellow, and with an intertexture of vines, which served as a kind of cage for parrots, humming birds, guinea hens, and all other curious kinds of birds. An excellent breakfast was provided in vessels of gold；and while the Paraguayans were eating coarse Indian corn out of wooden dishes in the open air, and exposed to the burning heat of the sun, the Reverend Father Commandant retired to his cool arbor.

He was a very handsome young man, round-faced, fair, and fresh-colored, his eyebrows were fnely arched, he had a piercing eye, the tips of his ears were red, his lips vermilion, and he had a bold and commanding air；but such a boldness as neither resembled that of a Spaniard nor of a Jesuit. He ordered Candide and Cacambo to have their arms restored to them, together with their two Andalusian horses.Cacambo gave the poor beasts some oats to eat close by the arbor, keeping a strict eye upon them all the while for fear of surprise.

Candide having kissed the hem of the Commandant's robe, they sat down to table.

“It seems you are a German，”said the Jesuit to him in that language.

“Yes, Reverend Father，”answered Candide.

As they pronounced these words they looked at each other with great amazement and with an emotion that neither could conceal.

“From what part of Germany do you come?”said the Jesuit.

“From the dirty province of Westphalia，”answered Candide.“I was born in the castle of Thunder-ten-tronckh.”

“Oh heavens！Is it possible?”said the Commandant.

“What a miracle！”cried Candide.

“Can it be you?”said the Commandant.

On this they both drew a few steps backwards, then running into each other's arms, embraced, and wept profusely.

“Is it you then, Reverend Father?You are the brother of the fair Miss Cunegund?You that was slain by the Bulgarians！You the Baron's son！You a Jesuit in Paraguay！I must confess this is a strange world we live in. O Pangloss！What joy would this have given you if you had not been hanged.”

The Commandant dismissed the Negro slaves, and the Paraguayans who presented them with liquor in crystal goblets. He returned thanks to God and St.Ignatius a thousand times；he clasped Candide in his arms, and both their faces were bathed in tears.

“You will be more surprised, more affected, more transported，”said Candide，“when I tell you that Miss Cunegund, your sister, whose belly was supposed to have been ripped open, is in perfect health.”

“In your neighborhood, with the Governor of Buenos Ayres；and I myself was going to fght against you.”

Every word they uttered during this long conversation was productive of some new matter of astonishment. Their souls futtered on their tongues, listened in their ears, and sparkled in their eyes.Like true Germans, they continued a long while at table, waiting for the Reverend Father；and the Commandant spoke to his dear Candide as follows.

Chapter 19 What Happened to Them at Surinam, and How Candide Became Acquainted with Martin

Our travelers'frst day's journey was very pleasant；they were elated with the prospect of possessing more riches than were to be found in Europe, Asia, and Africa together. Candide, in amorous transports, cut the name of Miss Cunegund on almost every tree he came to.The second day two of their sheep sunk in a morass, and were swallowed up with their lading；two more died of fatigue；some few days afterwards seven or eight perished with hunger in a desert, and others, at different times, tumbled down precipices, or were otherwise lost, so that, after traveling about a hundred days they had only two sheep left of the hundred and two they brought with them from El Dorado.

Said Candide to Cacambo，“You see, my dear friend, how perishable the riches of this world are；there is nothing solid but virtue.”

“Very true，”said Cacambo，“but we have still two sheep remaining, with more treasure than ever the King of Spain will be possessed of；and I espy a town at a distance, which I take to be Surinam, a town belonging to the Dutch. We are now at the end of our troubles, and at the beginning of happiness.”

As they drew near the town they saw a Negro stretched on the ground with only one half of his habit, which was a kind of linen frock；for the poor man had lost his left leg and his right hand.

“Good God，”said Candide in Dutch，“what dost thou here, friend, in this deplorable condition?”

“I am waiting for my master, Mynheer Vanderdendur, the famous trader，”answered the Negro.

“Was it Mynheer Vanderdendur that used you in this cruel manner?”

“Yes, sir，”said the Negro；“it is the custom here. They give a linen garment twice a year, and that is all our covering.When we labor in the sugar works, and the mill happens to snatch hold of a fnger, they instantly chop off our hand；and when we attempt to run away, they cut off a leg.Both these cases have happened to me, and it is at this expense that you eat sugar in Europe；and yet when my mother sold me for ten patacoons on the coast of Guinea, she said to me，‘My dear child, bless our fetishes；adore them forever；they will make thee live happy；thou hast the honor to be a slave to our lords the whites, by which thou wilt make the fortune of us thy parents.'

“Alas！I know not whether I have made their fortunes；but they have not made mine；dogs, monkeys, and parrots are a thousand times less wretched than I. The Dutch fetishes who converted me tell me every Sunday that the blacks and whites are all children of one father, whom they call Adam.As for me, I do not understand anything of genealogies；but if what these preachers say is true, we are all second cousins；and you must allow that it is impossible to be worse treated by our relations than we are.”

“O Pangloss！”cried out Candide，“such horrid doings never entered thy imagination. Here is an end of the matter.I find myself, after all, obliged to renounce thy Optimism.”

“Optimism，”said Cacambo，“what is that?”

“Alas！”replied Candide，“it is the obstinacy of maintaining that everything is best when it is worst.”

And so saying he turned his eyes towards the poor Negro, and shed a food of tears；and in this weeping mood he entered the town of Surinam.

Immediately upon their arrival our travelers inquired if there was any vessel in the harbor which they might send to Buenos Ayres. The person they addressed themselves to happened to be the master of a Spanish bark, who offered to agree with them on moderate terms, and appointed them a meeting at a public house.Thither Candide and his faithful Cacambo went to wait for him, taking with them their two sheep.

Candide, who was all frankness and sincerity, made an ingenuous recital of his adventures to the Spaniard, declaring to him at the same time his resolution of carrying off Miss Cunegund from the Governor of Buenos Ayres.

“Oh, ho！”said the shipmaster，“if that is the case, get whom you please to carry you to Buenos Ayres；for my part, I wash my hands of the affair. It would prove a hanging matter to us all.The fair Cunegund is the Governor's favorite mistress.”

These words were like a clap of thunder to Candide；he wept bitterly for a long time, and, taking Cacambo aside, he said to him，“I'll tell you, my dear friend, what you must do. We have each of us in our pockets to the value of fve or six millions in diamonds；you are cleverer at these matters than I；you must go to Buenos Ayres and bring off Miss Cunegund.If the Governor makes any diffculty give him a million；if he holds out, give him two；as you have not killed an Inquisitor, they will have no suspicion of you.I'll ft out another ship and go to Venice, where I will wait for you.Venice is a free country, where we shall have nothing to fear from Bulgarians, Abares, Jews or Inquisitors.”

Cacambo greatly applauded this wise resolution. He was inconsolable at the thoughts of parting with so good a master, who treated him more like an intimate friend than a servant；but the pleasure of being able to do him a service soon got the better of his sorrow.They embraced each other with a food of tears.Candide charged him not to forget the old woman.Cacambo set out the same day.This Cacambo was a very honest fellow.

Candide continued some days longer at Surinam, waiting for any captain to carry him and his two remaining sheep to Italy. He hired domestics, and purchased many things necessary for a long voyage；at length Mynheer Vanderdendur, skipper of a large Dutch vessel, came and offered his service.

“What will you have，”said Candide，“to carry me, my servants, my baggage, and these two sheep you see here, directly to Venice?”

The skipper asked ten thousand piastres, and Candide agreed to his demand without hestitation.

“Ho, ho！”said the cunning Vanderdendur to himself，“this stranger must be very rich；he agrees to give me ten thousand piastres without hesitation.”

Returning a little while after, he told Candide that upon second consideration he could not undertake the voyage for less than twenty thousand.

“Very well；you shall have them，”said Candide.

“Zounds！”said the skipper to himself，“this man agrees to pay twenty thousand piastres with as much ease as ten.”

Accordingly he went back again, and told him roundly that he would not carry him to Venice for less than thirty thousand piastres.

“Then you shall have thirty thousand，”said Candide.

“Odso！”said the Dutchman once more to himself，“thirty thousand piastres seem a trifle to this man. Those sheep must certainly be laden with an immense treasure.I'll e'en stop here and ask no more；but make him pay down the thirty thousand piastres, and then we may see what is to be done farther.”

Candide sold two small diamonds, the least of which was worth more than all the skipper asked. He paid him beforehand, the two sheep were put on board, and Candide followed in a small boat to join the vessel in the road.The skipper took advantage of his opportunity, hoisted sail, and put out to sea with a favorable wind.Candide, confounded and amazed, soon lost sight of the ship.

“Alas！”said he，“this is a trick like those in our old world！”

He returned back to the shore overwhelmed with grief；and, indeed, he had lost what would have made the fortune of twenty monarchs.

Straightway upon his landing he applied to the Dutch magistrate；being transported with passion he thundered at the door, which being opened, he went in, told his case, and talked a little louder than was necessary. The magistrate began with fining him ten thousand piastres for his petulance, and then listened very patiently to what he had to say, promised to examine into the affair on the skipper's return, and ordered him to pay ten thousand piastres more for the fees of the court.

This treatment put Candide out of all patience；it is true, he had suffered misfortunes a thousand times more grievous, but the cool insolence of the judge, and the villainy of the skipper raised his choler and threw him into a deep melancholy. The villainy of mankind presented itself to his mind in all its deformity, and his soul was a prey to the most gloomy ideas.After some time, hearing that the captain of a French ship was ready to set sail for Bordeaux, as he had no more sheep loaded with diamonds to put on board, he hired the cabin at the usual price；and made it known in the town that he would pay the passage and board of any honest man who would give him his company during the voyage；besides making him a present of ten thousand piastres, on condition that such person was the most dissatisfied with his condition, and the most unfortunate in the whole province.

Upon this there appeared such a crowd of candidates that a large feet could not have contained them. Candide, willing to choose from among those who appeared most likely to answer his intention, selected twenty, who seemed to him the most sociable, and who all pretended to merit the preference.He invited them to his inn, and promised to treat them with a supper, on condition that every man should bind himself by an oath to relate his own history；declaring at the same time, that he would make choice of that person who should appear to him the most deserving of compassion, and the most justly dissatisfed with his condition in life；and that he would make a present to the rest.

This extraordinary assembly continued sitting till four in the morning. Candide, while he was listening to their adventures, called to mind what the old woman had said to him in their voyage to Buenos Ayres, and the wager she had laid that there was not a person on board the ship but had met with great misfortunes.Every story he heard put him in mind of Pangloss.

“My old master，”said he，“would be confoundedly put to it to demonstrate his favorite system. Would he were here！Certainly if everything is for the best, it is in El Dorado, and not in the other parts of the world.”

At length he determined in favor of a poor scholar, who had labored ten years for the booksellers at Amsterdam：being of opinion that no employment could be more detestable.

This scholar, who was in fact a very honest man, had been robbed by his wife, beaten by his son, and forsaken by his daughter, who had run away with a Portuguese. He had been likewise deprived of a small employment on which he subsisted, and he was persecuted by the clergy of Surinam, who took him for a Socinian.It must be acknowledged that the other competitors were, at least, as wretched as he；but Candide was in hopes that the company of a man of letters would relieve the tediousness of the voyage.All the other candidates complained that Candide had done them great injustice, but he stopped their mouths by a present of a hundred piastres to each.

Chapter 22 What Happened to Candide and Martin in France

Candide stayed no longer at Bordeaux than was necessary to dispose of a few of the pebbles he had brought from El Dorado, and to provide himself with a post-chaise for two persons, for he could no longer stir a step without his philosopher Martin. The only thing that give him concern was being obliged to leave his sheep behind him, which he intrusted to the care of the Academy of Sciences at Bordeaux, who proposed, as a prize subject for the year, to prove why the wool of this sheep was red；and the prize was adjudged to a northern sage, who demonstrated by A plus B, minus C, divided by Z, that the sheep must necessarily be red, and die of the mange.

In the meantime, all travelers whom Candide met with in the inns, or on the road, told him to a man, that they were going to Paris. This general eagerness gave him likewise a great desire to see this capital；and it was not much out of his way to Venice.

He entered the city by the suburbs of Saint-Marceau, and thought himself in one of the vilest hamlets in all Westphalia.

Candide had not been long at his inn, before he was seized with a slight disorder, owing to the fatigue he had undergone. As he wore a diamond of an enormous size on his fnger and had among the rest of his equipage a strong box that seemed very weighty, he soon found himself between two physicians, whom he had not sent for, a number of intimate friends whom he had never seen, and who would not quit his bedside, and two women devotees, who were very careful in providing him hot broths.

“I remember，”said Martin to him，“that the frst time I came to Paris I was likewise taken ill. I was very poor, and accordingly I had neither friends, nurses, nor physicians, and yet I did very well.”

However, by dint of purging and bleeding, Candide's disorder became very serious. The priest of the parish came with all imaginable politeness to desire a note of him, payable to the bearer in the other world.Candide refused to comply with his request；but the two devotees assured him that it was a new fashion.Candide replied, that he was not one that followed the fashion.Martin was for throwing the priest out of the window.The clerk swore Candide should not have Christian burial.Martin swore in his turn that he would bury the clerk alive if he continued to plague them any longer.The dispute grew warm；Martin took him by the shoulders and turned him out of the room, which gave great scandal, and occasioned a proces-verbal.

Candide recovered, and till he was in a condition to go abroad had a great deal of good company to pass the evenings with him in his chamber. They played deep.Candide was surprised to find he could never turn a trick；and Martin was not at all surprised at the matter.

Among those who did him the honors of the place was a little spruce abbe of Perigord, one of those insinuating, busy, fawning, impudent, necessary fellows, that lay wait for strangers on their arrival, tell them all the scandal of the town, and offer to minister to their pleasures at various prices. This man conducted Candide and Martin to the playhouse；they were acting a new tragedy.Candide found himself placed near a cluster of wits：this, however, did not prevent him from shedding tears at some parts of the piece which were most affecting, and best acted.

One of these talkers said to him between acts，“You are greatly to blame to shed tears；that actress plays horribly, and the man that plays with her still worse, and the piece itself is still more execrable than the representation. The author does not understand a word of Arabic, and yet he has laid his scene in Arabia, and what is more, he is a fellow who does not believe in innate ideas.Tomorrow I will bring you a score of pamphlets that have been written against him.”

“Pray, sir，”said Candide to the abbe，“how many theatrical pieces have you in France?”

“Five or six thousand，”replied the abbe.

“Indeed！That is a great number，”said Candide，“but how many good ones may there be?”

“About ffteen or sixteen.”

“Oh！That is a great number，”said Martin.

Candide was greatly taken with an actress, who performed the part of Queen Elizabeth in a dull kind of tragedy that is played sometimes.

“That actress，”said he to Martin，“pleases me greatly；she has some sort of resemblance to Miss Cunegund. I should be very glad to pay my respects to her.”

The abbe of Perigord offered his service to introduce him to her at her own house. Candide, who was brought up in Germany, desired to know what might be the ceremonial used on those occasions, and how a queen of England was treated in France.

“There is a necessary distinction to be observed in these matters，”said the abbe.“In a country town we take them to a tavern；here in Paris， they are treated with great respect during their lifetime, provided they are handsome, and when they die we throw their bodies upon a dunghill.”

“How?”said Candide，“throw a queen's body upon a dunghill！”

“The gentleman is quite right，”said Martin，“he tells you nothing but the truth. I happened to be at Paris when Miss Monimia made her exit, as one may say, out of this world into another.She was refused what they call here the rites of sepulture；that is to say, she was denied the privilege of rotting in a churchyard by the side of all the beggars in the parish.They buried her at the corner of Burgundy Street, which must certainly have shocked her extremely, as she had very exalted notions of things.”

“This is acting very impolitely，”said Candide.

“Lord！”said Martin，“what can be said to it?It is the way of these people. Figure to yourself all the contradictions, all the inconsistencies possible, and you may meet with them in the government, the courts of justice, the churches, and the public spectacles of this odd nation.”

“Is it true，”said Candide，“that the people of Paris are always laughing?”

“Yes，”replied the abbe，“but it is with anger in their hearts；they express all their complaints by loud bursts of laughter, and commit the most detestable crimes with a smile on their faces.”

“Who was that great overgrown beast，”said Candide，“who spoke so ill to me of the piece with which I was so much affected, and of the players who gave me so much pleasure?”

“A very good-for-nothing sort of a man I assure you，”answered the abbe，“one who gets his livelihood by abusing every new book and play that is written or performed；he dislikes much to see anyone meet with success, like eunuchs, who detest everyone that possesses those powers they are deprived of；he is one of those vipers in literature who nourish themselves with their own venom；a pamphlet-monger.”

“A pamphlet-monger！”said Candide，“what is that?”

“Why, a pamphlet-monger，”replied the abbe，“is a writer of pamphlets—a fool.”

Candide, Martin, and the abbe of Perigord argued thus on the staircase, while they stood to see the people go out of the playhouse.

“Though I am very anxious to see Miss Cunegund again，”said Candide，“yet I have a great inclination to sup with Miss Clairon, for I am really much taken with her.”

The abbe was not a person to show his face at this lady's house, which was frequented by none but the best company.

“She is engaged this evening，”said he，“but I will do myself the honor to introduce you to a lady of quality of my acquaintance, at whose house you will see as much of the manners of Paris as if you had lived here for forty years.”

Candide, who was naturally curious, suffered himself to be conducted to this lady's house, which was in the suburbs of Saint-Honore. The company was engaged at basset；twelve melancholy punters held each in his hand a small pack of cards, the corners of which were doubled down, and were so many registers of their ill fortune.A profound silence reigned throughout the assembly, a pallid dread had taken possession of the countenances of the punters, and restless inquietude stretched every muscle of the face of him who kept the bank；and the lady of the house, who was seated next to him, observed with lynx's eyes every play made, and noted those who tallied, and made them undouble their cards with a severe exactness, though mixed with a politeness, which she thought necessary not to frighten away her customers.This lady assumed the title of Marchioness of Parolignac.Her daughter, a girl of about ffteen years of age, was one of the punters, and took care to give her mamma a hint, by signs, when any one of the players attempted to repair the rigor of their ill fortune by a little innocent deception.The company were thus occupied when Candide, Martin, and the abbe made their entrance；not a creature rose to salute them, or indeed took the least notice of them, being wholly intent upon the business at hand.

“Ah！”said Candide，“My Lady Baroness of Thunder-ten-tronckh would have behaved more civilly.”

However, the abbe whispered in the ear of the Marchioness, who half raising herself from her seat, honored Candide with a gracious smile, and gave Martin a nod of her head, with an air of inexpressible dignity. She then ordered a seat for Candide, and desired him to make one of their party at play；he did so, and in a few deals lost near a thousand pieces；after which they supped very elegantly, and everyone was surprised at seeing Candide lose so much money without appearing to be the least disturbed at it.The servants in waiting said to each other，“This is certainly some English lord.”

The supper was like most others of its kind in Paris. At frst everyone was silent；then followed a few confused murmurs, and afterwards several insipid jokes passed and repassed, with false reports, false reasonings, a little politics, and a great deal of scandal.The conversation then turned upon the new productions in literature.

“Pray，”said the abbe，“good folks, have you seen the romance written by a certain Gauchat, Doctor of Divinity?”

“Yes，”answered one of the company，“but I had not patience to go through it. The town is pestered with a swarm of impertinent productions, but this of Dr.Gauchat's outdoes them all.In short, I was so cursedly tired of reading this vile stuff that I even resolved to come here, and make a party at basset.”

“But what say you to the archdeacon T-'s miscellaneous collection，”said the abbe.

“Oh my God！”cried the Marchioness of Parolignac，“never mention the tedious creature！Only think what pains he is at to tell one things that all the world knows；and how he labors an argument that is hardly worth the slightest consideration！How absurdly he makes use of other people's wit！How miserably he mangles what he has pilfered from them！The man makes me quite sick！A few pages of the good archdeacon are enough in conscience to satisfy anyone.”

There was at the table a person of learning and taste, who supported what the Marchioness had advanced. They next began to talk of tragedies.The lady desired to know how it came about that there were several tragedies, which still continued to be played, though they would not bear reading?The man of taste explained very clearly how a piece may be in some manner interesting without having a grain of merit.He showed, in a few words, that it is not suffcient to throw together a few incidents that are to be met with in every romance, and that to dazzle the spectator the thoughts should be new, without being farfetched；frequently sublime, but always natural；the author should have a thorough knowledge of the human heart and make it speak properly；he should be a complete poet, without showing an affectation of it in any of the characters of his piece；he should be a perfect master of his language, speak it with all its purity, and with the utmost harmony, and yet so as not to make the sense a slave to the rhyme.“Whoever，”added he，“neglects any one of these rules, though he may write two or three tragedies with tolerable success, will never be reckoned in the number of good authors.There are very few good tragedies；some are idylls, in very well-written and harmonious dialogue；and others a chain of political reasonings that set one asleep, or else pompous and high-flown amplification, that disgust rather than please.Others again are the ravings of a madman, in an uncouth style, unmeaning fights, or long apostrophes to the deities, for want of knowing how to address mankind；in a word a collection of false maxims and dull commonplace.”

Candide listened to this discourse with great attention, and conceived a high opinion of the person who delivered it；and as the Marchioness had taken care to place him near her side, he took the liberty to whisper her softly in the ear and ask who this person was that spoke so well.

“He is a man of letters，”replied Her Ladyship，“who never plays, and whom the abbe brings with him to my house sometimes to spend an evening. He is a great judge of writing, especially in tragedy；he has composed one himself, which was damned, and has written a book that was never seen out of his bookseller's shop, excepting only one copy, which he sent me with a dedication, to which he had prefxed my name.”

“Oh the great man，”cried Candide，“he is a second Pangloss.”

Then turning towards him，“Sir，”said he，“you are doubtless of opinion that everything is for the best in the physical and moral world, and that nothing could be otherwise than it is?”

“I, sir！”replied the man of letters，“I think no such thing, I assure you；I find that all in this world is set the wrong end uppermost. No one knows what is his rank, his office, nor what he does, nor what he should do.With the exception of our evenings, which we generally pass tolerably merrily, the rest of our time is spent in idle disputes and quarrels, Jansenists against Molinists, the Parliament against the Church, and one armed body of men against another；courtier against courtier, husband against wife, and relations against relations.In short, this world is nothing but one continued scene of civil war.”

“Yes，”said Candide，“and I have seen worse than all that；and yet a learned man, who had the misfortune to be hanged, taught me that everything was marvelously well, and that these evils you are speaking of were only so many shades in a beautiful picture.”

“Your hempen sage，”said Martin，“laughed at you；these shades, as you call them, are most horrible blemishes.”

“The men make these blemishes，”rejoined Candide，“and they cannot do otherwise.”

“Then it is not their fault，”added Martin.

The greatest part of the gamesters, who did not understand a syllable of this discourse, amused themselves with drinking, while Martin reasoned with the learned gentleman and Candide entertained the lady of the house with a part of his adventures.

After supper the Marchioness conducted Candide into her dressingroom, and made him sit down under a canopy.

“Well，”said she，“are you still so violently fond of Miss Cunegund of Thunder-ten-tronckh?”

“Yes, madam，”replied Candide.

The Marchioness said to him with a tender smile，“You answer me like a young man born in Westphalia；a Frenchman would have said，‘It is true, madam, I had a great passion for Miss Cunegund；but since I have seen you, I fear I can no longer love her as I did.'”

“Alas！Madam，”replied Candide，“I will make you what answer you please.”

“You fell in love with her, I find, in stooping to pick up her handkerchief which she had dropped；you shall pick up my garter.”

“With all my heart, madam，”said Candide, and he picked it up.

“But you must tie it on again，”said the lady.

Candide tied it on again.

“Look ye, young man，”said the Marchioness，“you are a stranger；I make some of my lovers here in Paris languish for me a whole fortnight；but I surrender to you at frst sight, because I am willing to do the honors of my country to a young Westphalian.”

The fair one having cast her eye on two very large diamonds that were upon the young stranger's finger, praised them in so earnest a manner that they were in an instant transferred from his fnger to hers.

As Candide was going home with the abbe he felt some qualms of conscience for having been guilty of infdelity to Miss Cunegund. The abbe took part with him in his uneasiness；he had but an inconsiderable share in the thousand pieces Candide had lost at play, and the two diamonds which had been in a manner extorted from him；and therefore very prudently designed to make the most he could of his new acquaintance, which chance had thrown in his way.He talked much of Miss Cunegund, and Candide assured him that he would heartily ask pardon of that fair one for his infdelity to her, when he saw her at Venice.

The abbe redoubled his civilities and seemed to interest himself warmly in everything that Candide said, did, or seemed inclined to do.

“And so, sir, you have an engagement at Venice?”

“Yes, Monsieur l'Abbe，”answered Candide，“I must absolutely wait upon Miss Cunegund，”and then the pleasure he took in talking about the object he loved, led him insensibly to relate, according to custom, part of his adventures with that illustrious Westphalian beauty.

“I fancy，”said the abbe，“Miss Cunegund has a great deal of wit, and that her letters must be very entertaining.”

“I never received any from her，”said Candide；“for you are to consider that, being expelled from the castle upon her account, I could not write to her, especially as soon after my departure I heard she was dead；but thank God I found afterwards she was living. I left her again after this, and now I have sent a messenger to her near two thousand leagues from here, and wait here for his return with an answer from her.”

The artful abbe let not a word of all this escape him, though he seemed to be musing upon something else. He soon took his leave of the two adventurers, after having embraced them with the greatest cordiality.

The next morning, almost as soon as his eyes were open, Candide received the following billet：

“My Dearest Lover—I have been ill in this city these eight days. I have heard of your arrival, and should fy to your arms were I able to stir.I was informed of your being on the way hither at Bordeaux, where I left the faithful Cacambo, and the old woman, who will soon follow me.The Governor of Buenos Ayres has taken everything from me but your heart, which I still retain.Come to me immediately on the receipt of this.Your presence will either give me new life, or kill me with the pleasure.”

At the receipt of this charming, this unexpected letter, Candide felt the utmost transports of joy；though, on the other hand, the indisposition of his beloved Miss Cunegund overwhelmed him with grief. Distracted between these two passions he took his gold and his diamonds, and procured a person to conduct him and Martin to the house where Miss Cunegund lodged.Upon entering the room he felt his limbs tremble, his heart flutter, his tongue falter；he attempted to undraw the curtain, and called for a light to the bedside.

“Lord sir，”cried a maidservant, who was waiting in the room，“take care what you do, Miss cannot bear the least light，”and so saying she pulled the curtain close again.

“Cunegund！My dear！”cried Candide, bathed in tears，“how do you do?If you cannot bear the light, speak to me at least.”

“Alas！She cannot speak，”said the maid.

The sick lady then put a plump hand out of the bed and Candide frst bathed it with tears, then flled it with diamonds, leaving a purse of gold upon the easy chair.

In the midst of his transports came an offcer into the room, followed by the abbe, and a fle of musketeers.

“There，”said he，“are the two suspected foreigners.”At the same time he ordered them to be seized and carried to prison.

“Travelers are not treated in this manner in the country of El Dorado，”said Candide.

“I am more of a Manichaean now than ever，”said Martin.

“But pray, good sir, where are you going to carry us?”said Candide.

“To a dungeon, my dear sir，”replied the offcer.

When Martin had a little recovered himself, so as to form a cool judgment of what had passed, he plainly perceived that the person who had acted the part of Miss Cunegund was a cheat；that the abbe of Perigord was a sharper who had imposed upon the honest simplicity of Candide, and that the offcer was a knave, whom they might easily get rid of.

Candide following the advice of his friend Martin, and burning with impatience to see the real Miss Cunegund, rather than be obliged to appear at a court of justice, proposed to the offcer to make him a present of three small diamonds, each of them worth three thousand pistoles.

“Ah, sir，”said the understrapper of justice，“had you commited ever so much villainy, this would render you the honestest man living, in my eyes. Three diamonds worth three thousand pistoles！Why, my dear sir, so far from carrying you to jail, I would lose my life to serve you.There are orders for stopping all strangers；but leave it to me, I have a brother at Dieppe, in Normandy.I myself will conduct you thither, and if you have a diamond left to give him he will take as much care of you as I myself should.”

“But why，”said Candide，“do they stop all strangers?”

The abbe of Perigord made answer that it was because a poor devil of the country of Atrebata heard somebody tell foolish stories, and this induced him to commit a parricide；not such a one as that in the month of May，1610，but such as that in the month of December in the year 1594，and such as many that have been perpetrated in other months and years, by other poor devils who had heard foolish stories.

The offcer then explained to them what the abbe meant.

“Horrid monsters，”exclaimed Candide，“is it possible that such scenes should pass among a people who are perpetually singing and dancing?Is there no flying this abominable country immediately, this execrable kingdom where monkeys provoke tigers?I have seen bears in my country, but men I have beheld nowhere but in El Dorado. In the name of God, sir，”said he to the offcer，“do me the kindness to conduct me to Venice, where I am to wait for Miss Cunegund.”

“Really, sir，”replied the officer，“I cannot possibly wait on you farther than Lower Normandy.”

So saying, he ordered Candide's irons to be struck off, acknowledged himself mistaken, and sent his followers about their business, after which he conducted Candide and Martin to Dieppe, and left them to the care of his brother.

There happened just then to be a small Dutch ship in the harbor. The Norman, whom the other three diamonds had converted into the most obliging, serviceable being that ever breathed, took care to see Candide and his attendants safe on board this vessel, that was just ready to sail for Portsmouth in England.This was not the nearest way to Venice, indeed, but Candide thought himself escaped out of Hell, and did not, in the least, doubt but he should quickly fnd an opportunity of resuming his voyage to Venice.

Chapter 23 Candide and Martin Touch upon the English Coast—What They See There

“Ah Pangloss！Pangloss！Ah Martin！Ah my dear Miss Cunegund！What sort of a world is this?”Thus exclaimed Candide as soon as he got on board the Dutch ship.

“Why something very foolish, and very abominable，”said Martin.

“You are acquainted with England，”said Candide；“are they as great fools in that country as in France?”

“Yes, but in a different manner，”answered Martin.“You know that these two nations are at war about a few acres of barren land in the neighborhood of Canada, and that they have expended much greater sums in the contest than all Canada is worth. To say exactly whether there are a greater number ft to be inhabitants of a madhouse in the one country than the other, exceeds the limits of my imperfect capacity；I know in general that the people we are going to visit are of a very dark and gloomy disposition.”

As they were chatting thus together they arrived at Portsmouth. The shore on each side the harbor was lined with a multitude of people, whose eyes were steadfastly fixed on a lusty man who was kneeling down on the deck of one of the men-of-war, with something tied before his eyes.Opposite to this personage stood four soldiers, each of whom shot three bullets into his skull, with all the composure imaginable；and when it was done, the whole company went away perfectly well satisfed.

“What the devil is all this for?”said Candide，“and what demon, or foe of mankind, lords it thus tyrannically over the world?”

He then asked who was that lusty man who had been sent out of the world with so much ceremony. When he received for answer, that it was an admiral.

“And pray why do you put your admiral to death?”

“Because he did not put a suffcient number of his fellow creatures to death. You must know, he had an engagement with a French admiral, and it has been proved against him that he was not near enough to his antagonist.”

“But，”replied Candide，“the French admiral must have been as far from him.”

“There is no doubt of that；but in this country it is found requisite, now and then, to put an admiral to death, in order to encourage the others to fght.”

Candide was so shocked at what he saw and heard, that he would not set foot on shore, but made a bargain with the Dutch skipper（were he even to rob him like the captain of Surinam）to carry him directly to Venice.

The skipper was ready in two days. They sailed along the coast of France, and passed within sight of Lisbon, at which Candide trembled.From thence they proceeded to the Straits, entered the Mediterranean, and at length arrived at Venice.

“God be praised，”said Candide, embracing Martin，“this is the place where I am to behold my beloved Cunegund once again. I can confide in Cacambo, like another self.All is well, all is very well, all is well as possible.”

Chapter 24 Of Pacquette and Friar Girofee

Upon their arrival at Venice Candide went in search of Cacambo at every inn and coffee-house, and among all the ladies of pleasure, but could hear nothing of him. He sent every day to inquire what ships were in, still no news of Cacambo.

“It is strange，”said he to Martin，“very strange that I should have time to sail from Surinam to Bordeaux；to travel thence to Paris, to Dieppe, to Portsmouth；to sail along the coast of Portugal and Spain, and up the Mediterranean to spend some months at Venice；and that my lovely Cunegund should not have arrived. Instead of her, I only met with a Parisian impostor, and a rascally abbe of Perigord.Cunegund is actually dead, and I have nothing to do but follow her.Alas！How much better would it have been for me to have remained in the paradise of El Dorado than to have returned to this cursed Europe！You are in the right, my dear Martin；you are certainly in the right；all is misery and deceit.”

He fell into a deep melancholy, and neither went to the opera then in vogue, nor partook of any of the diversions of the Carnival；nay, he even slighted the fair sex.

Martin said to him，“Upon my word, I think you are very simple to imagine that a rascally valet, with fve or six millions in his pocket, would go in search of your mistress to the further of the world, and bring her to Venice to meet you. If he fnds her he will take her for himself；if he does not, he will take another.Let me advise you to forget your valet Cacambo, and your mistress Cunegund.”

Martin's speech was not the most consolatory to the dejected Candide. His melancholy increased, and Martin never ceased trying to prove to him that there is very little virtue or happiness in this world；except, perhaps, in El Dorado, where hardly anybody can gain admittance.

While they were disputing on this important subject, and still expecting Miss Cunegund, Candide perceived a young Theatin friar in the Piazza San Marco, with a girl under his arm. The Theatin looked fresh-colored, plump, and vigorous；his eyes sparkled；his air and gait were bold and lofty.The girl was pretty, and was singing a song；and every now and then gave her Theatin an amorous ogle and wantonly pinched his ruddy cheeks.

“You will at least allow，”said Candide to Martin，“that these two are happy. Hitherto I have met with none but unfortunate people in the whole habitable globe, except in El Dorado；but as to this couple, I would venture to lay a wager they are happy.”

“Done！”said Martin，“they are not what you imagine.”

“Well, we have only to ask them to dine with us，”said Candide，“and you will see whether I am mistaken or not.”

Thereupon he accosted them, and with great politeness invited them to his inn to eat some macaroni, with Lombard partridges and caviar, and to drink a bottle of Montepulciano, Lacryma Christi, Cyprus, and Samos wine. The girl blushed；the Theatin accepted the invitation and she followed him, eyeing Candide every now and then with a mixture of surprise and confusion, while the tears stole down her cheeks.No sooner did she enter his apartment than she cried out，“How, Monsieur Candide, have you quite forgot your Pacquette?Do you not know her again?”

Candide had not regarded her with any degree of attention before, being wholly occupied with the thoughts of his dear Cunegund.

“Ah！Is it you, child?Was it you that reduced Dr. Pangloss to that fne condition I saw him in?”

“Alas！Sir，”answered Pacquette，“it was I, indeed. I find you are acquainted with everything；and I have been informed of all the misfortunes that happened to the whole family of My Lady Baroness and the fair Cunegund.But I can safely swear to you that my lot was no less deplorable；I was innocence itself when you saw me last.A Franciscan, who was my confessor, easily seduced me；the consequences proved terrible.I was obliged to leave the castle some time after the Baron kicked you out by the backside from there；and if a famous surgeon had not taken compassion on me, I had been a dead woman.Gratitude obliged me to live with him some time as his mistress；his wife, who was a very devil for jealousy, beat me unmercifully every day.Oh！She was a perfect fury.The doctor himself was the most ugly of all mortals, and I the most wretched creature existing, to be continually beaten for a man whom I did not love.You are sensible, sir, how dangerous it was for an ill-natured woman to be married to a physician.Incensed at the behavior of his wife, he one day gave her so affectionate a remedy for a slight cold she had caught that she died in less than two hours in most dreadful convulsions.Her relations prosecuted the husband, who was obliged to fy, and I was sent to prison.My innocence would not have saved me, if I had not been tolerably handsome.The judge gave me my liberty on condition he should succeed the doctor.However, I was soon supplanted by a rival, turned off without a farthing, and obliged to continue the abominable trade which you men think so pleasing, but which to us unhappy creatures is the most dreadful of all sufferings.At length I came to follow the business at Venice.Ah！Sir, did you but know what it is to be obliged to receive every visitor；old tradesmen, counselors, monks, watermen, and abbes；to be exposed to all their insolence and abuse；to be often necessitated to borrow a petticoat, only that it may be taken up by some disagreeable wretch；to be robbed by one gallant of what we get from another；to be subject to the extortions of civil magistrates；and to have forever before one's eyes the prospect of old age, a hospital, or a dunghill, you would conclude that I am one of the most unhappy wretches breathing.”

Thus did Pacquette unbosom herself to honest Candide in his closet, in the presence of Martin, who took occasion to say to him，“You see I have half won the wager already.”

Friar Girofee was all this time in the parlor refreshing himself with a glass or two of wine till dinner was ready.

“But，”said Candide to Pacquette，“you looked so gay and contented, when I met you, you sang and caressed the Theatin with so much fondness, that I absolutely thought you as happy as you say you are now miserable.”

“Ah！Dear sir，”said Pacquette，“this is one of the miseries of the trade；yesterday I was stripped and beaten by an offcer；yet today I must appear good humored and gay to please a friar.”

Candide was convinced and acknowledged that Martin was in the right. They sat down to table with Pacquette and the Theatin；the entertainment was agreeable, and towards the end they began to converse together with some freedom.

“Father，”said Candide to the friar，“you seem to me to enjoy a state of happiness that even kings might envy；joy and health are painted in your countenance. You have a pretty wench to divert you；and you seem to be perfectly well contented with your condition as a Theatin.”

“Faith, sir，”said Friar Girofee，“I wish with all my soul the Theatins were every one of them at the bottom of the sea. I have been tempted a thousand times to set fre to the monastery and go and turn Turk.My parents obliged me, at the age of fifteen, to put on this detestable habit only to increase the fortune of an elder brother of mine, whom God confound！Jealousy, discord, and fury, reside in our monastery.It is true I have preached often paltry sermons, by which I have got a little money, part of which the prior robs me of, and the remainder helps to pay my girls；but, not withstanding, at night, when I go hence to my monastery, I am ready to dash my brains against the walls of the dormitory；and this is the case with all the rest of our fraternity.”

Martin, turning towards Candide, with his usual indifference, said，“Well, what think you now?Have I won the wager entirely?”

Candide gave two thousand piastres to Pacquette, and a thousand to Friar Girofee, saying，“I will answer that this will make them happy.”

“I am not of your opinion，”said Martin，“perhaps this money will only make them wretched.”

“Be that as it may，”said Candide，“one thing comforts me；I see that one often meets with those whom one never expected to see again；so that, perhaps, as I have found my red sheep and Pacquette, I may be lucky enough to fnd Miss Cunegund also.”

“I wish，”said Martin，“she one day may make you happy；but I doubt it much.”

“You lack faith，”said Candide.

“It is because，”said Martin，“I have seen the world.”

“Observe those gondoliers，”said Candide，“are they not perpetually singing?”

“You do not see them，”answered Martin，“at home with their wives and brats. The doge has his chagrin, gondoliers theirs.Nevertheless, in the main, I look upon the gondolier's life as preferable to that of the doge；but the difference is so trifing that it is not worth the trouble of examining into.”

“I have heard great talk，”said Candide，“of the Senator Pococurante, who lives in that fne house at the Brenta, where, they say, he entertains foreigners in the most polite manner.”

“They pretend this man is a perfect stranger to uneasiness. I should be glad to see so extraordinary a being，”said Martin.

Candide thereupon sent a messenger to Seignor Pococurante, desiring permission to wait on him the next day.